Okay, awesome. Okay, thanks for pointing this out. Sorry about that, everyone. So we have
now what are the rules for the GCR? Still mostly this class will be remote. All lecture
will be remote. This is what the department decided actually early on even before Delta
variant and all exams will be remote. We'll have three midterms. There is no final. And
we have 17 discussion sections on Thursday and Fridays, four on Thursday, 13 on Friday.
Out of those, four will be in person. They will be on Friday and 30 will be remote. Now,
please make sure because of that you have a working camera because you are going to
have Zoom proctoring of exams and require section design reviews, working with your
colleagues for the group projects, all requires to see each other and also screenshots. So
goals of today lectures, it's an introductory lecture, obviously, is to try to figure out
a little bit what is an operating system and in particular also what is not. And also I'm
going to say a few words about what makes operating systems so exciting. It's a while
and is actually probably one of the most exciting times to study and work on operating systems.
And then we are going to talk a little bit more at the end about how does a class operate.
Please interactivity is important. Now I know that it's harder, especially with a webinar.
I'm going to stop from time to time and look and take questions. And of course, please
ask questions and notes because even while I am talking, other people could answer them,
you know, some of our TAs. So what is fundamentally an operating system? So one way to think about
the operating system is that is that software layer which runs on top of hardware of the
hardware and provide support to the application. Right. What does that mean, providing support
to applications means that it makes it easier to develop applications and take advantage
of the hardware capabilities. It also protects applications from each other. It provides
security and authentication. So only the applications which should use the hardware and have access
to the data and also provide support for cooperation. There are applications which cooperate with
each other. And obviously this is more and more expected today. We are in the age of
the internet. Right. And why do we care to provide support for applications? Well, because
most of the things you do online, you do through applications. That's it. Right. It's the most
is a way people interact with computers is that people are going to interact with the
virtual world. So a physical world, virtual world. Virtual world means applications. And
also to drive home the point, here are some numbers about how the global mobile market
size. And you can see it is huge. And actually even year over year, the growth is significant.
Right. 20% or more. Right. And it's again an application provides the abstraction, manages
the resources, hardware resources. And it's achieving that through using a bunch of algorithms
for scheduling application or processes, providing access to resources from different concurrent
applications running at the same time. And security and many more. Okay. So right now,
let's look again a little bit. Oh, there is a question here. What is now an exciting time
for starting working in OS? Yes, we are going to answer that later because the impact of
the OS and the challenges are bigger than ever. That's a short answer. Okay. And here
it's again, it's not a problem during this lecture if you don't understand everything.
This is, you know, we are in here to provide some kind of end to end feeling about what
the operating system is doing. But the rest of the class, we are going to dive in and
we are going to, you know, to look at all these aspects I'm going to touch during this
lecture in more detail. So basically it's again, it's an application you want to run
an application, run a program and you have to run it on top of the hardware. Now, what
is a hardware consisting from? You have a processor which needs to execute the instructions
to run your applications and you clearly have a memory, right? We store the data and store
the program, you store the application code, right? So the processors read the instructions
and read the data and executes those instructions on the data and this is how your application
is running. In addition to just memory, you have a cache to keep the most recent data
or the most accessed data around closer to the processor. So this is obviously for improving
the performance. You have a page table and TLB translation, look at side buffers, this
is again, it's our mechanism for improving the performance. And besides that, you have
a storage where you need to store the data, the program at rest, the processor and memory
are storing the data and run the program only when they are powered on. And obviously you
have a lot of peripherals. You have displays, you have a mouse, you have network, you are
connected to the internet and many more, right? So this is quite complex, right? So now the
key here and they are connected, right? All of these pieces are connected. So the key
here is basically how you are going to make easy and secure for the application to run
on this hardware and also take advantage of the hardware capabilities. Okay. And many
of these things you learn, like this is a machine structure in CX61C. And it's again,
one of the main functionality of the operating system is to abstract away this hardware to
the application. Okay. So let me do this next set of few slides and then I'll stop for
questions. So one way to think about operating system is this like illusionist, right? And
why is that? Because again, it's provide this kind of abstraction of the physical resources
and the abstractions are much easier to use on the applications than the application using
directly the hardware, right? And one of the way it makes it easier to use, the operating
system makes easier for the application to use is removing limitations, right? So for
instance, it provides you the illusion to you being the application, the illusion that
you are the only one, the application is the only one using that machine. It provides the
illusion that the memory is like infinite, there are no limits, right? It provides a
illusion, you know, you have files and data is stored in files. You have users, you have
messages. So it's a much higher level of abstraction than operating just on bits, right? And the
main way the operating system provides abstracts these resources, hardware resources to the
application is through the process. The process is execution environment in which the applications
run and the process consists of threads. This is basically the concept, the unit of execution.
It's an address space. This is a unit kind of allocates, allocation, right? Allocate
the resources and you allocate addresses, memory, and you have access to files and sockets
to communicate over network, right? So the process encapsulate and provides all this
abstraction to the application. So the application only need to understand about how to operate
on threads and address space, how to read, write files, how to communicate over a sockets
to communicate over network, right? So that's it much easier. And how does application take
advantage? You write the code and you compile the code and your code is not only the code
you are writing, but it's going to use also libraries and a bunch of system libraries,
which are coming with any operating system, right? So again, to summarize the application
view of machine is that of the process. Each application program runs in its own process
and this process provides this much higher level, much nicer interfaces than the raw
hardware. Okay? So it's again, here you can see is like I mentioned, you have the program,
the code you write, which is going to use some calls to the system libraries, which
are going basically to implement this API for this abstraction, API, it's application
programming interfaces to manipulate these abstractions. And then you take care of this,
you compile it, you get the executable code and that you run it on your machine. Okay?
So let me stop here and let's see, there is a question. Oh, what OS do you like the best?
Well, I think that's a good question. I think, look, you know, it's like you, I'm not going
to surprise you here. I think that our two systems which are quite good, it's and I'm
using them, it's Linux and Mac OS. And you know, Mac OS, we are going to talk about that.
It's actually built also of the Unix BSD, which originated from Berkeley. So, okay.
So please ask questions. I am, and sorry, you know, again, it's I've never used webinar.
We are using it because it's more scalable, but it's less interactive. And yeah, so, but
we promise to improve on using these tools. So, excellent. Again, just to summarize, and
I'm going to repeat a lot of things, you know, a lot of over and over again. So hopefully
I'm not going to bore you, but you know, there are actually not a lot of big concepts you
are going to learn in this class, but the concepts are quite difficult and intricate
it. And also because they need to, they are going to inter-operate and interact with each
other. But just to summarize a process consists of an address space, one or more thread, and
this is the controls execution in that address space and a bunch of other resources like
files, sockets, and things like that. Okay. This is activity monitor. If you go, if you
have a Mac, if you go on here, you can look and you can see all these processes and you
can see actually the processes. It tells you also, I think the column probably, I'm not
sure you see my mouse, but there is a column here called threads, right? So this is your
unit of execution. So basically for Chrome here, you have 22 threads. So 22 activities
which are running concurrently in the same process. Okay. So that's one. Again, we abstracting
away hardware resources to the applications. It's one of the main, main things that the
application is that the operating system is doing. The main capabilities. Now let's, we
are going to look for other, we are going to go over the other capabilities that the
operating system provides and to illustrate the need for the next one. Now assume that
you are going to have not only one program, but two programs, two applications running
on your machine. And you know that every actually today, almost every computer your laptop,
your phone allows you to run multiple applications, which means multiple processes at the same
time. Right? And this now the point is that it's again, it's like one of the abstractions
remember that I mentioned that the operating system provides to the application is that
provides the illusion of a dedicated machine. Right? But now how you are going to do it
when you are going to have multiple applications running at the same time, because they are
going to run on the same hardware. And here is where it comes this kind of the other way
you can look at the operating system as a referee. Because the only way you can provide
the illusion of two applications and each of them they have their own virtual machine,
so to speak, is to protect one of each other, to isolate one of each other. Right? That's
the only way. And here it's just let's go in a little bit more details to illustrate
the need for that. Now, let's start with a processor. So you have only one processor
and you have two applications and you have to run on the same processor. At a given time,
you can run on the processor only one application. So to give the illusion that both of them
are going to run, you know, they have their own machine, so to speak. The way you do it
is that you are going to divide the processor time in slots or slices. And each slice you
have a different application running. The slices are, you know, a few milliseconds.
One millisecond, 10 milliseconds, something like that. Right? So in this particular example,
you have the brown application, right, running. And if you can see here, the processor accesses
memory, which is allocated to the brown process, process one, and it reads the code and executes
that code. So is there a for running program one. Right? But now, next, you will also have
program two. So for program two, in memory, you also have some piece of, you also have
some piece of memory which is allocated to process two. Right? And at some point, right,
you run, and at some point now, I said after a little bit of time, you allocate to program
one to run. Now you are going to switch to program two. Right? And you are going to run.
And by doing so and switching at a very high frequency, you give the illusion to each of
these applications that it's using the computer alone. Right?
Now, the problem here, if you can see, for instance, if you look at the memory, you're
having the same memory, physical memory, you have the data from multiple applications,
and they have to read and write the data. Right? And certainly, you do not want, say
in this case, a program two or process two to read or even more to write the data in
process one, of process one. Right? You also don't want any process two or for that matter
of fact, any process to write, to modify the operating system memory. Right? Right?
because then the operating system may crash, right?
If you let out an application,
modify the operating system in memory, right?
And also you need to be careful with the storage, right?
You shouldn't allow one program of one user
to modify the data of another users,
especially if that data is private or read it, okay?
So this is what we mean now you need to,
you protect, protection.
So you need to protect one application,
one process from another.
You need to protect one process from the operating system
and protect the operating system from the process, right?
So when an application on a program tries to
execute some of these actions, which are precluded,
like accessing the data of, or the memory,
which belongs to another process
or accessing the memory belongs to the operating system.
The operating system, one way is going to deal with this
offending application is crashing, crashing the processes,
segmentation fault, okay?
But it's again, the main point here is that
in order to create this illusion of,
to a process that they are using the machine alone,
you need to isolate and to protect processes
from each other.
Also in order to make sure that the operating system itself
is not crashes as a result of processes,
modifying operating system data,
then you need also to,
we need also to isolate the operating system itself
from the processes.
So let's see.
Okay, I was looking at the question,
why is a good time for learning OS right now?
It's again, we are going stick around until,
you know, for the next half an hour or so.
Okay, so now the last way we can look at the
operating system is like a glue, right?
So why is that?
It's again, it's like, it's very logic, right?
It's logical.
First, you need to abstract away the hardware
to make it much easier for the application developers
to write applications.
Second, you need to provide protection, isolations,
because typically you are going to have multiple
applications, multiple processes sharing the same hardware.
And the final part is that these applications
or some applications are communicating with each other.
So you need to provide some kind of glue between them.
You provide some common services.
And this is coming in the form of networking or storage,
right? You can, application can communicate through files.
One application writing a file,
another application reads from a file.
And obviously this also comes with authorization
and things like that.
But this is when you can think about the operating system
as a glue, right?
And they need to provide the communications,
enable you the ability to share the resources.
And again, the operating system is doing that
by providing these common services,
file systems, networking, and so forth.
Okay?
So I'm going to stop here.
Are there any questions?
So one question is what are the methods
that allow different processes to talk with each other?
I know with socket communication, it's a valid method.
So there are a few of them
and we are going to learn about them.
Yeah, one is socket communication.
So it's like networking, right?
You can communicate with each other, two processes,
whether they are on the same machine
or different machines through sockets,
through a network interface.
Okay?
The processes which are on the same machine,
they can also communicate through shared memory.
You can also have the ability
to communicate through shared memory.
And also, like I mentioned earlier,
you can communicate through storage.
An application can write a piece of data
on the local file system,
or even for a global file system,
and others application can read.
Okay?
Is a processor just what we call a CPU?
Yes, for most cases, these are interchangeable.
Although we are also going to call processor
like specialized hardware, specialized processors.
So processor is a little bit broader,
but unless otherwise specified, they are equivalent.
Will ARM replace x86 in consumer space soon?
Well, it's clear that ARM has a lot of momentum right now.
One example, it's obviously it's M1 from Apple.
And you see that become more and more powerful,
but there are also ARM starts to be deployed in data centers.
Actually, there is one new instance
which from Amazon called Graviton.
And this is around ARM processor.
And it's quite fast.
It's actually has very good performance and it's cheaper.
Now we'll see, right?
Because you know what Intel is going to do,
clearly they announced a bunch of initiatives, but yes.
ARM, it's has a lot of momentum at this point.
Okay.
Let me go here.
Yeah, there is something about virtualization.
There is something about,
there are a few more questions here.
Let me answer them.
It's one question on the chat.
By the way, please try to ask question for on Q&A.
So I have one source I can read them from.
So yeah, there are a few more questions here.
Yeah, there are some comments about VMware,
about virtualization.
Yes, we are going to talk about virtualization
even a little bit during this lecture.
But yes, virtualization is a way to provide the illusion
to every process, to every application
that they are using alone the machine.
There is another question about RISC-V.
This obviously was done at Berkeley.
I think RISC-V has a great future.
And for those of you who don't know,
RISC-V is an open instruction set architecture,
which means that you don't need to pay any license to use it
to build processors around it.
In contrast ARM, for ARM you need to pay license
in order to use and to provide the ARM instruction set.
But RISC-V now it's targeting Internet of Things
or mobile devices, very low power.
This is how they started, but this is the way ARM started.
So you'll see maybe RISC, there is a chance
they are going to follow the trajectory of ARM
and it can become for ARM what ARM is for Intel, right?
But it's okay, it's obvious.
This is in the future, but obviously it has a lot of promise.
Okay, I'm going to go back now to the lecture slides.
Oops, okay.
So it's again, this is give examples
about some of the services which are provided
by the operating system, we didn't discuss so far.
And some of the management services
and that the operating system provides
and maybe you do not think right away to them.
It's like power management, right?
Well, especially for mobile devices,
you need to manage the power and across the application,
you have a application which use a disproportionate amount
of battery, maybe you want to isolate
to protect other application from that.
And of course you need to manage the network,
you need to manage almost every shared resource, right?
When I mean share, I refer share by multiple applications.
Okay, so in summary, it's again repeating, right?
There are three things an operating system is doing.
One is providing a clean, easy to use abstractions
of the physical resources to the application,
make it much easier for application developers
to develop this application.
And this piece like you can think about this,
like is like you lose your list.
Then which follows from providing clean abstractions,
you can think about operating system as a referee.
And in this case, the operating system provides protection
and isolations of shared resources
across for multiple applications, right?
We share those resources, okay?
And the final is that it's a glue
that operating system provides common services
and in particularly also enables this application
to communicate to each other, right?
So now let's talk a little bit more
about CS162 in general,
and then talk a little bit about why now
and why it's exciting and challenging.
So why take CS162?
It's again, because some of you will actually design
and build operating system or components of them,
like file systems, right?
You go to Google, you may work on Android, for instance.
You go to Apple, you may, or Microsoft,
you may work on their operating systems.
Or if you are to any company,
which depend running its software on Linux,
you may work on Linux to provide new capabilities
for the applications that are important for your company.
But many of you are going to build software
which run on top of the operating systems.
And to build better software,
you need to understand how the operating system was working.
You need to understand the concepts, right?
So that's what it is.
So next time I'm going to talk about
what makes operating system exciting and challenging.
And let me check again for the questions.
How can application interact with these common services?
Through the API, application programming interfaces.
I mentioned a little bit in passing earlier on.
And these are exposed by system libraries, right?
For instance, if you want to access a file,
you are going to have an API to access that file.
Read, write, seek.
The same for communication, sending and receiving data.
You are going to have another API.
And this is exposed by the system libraries
and implement it.
Well, why does searching for files
on Windows File Explorer feel super slow?
Unfortunately, I don't know.
I have no answer to that question,
but if you get the answer,
I'll be interested in the answer.
Okay, so in short,
what makes the system, the operating system,
now extremely exciting
is because there are many things happening.
In the next few slides,
I'm going to tell you what happens.
And these things actually makes operating systems,
addressing the operating system problems more difficult
and hopefully more rewarding once you solve the problems.
So as you probably know, and you heard that,
I'm sure everyone heard that many times,
for the most than, more than 50 years,
all our industry, hardware industry, software industry,
and large part was really driven by the morsel.
Machines are harder becoming more and more powerful,
very fast.
So according to Gordon Moore,
who was a co-founder of Intel,
in '65 he predicted that the transistor density
of semiconductor chips will double roughly every two years.
That's a morsel, right?
And you have this plus here and you see a line,
but you see a line on the X axis is the time,
on the Y axis it's the performance
or the number of transistors.
And you have a line, why?
Because the Y axis is in log scale.
Now, Moore's law says every,
the transistor density doubles roughly every two years.
So in the same, on the same area,
you can cram twice as many transistors.
And this leads to the performance of the processor,
doubling roughly every 18 months.
Why discrepancy?
The discrepancy is because since the transistors
are becoming closer to each other,
the latency between transistors to communicate
between transistors decreases.
And therefore you have double reasons.
You know, you have, there are these compounds.
To increasing the transistor density.
And therefore the performance increases a little bit faster
or used to increase a little bit faster.
Okay?
The challenge is that the Moore's law ended.
This again, it shows here the performance
and versus time, the performance of a single core
of a processor.
And between 1985 and 2002 or 2003,
this was where you see here with green,
this is the golden age, so to speak.
Because in this period, performance,
increased, doubled every 18 months
or increased 52% every year.
And the problem right now is that this performance per core
increases just a few percent every year.
Okay?
So that's it.
So this is a big problem.
And why is this a big problem?
Because at the time when the capabilities of a single core
basically are no longer increasing.
The demands of the new applications
are increasing faster than ever.
So here it's a plot, open AI plot.
Many of you maybe may have seen it.
And it shows compute requirements
to train the state of the art models.
This is plot was going back to 2012, was published in 2019.
Again, it's a log scale.
And if you look here, this growth is absolutely astounding.
The requirements, compute requirements
grew 35 times every 18 months.
And I added here another data point for 2020.
A new model was released, if you remember,
a little more than one year ago, GPT-C.
3 from OpenAI made a lot of waves.
It has 175 million parameters.
And it's again, it fills a curve.
And this again, is not only esoteric models.
You have models like GPT-3 is actually language model,
video model, pattern recognition,
and things like that.
And now here is a Moore's law.
Actually, the Moore's law even forget that it ended.
Even if it weren't ended, we would be in a big trouble.
But of course, it ended.
And this is actually how the Moore's law looked like.
So you see the gap.
This is huge.
And this is exponential.
It's again, you have a log scale here.
And the gap increases exponentially every year
or every day if you want.
OK?
So now what do you do about it?
Of course, you heard about specialized processors.
You have GPUs like Nvidia GPUs.
A100 is the latest one.
TPUs from TensorFlow processor units, from Google.
Cerebras, this is a company building huge chips,
very powerful.
And everyone else builds their own version of GPU.
Intel, Alchemist, Newer Announcement, AMD, Radion,
and so forth.
So the main idea here, obviously with this specialized hardware,
is that you are going to narrow the workloads you
want to support.
And because of that, you know more about that workload.
So you can do more optimizations.
And you can be smarter in the way you design the chip.
You increase the parallelism and things like that.
So you can make it much faster for that workload
than a general proposed processor.
But now you need to program these things as well.
You may need to share these things as well.
And they are going to be quite different from the CPUs.
And who has to deal with that?
That's biggest stand if your operating system
has to deal with it.
OK?
Now, the problem is that even with this specialized hardware,
they help.
Obviously, they are more powerful than a single core.
But still, they don't close the gap.
And here, it's the performance of the GPUs and of the TPUs
on the same plot.
And there is a star here, basically,
saying we are assuming in order to make sense
and to normalize, typically, in particular,
based on open AI data, the utilization of the hardware
by this state-of-the-art training algorithms
is like 33%.
So when I show the performance of the GPUs and TPUs here,
I am factoring it for that utilization.
So that's a huge problem, right?
Even with the CPUs and GPUs.
And these memory demands are growing as fast, even faster.
So here, it's a log-log scale.
Here is the number of parameters of these models.
And this is from 2016.
And now, the last point is this Vodao.
This is from China.
And this is 1.75 trillion parameters.
So it's 10 times larger than GPT-3.
And I'm sure you are going to hear
about other announcement, even bigger models.
So if you plot and if you look at this data,
it's again, it's again log scale,
although it may not look like.
Since 2016, the size of this model
increased 40 times every 18 months.
And if you look at the last three years, 340 times.
This is phenomenal.
During this time, the GPU memory, 1.7x every 18 months.
So it used to be, not a few years back, in 2017, '18,
you can fit the largest models on a single GPU.
Now, you need more than 1,000 GPUs
just to store the parameters of the largest models.
OK?
So let's see what are the other trends.
Now, let's move to storage capacity.
Storage capacity is still growing,
still growing exponentially.
And the one thing here, it used to be dominating the storage
by hard disk drives.
No longer.
Now, you have more and more solid state devices.
And you can see here the capacity of a solid state drive
started to exceed in 2015, '16.
So the biggest SSD drive exceeded
the capacity of the biggest, hardest drive around 2015
to '16.
And today, if you are looking, the largest SSD,
3.5 inch drive, is 100 terabytes.
The largest SSD is 18 terabytes.
Now, you are going to pay dearly for this 100 terabyte SSD
drive.
It costs 40K.
It's 400 per terabytes.
While to get 18 terabytes, sorry, this
is hardest drive.
I'm sorry.
I'm going to just correct this one.
OK?
So for that, you pay only $600, so you're $33 per terabytes.
Now, you can have more economical choices
when you look at the SSDs.
Like, for instance, if you want 4 terabytes SSD,
it costs $95 per terabyte, still more expensive
than the hardest drives.
Despite of this, the SSDs are winning the war.
There is little question about that.
And why?
Because, yes, the hardest drive are cheaper,
but they are much slower.
Sometimes between 10x and 100x consumes much more power,
very important for data center and mobile devices or laptops.
And they are less reliable.
And these are some projections to drive home
that point on the left-hand side.
It's about, you can see different technologies.
It is projected up to 2030.
And you can have here with dark blue, it's SSDs.
With light blue, it's flash.
So this is USB, the storage in your camera,
and things like that.
And then the yellow, it's actually are tapes.
It's older technology.
Probably many of you have never seen a tape,
but they are very cheap.
That's why.
And then, always, the dark orange--
well, with orange, it's actually hardest drives.
Also, the same study anticipates that in 2026, actually,
the SSDs will be cheaper per terabyte than hardest drives.
And that's why probably you are going to see
on the left-hand side a point in around 2025
after which the market share of not only of the hardest drive,
it's going to decrease.
Networking, still growing very fast.
Today, you can have 100-gabits connections
to your machines in AWS.
Next will be probably 400-gabits per second.
And there are other factors.
It's like, for instance, another important aspect
is the fact that it used to be early on,
you have very few huge computers because they
are extremely expensive, tens of millions of dollars.
So in that case, you have a lot of people
using the same machine, right?
Actually, in '60s, if I remember correctly, or '50s,
when IBM started to build computers, Watson,
who was the founder of the IBM and the CEO,
was saying that he doesn't believe
that there is a need for more than five or six computers
in the entire United States.
And of course, over time, the computers have proliferated,
become smaller and smaller.
And it used to be probably in 2000s,
at the end of the previous century,
you have one user, one computer.
And now you have one user with many, many computers.
If you're in your car alone, you have 10 and 10 of CPUs, right?
So this change, and as you can imagine,
this also is going to impact the way
you are going to design the operating systems.
And there is another aspect here.
There is an extreme range of timescales.
This is from Jeff Dean of Google,
very influential computer scientist,
built many of the distributed systems there.
And if you look about from an application and the operating
system, you have to deal with a latency as low as lower
than one second.
This is L1 cache.
This is a cache which is the first level cache which
is on the chip, on chip.
And all the way, if you are going
to send a packet to communicate with someone in California
to Netherlands, it's what?
It's 150 milliseconds.
So you need to handle a scale, a difference in scale,
and range of what, eight order of magnitude, more, OK?
So basically, let me actually stop here
and see what are the questions.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
Why does industry Intel Apple say the Moore's Law is not
over?
So the Moore's Law, from that very definition of the Moore's
Law, it is pretty much over.
It's physical, right?
What they say is that--
what this company is saying, it's fundamentally-- look,
if the Moore's Law--
if you say that the Moore's Law is over,
and I'm building chips, why would you build--
why you would buy chips from me?
Because this means that the new chips
will be the same like the old chips.
No more power, right?
So there is a limit also of this, that I cannot say that
the Moore's Law is over, because the Moore's Law is
what the public associate with the performance, right?
So it's a limit of also marketing.
The Moore's Law is over, but the Moore's Law
has a very precise definition.
And these companies, they talk to the public,
and the public doesn't know the precise definition.
Now, Moore's Law means fast.
Things become faster and faster.
Now, in truth, they use a lot of other techniques,
and we are going to talk about those in order
to improve the performance, right?
And this is very visible in your iPhone or in your Android phone.
And we'll talk a little bit about how they do it.
But that is not by improving necessarily
the performance of a single core.
It's by adding GPUs, neural engines, adding more cores,
things like that.
OK?
We'll talk more about it.
But good question.
So there are programs like Spark and Mavic
that allow us to use networks or computers to process
a parallel workload.
But would it be feasible to create
some type of operating system of software
that could string together resources of multiple computers
for personal consumer use?
I think-- so the question is, is a distributed operating system.
I think that there is not a coherent operating system,
but the elements of a operating system, distributed operating
system, are already there.
Because one thing you can have, you can have--
you probably know about Kubernetes.
Kubernetes provides resource orchestration,
resource management over multiple machines,
over a cluster.
So that's one.
Then now, then you have distributed file systems,
like HDFS, or you have these block stores, like AWS S3.
We'll talk more toward the end of the class.
It's a good question.
So probably you should expect that at some point
you are going to see these kind of pieces coming together
in a more coherent way in what you could call a distributed
operating system.
So fundamentally, it's again-- so why things are exciting?
Because they are challenging.
Why are things challenging?
Because they are complex.
And this complexity, it's growing fast.
Why is complexity growing?
Because you have the demands of your new application
are growing faster than ever.
Capabilities of the hardware are no longer
growing like they used to be.
So then you need to add to have--
to innovate on the architecture.
You have different specialized chips.
You need to distribute these applications.
You need to parallelize the programs and many more.
And I'll talk a little more about it.
So and then the applications themselves are more complicated.
The application consists of a variety of software modules.
And we'll talk more about that.
But remember, if you--
almost every application you are using today
is not running only on your machine.
It has a back end.
Use Facebook.
A lot of things happen in the back end.
Use Google or any other Google applications.
80% is in the back end.
Twitter, everything almost, right?
Netflix, name it, right?
And then it has to run on different hardware
architectures.
And because of the Moore's law has ended,
you are going to have to see a proliferation.
You are already seeing a proliferation
of hardware architectures.
Just to give you an example here,
and it's a personal example.
When we started Spark and we started in 2009, so what,
12 years ago, we are focusing only
for processing data which is in the memory efficiently.
We are focusing only on CPUs, right?
It's like we assume that the processing is
done by the general proposed processors, Intel.
When we started Ray, which was--
that was happening like in 2016.
So it's after only six, seven years.
We already have to take into account
and to design it for heterogeneous hardware
to handle GPUs at that time, now to handle GPUs and so forth.
So this is real.
And obviously, this comes with additional complexity.
And of course, it's once you are over the network,
you are also exposed to attacks.
And this means that because the heterogeneity is increasing
dramatically, that the operating system becomes
even more important because it's much harder
to abstract them away, right?
Because if you don't abstract away,
it's very hard to write applications.
And the operating system is one of the key roles,
like we discussed, is to make that writing, developing
application very easy, right?
So that's why its operating system are more challenging
and more needed than ever.
Now, we discussed and when we discussed about specialized hardware, I mentioned that it's
not only specialized hardware, how people try to go around the more slow or kind of,
so to speak, extend in terms of performance.
In other ways, having more and more cores, even for general proposed processors.
Like Intel Xeon Phi has a processor with 64 cores, AMD Epic, the same 64 cores, although
there are rumors that the new version will have 128 cores.
And if you look at these processors, actually, they are damn complicated, right?
This is how it looks like.
You have a bunch of cores, you have cache, you have some other components to manage memory.
You have other components here down to also control the IO, input output, getting the
data in and out of the processor and reading from the memory, which is not on the chip,
it's off the chip.
And you have also in many systems, you have processor, you have some integrated graphics,
right?
And this is a trend which, sorry, if you look under the hood, they are connected.
It's like a mini system in miniature, right?
In this case, you are going to have, this is a core, processor core, and now you are
connected to different IO ports, memory, and many other things, right?
And this complexity just increasing.
So here down is like, it's what we are seeing here, it's another trend.
It's system on a chip, right?
And when going back to that question, when Apple say, maybe say Moore's law is not done,
this is what they do and how they sustain the increasing performance, again, which is
not necessarily related with the Moore's law.
It's putting more and more intelligence, more and more functionality on the same chip, right?
And here I will show, you have not only CPUs and if CPU have multiple cores, I mean, send
or eight between six and 10, but you have GPUs, right?
Integrated on the same chip.
You have eight core GPUs, right?
Eight core CPUs.
And in addition to that, you have neural engine, which is really focused on neural, to sort
of supporting machine learning workloads, deep neural network workloads, right?
This is the things which are like, you know, your fingerprint sensor or recognizing, you
know, as your face, using your face to unlock the phone, right?
Face recognition, right?
So that's why, how you are going to get more performance.
The code is also very complicated.
It's growing in complexity and I don't have the numbers, more recent numbers, but here
is a Vista, this one, you know, 15 years ago, code.
It was what?
50 millions code, lines of code.
It's huge, huge complexity.
And just to give you a sense, the NASA space shuttle, you know, you remember it was a space
shuttle.
It's no longer in service.
It has what?
I don't know.
One or two millions lines of code.
It's crazy.
And then it's again, like I mentioned several times, you have to scale everyone to, because
you can no longer do these workloads on a single node, on a single machine, right?
Like I show you the data for machine learning workloads.
The same thing is for big data analytics, scientific computing.
You have, so we have supercomputers, which are parallel computers or in this big computers
since 80s to support this kind of workloads.
And then on top of that, everything is connected.
This is the internet.
Probably the most impressive artifact that humans have created, right?
It's linked the entire world, right?
And it's what?
You have 4.5 billions people connected to the internet.
This is what this plot shows, right?
And this is what?
It happens only 25 years.
It's quite amazing.
And then the smartphone shipments exceeded the PC shipments, what I think in 2011.
And today, right, today actually it turns out that you have close to 4 billion smartphones
and 5 point something billions mobile phones, right?
This data is a little bit old.
And all of those, all the phones are connected.
So you have 4 billion, this kind of very powerful devices at the end of the day, which are connected,
right?
So you have everything.
You have a huge range, right?
You have everything from data center, which hundreds of thousands of computers to sensor
networks, right?
Which you may not be even able to see these chips, right?
And everything in between, right?
And different workloads.
And just to drive home the point and I'll here, so just like I mentioned earlier, many
of the applications you are using today, they are distributed, right?
Facebook, Twitter, and so forth.
And this is what happens under the hood, right?
And let's say you do a simple search, right?
From your Android 4 or iPhone, right?
What do you do?
So first of all, you need to figure out what backend, what servers you need to connect
to, to get, to send the request, your search request, and to get the answer.
In order to do that, you need to do this DNS request, domain name service, right?
And this is, you know, it's like you need to resolve, use this link, right?
It's google.com to a particular server, right?
So you have an entire domain DNS infrastructure, which consisting of many servers, and they
will cooperate to give you an answer to tell you who you need to connect to, who you need
to send the packets.
Now, so once you get that address, which is an IP address, you are going to send it over
the internet, right?
Over the internet, these packets are going to be routed by switches, routers, and so
forth.
And it's going to go, based on the IP address, probably in a data center, they are going
to land to a load balancer.
The load balancer, you get the packets, you send to a server, the web server probably.
The web server is going to look at the request and based on the request, it's going to send,
you know, request an entire other system to resolve that request, right?
To give you the answers if you have a Google query.
And obviously, you may also have to get some ads in the process.
You have another infrastructure doing only that, figuring out what ads to show.
And then you need to put together the entire page and send it back and to be displayed
on your computer, right?
So this is just to give you a sense how complicated things are.
And all of these interactions are handled by the operating system, right, at the low
level.
So let me just, we have only five minutes.
So what I'm going to do, I'm going to do the following thing and we are going to continue
next time.
Let me first try to answer some of the questions and then I'm going to go straight to some
logistics.
How low level does this class get?
Do we talk about things like pipelining?
We won't talk much about like pipelining, if you are referring at the CPU process, in
the CPU pipelining, like instruction pipelining.
We are not going to talk.
We are going to talk a little bit about hyper-threading.
We are going to talk about that.
So we'll answer, so this is about hyper-threading.
We are going to talk more about, in short, it's a way in which you can share the core,
one core between two threads, which can come from different applications.
So it's multiplexing one core.
Okay, so yeah.
Okay, so let me just skip and obviously we'll do the rest next time and talk a little bit
here about, more about the class.
Okay, syllabus and it's online.
You have the class.
So we are going to obviously to learn the operating system concepts and how a system
programmer is going to use these concepts.
What are the interfaces, APIs, and then we are going to learn about how the operating
system implements some of this functionality.
Like how is it going to manage concurrency, multiple applications accessing shared resources
at the same time.
Address space, how you are going to provide isolation between different applications so
that each one application or process will not step over the memory of another application
or process.
File systems, how you are going to access and store the data and retrieve the data,
send the data and receive the data over the network.
We are going to talk a little bit about distributed systems and the protocols, which are, and
the mechanisms which are implemented by distributed systems to make them easier to use and to
be more efficient.
And we are going to talk about reliability and security, fault tolerance protection and
so forth.
And finally, we are going to talk about a little bit about cloud infrastructure, which
is very relevant because right now, cloud is a de facto standard.
Many companies are building, especially startups are building their application.
This class is hands-on.
You are going to learn by doing.
You have a bunch of homeworks and projects.
Projects are extremely important.
And with the projects you are going to implement actually also is the homework, some mechanism,
some functionality that operating system do.
Like your stress and scheduling, file systems and so forth.
Memory allocation.
This will be very, very exciting.
Now what are the demands?
The project will require you to be very comfortable with programming and debugging C. So remember,
recall pointers, memory management, use GDB for debugging.
So just go over 61C again.
And you need to know how to use Git for version control.
And there is a C programming reference here if you need.
So please consult that.
I think the first two sections are dedicated to programming and debugging reviews.
So please attend these sections.
And you can attend any two section, I believe, for the first two weeks.
After that, you need to choose one section.
The other thing I want to say, and to be quick here, but also I want to emphasize that projects
are very important.
And projects are not only about doing a piece of software and building a piece of software,
a project about teaching you how to collaborate, how to work in a team.
This will be extremely important for you.
If you go and to be a software engineer, this is a key skill you need to learn.
You are going to learn to work in a team.
You need to make the team successful because that's how you are going to become successful.
You are not going to work alone.
We require the project to have four members, number five.
And the exception will be very rare.
Please, this is pandemic, still pandemic.
It's very hard.
Most of the activities will be online.
If you do online, turn the camera on.
Try to emulate the physical presence as much as possible.
But also now you can also, the campus is open.
You know, if you feel comfortable, you can go and meet in person.
But collaborate, collaborate, collaborate.
And also not only between you and your members of the team, but also your TA.
Overcommunication is how you make this project successful.
Then you need to devise the work among the members of the team to require both decision
and additional collaboration because you are going to depend on the work of other people
do in your team.
This is a grading, 36% is for three midterms.
We have only midterms, no final.
36% projects, 80% homework, 10% participation, section, lectures, and so forth.
You'll hear more about the project.
You'll have a design document.
Design document will be due.
You are going to get feedback from the TAs and so forth.
Books and infrastructures.
You should be able to find all the information.
There's a class web page.
There is a Piazza.
You find the link to the Piazza as well there.
The lectures will be recorded.
Yeah, sorry about today, about the beginning of the lecture.
The textbook is the operating system principles and practice from Tom Anderson and Mike Dalin.
And there are a few other books, very good.
And you are encouraged to consult and you can refer to.
And we are going to have a few supplemental materials, a few research papers and so forth.
We are going to let you know.
Finally, please, it's like, this is not a joke.
Personal integrity, you signed the UCB Academy Honor Code.
So please live by it.
You can explain the concept of other people in the group.
You can discuss the concept with other people on the group.
You can even help your friend to debug your code, the code.
Or you can search online for generic codes.
This is good, but you cannot share the code with other groups.
You cannot copy or read another group's code or test cases.
You cannot copy or reading online code or test cases from prior years.
And we are going, as you know that, we compare all project submission against prior year
submissions and online solutions and will take actions right against your funder.
So please don't do that.
It's not going to help you with learning.
That's probably the most important reason you shouldn't do it.
Let's try hard to make this class and to keep this class interactive.
And I'm going to stop here.
I'm going to take it about the talk, obviously, a little bit more about the operating system
general overview next time.
And now let me answer the questions which are still here.
So there are two other questions.
There is actually one last question.
Will it be good to review material of the later half of 6.1c like cache?
Yes, absolutely.
Components of the CPU, how much of this?
This will be very useful.
We are going to talk about caching.
We are going to talk and reviewing that it will be so useful.
How does participation grading work?
This will be mostly because it will be smaller groups from interacting with your TAs, office
hours and discussion sections.
I am, at the size of this class, I don't think I will have the opportunity to interact with
many of you, especially since we are remote.
But obviously, if you have any problem, anything, please do not hesitate to drop me an email
and you can look for me.
I'll be in soda, soda hall, at least now and then.
So thank you so much, everyone.
And I'll see you next Tuesday.
And if you have any other questions, please ask the questions.
And if you also have any other suggestions about how to make the class better, more interactive,
please do not hesitate to let us know.
It's again, the first time I'm using the webinar and it's not a lot of, you know, it's hard
to just talk at the screen and see the slide, not see any of your faces.
So but, you know, let's try to do our best.
And yeah, any idea you see, you have to improve interactivity, to improve the class in general,
let us know.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]