Hello everyone, welcome to the 10th lecture. So today we are going to finish synchronization
primitives and then the rest of the lecture we are going to focus on scheduling main key
concepts and we are going to learn some of the basic policies.
So recall that last time we learned about monitors and condition variables and just
to, if you remember a monitor it's a lock and which owns one or more condition variables
and these condition variables are used for managing the access to share data. And the
way this is happening is that condition variable you can imagine it as a queue of thread waiting
for something to happen inside a critical section and they are waiting for a signal
for this condition variable. And the key here is that because you are waiting for something
to happen in the critical section, the critical section has a lock. You need to lock a critical
section to implement mutual exclusion but because you are waiting in a critical section
before you being the thread you are put to sleep on the waiting queue you need to release
a lock and the monitors does the art for you. You don't need as a programmer to do anything.
So basically from the programming perspective you can wait in the critical section for the
event to happen but under the hood the lock is released once you are put on the waiting
queue. And besides the wait we take the argument as a lock of the critical section you are
going to wait in. In order to trigger events to wake up the threads which are waiting for
these events to happen there are two primitives signal and broadcast. A signal wakes up only
one waiter, a broadcast can wake up all the waiters which are waiting for that particular
event to happen. And when you do condition variable operations then you are going to
have to obviously to keep the lock. So one question here from Akshay is that why it is
nice to be able to wait in the critical section. So if you remember if the program doesn't
allow you to wait, if the program constructs API doesn't allow you to wait then you need
somehow programmatically to give the lock while you are going to sleep. Because if you
are going to sleep while you keep the lock then no one else can acquire the lock. So
basically the entire system, so no one even can wake you up. So the entire system is that
lock. So it's fundamental that as you are going to go to sleep you have to release the
lock. But doing that in a program as two separate instructions going to sleep and releasing
the lock is very difficult. The instruction has to be atomic. These two actions should
be atomic in the same instruction. And that's what monitors provide to you.
Now, a key question is that the monitor is clearly a much more advanced API for synchronization.
And one of the natural questions actually is about can you use lower level synchronization
primitives like summer for us to implement monitors. And again there are two constructs
you need to implement. One is about you need to have a critical section you need to implement.
So you need to lock the lock primitive and the other one is signaling, right? The signal
in the events or condition variables. So the condition variables basically you can think
you can do it because you can one possibly do it to wait to use a semaphore and you wait
for a semaphore and the way you do it you do it use a p operation on the semaphore.
If you remember the p operations decrement the semaphore it has a value greater than
one. If it has a value greater than the semaphore value is zero then you wait. And then signaling
it's use other operation which is v which is just increments the semaphore. So if you
are waiting on a semaphore because the value is zero and I am incrementing the semaphore
value to one I am going to basically wake you up. I'm going to signal it. So does this
work? Okay. So one reason this may not work because if you call wait in the critical section
then it doesn't release a lock. And you have the problem I just mentioned earlier that
you are going to sleep while you hold the lock so no one else can enter the critical
section. And in order to avoid this problem you can think to have something like this.
It's like when you wait this is the implementation of the wait function and you release a lock
then you do semaphore p and again you try to decrement and you acquire the lock. So
basically in this sense is that if you are going to sleep because semaphore is zero your
lock was released. And the signal is the same. It does this work. It doesn't work for a
series of reasons but one of the things which is again we discussed last time but I want
to emphasize is that the condition variables when you send a signal there is no history.
If no one is waiting on a condition variable and someone sends a signal for that condition
variable that signal was lost. That is if you send a signal upon a condition variable
on which no one is listening is waiting and now someone else comes after you send the
signal waiting on the condition variable that someone else is going to be stuck is going
to wait. This is different from semaphore. The semaphores have history because you are
incrementing the semaphore. So take the same scenario. No one is waiting but now the semaphore
you called a signal and you use a semaphore implementation. What will happen then? What
will happen then? Then you are going to increment the semaphore. Now the semaphore is one. So
next if someone else waits on the semaphore, tries to wait, it's no longer waiting because
the semaphore one is going to decrement to zero and it's going to go ahead. This is one
of the key differences. This is exactly what I mentioned. This is a key difference in the
semantics. So the main problem here is that, another way to say it is that P and V are
commutative. It doesn't matter in which order happens. The value of the semaphore will be
the same. On the other hand, the condition variable are not because like we explained,
if you send a signal on a condition variable and no one is waiting on that condition variable,
that signal was lost.
So here is another try. Let's try to fix the problem and how do we try to fix the problem
here? You are going only to increment the semaphore if there is no one waiting on the
MPQ or if the Q is MP for that condition variable, the condition variable associated with the
semaphore. So is that working? It doesn't work either because for instance, you cannot
look at the semaphore. You cannot look at contents on semaphore Q. There is no primitive.
There is no API for that. So that's one of the reasons it doesn't work. And also there
is a race condition. The signaler can just signal after the lock release and before the
waiter executes semaphore P. Here is where the race condition can happen.
So anyway, it turns out that it's actually possible to implement this correctly with
semaphore, but it's a very complex solution. So the takeaway here is that the monitor is
a very useful abstraction. And one way to see that it's useful abstraction is by the
fact that it's very hard to implement it using more primitive or more basic abstractions
like semaphores.
So in conclusion, monitors, they synchronize the present synchronization of the logic,
encapsulate the synchronization logic of the program. And this means that to wait for some
event to happen and the ability to signal that event. And the typical monitor based
program, it looks something like that, right? You lock the critical section, you acquire
the lock on the critical section where you are going to manipulate state variables. If
you remember in the previous lecture, we have to acquire the lock while we are manipulating,
we are updating, or we are testing that active writers or waiting writers, active readers,
waiting readers. And you are going to wait if necessary for some condition to happen.
Right? And in another, typically in another critical section, you are going to signal
that condition and that condition becomes true. You are going to signal. So now you
are going to wake the threads, one or more threads, which are waiting for that condition
variable to happen. If you send a signal, only one thread remember is going to wake
up that if you send broadcast, then all the threads which are waiting on that condition
variable are going to wake up.
Okay. So now question is about, what about these languages? What is the support in today's
languages? And there is every language has some level of support for synchronization
primitives, some better than others. Like for instance, for the C language, you do have,
they do have support, you do have support for locks, right? Now with this support for
locks, so you need to be careful if you are going to return, right? Because if you acquire
the lock at the beginning of your function, naturally you are going to release a lock
at the end of the function, but you need also to release a lock at every time you return
from that function. So you need to be very careful because if you forget to do that,
you can, you can happen, a deadlock can happen. Okay. Now the other problem is that in C,
it's actually, or unfortunately you can also jump and if you are going to jump into the
program again, you can create that lock.
So it's, but even when you have more locks, things are just becoming even more complex,
right? Because you need to keep track in the program as a developer where when to release
every each lock and it's the program is not even going to look uniform in the same function,
right? So depending on where you are, locate the locks and so forth. So for example, it
turns, you have to at least two locks in this example, for some of them, only one lock.
So you can imagine that it's very easy to make mistakes. And again, once you make a
mistake, you run into the danger to create deadlocks. Okay. Of course, you know, that
another problem I just mentioned why it's hard in C to get locks because in C you can
also jump around. You can have a go to statement, right? Now you can think about, you can use
go to statement to provide something syntactic sugar to make it easier, right? So instead
of having two instruction release and return, you are going to have, you are going to jump
to an address where you are going to release a lock and basically return, right? So you
can write only one instruction to release and to release and return a lock. Now the
big obvious problem is that if you need to release two locks, you need to write another
kind of instruction to release both locks and so forth, right? Or to organize a code
so that when you jump to one address, you release both locks and you jump on another
address, you release only one lock. It's again, very complicated. Okay.
C++ again has support for locks and now with C++ actually things are even a little bit
even more complicated when you have locks. Why? Because you have, if you remember in
C++, you have exceptions, right? And if you get an exception during the critical section,
you jump to three exception, but you still hold the lock. Okay. So you don't release
a lock. So in order to release a lock, you need to catch every exception and release
a lock explicitly. Okay. Because if you don't do that again, you are going to go and treat
the exception and with, while you still have the lock. So you don't release a lock. Okay.
Now fortunately C++ has a new version of locks, which is called lock guards. And you can think
about this lock like a variable. And the cool thing about that is that you acquire the lock
when you declare the variable and whenever the variables is going to go out of scope,
the lock is automatically released. Okay. So you don't need to, you basically don't
have an explicit instruction to release a lock. You just declare the lock as a variable. And
in that function, everything under that lock is a function. And whenever you, or method
because it's C++, and whenever you are going to go out of scope returning, whether that's
basically, you know, still an exception or just return, then the lock is automatically
released. Okay. With Python, you have this other construct, which is pretty cool. Again,
you can declare lock like almost like a variable, and then you can use a statement with lock
to basically declare a critical section. So everything under this with lock is going to
be locked. It's under the, it's a critical section protected by the lock. And again,
when you are going to leave the block, the release of the lock happens automatically.
A little bit similar with bar blocks. And with Java goes one step farther and also provides
you, you know, what they call synchronized methods, right? So basically you can have
synchronized methods in a class. And basically the synchronized methods are, think about
that they protect all the variables in the class, in the object, by a lock, by an implicit
lock. Okay. So you can think about when you say public synchronized, then this method
automatically acquires a lock and releases a lock for everything, what is happening in
this particular method. Okay. So pretty cool. And Java also support monitors. Okay. You
can wait and you can also have the notified.
and notify all for us to notify when an event happens.
OK, any questions here?
OK, so announcements.
So tomorrow we have the midterm between 5 and 7 p.m.
It's a bit of a proctor over Zoom.
Please read the proctoring policies very carefully.
You can have one handwritten cheat sheet.
And in addition to that, upcoming deadlines are homework two.
It's due on Monday, next Monday, and the project, the first project is due next Monday.
OK.
Great.
So now let's switch gears and next we are going to start talking about scheduling.
OK, before talking about scheduling, remember about, you know, why do we need scheduling?
And remember about the user cannot thread models.
And before there is a question here.
Oh, I think it's 7 9.
Sorry, it's 7 9.
Thanks for...
OK.
Thank you.
OK, so in general, so you have user level threads, right?
Which are defined, say, with a pthread library.
And then you have the kernel thread.
And typically, unless otherwise specified, we assume that one user level thread is going
to be mapped in the kernel thread.
OK, so the kernel, and the kernel only see kernel threads.
OK, and the kernel responsibility is to share the resources, the CPU resources across threads.
OK.
And there are a few other ways to, you know, that you can also have many user threads mapping
on the same kernel thread or many user threads mapping on many kernel threads.
But in this particular case, and again, for unless otherwise specified, we are assuming
that it's one user thread mapped to one kernel thread.
And for each thread, if you remember, in a process, a process has at least one thread.
The kernel maintains a thread control block, PCB.
And what you have in the thread, you have the state of the thread when you suspend it.
And that's the state which is enough to resume the thread execution from the point where
it was suspended.
And this means the content of the registers, the program counter and the stack pointer.
OK.
In addition, some kernels are only belongs to the, some threads only belongs to the kernel.
And this is for the kernel to do some work in the background.
OK, so you can do some, maybe you can do compaction of the file or things like that.
So let's again look at this layout of, we have two processes here and one kernel process.
Each process here has a thread.
Remember, a process has at least one thread, the thread is a unit of execution and concurrency.
And a process owns, before the stack, it defines an address space which contains, besides the
stack, it contains a code, global variables and the heap.
And if you look at what happens in the kernel, what the kernel maintains for these processes,
it's going to maintain the PCB, the process control block.
And the kernel stack, the stack for the kernel stack for the process.
So when you are going to execute, you are going to run, say, for instance, things like
syscall on behalf of that process in the kernel.
And obviously the kernel has its own code and global variables and the heap.
OK, now, as you know, like a process can have more than one thread and here is a process
one, now have two threads, thread A and thread B.
And as you can see, the only thing which we are going to replicate is a stack in this figure.
OK, this thread has its own stack, but all threads in the same process, they share all
the rest of the address space, which means a code, global variables and the heap.
Right.
And remember in our example, in our model, we have one user thread per kernel thread.
So basically in the kernel, we are going to have now two threads, one for each user threads,
for process one.
OK.
And in addition, like I mentioned, the kernel itself can have some threads on its own to
do some activities in the background.
OK.
So these are used internally by the kernel, they don't correspond to any user thread.
OK, so now, so this is any question here.
The kernel thread, so the question is kernel thread an actual thread or just a block of
data in the kernel that stores the state?
Fundamentally, every thread is just a block of data, right?
When is not active and a bunch of pointers.
It's a data structure.
A thread is a data structure and there is some data associated with it.
Right.
OK, you have so in this particular case, you have oops.
Right, in that in this particular case, again, you have.
Thread control block and just, you know, what you have in the stack.
OK.
And when you run the threads, though, OK, then when you run the thread, you activate
the thread and now you have some active part of the thread, which is running, executing
the instructions on behalf of the thread.
Pointed by the program counter.
OK.
So that's that's what.
OK, why do we need another question?
It's a very good question.
Why do we need multiple kernel threads?
What is the benefit of having many over having one?
It's again, remember, the kernel does not see user threads.
Right.
The kernel only see kernel threads.
If your kernel has only one, there is only one kernel thread, the kernel only will schedule
that thread.
And now if the user wants to have multiple user threads, the threads, the only way for
the threads to have threads running in turn, while there is only one kernel thread is for
the thread to voluntarily release a CPU, basically say yield.
And then the yield will let another thread from the same process run.
OK.
So in this particular case, the application itself is responsible for allocating the time
across threads.
If you map a user thread on a kernel thread, then the operating system automatically make
sure that allocates times, CPU times to each thread.
The application doesn't need to do anything.
Where are the PCBs and PCBs stored in the kernel data segments?
Typically, they are going on heap because they are allocated at new processes and new
threads are created.
OK.
So now, remember about the stack segment.
So you want to do this and this actually has yield.
And you remember that you have this kind of two procedures.
One procedure calls B and B is calling while and from time to time yield.
And what happens in this case when you call yield, then you release and again, when I
say yield, there are three implementation of yield.
One implementation of yield, which is gives a control.
This is a yield here.
It's a syscall.
It's an operating system call, kernel call.
But there is also yield when you have only one single kernel like we discussed in the
past, which is only at the application level.
It's a library in the application.
And when you do the yield, you just jump to another function in the application level
to another function in the same to another thread in the same process.
So in this case, the yield is basically operating with a kernel.
It's a syscall.
And when you call yield, you basically tell to the kernel to run another thread and the
other thread in this case is going to be B.
And sorry, the other thread will continue to run the same code.
And that code will again run call A and A call B, B starts to execute while, and then
it calls yield and then it relinquishes the CPU.
And then the kernel is going now to go and back to S.
Okay.
So basically the important thing is to see here that when a yield happens, you ask the
kernel, the red things are executed by the kernel, the blue things are executed by the
application, but run new thread, you basically ask the kernel to find a new thread and run
it.
Okay.
If you don't have yield, then if you remember, how do we make sure that we still share the
CPU between different threads?
Well, you have a timer and the timer after you devise a time in time slices and every
at the end of every time slices, you have this timer interrupt.
And this is stated by the operating system and as a result, it's again, it's looking,
it suspend the current thread, which is executing.
And then it selects another thread to switch, switches to another thread.
Okay.
So you run a new thread.
And the same things happens when you now call a system call, say for instance, the copy
of file and IO operation, and that is a syscall.
And if it's a waiting operation, then the current thread is suspended and again, a new
thread is selected to run.
Okay.
So taking a step back, you've seen here a few use cases in which the thread voluntarily
yield to the CPU.
Another one, when you have the timer, the system timer forcing the suspension of the
current thread.
And here in the last case, you have a syscall, which is a waiting syscall, which leads to
the thread which invokes that call, waiting, so being suspended.
So in all these cases, you need to look for a new thread to run.
Okay.
And this is what the scheduling is about, right?
Which thread you are going to pick if there are multiple threads, which are going to be
able to run, are ready to run, which one you are going to pick.
That's it.
Okay.
And, you know, thread, you know, scheduling is complicated.
And this is a comment from Dennis Ricci, you know, one of the inventors of, you know, UNIX
and C.
And it's a comment which is in for scheduling, some scheduling functionality.
But the main point here, you know, you are not expected to understand it because it's
too complicated.
So scheduling is complicated.
And the reason it's complicated because it has a time dimension, right?
You need to be careful about the time.
And that's part of, you need to integrate the scheduling.
Okay.
So run your thread.
It's about, and this is, it's about, you look at the threads which are ready.
And you select the next one to schedule and run the next one, run this next, the selected
thread.
Okay.
So that's it.
So the rest of the lecture, we are only going to focus on scheduling.
And again, the scheduling is selecting which thread to schedule out of all currently threads
which are ready to run.
Now, this is basically a diagram about the flow in the scheduler, a flow diagram of the
scheduler.
This is a CPU, right?
We are running the side on the CPU and it's a ready queue.
The scheduler is going to pick one thread from the ready queue to run.
Once, while the thread is running, the thread can go into have IO request and it can wait
for the IO request to complete.
It can wait for the time slice to expire.
This is going to for the timer to kick in, say after 10 milliseconds.
You can wait, for instance, if you fork a chilled child, you wait for that child to
finish to execute or to execute.
And you can also be interrupted by an interrupt.
Okay.
And then once you are waiting, it's over, you are going to be put back in the ready
queue.
And again, scheduling is about deciding which thread from the ready queue to schedule.
Next.
And when you say automatically, when you say to, you know, the scheduling, it's about which
task to run.
If I have more than one task, then I automatically have a queue.
So queues are integrated, you know, are fundamental part of the schedule.
You are waiting in a queue to be scheduled.
So CPU scheduling has been a big area of research since what?
50 years, for 50 years.
And there are many implicit assumptions and many kind of scheduling problems.
Like you can have one program per users, you can have one separate program or multiple
separate programs.
Programs are independent.
And so you make these assumptions to simplify the problem, to make it more predictable.
Right.
And therefore to solve it.
But this problem is much more complicated.
That's why there are so much research since 70s.
Because there are different concepts.
So when you decide to run a new thread, to pick a new thread to run.
Okay.
When you decide that, which thread you are going to pick according to what?
The one is ahead of the queue.
Is that fair?
What does fairness mean?
Right.
If I, yeah, if you.
And for different programs, it's like for different user, okay, maybe fair is that I
get the same amount of CPU like you get.
But talk about the applications, because the applications are applications which are IO
heavy, like an editor.
Spend very little CPU.
Basically it's waiting for you to type in new characters.
Or you can have like compilers.
If you do run a compilation job, then that's very CPU bounded, right?
So what does mean to be fair between these two kinds of jobs, right?
No matter what is your answer there, at the end of the day, you need to allocate the CPU
if you have one CPU or you have fewer CPUs than threads, we need to allocate to slice
the CPU and allocate different time slices to different threads.
So now there is another implicit assumption which is done by today's, but many of the
today's schedulers, operating system schedulers.
And that assumption is that many of the applications are bursty applications.
This means that they use a CPU for a little bit and then wait.
Then use again the CPU for a little bit, then wait.
And like application, like user facing applications, like editors, like anything you interact with
your computer, web browsers, any other thing like that, fit in this category, right?
Because most of the time that program waits for your input and while it waits, it doesn't
need to use a CPU.
And again, this program is alternating between CPU and I/O, like we discussed.
And so this means that you want to prioritize for short bursts, right?
Because you want to be responsive the program.
So this is one way to think about the schedulers.
If you think about scheduling discipline, I want to prioritize the short bursts, right?
Because the studies are facing, they are going to be interactive.
I provide good experience to the user.
And if something is longer burst, takes for a while, like a compilation job, it can be
lower priority.
So keep in mind that one.
Now we move on.
What are the other possible policies?
What are the properties you want for a scheduler?
And there are many of these properties.
Again, that's the reason or the many of these policies.
And that's the reason for it to have a lot of research in scheduling for decades.
So one, it's obviously meaning my response time, right?
You want to finish the task, the job as fast as possible.
Okay.
Fair enough.
Another one is maximize the throughput.
The throughput is about the number of queries per second, right?
Number of transaction per seconds.
And here, this is more complicated because there are two parts.
It's an IO part and the CPU part.
And it's also, if you, in general, and it's also one way typically you maximize the throughput.
It's batching, which hurts you with elapsed time.
So for instance, let me give you an example.
If I want to optimize each response time, the latency of each read to the disk, it's
one problem.
If I want to maximize the number of reads to the disk, it's another problem.
In the first case for each read, I'm going to execute separately and trying to execute
as fast as possible.
In the second case, instead of executing one read at a time, I'm going to batch the reads
and send them to the disk.
And the disk can do a better job of serving these reads in a more intelligent way.
So it's going to increase the throughput to serve more reads per second, but at the expense
of the latency, because now I need to wait for the batch to complete in order to get
the result for my read.
So typically this is one trade-off between the latency and the throughput.
The other thing is about, let me give you another example just to talk about it.
If you want, you go to grocery.
I know that many of you now you are buying online, but think about when you go to grocery.
If I need something right now, I need milk, in order to reduce the latency by when I'm
going to get the milk, I'm going to go right away and get milk.
But typically we don't do that.
And I get the milk, say, in half an hour.
What we do is basically we batch and when we go to grocery, we buy many things.
So I can batch.
So instead of buying milk today, I'm going to go to grocery and I'm going to wait until
tomorrow because I have a lot of other things to do.
And then I get the milk by tomorrow.
So it's lower latency.
But in terms of the throughput, I'm going to get a lot of more things at the same time.
So the throughput will be higher, but the latency will be lower.
And another thing it's about policy could be like we discussed in the past is fairness.
You want to share the CPU in some equitable way.
Good.
So now next we are going to go through some scheduling policies and we are going to start
from simple to more complex.
And for each of them, we are going to look at what properties they have and what we are
going to again compare them based on some metric.
And typically the metric we are going to compare them is response time.
How long it takes to finish things.
This is what we are going to do now.
One of the first and the simplest scheduling discipline is first come first serve or first
in first out.
And this is like you go to grocery everywhere.
This is exactly what it is.
People are served in the order in which they arrive to the queue.
And now let's assume that now we have three processes.
And let's assume that we first come first serve, each process runs to completion.
Is the remaining of this lecture I may use processes and jobs interchangeable, but it
should be clear from context.
So now P1 say takes 24 time units, let's say 24 seconds.
P2 takes three seconds and P3 takes three seconds.
Now suppose the processes, these processes arrive in the queue in the order P1, P2, P3.
With the first come first serve scheduling discipline, we are going to serve to run the
processes in the same order.
First P1, then P2, then P3.
So now let's see when each of these processes finishes.
And what is the waiting time?
The waiting time is how long you wait before being scheduled.
And when you complete.
So the first process doesn't wait any time, so starts immediately.
The P2 waits 24 seconds for P1 to finish and P3 waits for 27 seconds for P1 and P2 to finish.
And so the average waiting time is zero plus 24 plus 27 over 370.
Now if you look at completion terms of the finishing time, P1 takes 24 seconds to finish,
P2, 27 seconds from the time was submitted and P3, 30 seconds.
So again, in this particular case, we assume that all processes arrive basically the same
time, but they are inserted in the queue in the order P1, P2, and P3.
So let's see.
It's actually a very good question.
Is there any way for the kernel to estimate now the burst time of a job without actually
running it?
That's an excellent question.
I think in general now, and you'll see this is one of the problem with the scheduling
discipline, one of the many.
But you know, in some cases you can now it, for instance, from historical data.
So in some cases it is possible.
But in this case, again, this scheduler doesn't even care about the running time of a job,
of a process.
It doesn't care.
It just executes them in the order they arrive at the queue.
But we are going to go back and touch this very question later in the lecture.
Okay, good.
So now if you look at this one, I'm just curious, can you think about a better way to schedule
these processes to have lower completion time?
Yeah, run P1 after P2 and after P3.
Very good.
That's very good.
Okay.
So you see this is a problem.
It's exactly the problem with this kind of scheduler.
It's very simple.
Very simple.
But the problem is that if you have some short processes, they can get stuck behind a long
process.
This is called convoy effect.
Think about you go to the grocery and you are going to be stuck behind someone which
has 100 items in the cart.
You don't want that, right?
And you have only three or four items to buy.
How does a solver grocery this problem?
How they try to alleviate this problem?
Express lanes.
Yes.
And in express lanes, there is a cap on the size of the job, of the size of the process.
So it's a cap, you can only have 15 items, no more than 15 items.
To cap basically how long it takes to process.
Indeed, this is a much better answer.
So now the average waiting time is three instead of I think 24 and 13, I believe instead of
27.
Yeah, so it's three instead of 17 and 13 instead of 27.
Okay, good.
So we learned that.
Now here is another one.
And this is implemented by many schedulers, this policy.
Round robin, right?
So round robin, first come first serve, depends on the order you submit.
The round robin uses preemption.
It's exactly, we discussed this many times so far.
So basically here, you do not wait for a process to finish execution.
Instead you preempt it after you let it run, say for until it blocks because wait for something
or until it runs for say 10 milliseconds and then preempt it.
You suspend it and you run another process.
So this is a round robin.
And the reason it's called round robin is because you take it one by one.
You have 10 processes.
Okay, now I run for 10 milliseconds one process.
I run process two for 10 milliseconds, process three for 10 milliseconds and so forth.
After 100 milliseconds, I am back to running process one.
So in this case, each process gets one over, if there are N processes, each process gets
one over N of the CPU time.
And if a time quanta is Q, then each time gets for Q time quanta.
And each process has to wait how long?
N minus one over Q, right?
So if you have 10 processes and each process takes the time quanta is 10 milliseconds,
it takes for an entire round, it takes 100 milliseconds, but for one process, therefore
it transfers 10 milliseconds and it waits for another 90 milliseconds for its turns
to come.
So it's N minus one, in that case 10 minus one, nine times 10 is 90 milliseconds.
And, and here it's very interesting to look at and consider it like what happens when
the Q is very large, right?
When the Q is very large, if the Q is larger than the largest running time of a process,
then this, it provides identical results like first come first serve.
If Q is very small, you have a lot of interleaving between the processes.
Okay.
So now there is a trade off here.
Ideally you want to be as small as possible.
However, remember about context switching, there is an overhead of the context switching.
So if this quanta is too small or time slice is too small, then you can spend more time
in switching between the contexts than actually running the processes.
Okay.
So sounds good.
the chat default instead of having using the Q and A. I'm trying, I'm going to try
to answer and I decided right in the past to answer both from Q and A and the chat.
But if people prefer to use chat, I'm fine with that.
Okay.
So, so here is an example time quanta 20 for our example, right?
So what will happen?
You first run P1, remember, now and look at, here we take another example in which you
have four processes P1, P2, P3, P4, which takes 53, 68 and 24 seconds respectively.
And now say the time quanta is 20 and this is your order in which you arrive at the Q.
P1, P2, P3, P4.
So let's see what happens.
First we start with the first process P1 and it runs for 20 seconds, 20 seconds.
And then after 20 seconds, we interrupt it.
We preempt it and we start running P2.
P2 is only eight seconds.
So it's less than the time quanta.
So after eight seconds finishes.
So we are done.
And now you are moving to the next one, which is P3.
P3 takes 68 seconds.
So therefore it runs for 20 seconds after which is preempted, after we run P4 for 20
seconds after which is preempted.
Now you come back for P1 and P1 you only run 20 seconds out of P1.
So you have another 33 seconds to run.
So you run 20 seconds for 20 seconds and you preempt.
Now P2 is done.
Now you need to run it.
And you are P2, P3.
From P3 we already run P3 for 20 seconds.
So now I have another 20 seconds.
We take another 20 seconds to run for P3 after which we preempted.
And then things continue like this.
You can easily follow up on it.
The one interesting case is that at the end you have only P3 remaining to run.
So you are going to run, you have only one process in the queue.
So you are going to run the process over and over again.
So what is the waiting time here?
Well, it's more complicated to look at the waiting time because for P1 you have, what
is the waiting time?
You run P1 three times.
Here at time zero, at time 68, at a time on 12.
So the waiting time initially is zero.
The second time on your run at time 68,
the waiting time of what?
68 minus 20, because it finishes,
previously P1 finishes the cushion at time 20.
And for P1, when the last time on P1 runs,
it started at 125,
but the previously it finished at time 88.
So it's 125 minus, sorry, 112.
Sorry, I'm sorry.
P1 starts at 112 and previously finishes at time 88.
So it's 112 minus 88.
So the total waiting time is 72.
P2 starts at time 20.
So it says, runs only one time is 20
and so forth for the other processes.
So what is the average waiting time?
Well, you add all the waiting times of all processes
and you divide by four.
So it's 66 and a quarter.
The same completion time, right?
The P1 completes at time 20.
Sorry, P1 completes at time 125, sorry.
P2, this is 125 here.
P2 completes at time 28.
P3 completes at time 153.
And P4 completes at time 112.
So the average waiting completion time is 104 and a half.
Okay?
So round robin, what are the pros and cons?
Better for short jobs.
If you are a short jobs, your turn will come faster,
especially if you are at the end of the queue.
But now it adds context switching.
It's more context switching overhead.
Okay?
So, and it's again, if you have the,
you know, the response time, right,
is like, it can decrease, here is an example
to illustrate how you round robin,
decrease the response time,
and assume the duration of a task now is 10
and of the other one is one, P2 is one.
We are using the task and processes interchangeable.
And here, if P1 runs first and P2 next,
the average response time is 10 and a half.
Okay?
However, if you use a time quanta,
that was a time quanta 10, where it's larger than any burst.
If you use a time quanta of 10, of five,
P1 will run only for five seconds.
Then you run P2 after you run P1.
So the average response time in this case will be 8.5,
because P2 finishes at time six,
where P1 finishes at time 11.
Right?
And now, okay, so now think about,
if you have two tasks, but they are one time unit,
and you average the quanta is 10,
then it's obviously the average response time is one and a half.
And if it's time quanta is one, it's the same.
So the point here is that if the average,
if the time quanta is larger than the burst length,
there is a time it takes a task or a process to complete,
okay, then it doesn't matter.
There is no difference in the average response time.
Okay?
Now, obviously if now,
if the quanta is smaller than the time it takes
to complete for a task or a process,
then this is an interesting case here is 0.5.
So basically you run P1 for 0.5,
then P2 for 0.5, then P1 for 0.5, and P2 for 0.5.
So if you look at the average response time, it's 175.
So it's larger, it's larger.
Okay?
So that's kind of interesting, right?
So we, at some point, at least in this scenario,
we reduce the time quanta,
and instead of the response time to decrease,
it's actually increase.
And it's very easy to see why this happens.
And this happens when, in particular,
when all tasks or processes take the same amount of time.
Right?
Because everyone takes the same amount of time.
If you see one first come first serve, you know,
it's your first time you finish the first process
and the second process and sub-process and so forth.
So clearly the first process finishes earlier
than the last process.
But now if you have very small time quanta
and you do round robin between them,
you do a little bit of each of them,
you serve a little bit of each of them,
then all of them are going to finish
almost at the same time.
Meaning that all of them are going to finish
more or less when the last one finishes.
So that's why is the intuition why this round robin
actually can also lead in some cases
to increasing the response time, not only decreasing it.
How do we implement round robin in the kernel?
Well, it's using the timer interrupt.
Every time a quanta expands,
every time a quanta expires, you trigger a time interrupt.
Right?
And this is what your project two is going to be about.
Okay.
So in summary, the round robin,
if the time slice or quanta is too big,
the response time will suffer.
If it's infinite, it's basically first come first serve.
Or five.
If the time slice is too small, the throughput might suffer.
And in some cases also the response time might suffer.
So it's,
the actual choice of time slice has to be
large enough.
So it amortizes the context switch overhead.
So I think it has to be a few times,
maybe one order, two order of magnitude
larger than the context switch.
That's basically what it is.
Right?
So basically you want,
if the typical context switch is one millisecond,
you want the time quanta to be say 100 milliseconds,
two order of magnitude larger.
Okay?
That's the rule of thumb.
This is an example again, to drive back home,
like assume that you were in ignore,
ignore the context switching overhead.
Is round robin always better than first cast for serve?
And like we discussed, the answer is no.
This drives home the point by having another example,
in which we have 10 jobs and each job
or 10 takes 100 seconds.
Right?
And the round robin scheduler,
the time quanta is one second.
Okay?
So if this happens in the round robin,
in the five of case, or first count for serve case,
the first job finishes after 100 seconds,
the second after 200 seconds, the last one after 1000 seconds
while in the round robin case,
the first job finishes after 991 seconds,
the second one after 992 seconds and so forth.
Right?
So both round trip time and first count for serve
finish at the same time, but they are very response time
is much worse for round trip time.
So round trip time, sorry, not round trip time.
Round robin, it's bad when all jobs have the same length.
Remember.
And there are other reason for each round robin may suffer.
With round robin, you can switch between processes.
If you switch between processes, the cache will suffer.
Right?
Because each process can be a different program
and is going to need to run different code,
it's accessing different data.
So it's going to not benefit from the caching
from the previous process.
Okay?
So it needs to again bring everything into the cache.
In the case of the first count for serve,
then one program or one process run until finishes.
So it's going to maximize the benefit of cache.
Okay?
This is another example here.
In our, we have this one of the previous examples
we have three, four processes, which takes 8, 24,
53 and 68 seconds respectively.
And here, best first count for serve.
What is the best order?
P1,
P2, P3 and P4.
And what is the wait time?
Right?
This is the best order.
Best first count for serve, right?
And you start with P2, then P4, then P1, then P3.
Okay?
So what is the wait time?
For wait time for P1 is 32, for P2 is zero,
for P4 is eight and P3 is 85.
So you have 31 and a quarter.
Worst first count for serve is when does this happen?
When you run first P3, then P1, then P4, then P2.
So reverse order.
And in that case, the worst case is 83 and a half.
The corresponding completion times
for the best first count for serve is 69 and a half.
And for the worst one,
it's 121 and three quarters.
And in the meantime, in between here,
you have four different time quanta.
For this is the result for the time quanta
when time quanta is eight and one and five and 10.
Okay?
So please, as an exercise, you know,
take a sheet of paper and you can check the results
for different time quanta.
Great exercise to better understand how round robin
scheduling is working.
And as you can see here,
the average waiting time for the round robin
is between, as you might have expected,
is between the first count for serve
and the best first count for serve
and the worst first count for serve
and the same for the completion time.
Okay?
Okay.
So let me see, there are a few questions here.
Since we cannot estimate the runtime of each burst,
how can we schedule the order in each first count?
Scheduling is the best.
That's a very good question.
It's again, you can use historical data if available,
but one reason we study the best first count for serve,
which is also called like you'll see,
shortage of first for obvious reasons,
is that this is like a baseline.
You can actually, as you'll see,
you can prove that running shortage of first,
using shortage of first,
leads to the lowest wait time or completion time.
Okay?
Another question, is the best first count for serve order
is shortest or longest?
The best first count for serve is a shortest.
It's when you start with the shortest job first.
The worst first count for serve is the longest
and you start with the longest job first.
Okay?
And you can see here about like P2
and where P2 is, we are all over the place.
It's very sensitive, right?
Depending of where, depending when it's scheduled, right?
You go from zero to 145, right?
Which is pretty bad.
While for P3, which is the largest,
it's more stable, right?
And it's natural, right?
Because the longer, the bigger you are,
the more you are going to dominate the wait time
and also the completion time.
Okay, this is P3 and this is P2.
There are many other scheduling disciplines.
Another scheduling discipline here,
we are going to talk a little bit about is priority.
You can have different jobs here
and different jobs have different priorities.
Like for instance, jobs which are associated
with interactive user interaction,
they can have higher priority
than jobs who are doing compilation
where, or jobs which are going to process data
you receive on the network, from the network.
They can have higher priority, okay?
So, and with this scheduler,
you assign a job a priority
and then you always execute the highest priority job first.
So in this particular example,
you are going to execute job one, job two, and job three
before you execute job four.
And you execute job four before you execute job five,
job six, and job seven, okay?
So one of the biggest problem with this one is starvation.
What is starvation here?
Assume that you always have new jobs
arriving with the highest priority.
So as long as you have jobs
with the highest priority arriving,
you cannot process jobs with lower priority.
You can also have this, what is called priority inversion.
We talk a little bit about that in a different lecture,
but here is what assume that say job five
owns a lock after which job one waits.
So job five, okay, it's in the critical section.
It was preempted by a higher priority job.
And then job one comes
and wants to enter the critical section,
but it cannot because job five still owns a lock.
And it cannot be scheduled before job one.
So that's why you have a deadlock.
There are many ways to fix the problem.
We are not going to talk as much about this,
but there are heuristics and dynamic priorities.
Like you'll see, if a job is too much at a high priority,
then you are going to push it down to a lower priority.
And there are many other heuristics,
but it's important for you to know about this problem
that strict priority can lead to starvation
and can lead to deadlock.
Now, what about scheduling fairness?
Oops, sorry.
So strict priority, what we now solve,
what we see clearly is not fair, right?
Because by definition, priority is not fair, right?
You give priority to processes the highest priority.
And so the fairness is at odds with the prioritization.
And round robin on the other hand is fair, right?
Because there is no difference between the jobs.
You give to each of the jobs at time quanta
until it finishes and you go round robin across the jobs.
But you'll see that the trade-off is like fairness,
which is round robin, one of the policies is round robin,
can hurt the average response.
Okay.
And how do you implement the fairness?
Again, this is, you can do round robin.
There are other ways to get some,
even if you have priority scheduling,
there is an ad hoc version in which if you wait
for too long on a lower priority queue,
your priorities bump up until you eventually get
to the higher priority queue and then you can run.
Now let's go to answer the...
Okay, so let me answer this question before
and then I'm going to stop because we are done.
So the best first-comforts order is shortest to longest.
Okay.
So, sorry, it's, yes.
The best first-comforts order is shortest to longest.
That's correct.
And we are over time.
So we are going to stop here.
We are going to continue Thursday to talk about scheduling.
And if there are any other question,
I'll be happy to answer.
Until then, good luck at MiTERO.
(silence)
.
[BLANK_AUDIO]