Okay.
Hello everybody.
So welcome to the 11th lecture.
So hopefully you hear me.
And today we are going to continue our discussion about scheduling.
We are going to learn a bit about fairness, real time, and making forward progress, avoiding
starvation and do one or two case studies.
So one thing just to start with, this was a question I got from some people also before
the midterm.
It's about what is the operating system scheduling?
Processes or threats?
And the answer obviously is threats.
A process has at least one threat.
So when a process has exactly one threat, then you can think about it's interchangeable.
The kernel will schedule either a process or a threat, you can say.
But obviously when a process has multiple threats, kernel threats, then the operating
system will schedule independently each threat of the process.
Okay.
Now, the one thing to keep in mind is that when you switch between two contexts, switching
between two threads, if you remember, which belong to the same process, that's much quicker
because they are living in the same address space.
So you do not need to switch the address space.
However, when you switch between two threads, which are in different processes, then you
need also to switch the address space.
And that's much more expensive.
Think about one order of magnitude more expensive to switch, to context switch between two threads
in different processes, then switching between two threads in the same process.
Okay.
And also remember here that actually there is this multi-threading or simultaneous multi-threading
or hyper-threading, that's kind of the hardware level, which allows you to run multiple threads
on the same core.
But from the operating system and from the application, the only difference is that with
hyper-threading, you can run more threads, kernel threads at the same time.
That's the only difference.
Okay.
Nothing more.
Now, we discussed last time we did first come first serve, and we also ended up with this
kind of discipline, which is when we look at the best first come first serve, if you
know, we are starting with the smallest job first, and then to minimize the waiting time
and to minimize the completion time.
Okay.
So, obviously the question here is that for that we need to know the future.
And if we know the future, can we mirror the best first come first serve?
And the answer is obviously yes, we all be set what is the discipline.
And that is to run the first job first, right?
So whatever job takes the least run, it has priority over other jobs.
Okay.
And there are two versions of that.
One it's a preempt, it's non-preemptive version and one and the other one is preemptive version.
As the name implies for the non-preemptive version, you run each job all the way to completion.
In the preemptive version, you are going to can preempt the existing jobs for, for instance,
if an existing jobs, say still 10 seconds to run, and now a new job arrives, which has
only one second to run, the new job is going to preempt the existing job because it has
only one second to finish while the previous, while the existing job still has 10 seconds
to finish.
Okay.
And this is about shortest remaining time first, right?
And this is a preemptive version of shorter job first.
Okay.
So, so remember about that.
So this is optimal and you can show that this is optimal from the point of view of reducing
or minimizing the completion time.
Okay.
So, so keeping, keep, keep in mind, this is an optimal schedule basically.
Now so it's so one, one question here is that when you have a shortest remaining time first
and if you want to compare with first come first serve, the one question is what if all
jobs have the same length because it's all jobs at the same length, what you are going
to do, all of them are going to take the same time.
And in this case, there is no difference between them, right?
Because it doesn't matter in which order you are going to run because they have, you need
to break the ties because they all have the same length in some arbitrary fashion and
first come first serve is one of these ways to break the ties.
And you are going to get the same results.
Obviously if the jobs have varying length, then with the shorter remaining time first
is going to prioritize obviously the short jobs and they are not going to go to be stuck
behind the long ones.
Remember that the first come first serve, they didn't have, you may not have a good
average response time when you have a big job and then other small jobs are just stuck
behind the big job because all the small jobs are going to inherit the completion time,
the running time of the big job because they have to wait after it.
Here is a simple example to illustrate the benefit of the shortest remaining time first
against the shortest remaining time first.
It's a preemptive version of shorter job first.
And here you have two jobs, A and B, and they are CPU bound, meaning that they use only
the CPU, say run for a week or for a long time.
And then you have another job C, which is IO bound.
This means that you do an IO operation in one, it takes one minute seconds to do IO operation,
like say read or write to the disk, but then you wait for nine milliseconds for the operation
to complete.
Okay.
So if you run one of the jobs at a time, then job A or B will use 100% of the CPU and 0%
of the IO of the disk.
While if you run C at the time, C will use 10% of the CPU and 90% of the disk.
So what will happen with first come first serve?
Once A or B is scheduled, then it's going to hold the CPU for two weeks together.
And they are going to get in because even if C starts to run, after one minute seconds,
it's going to give up the CPU because it has to wait for, you know, to get the IO operation
complete.
Right?
Now, what about round robin or shorter remaining time first in this particular case?
So let's see what happens.
So this is round robin and assume the round robin, the time slice is 100 milliseconds.
Okay.
So you're executing round robin every job.
So let's start with C. It's again, and say the time slice is 100 milliseconds again.
So you start with C. C runs for one millisecond and then gives up, yields the CPU because
it needs to wait for the IO operation to complete.
Then you have to run A and then B and C again.
Now A and B because they're CPU bounded, they are going to take their entire time quanta,
that is 100 milliseconds.
Right?
So in this case, a disk utilization, if you look about, is like from around when you schedule
C, A, B, C, then it takes to all of them to complete, takes 201 milliseconds, 100 for A,
100 for B and one for C. And out of this time, because you are exactly only one IO operation,
because you schedule C only once, the IO operation takes nine milliseconds.
So the disk utilization is nine over 201, which is 4.5 percent.
Very, very little.
Now let's say you do the round robin of one milliseconds.
If you do round robin of about one milliseconds, what happens?
You schedule C first, it takes one milliseconds.
Then C will have to wait for nine milliseconds is going to be in the waiting queue to wait
for the IO operation to complete.
And during these nine milliseconds, you are going to alternate between A and B, each of
them for one milliseconds, because they are ready to always run because they are only
CPU bounded.
And what you get here, the disk utilization is 90 percent.
Because C, it's already, once an IO completes, C is ready to launch the next IO.
The problem here is if you see, and this is great, maximize the disk utilization, but
in this particular case, you have a loss of context switches, right?
Because between A and B, you have a lot of context switches, you know, and at every one
millisecond.
Now, what happens is the shortest time first, the shortest time first, remaining time first,
sorry, shortest remaining time first.
Let's see what happens.
First, execute C, like in the previous two cases, it takes one millisecond and then it's
going to wait for nine milliseconds for the IO to complete.
So C is on the waiting queue, so now you need to schedule between A and B. Let's say you
schedule A. You are going to schedule A until C becomes again ready for execute and C will
become ready to execute when its IO has completed.
So after nine milliseconds.
So in the first nine seconds, you run A and now C is ready to execute and C takes only
one second.
So the remaining time to finish for C it's one millisecond while for A it's one week
minus nine milliseconds.
So we are going to schedule C. C again takes one millisecond to go to sleep because it's
just waiting for the IO operation to complete.
And now you have A and B. A remaining time is one week minus nine milliseconds.
The remaining time for B, we didn't run at all B, so it's one week.
So A is one week minus nine milliseconds, B is one week.
A will take shorter to complete to terminate, so therefore you are going to schedule again.
So you do C, A, C, A, C, A until A finishes.
Disc utilization 90% and much fewer context switches.
Any questions, please ask.
Let's make it again more interactive.
It's pretty hard to just stare at the screen.
So anyway, so now what is the problem with shortest time first?
Shortest remaining time first is starvation.
So what does it mean starvation?
Can someone tell me what starvation means and why we are going to have starvation in
this case?
Never getting to run B never is scheduled.
Yes, in the previous example, well, in the previous example, actually, after you finish
A you are going to eventually run.
So yes, B will wait a long time, but starvation means that it may never be, you may never
run a job.
OK, any other answer?
So starvation means that the job remains in the system without ever being run.
When can this happen?
That's great.
So Alison, so if you have a stream of short jobs, you always get new short jobs, then
the long job may never be scheduled.
That's exactly what happens.
OK.
The other problem with this shortest remaining time first is that you need to predict the
future, you need to know how long a job is going to take.
And there was a question or two last lectures about this.
And there are some ways, none of them is perfect.
One way is to rely on the users and as the users, how long will take the job or a job
will take.
But with this has certain problems.
First of all, you assume the user knows, which is not always true or which is rarely true.
And also you open yourself to an attack in the sense that a user, because if the user
knows that the system using the shortest remaining time first will declare a very short time,
even if the job will take long, because in this way, she can ensure that the job will
be scheduled.
The other thing which is not here is basically to keep the history.
If you run a job repeatedly, you look at the history and if you see how long you basically
assume that the past running time is a good predictor for the future running time for
the same job.
And you are going to use that prediction.
But anyway, so this is hard.
However, shortest running time first is still a very important discipline for one reason.
It represents a yardstick.
It's a baseline for measuring other policies when it comes to minimize the average response
time.
So it's optimal.
You cannot do it better.
So if you are designing a new scheduler, one of the metrics will be average response time
and you are going to compare the average response time of that new discipline or scheduling
disciplines you design against the shortest remaining time first.
The closer you are, the better you are.
So in summary, for shortest remaining time first, it's optimal with respect to average
response time, but it can be hard to predict the future.
You need to predict the future and this is hard and can be unfair here means also starvation.
The long jobs may never be scheduled.
So this is what I said in the early, this is one way to implement what I said in the
previous slides that one way is to predict is based on the past behavior.
So you look at how long a particular job or process, the burst time in the previous burst
time and you use that as a prediction for the future of times and for the future.
And one way is to do is to do this exponential averaging in which you are going to put away
against the duration of the last time the job runs and then discount to, and one minus
alpha for the existing prediction.
So you have an existing prediction and then you are going to put, you can multiply that
for existing prediction with a weight and then you add to one minus weight the last
running time of the job.
So at one extreme, if you wait with zero, the previous prediction, this means that you
don't care about the past execution, but the last one, because the weight will be one for
the last execution.
And if you have a small weight for the last execution, this means that you are going to
put a lot of weight on the previous executions before the last one.
So what about the fairness?
And this is a very important aspect we are going to talk about.
We discuss about first come first serve, not really fair.
We discuss about shortage of first, not really necessarily fair.
We discuss about Ron Robin, actually that's kind of fair.
And now, keep in mind that this kind of fairness is another very important metric we are going
to use to characterize the scheduler.
And fundamentally there is a strict, it's a hard trade-off between the average response
time and the fairness.
And if you remember, we had, last lecture we had this example between the round Robin,
which is fair because during one round you schedule every process or, you know, every
every job, and first come first serve.
If you remember, we are looking at equal length jobs.
And because if you really want to be fair, everyone will finish at the same time, so
everyone will be late.
So her job is response time, while if you are not fair, and you run everyone at comfort,
every job to completion, then the one which you get first are going to finish much earlier
than the last one.
So you are going to get better response time.
So keep in mind, the fairness may in general hurt the response time.
So how do you, and basically also have other scheduling discipline, like we are going to
learn about fixed priority, and the fixed priority is also fundamental and fair, with
a priority basically assign different jobs, different priorities, because you deem that
some jobs are more important than the others.
And by the way, whenever you say something is more important than the other, basically
you give up on the fairness at some level.
So how do you implement fairness?
One is round robin, but the fundamental thing is that to implement fairness, you need, in
some sense, to divide, to virtualize the CPU, you need to divide the CPU and give each job
a fraction of the CPU.
And now let's talk a little bit about Unix.
So in Unix, it's using, in original Unix, it's using priority scheduling.
So you have a bunch of priorities, and if you remember from last time, and the jobs
that are with the highest priority are going to run first, and jobs with a lower priority
can run only if there are no other jobs with higher priority which are ready to run.
So this is a call.
But now how you are going to get some fairness?
And there are many, many, many proposals.
One way to implement is lottery scheduling.
So this one, and it's a very nice analogy, is basically the lottery scheduling will give
each job some number of lottery tickets.
And each time slice, you randomly pick a winning ticket.
And on average, the CPU time is proportionally allocated to the number of tickets given to
each job.
Now how you can assign the tokens, right?
How you are going to-- and it turns out that the nice thing about this lottery scheduling,
you can approximate some of these other recipients.
If you want, or you can use to implement it.
If you want to implement shortest running time first, you can give to the small jobs
a much larger number of tickets, right?
And the long jobs get fewer tickets.
Now the nice thing is also you can avoid starvation.
If I give to each job at least one ticket, right?
At least one ticket.
Then that job is not going to be stuck forever because it will be at some point that each
ticket will be selected and therefore it will be scheduled.
So this is one advantage of our strict priorities, right?
So again, with strict priorities, if a job cannot run unless there is no other job ready
to execute, which has higher priority.
With this one, we say, okay, the jobs with a higher priority have more tickets, but job
with a lower priority have at least one ticket.
So now I will be stuck.
So here is one example.
Lottery scheduling, so assume that you have short jobs and long jobs and you have a job
get 10 tickets and long job get one ticket, right?
So if a short job gets 10 tickets and a long job gets one ticket, then the CPU get given
to the short jobs is 91%, right?
And the other one is 9%.
Because in total you have 11 tickets in the system, 10 for the short jobs, one for the
long jobs.
If you are going to give, you have two long jobs, okay?
And you zero short jobs, you are going to divide because each long job get one ticket.
So you have only two tickets in the system.
So each of the long jobs will get 50%.
If you have two short jobs, you have 50% each short jobs, you don't have any long jobs.
You have 10 short jobs and one long jobs.
You have now 101 tickets in the system because each short job will have 10 tickets.
So therefore the short jobs get, each short job get 9.9%.
All short jobs will get 99%.
The long job will get 1% and so forth.
Okay.
Let me see if there is a question.
Ah, since the scheduling is probabilistic, isn't there still the possibility that the
long job gets started for quite a while?
Yes, that's correct.
The long job can still wait for a while, but eventually is going to be selected.
While in, say for instance, with shorter job first or with strict priority scheduling,
a job might never ever be scheduled if there are always enough lower priority jobs in the
system.
Very good question.
Okay.
So, what if too many short jobs are in the system to give reasonable response time?
Well, you know, it can take a long time, so it can be hard to make progress, right?
Because there are too many jobs.
So it takes too long to get your tab.
Of course, one answer here is that, you know, kick some users out of the system.
So now let's take a step back and let's say, what are the kind of jobs you are expecting
to run on your computer?
And typically there is a mix of jobs.
Okay.
So one of them will have the short burst time and some of them longer burst times.
And let's think about what are these kinds of jobs?
What are the possible ones?
Some jobs are interactive jobs, right?
These are, you know, it's editors, your chat application, you're interacting with the browser.
And these are short bursts, right?
It's interactive, right?
With the short bursts, they have to respond quickly to the user in your interaction.
Okay.
Then there are other ones which are IO.
It's also IO, not necessarily the users, but they are waiting for networking to get data
from the network or for an IO to complete, right?
And there are others which are long running.
Like for instance, one example would be a compiler or one example you do training, machine
learning.
Okay.
And, you know, you'd expect here that if something is interactive, it has to get a higher priority
because it needs to provide the user good user experience.
And the one which are not in long running jobs, it's okay if they are not interactive
because they are running in the background, right?
It doesn't matter if a training neural network model is going to take five hours or five
hours and five minutes.
Okay.
The user will not realize.
So, again, in general, it's hard to characterize all the application, but again, you can classify
broadly in interactive applications.
They typically have short bursts and long running applications, which have obviously
longer bursts.
So in recognizing that, this is how Unix implements the scheduler.
This is multi-level feedback scheduling.
And the mind level scheduling is like it has a bunch of queues and each queue has a different
priority and a different time quan.
So the queue at the top has a highest priority and there were a task, it's a process, it's
a queue first and the same time quanta, it's eight milliseconds.
And if a job spends too much time on at some level is demoted to the next level, in this
case to the next queue, which is quanta of 16 milliseconds.
And if you spend too much in this level, at this level, you are demoted to the next queue,
which is first count for seven.
So the first two, each of these levels can use a different scheduling discipline.
The first two in this case can use round robin, the last one first count for seven.
So basically what does this mean is that if you have an interactive job, which has small
bursts, that will be first and queued at the first level, has a highest priority, it will
be scheduled quickly.
And if it's a small burst, then it relinquishes the CPU, goes to sleep.
So it will always remain at the first level.
Now consider a long job, like training a neural network.
It starts at the first level and after a while, say after several seconds, it's still running
right?
It's going to be demoted to the second level.
And the second level, if it stays and continues running for, say I'm just making up like for
another one hour, then it's pushed to the lower level.
So you can see that in this way, the jobs which takes a long time, they are going to
fall through these kind of different levels to the bottom level and will have lower priority.
It's a very nice mechanism, adaptive mechanism, in which that jobs with short bursts remains
a high priority, remains a high priority at high levels and the one is lower, which takes
a long time, they are going to be demoted naturally to the levels with a lower priority.
And the results really here, you can think of approximately the shortest remaining time
first, because if again, if the job is small enough, you always are executed with the highest
priority.
Again, between the queues, you have fixed priorities and then you can have different
time quanta like we saw in these examples between different queues.
Oh, here is a question.
This was probably about lottery scheduling.
Sorry for not seeing it.
Did short job, did a short job and long job run simultaneously?
Yes.
In that case, we assume, well, they don't run to completion.
We assume a lottery scheduling, assume a preemptive scheduling.
This is a preemptive scheduling discipline.
So you're basically, you know, each time quanta is again, you run a lottery and you award
the CPU to the winning ticket, to the process with the winning ticket.
So from that perspective, yes, they are interleaved.
The short jobs, the long run, long jobs are interleaved.
Now, obviously, if you know the scheduler, you can actually fool the scheduler.
And for instance, if I want, what can I do for my job to remain as a high priority?
Well, I'm going to insert some IO operations from time to time because IO operations put
this the process or the job to sleep and therefore it remain as a high in the top level queues.
And there are actually even games in which it's an old program game and you try to play
against competitors.
So the key is to do computation at a higher priority than the competitor.
And again, the way you do it, the way you are doing it, some of these game developers
just put a bunch of print Fs because the print Fs again, you have IO.
So the thread is put to sleep and then when you come back, it's going to go to the high
priority queue.
While if you don't have to go to sleep, you are going to fall through the levels to the
bottom level and you are going to be treated with a lower priority.
So it's fun.
Multi-core scheduling.
You have multiple core.
Now all the processors have multiple cores, your Mac has multiple cores, your PC has multiple
cores, your phones have multiple cores.
Algorithmically is not a huge difference now, but implementation wise, there are some things
you need to keep in mind.
And one thing to keep in mind is a cache coherence.
Every core has its own cache and therefore you want to have this affinity scheduling.
You want to schedule a thread on the same CPU when it turns calm.
Why?
Because if you do so, that thread, you can leverage the data of that thread, which is
still in the local cache of the same CPU.
If you schedule the thread on a different CPU, then that cache will not have any data
of that thread.
So spinlock and multiprocessor.
Let me just...
So it turns out that the one way actually to, especially for multiprocessors, is not...
There are two reasons why you use spinlocks.
And the spinlock is just waiting for some condition to become true and you can do the
test and set on a particular value.
It's like, think about acquiring the lock.
And there are two cases to use a spinlock.
One is typically when you have multiple threads to execute at the same time.
Like for instance, you have two threads which communicate between each other, so you have
to run them at the same time.
So you want then the threads to wait for each other to be scheduled at the same time.
So if one thread is scheduled first, the second thread, it has to wait for the second thread
to be scheduled in order for instance to start the communication.
And you use typically for that test and set.
Now, the problem is this test and set.
If this test and set is done on, you know, you have different threads on different cores,
the test and set you are going to enforce a write, right?
If you remember the test and set takes a value from the others.
and then set that value to one,
irrespective of what was the value before
and write it back in the memory
and then return the original value.
Okay, so this is what is test and set if you remember.
But if I'm going to write
and another test and set is going to read
from a different processor,
then you are going to,
the value has to go through the memory
and then go back between,
it's going to need to go to the other process
which runs the thread again,
it is in test and set.
So if two threads are going to test and set
and they run on different CPUs,
then you are going to ping pong the value
between each other without doing anything.
Okay?
Another way to do it,
if you need to do that,
is to do this test, test and set.
And basically instead of doing,
having in the wild test and set,
in the wild you have the value,
just look at the value
and you look for the value for the acquiree,
look for the value to become zero.
And then, so this is going to just do a read.
So you read local value always.
And then you are going to do again a wild test and set
if the value read is zero.
And the reason it was a second test and set
is because the race condition,
because you don't want,
because you want to acquire the lock in this case,
or which means to set the value to one
and you don't know the race condition
is that two threads executing test and set at the same time,
they receive the value zero
and then the both of them,
they are going to set to one.
In order to avoid that,
you do a test and set again to the value
and you have only one will succeed
because test and set is going to be atomic.
But again, the main point here is that you avoid a write
and because you avoid a write,
you are going to go through the main memory
and you are going to go to avoid a lot of context switches.
This, okay, that's great question.
Is this an issue of correctness or efficiency?
This is a question from Arshad.
Yes, it's about, this is about the efficiency.
It's not about correctness.
Both codes are correct.
Both using both test and set
and test and set are correct.
It's only about efficiency.
Okay, good.
And this is exactly why when these are used,
this spin locks and spin waiting,
when multiple threads, again, like I just mentioned,
work together on a multiple core,
try to schedule them together.
This is also called gang scheduling.
There are other ways to do it instead of using spin lock.
Another way is basically to tell the OS
to tell the application,
hey, I could schedule only three of your threads
and you take care.
You know that you have three slides running parallel.
So you configure the way you run the program,
knowing that you have only three slides
which are running in parallel.
Right.
By the way, there is another reason,
there is another example in which you do the spin locks.
And the reason is that if you expect
that you have an IO operation,
which we expect to finish very quickly.
Okay.
So, and this is to avoid context switches.
So say a context switch, it takes one millisecond,
but you are a program and you do an operation
which takes 0.1 milliseconds.
So you do not want to be just
suspending the link with the CPU.
And also it's not very effective for the system
because it takes one milliseconds,
which is wasted time to context switching to another slide.
Instead, you just do a,
you are waiting, busy waiting
for the IO operation to complete.
And then you wait only for 0.1 milliseconds
and then continue.
Right.
No context switching.
Yes, you wasted one 0.1 millisecond,
but it's shorter than one millisecond
since the context switching.
And you are going to get much better response time
because you are continuing to run
instead of waiting to be scheduled again to run.
Okay.
So announcements, congrats for finishing with term one.
We started to grade.
It will take a little bit of time.
We'll let you know for sure what is the EPA
to give you a grading on Monday.
Hopefully it will be very close to Monday after Monday.
Homework two is due on Monday
and project one code and final reporting member
is due on Wednesday next week.
Now I understand that things are difficult, right?
It's like we are still in this kind of remote instruction
and you still have a tough time, maybe home and so forth
and making things work, you are stressed.
So make sure that your DA understand any issue
that you may be having
because of that and also as a group.
And if you want to escalate,
I'll be happy to meet with a group, just send me an email
and I'll be happy to meet with you
and provide some best practices and some advice.
Okay.
So next let's talk about real time scheduling.
So real time scheduling, think about
the programs which runs on your car, like ABS,
anti-blocking, whatever for brakes.
You have in your car, you have probably tens of processors,
tens, hundreds of programs run, okay?
Or think about self-driving.
You really want their predictable performance.
You run things to finish by a certain time,
like out steering or, you know,
if out in a self-driving car, you need to steer in time,
right? If you don't steer in time, you have an accident.
Okay?
So therefore these are the core of the power plant,
or, you know, think about landing
and taking off for airplanes, which is done automatically.
For all of these use cases, you need to have programs.
For sure it doesn't, you know, you don't get starvation,
right? And you can predict they're predictable.
So now the real time is again,
is predict about predictability about things happening
by a certain time is not about being fast.
Okay?
And there are multiple classes about real time
and real time, it's again, a big area.
There are conferences only dedicated real time.
And it's about meeting the deadlines, right?
You have some deadlines by which some task is to finish.
And in these areas, there are different categories.
There are soft real time deadlines,
hard real time deadlines, hard real time deadlines.
You need to meet all the deadlines.
Soft real times, best effort.
Try to be your best to meet most of them.
Depends on the application.
And like you expect, there are a lot of algorithms
and the algorithms, scheduling algorithms are quite different
and we are going to look at only one,
which is very simple, which is early deadline first, right?
By the way, another, an example of our soft real time
is for multimedia, for your playing back video
or voiceover, when you chat over your phone, right?
It's great to have hard deadlines,
your message, what you are saying to arrive to the other end,
say within 15 milliseconds, never later.
But if it's a little bit longer, it's okay.
The humans are going to adapt.
And here we are, and we are going to talk about
only one soft scheduling discipline,
which is early deadline first.
But here is a model.
The model is that the task have deadlines,
and they declare about the computation time is now.
So here we are talking about things
getting repeatedly being done.
So you have pretty good idea about when each task,
how long each task is going to take.
So it's different from general case
in which it's hard to predict the future.
Here you have to predict the future
because how can you set up a deadline
without knowing how much the computation will take?
It's impossible.
So it's part of the game here that you are going to know
how long the task is going to take.
And now the question is you have multiple tasks,
each of them, they have certain computation time
and certain deadlines.
And the thing is that,
can all the tasks meet their deadlines?
That's the key question.
And here is one example, one of example of scheduling.
It's again, it's preemptive.
You still have time quanta between these tasks.
And it turns out these are the deadlines,
you know, the app arrows,
the app arrows is when the task,
a event which triggers the computation arrives
and the down arrows are the deadlines.
And here is an example in which this scheduling,
particular scheduling of these tasks
is going to violate the deadlines for task one.
Okay.
So now,
like I mentioned,
we are going to learn about one such scheduling discipline,
a leader line first.
Typically they assume that the task I is periodic,
is periodic PI, meaning that, and computation CI,
meaning that in each period,
you have to perform a computation for that task.
Like for instance, every 100 milliseconds,
the task needs to perform a computation of 10 milliseconds.
Example, think about,
it's again, something like a self-driving car
or anything in the car,
you have sensors,
which are like video cameras and so forth,
which periodically take, you know,
take a measurement,
maybe the state of the brake or the speed,
or obviously a video frame, right?
And these are periodic and they need to be processed.
So before the next measurement is taken,
we need to process the previous measurement, right?
That's kind of our motivation.
And the early deadline first is very simple.
It's basically saying, like the name implies,
you always schedule the task,
whose deadline is the earliest.
Okay.
That's it.
Let's take an example.
Okay.
So let's have three tasks.
And for each task,
the two numbers in parentheses represent the period,
the first number,
and how long it needs to come,
it should take to compute in this period.
So 4-1 means that every four time you need,
say for every four seconds,
T1 requires one second of computation.
T2 during five seconds requires two seconds of computation.
T3 every seven seconds requires two seconds of computation.
Right?
And these are the first two deadlines, right?
Because you need to finish to process
in the current period before the next period starts.
So for T1, the first deadline is time five,
for T2, time four, sorry,
for T2 is five, for T3 is seven, right?
So therefore, first,
you are going to schedule,
and say the time quanta here is one.
So first you are going to schedule T1, right?
Why?
Because the deadline is the earliest, right?
You see, it's at four.
The other deadlines are at five and seven.
Once you are done with that,
you are going to schedule T2.
And let's assume that we don't preempt here,
for simplicity.
And because T2 has earlier deadlines than T3,
five versus seven.
So schedule that, and finally, you schedule T3.
Now, what are the next deadlines?
These are the next deadlines.
The next deadlines of T1,
it's at time eight.
The next deadline of T2 is time 10.
And the next deadline of T3 is time 14.
We are going to schedule first here.
Which is the next deadline?
Again, T1 is the earliest one.
Then again, T2, and again T3.
Again, but again, before going to T3,
let's look at the next deadlines.
So the next deadline of T1 is now 12.
The next deadline of T2 is now 15.
And the next deadline of T3,
actually the second deadline, it's 14.
So which is the earliest deadlines
we need to consider now?
Right?
T1 is the next one.
It's 12, T2, 15, T3, 14.
Obviously, it's T1.
So you are going to schedule T1.
So now you see that you schedule
for the first three periods of T1,
while for T3, you schedule for only one.
But now after the schedule for T1,
you are going to consider T3
because it's deadline is earliest.
It's earlier than T2.
And then you continue.
Okay?
Now, an interesting question here.
Oh, let me just, sorry.
How do you know that you can satisfy,
the algorithms can satisfy all the task deadlines?
As you can see from the beginning,
that is not easy.
The order, you know, it changes as you progress.
Okay?
It's actually quite complicated.
Now, it turns out that with early deadline first,
there is a simple condition you can use to check
whether you can satisfy early deadline first,
satisfy the deadlines of all tasks.
And that you've sum up the computation
of a period for all tasks.
And if that is less than one,
you, the EDF is feasible.
It's working.
In our case, it's one over four,
plus two over five, plus two over seven,
is less than one.
So it's feasible.
Like we've seen at least from our simulation
for the first, you know, whatever, 20 seconds.
Okay?
And this is very cool because you see,
this is also optimal from the point of view of utilization
because C over D for a task is how much
is going to utilize from the CPU.
If I want to utilize, I have like the first task,
one time unit, one second out of four seconds,
the utilization, that task alone is going to get
one over four of the CPU, 25% of the CPU.
So the sum of these C over Ds cannot be greater than one.
Right?
Because you cannot use more CPUs than you have.
This is a very good,
that's why you are talking about server
because it's very good.
It's also optimal.
Okay?
Now, things are more complicated
and we touch a little bit about starvation
and we are going to talk more during this lecture
and the next lecture.
And one thing to make sure is that starvation
is different from deadlock.
Starvation means that you are starved,
but, you know, eventually you are not,
you can still run.
Like we are talking in the previous case,
you are starved and you can restart forever
if there are police priority scheduling,
if there are always lower priorities,
tasks or jobs in the system.
But once that they are no longer, you are scared.
Deadlock is a different in the sense that
you get to a point that you cannot resolve that
no matter what happens in the system,
unless you kill the process or you start the system.
Right?
We'll talk more about that next time,
but we're also going to touch a little bit
during this lecture.
Right?
And you have this causes of starvation,
scheduling policy, like we said,
never runs a particular thread on the CPU and so forth.
But we'll explore more about these problems.
One way to avoid starvation is not one way.
It's obviously one way to alleviate starvation
if the CPU is always used, if there is work to do.
If you have a scheduler who doesn't use a CPU
and keeps a CPU idle, obviously it's much higher chance
that you are going to stop some threats.
The schedulers which are always using CPU,
they don't leave the CPU idle while there is work to do,
while there are ready processes in the system,
or ready threats, they are called work conserving.
The schedulers which are not work conserving
are schedulers which are--
they may maintain the CPU idle even
if there are processes in the system which
can already be executed.
And obviously, like I said, they can leave the--
trivially lead to starvation.
In this class, we assume that the schedulers
work conserving.
So we don't need to worry about work conserving,
but just to keep--
for completeness, let you know that there are such schedulers.
So here is another thing--
there's another example of schedulers,
a few examples of schedulers which leads to starvation.
Again, you already know about some of them.
Here is a new one.
It's LIFO, last in, first out.
So it's as opposed to first in, first out, or first come,
first serve.
This is going to serve the tasks which are inserted,
which arrived the latest first.
And this can be very unfair and obviously can cause starvation
because you can have new tasks always arriving.
You are only going to schedule those.
And when arrival rate exceeds how much
the number of tasks which you get,
it's more than what you can process, obviously,
you are going to starve the whole tasks for that purpose.
FIFO doesn't really have that problem.
But anyway, this is just about what about first come,
first serve.
FIFO or first come, first serve is the same thing.
They don't have as much of a problem
because eventually you are going to drain the cure.
Let me see.
It's a question.
Why would you ever want a non-overconserving scheduler?
That's a good question.
Why always you would like to?
So there are schedulers which you
want to be predictable, very predictable.
There are schedulers you want certain things to happen
exactly at the right time.
So you want, for instance, to produce
a result every 100 milliseconds.
So in that particular case, even if you
can process more and earlier, you
are not going to process because you are going
to produce a result there.
So that's kind of one example.
When you want to--
regularly, this is also in networking.
In networking, you want to send one packet every--
say you have one packet you are going
to send every one microsecond.
Now, you may ask, why do you want to do that?
Why?
And in general, one reason you may
want to do this to keep this kind of space
because you don't want to overwhelm the next stage
or the next processing stage.
Like, for instance, in networking,
if you send bursts of packets instead of spacing them,
then you have a higher probability
you are going to go into overflow
to send more packets than a downstream router can handle.
And then packets will be lost.
So that's an example.
OK?
So it's again, the first comfort served,
the only problem you have is that you
are going to have a very long job.
You never yield.
And then you have to start for some hours, a while.
But it's again, as long as over some time intervals,
the load offered to the system that the system has to process
is lower than the capacity of the system,
everyone is going to run.
Is round-robin prone to starvation?
Well, if you have n processes and if you have a time quanta
then of q, then your turn will come every n minus 1 times
q milliseconds to run again.
So you don't have starvation.
Now, is priority scheduling prone to starvation?
Of course it is.
We just discussed about that, right?
Again, priority scheduling runs every job.
Every-- first it has to finish all the jobs
at the high priority level before going to the next step.
OK?
And now, as-- what is our-- it's like,
as a preview for the next lecture for the deadlocks,
let me give you one example about a deadlock.
We alluded about this deadlock last lecture
when we talk about priority inversion.
And this is what can happen.
OK?
So, but again, deadlock means you are stuck.
Can't do anything.
Even if you have no other job in the system,
you are still stuck, you cannot make progress.
So say a job at priority 1, lower priority, acquire a lock.
OK?
And now the job 1 is in critical section.
But now job 3 comes, it's a higher priority.
And job 3 tries to acquire the lock held by job 1.
Right?
OK?
But you cannot, you are block on acquiring.
Right?
And by the way, so now job 3 waits for job 1
to finish to release a lock.
And job 1 is not executed because job 3
has a higher priority.
That's kind of deadlock.
Right?
And this is priority inversion.
Because you are waiting for a job with a lower priority
to release a lock.
And you cannot release a lock because of you.
And this is the definition of priority inversion.
OK?
This is another example with a live lock.
You have lock acquires, lock release, the low priority,
and the high priority is again try to achieve, fly block.
Always busy waiting.
So what are the solutions?
One solution is priority donation or inheritance.
So in this particular case, if job 1, which is lower priority,
holds a lock and job 3 wants to acquire it,
what happens in this case?
Job 3 donates its priority to job 1.
So job 1, while it is a critical section
and while holding the lock, now is
going to be promoted to priority 3, the highest priority.
So now you get time to run and to finish.
And after it releases, it goes back, job 1 on priority 1,
lower priority on its previous priority,
and job 3 can acquire the lock.
And this is you are going to have in project 2.
OK.
So here is an example.
This is not only theoretical.
This is a Martian Pathfinder rover.
And I have here for the fun, which is not
necessarily related to the lecture.
This is in '97 or so many years ago.
But it was a big event because it was the first one
of these satellites.
And actually, it has also landed on the planet since '76,
so after 21 years.
And one thing it has, it was fun.
It was this kind of different delivery mechanism.
Let me just see whether I have this one.
So I'm just-- OK.
Do you see my screen?
You don't see my screen.
OK.
Let me just-- I'm not sure how much you see it.
And for some reason, I cannot let me see if I can do it.
Yeah.
Let's do this for now.
So it's a very interesting delivery mechanism.
How was this lander delivered?
How it landed on Mars?
It has like balloons, like everything.
It has like balloons, like airbags all over the place.
And this is how it was delivered.
Very innovative, very cool.
OK.
So it eventually stopped.
But this is the one we are talking about.
And now the problem is that a few days into the mission,
multiple systems resets occurred.
And it was for the software.
And the system appeared to reboot randomly,
losing valuable time and making progress.
And what it turned out to be was priority inversion.
It was this priority two, highest priority,
which was a data distribution task.
And it needed a lock.
The problem is that the collector, the one--
another task, which was collecting samples,
collecting data, which was lower priority, was getting the lock.
So now the priority--
the collector had the lock.
And the data distribution task couldn't acquire the lock.
Now what happens typically in these systems,
you have a watchdog.
And the watchdog is a process which
looks whether there is forward progress.
And if there is no forward progress,
and you have this in this case, a backlog, what it's going to do
is going to reboot the system.
And it turns out that there was actually
code for the priority donation to avoid this problem,
priority inversion.
But it was turned off because the developers thought
they were worried about the performance.
Of course, in this case, the fix was
to upload and fix back the code.
So again, what we are talking here is not only theoretical.
It happens.
Let's look about others.
Is shortest time first and multi-level feedback
cube prone to starvation?
They are, right?
Like we discussed, shortest time first,
the long job can be starved in the favor of short ones.
If you have always short jobs arriving,
they are going to starve the long jobs.
With multi-level feedback cube, it's
an approximation of short remaining time first.
So it suffers from the same problem.
And again, in some sense, the case,
the cause for starvation, it's always a priority.
Whether it's a fixed priority or whether it's
implicit, explicit fixed priority or implicit priority
like the length of a job.
So you have this kind of a priority
which is encoded in the schedulers,
how schedulers make the decision.
It should raise a flag that you may then end up with starvation.
And again, our job, remember, is to serve
a mix of CPU-bound and I/O-bound interactive jobs effectively.
And here you want to have interactive jobs
to be interactive, be very quick, response time,
very fast response time.
We need to give I/O-bound the jobs enough CPU
so then they are going to do their work.
Ideally, you want them to be I/O-bound, right?
And then the CPU-bound ones, you want to still let them
running to eventually finish, right?
Now, the scheduling discipline, it's also,
we are going to learn and we learned,
it's also a reflection of the changes
in the landscape of computers.
For big mainframes, so you have a lot of users using them.
To PCs, you have one user and maybe one programmer
earlier on a single machine to multiple programs
on a single machine but only one users.
And to even Internet of Things, which the things are sitting
there just to get some information
from the environment.
So priority-based scheduling is rooted in times sharing
when you have fewer resources and a lot of things
running on the same, competing for the resources.
And that's why, but and then they led to starvation.
People try to resolve the starvation,
try to develop new scheduling which are more fair,
and things like that, right?
And one question here is that this is does prioritizing
some jobs necessarily start those that aren't prioritized?
Not strict priorities in certain cases like we've seen,
absolutely.
But it turns out that people have a bunch of heuristics
to reduce at least, to reduce, alleviate starvation.
And there are a few ways to do it.
Multi-level feedback queue, if you remember,
tries to reduce the starvation by having CPU-bounded jobs
falling.
That's also one which takes a long time
to be prioritized to go to a lower priority in time.
The other things, other mechanics,
like the mechanics which are API exposed to the users
to being nice, right?
So basically, if you wanted to be nice,
and this is a Unix command, you can deprioritize your task,
your program, so other people can run their programs.
The nicer value range from minus 20 to 19.
Negative values are not nice.
The thing is that in this particular case,
you can think about for Unix, some systems, like Unix,
at least some version of Unix, the lower priorities values
are higher priorities.
So far, in all our examples, you assume the higher priority
values of priority three has the highest priority.
But in Unix, at least some version of Unix
is the other way around.
The lower priority values of priority zero
has the highest priority, and priority three
is the lower priority.
So in this case, so therefore, if you increase a nice value,
you basically decrease the priority of your--
you increase the priority value, but you decrease the priority
of your job.
OK?
And let me stop here.
And we are almost done with the lecture,
but we are going to continue next time.
It's the last lecture on scheduling.
And we are going to look a little bit about Linux,
how Linux is implemented.
And then we are going to talk a little bit more about fairness.
With that, if there are any other questions I could answer,
please raise your hand.
Yeah, the deadlock there only happens--
that deadlock only happens here on spinlocks.
Yes, in that particular example, yes.
But yeah, but a deadlock is a much more general concept,
like we'll see next time.
OK, no other questions.
Thank you so much.
I am going to see you on Monday.
Good luck with your homework and the project.
Bye.
.
( purposeful silence )