So, hello, everyone.
So today we are going to finish the discussion on scheduling.
And then we are going to start the discussion on deadlocks.
So last time we discussed quite a bit about a few scheduling disciplines.
And if you remember one scheduling disciplines, which has been very popular and is still popular,
it's priority scheduling.
And one of the reason it's popular, it's very simple.
The pure priority scheduling, if you remember, you have different levels of priorities and
you always start from the highest priority and then you run the jobs at the highest priority.
And only after you are done with those jobs, you can go to the lower priority.
And one obvious question is does prioritizing some jobs necessarily starve those that aren't
prioritized?
So do higher priority jobs necessarily starve lower priority jobs?
And this is what we are going to talk a little bit about here and what kind of tweaks you
can do to priority scheduling to avoid starvation.
Because if you remember, if you have always high priority jobs, then you'll never serve
the low priority jobs.
So therefore, you are going to starve the low priority jobs.
So let's look through some of these mechanisms.
So one mechanism, it's an API which is provided by early Unix systems, which is called Nice.
And this, as the name implies, it allows you as a user to be nice to others.
And the way you are going to be nice to others is by lowering the priority of your job, of
your application.
So in this case, in the case of Unix, lower values of priorities mean high priority.
And the nice value ranges from minus 20 to 19.
So negative values are not nice.
And in order to be nice, you can increase this value, which means lower priority.
So that's very interesting.
So now a few words about Linux.
Let's see how Linux, the basic scheduler, it's organized and it's implemented.
So you have 140 priorities.
And the first 100 are for the kernel and the real time tasks.
Again, the real time tasks are the ones who are predictable, you want to be predictable.
And then the last 40 are for the user tasks.
And again, lower priority values, it means higher priority.
And the algorithm is O(1).
O(1) complexity meaning that it takes constant time to select the next process to run.
And you also have time slices, so it's preemptive scheduler.
So a job or a process doesn't run to completion is going to be interrupted when its time slice
expires.
There is also 140 bit mask, which indicates the presence or absence of a job at the given
priority level.
So why do you have that bit mask?
So the reason you have that bit mask is that, think about you want to be very quick and
you select the next job or next process to run.
And now assume that you have two processes in the system, one process at priority zero
and one process at priority 139.
So once you're finished to run the process at priority zero, you need to run the process
at priority 139.
But you need to find that process.
And the simple implementation is to have a list of priorities and each head of that,
for each item in this priority list, it's a list of processes at that priority.
So now you start from zero and you are done with the process.
And now you have to go to next one, which is the next level and the next level and the
next level until you get to 139 in order to find the next process to run.
If you have a bit mask, then basically the bit mask, I'm just going to look at the bit
mask, which is 140 bits.
And the bit mask will say that the next automatic will say that only there are processes active
at level priority level 139.
In between, there is no process active.
So the bits in the bit mask are not set.
So it's very easy to do.
The other thing which is doing is that you have two priority queues in terms of for active
processes, the processes which you have to, they are still to run and then expired processes.
Expired means after you are going to run a process, you are going to put it in the expired
queue.
And then once you are done with all the processes in the active queue, so the active queue is
empty, you just switch to expired.
So active become expired queue and expired becomes the active queue.
You swap them.
Okay, so this is what an example.
You go through the active queues, you have here all these priorities, each task with
its own priorities.
And once you are done with all the tasks from the active queue, you are going to put them
all in the expired queue.
And then you are just going to swap the expired queue with the run queue.
Any questions?
And then in order to avoid kind of starvation, like we discussed last time, there are many
heuristics.
Like if a task is IO bound, you try to boost this priority, to increase this priority.
If a task running for too long, you are going to lower like his priority.
More precisely, here is a list of heuristics.
The user task priority is adjusted in plus minus five increments.
It's again, you have the user task priority is between 100 and 139.
And basically you are going to update it like for instance, if the sleep time minus run
time, if the process sleeps much longer than it runs, you increase its priority.
This is probably because it's an IO bound task.
If it's running for a long time, you are going to decrease its priority.
And if it doesn't sleep at all.
So yeah, again, if your task sleep for a long time, you are going to accrue credit, you
are going to increase the priority.
When it's going to run, you are going to spend this credit, you're going to decrease this
priority if it's running for too long.
And for interactive tasks, you give them special treatment because you want to always have
high priority.
Although in general, many of the interactive tasks are IO bound because they are waiting
for the user input, many of them.
So then they can go automatically higher priority because they are going to sleep more than
they are.
So let's see, there are two questions here.
That's a very good question.
So the question is, does this mean getting a new process scheduled takes a long time
since the existing queue needs to be exhausted before new things can be added?
Yeah, you are right.
It's a strategy in the process is getting scheduled, not the process itself.
So you are again, when you have one process, one thread, we are going to use interchangeable.
So this very much depends on the scheduler.
But when you are going to run a new process, typically you put the process as the highest
priority.
So this means that you are going to start executing that process or thread quickly,
which is the highest priority.
You can start executing that thread as soon as you finish executing the current thread,
when the time slice of the current thread you are executing is expiring.
It's also here, you see the word of hysteresis.
You use hysteresis to avoid changing interactivity from temporarily changing changes in behavior.
What is hysteresis?
Do you know?
Anyone you can say on the chat?
Okay, we are not going to go into a lot of details here, but hysteresis means that when
you have a process, a control system in general, and you have a threshold, and when that exceeds
that threshold, you change the output and you decrease the threshold, you reduce the
gain change output.
So if you have a system which is just around that threshold, the system changes its behavior
quite frequently.
So you get one, two, and even if you have noise, if you have to imagine that you have
noise around that threshold.
So you want to avoid that.
So in order to avoid that, you have actually in general two thresholds.
You have one threshold, low threshold and high thresholds.
And you change the behavior when you exceed a high threshold or when you go under the
low threshold.
So in that sense, you have a range in which the system behavior doesn't change it.
So if there is a noise and we are within that range, the system will become constant.
So for instance, in this particular case, you don't want to change the behavior.
Like for instance, imagine that you have an editor.
And with an editor, not editor, maybe, I don't know whether you use LaTeX or something like
that.
So you have an editor.
Okay, let's take an editor.
So you take an editor and there are two different regimes.
One you are entering the text, editing the text.
And another one is for instance, you save or load.
So you don't want, say save or load or even worse, the editor doing some rendering and
doing some compute heavy, say maybe operations.
You don't want that just because you do a little bit of computation, that to make the
editor less responsive.
You want to be more robust and only if it's for a long, long time, the editor is just
doing a lot of rendering, maybe you are going to deprioritize it.
That's what hysteresis means.
Real-time tasks, they have lower than 100 priority.
They also preempt the non-RTH task.
For each queue at each level, there are two kinds of schemes.
So at each priority level, again, you have multiple, at each priority level, you have
a queue which contains multiple processes or threads.
And you can use all the FIFO without no time slice or round-robin, in which there is a
time slice.
Here is a real-time task.
They are not scheduled using the early deadline first, which we learned last time, the last
lecture.
They are assigned priorities.
There are other scheduling algorithms, real-time scheduling algorithms, which can use priorities
to schedule these tasks and still guarantees you can meet the deadlines.
Another thing, like if you remember, we can do and to be more robust and avoid starvation,
is basically using proportional share scheduling.
And this is related with lottery scheduling.
lottery scheduling is an implementation of proportional share scheduling.
And basically here, it's again, if you remember, you allocate these tickets and you have say
100 tickets, and maybe you are going to give to one thread, you are going to give 10 tickets
and the other 190 tickets.
And now you are going to do the lottery so every time you select a winning ticket.
Now obviously, the probability of selecting the second thread, which has 90 tickets, is
nine times higher than probably to select the first thread, which has only 10 tickets.
So this means that you give to the second thread 90% of the CPU on the average, and
the first thread only 10%.
So you can see that you can use this kind of weights, these different number of tickets,
you are giving to each thread to approximate priorities.
Because clearly, you can see that the thread with 90 tickets has a higher priority than
the task with 10 tickets.
And the nice thing about this kind of scheme is that it avoids starvation.
So even if you give a task, a thread 99 tickets and another thread only one, still out on
the average, out of 100 time slices or quanta, the thread which has only one ticket is going
to get a chance to run.
So it's not stopped.
And this is basically tells you a little bit more, giving you a little bit more math on
that.
Now, you may ask, well, then why we don't do only this lottery scheduling or this proportional
sharing?
The answer is that it's harder to implement.
It's more complex to implement.
It's slower than the priority.
The priority or so is so on of one super simple to implement.
So that's the answer.
So look, let's again, Unix has a lot of schedulers, actually.
The first one was a basic scheduler.
You have this kind of two queues, active and expired.
And it's all fun, very simple.
But it has also a more sophisticated scheduler.
And one of that, this is completely fair scheduler.
And the idea here is to track the CPU time per thread and schedule threads to match up
on average rate of execution.
So basically, in other words, you want different threads.
If you don't have different threads, more than one thread, you want all of them to make
kind of progress at the same rate.
That's it.
That's a high level.
So this is if the CPU time, like this is CPU time and this is one over n, you have three
threads.
So in this case, n is three.
So this is each of them, you get one third of the CPU.
Then you look at how long each of them they run, starting for a given time.
And in this case, the one that are longer than T2 and T3.
And therefore, here you are going to give the next time when you are going to schedule,
you are going to schedule.
select probability two, because you want to catch up with,
T2 to catch up with T1 and T3.
Of course, it's again, this is a simple one,
a simple case, but it's sort of complicated, right?
Because threads do not start at the same time.
Threads, excuse me, threads are IO bounded, right?
They instead of, you know,
they don't use their entire full quanta, okay?
So there are many things and that's why these schedulers
are much more complicated.
There are a lot of papers, research papers,
written about the schedulers.
This is discussion is to give you a sense,
some intuition about what are the problems
and how these schedulers are working, okay?
So this is, it's again, this is a goal here
is to provide this illusion of complete, of fairness.
Each of the tasks thread gets the same kind of,
makes progress at the same rate, gets CPU at the same rate.
And it's closely related to its fair queuing, okay?
How do you implement it?
You can use a heap scheduler, but it's hard.
A heap scheduler is log N, right?
Or N is a number of threads.
And if you look about the number of threads on your Mac
or on your probably PC, you'll see that you can have
on your machine, you can have like tens of thousands
of threads at a given time, tens of thousands.
So this is, can be quite slow, the log N.
Hard to remove threads, right?
Right, but this is a very easy, you know,
using a heap like scheduling, it's easy because you are,
you can always from a heap, you are going to get,
select the task, which has a lowest CPU time,
which use a CPU as a list, okay?
Now, we said that these things are more complicated.
You can have a sleeping, you know, threads.
What do you do if a thread is slipping?
Because, you know, waits for some event to happen,
or, you know, it's like, think about the thread is slipping,
which as a process, when forks, another process
is going to slip and to wait for the other process
to finish and to join back.
So basically one thing to hear is like when you,
when a thread slips, you don't add basic CPU types.
If you don't advance your CPU time, then when it wakes up,
it's going to have low CPU time,
so it's going to have priority,
it's going to be scheduled, right?
But now the problem is that you cannot do that unbounded.
Like what happens if I have a thread,
which is slips from here since yesterday, right?
That will have a higher than, a lower CPU times
than anything in the system.
And basically, you know,
it's going to have priority over all of them.
So you need to adjust for that as well.
It's again, we are not going to go into all the details.
So, but at the high level, one trade off with the schedulers,
like we also discussed last lecture,
it's about between being very responsive
and between, within responsibility and fairness.
Right? You remember, it's like an algorithm,
which is fair, it's round robin, right?
Each of them, you know, you go over, you know,
around the threads and every round you are going to schedule
to give a time quanta to each thread, right?
So that's very fair.
However, maybe don't be very responsive
because you have any threads,
you need to wait for N minus up to N minus one times quanta.
To get a time quanta to a thread, right?
So thread, particular thread can wait
for N minus one times quanta.
On the other hand, the priority, it's very effective
and provide you low response time,
at least for the threads with a high priority, right?
If you have, say 10 threads
and the interactive thread is priority,
the highest priority, that is going to serve very fast,
but it's not going to be fair, right?
Because the high priority threads are going to get
all the CPU at the expense of low priority threads.
Right? So that's a fundamental trade-off.
And what Linux is doing, it has this kind of,
you have put this constraint about target latency.
So it's a period of time over which
every process gets serviced, right?
I am guaranteed that, you know, target latency.
So say it is 100 milliseconds,
I am guaranteed that I'm going to get access to the CPU
within every 100 milliseconds.
Okay?
And this defines a time quanta,
because if you have N number is a number of processes
or thread, then the time quanta
is a target latency over N, right?
So for instance, if you have the target latency,
20 milliseconds, and you have four processes,
but it's a time quanta, it has to be five, right?
Because if it's longer, you cannot guarantee
that each process is going to get access to the CPU
within 20 milliseconds.
Right?
But now if you have 20 milliseconds,
and you have 200 processes,
the time quanta can be 0.1 milliseconds,
which is too little, right?
You remember, if it's a time slice
or time quanta is too small,
then the overhead of context switching can dominate.
So you are doing more context switches
between these kinds of processes
than really running these processes.
Right?
So this is one thing.
The other thing is about,
obviously, the reason you want to avoid
a lot of overhead in context switching
is to preserve the throughput, right?
The throughput is defined as a useful work done by a system.
Context switching is not useful work, okay?
And therefore, in order to make sure
that the throughput is not going to plummet,
it's not going to be too low,
you are going to, we are going to say,
what is the minimum length of any time slice?
So it's a minimum granularity constraints.
So you have a target latency and minimum granularity,
which in general can be at odds, right?
So,
so, but, and because they are at odds in,
sometimes you have to violate one.
Like for instance, if you have target latency
of 20 milliseconds and minimum granularity
of one millisecond,
then in this case, you can,
minimum granularity is going to prevail and is going,
you know, you cannot reduce the time slice
to less than one milliseconds.
And, you know, the target latency, you cannot do it
if you just do round robin, right?
Because if you do round robin,
it's going to take 100 milliseconds
to a process to get it's turn.
So you need to wait for 99 milliseconds to get your turn.
So of course, we are going to violate
the target latency here.
Okay?
Okay, it's a question here.
Oh, what is granularity?
Oh,
yeah.
Okay, so these are very good questions.
So what is granularity?
Granularity is how granular you are going to,
what is the granularity at which you are going
to provide the service?
I mean, it's, this is what we mean.
It's like, what we mean is about
what is the minimum length of the time slice in this case?
This is what I mean by granularity.
What is the time slice size?
Okay.
Why would we have both?
It seems like minimum length is the only real
powerful constraint.
Yes, you are correct.
And this is, in this example, we illustrated that.
That minimum granularity is a stronger constraint
if you want, because if you go too low,
then the system doesn't, may not do any work, right?
It's, again, spend all the time doing context switching.
But target latency, it's also a constraint if you want,
you know, if you want to support interactive workloads.
Right?
How we are going to, you know, it's,
there is, there has to be, there are limits
in terms of how responsive your editor
or your computer should be,
different applications should be,
to provide you a good experience.
Okay?
So you should strive to provide that kind of level
of interactivity and the level of interactivity,
it's obviously related with this target latency.
Right?
Because if you, if you are going, if the target latency,
you know, like if you cannot get your turn,
say in 500 milliseconds, this means that your application,
you know, you may wait, you may have to wait
for half a second for your application to respond,
your text application, editor, whatever.
So in summary, yes, the minimum granularity,
it's a stronger constraint,
but target latency captures the demands
of the interactive applications.
So it's also important.
The other question here is about priority,
like this kind of a little bit prioritization.
What if we want to give more CPU to some,
to some threads or less to another,
so allowed for different rate of execution,
is very similar.
It's like, it's a weight, it's like you give,
you give a weight in some sense, you see that is W.
So basically you have the equal share is basically the,
the equal share here, it's about how much of the CPU
you are going to give and its target latency over there,
right, like we discussed earlier on.
And here is a way to sharing, you are going to basically,
you are going to give within one of these target shares,
you are going to run one thread more times, multiple times.
Okay, so this is very, very similar,
but it's using different notation,
but the outcome is basically identical.
It's another implementation to having different number
of tickets, to giving different number of tickets
to different threads or processes, right?
So that's basically what it is, right?
So this is basic equal share, it's one over N.
And if you want weighted share, you do W,
you give up higher weight to one process.
And this, so then you get the fraction
you are going to get from the CPU.
It's your weight divided by the sum of the weights
of all the other threads or processes.
And they use a value nice,
value to reflect shares rather than priority.
And this is over using an API, an existing API,
and this is how you use it.
You have the nice is becoming the exponent.
This is how you are basically think about that.
When you are going to use nice, what will happen?
You are going to change the weight
as provided by this formula, right?
So your weight by default is 1024 over 125, it's 1024.
If you are going to increase your nice,
so you have to basically being nice,
it means that you get less access to the CPU.
So you let others use a CPU for longer, right?
That means to be nice.
And this is reflected in getting a lower weight.
And the way you, again, the particular weight
you are going to get by using nice
is given by this formula 1024 over 1.25 at power nice.
And it's here just to give you a sense,
if it's nice, it's incremented of in terms of incremented.
If you remember, it's that you can increment
units of five, 1.25 power five is three, right?
So if you increase your nice by five,
this means that your weight will decrease by three.
Okay, yeah, there is a concept of virtual time.
We are not going to discuss it here,
but if you have questions,
I'll be more than happy to talk about this virtual time.
I did a lot of research during my PhD
many years back on this one.
So really, really again, scheduling is a complex problem.
There are many hundreds of scheduling algorithms,
hundreds, thousands of research papers
that are probably only about,
you know, just talking about fair queuing
or proportional sharing is the same name
for the kind of the same scheduler,
but in different domains like CPU or networking.
There are probably hundreds or thousands of papers
only for this particular discipline, okay?
So it's huge.
And why is that?
Is because, you know, the scheduler is hard
because you want to do it extremely fast.
And then there are different competing priorities,
competing demands from the applications, right?
You want to be fair, you want to be interactive,
you want to have high throughput and so forth.
And therefore, that's why for different demands
from the applications,
you can come up with different schedulers,
which are best fit to satisfy those demands.
So for instance, if you want CPU throughput,
it's first come first serve
because what you want to minimize,
you want to minimize the overhead for the scheduler.
First come first serve, picking a new job,
it's super easy, it's all fun, right?
It's ahead of the queue.
And then there is no context switching.
And you are going to continue to run that job to completion.
Okay?
So minimizing the operation to select,
you know, the overhead to select the next job,
minimizes the overhead, the number of context switches.
Average response time is shortest time first, right?
This is provable optimal
to minimize average response time.
And so forth, you know, fairness here,
you have Linux CFS, you can lay lottery scheduling.
This is for CPU time.
Also fairness, and fairness,
if you want to be very predictable
or however long to wait until to get the CPU,
just do the round robin.
This is related to target latency,
meeting the early deadline first.
If you want to have some very few important tasks,
which they cannot be delayed, you can use priority.
And for IO support is SRDP approximation.
Again, we discuss about that, I think two lectures ago,
where we have these examples of two tasks,
which each of them takes one week,
and then you have this other task, which is IO bounded,
takes, runs for one millisecond
and waits for nine milliseconds, if I remember correctly.
Okay.
Now how to evaluate this scheduling algorithms, right?
You have all of those different properties,
how, and you are going to design them,
how you are going to evaluate it.
There are several ways.
First of all, deterministic.
You basically, you get a workload
and given this workload,
you compute the performance of the algorithms
in the face of that workload.
Performance meaning, response times, throughput,
latency, whatever metrics you care about
for your application, right?
And a deterministic preterm workload,
you say, okay, you are going to have,
each processes continue,
one process, you have one process arriving
every one seconds,
and each process is going to have,
10 seconds or so of compute, right?
Or things like that, okay?
Queuing models.
This is a mathematical approach for stochastic workloads.
So in this particular case,
basically you are saying that
the load is non-deterministic, right?
You give the load in statistical terms,
is all you say on the average,
you have one process arriving every seconds.
And this process on the average has,
it takes, running time is 10 seconds.
And those numbers are drawn from a particular distribution.
Like for instance, the length of that process
is exponentially distributed, right?
The average, the mean is 10 seconds.
And the arrival time is like say,
Poisson distributed.
Poisson means that the inter arrival between processes
is drawn from an exponential distribution.
This is just an example.
And for that, you are going to get statistic,
you are going to be able to compute statistically,
what are the performance of the scheduler,
like for instance, again, mean response time,
or anything like that.
And the other one, you just implement it,
you just text, Python,
you implement a simple simulator and run it,
and see what results you get.
This is general flexible,
as long as you don't have bugs in your simulator.
So,
a final word on scheduling.
The scheduling matters
when there are not enough resources.
And many of the things we learn in this class,
many of the algorithms and many of the problem we solve,
these problems occur
because there are not enough resources.
We'll see virtual memory.
Why do we have virtual memory that I'm that?
Oh, because there is not enough physical memory.
It's one of the reasons.
No, right?
Scheduling.
Why do we need to have a scheduling,
a sophisticated scheduling?
Because there are not enough CPUs.
If you have one CPU per thread,
there is no scheduling, right?
Okay.
Why should you simply buy a faster computer or highways?
Well, look, you can buy it if you can afford it.
But remember, the more slow is ending.
So now if you buy a new computer, you could buy your Mac or your PC, it's not a lot of
more powerful than the one you have from three years back.
Okay.
And of course, you need to be careful about not...
You don't want to spend too much money.
The other thing what you need to understand, and this is a curve on this right hand side,
maybe you should do a lecture on it because it's extremely important.
It's an extremely important curve.
And this is what I say this curve.
Say your system has a certain capacity.
When you are approaching the capacity of the system, the response time is growing super
linearly.
This almost goes to infinity if you go to 100%.
Okay.
And again, we don't have time here to say why, but intuitively think about the highway
and the rush hour.
So it's like the difference where you start to be to approach the capacity of the highway.
And if you just inject a few cars, a few more cars, then the delay is going to shut up.
For instance, if there are on the highway, now there are 100 cars per hour and the capacity
of the system is 120.
And now you have a speed and the latency is 50 miles per hour.
Now if you add 10 more cars, so it's still a less than capacity.
Instead of going 50 miles per hour, you are going to go suddenly 20 miles per hour.
And again, think about your experience.
Just a few more cars, everything can bring everything to a crawl.
So again, let me see where I can have a lecture on that.
So now, let me see.
What if all the cars are managed by computer and all of them move simultaneously?
Yeah, in that case, you can achieve the capacity.
But the point is that that's not the case.
And the car leaves gap between them and these gaps, you cannot recover them.
So these gaps take from the capacity of the system.
That's kind of the intuition.
So announcements.
I know that everyone waits for that.
Mittermon, we are planning to release the grades by next Monday.
So we are grading your Mittermon.
Project due is due this Wednesday.
Code, final report, peer evaluation, everything.
If any of them is late, you are going to incur sleep days.
Okay, remember that.
Group evaluation coming for Project ON, right?
Every person, I believe you get 20 points per partner, which, you know, so everyone,
every person get 20 points.
And you are going to hand out these points to other members in your group, not to yourself.
Okay.
So this is a way to measure what is the contribution of other members in your team.
Office hours.
You know, there are a lot of students, and we all want to, again, to answer all your
questions.
But like you say, like you see in this lecture, you know, when the resources are scared, we
need to put some conditions, some policies in place, right, to try to provide some level
of fairness to you guys.
And so, TAs are spent, in general, are bound to spend 15 minutes per student.
It's again to give, to not starve other students from their attention.
And you need to have a detailed ticket filled out and the GDP pulled up, right?
So to be absolutely ready.
So the context switching is minimal, right, between students.
Okay.
And from these 15 minutes, you get the full value for these 15 minutes.
You don't have to wait for five minutes to set up your GDP and provide the ticket detail
explaining to the TA and thing like that.
Okay.
Great.
So now we are going to switch gears and we are going to talk about deadlocks.
And deadlock is a particular type of starvation.
Yes.
Thank you for, of course, this is, my date is wrong.
The Wednesday, it was Wednesday.
Thanks.
So deadlock is a deadly type of starvation.
Okay.
Starvation, the stress may wait indefinitely, right?
Allow priorities, try waiting for resources, because there are many other high priority
threats.
The deadlock, it's a circular waiting for resources.
And this is a very simple example.
Say you have two threats and both threats in order to make progress, require to get
access to two resources, resource one and resource two.
And now one threat gets access to resource one and the other said, get access to resource
two.
And both of them, they hold these resources.
So none of them can get the other resource.
So they are deadlocked.
They cannot make progress.
Okay.
This is what it is.
So deadlock implies starvation.
Because starvation, because you are guaranteed that in a deadlock, now one will make progress.
Starvation doesn't imply deadlock because starvation can end.
Eventually, if the high priority task finish, the low priority tasks can be executed.
Deadlock cannot finish without some external intervention.
Here is example.
It's a real example.
It's a one line bridge.
And as you probably know it, if you went to Yosemite on California on 140.
And so the point here is, again, there are two directions.
Now typically you have a traffic light for these ones.
But assume that you don't have a traffic light.
So if you don't have a traffic light, what happens?
What can happen intuitively?
What is the problem?
The problem is that two cars come from both ends.
And because there is no line, they are stuck.
They are deadlocked.
And the way you can model this is basically thinking that you have two halves to the entrance,
two halves of the bridge.
And each car acquire one half.
But in order to cross the bridge, you need two both halves.
So it's exactly like the previous example.
Each car has one half.
Each car require both halves.
They are stuck.
So in order, how you solve this, the only way to solve this deadlock is for one car
to back up.
And this is equivalent with the other car who didn't back up to preempt the resource
which is hauled by the car who backed up.
Because now the car which didn't back up is going to acquire the second half of the bridge.
Now it has the first half, second half, and then it's going to cross the bridge.
Now the equivalent of starvation here is basically saying you have a lot of cars from one side
east and you have cars after car after car and the car which comes from the other direction
will not get an opportunity even to get on the bridge.
Just starvation.
Again, starvation eventually can end when there are no longer cars coming in this case
from the west or from the east.
Now let's look about what does it seem from the point of view of the program.
You have two threads here and let's go to, you know, it's like locks, right?
These resources are like locks.
Locks are resources.
And this figure and the examples we consider so far can be expressed the following way.
Thread A, you have two locks, X and Y.
Acquires lock X and Y and then releases Y and X.
And B, acquires the locks in the different order and releases them in the different order.
So in this case, you can get that lock, right?
When does this happen?
Well, when this kind of order, you know, the CPU interleaves execution of instruction from
different threads.
So for instance, when this happens on thread A acquire X, then thread B acquire Y, now
thread A is stalled because thread B owns Y and thread B cannot progress further either
because it wants to acquire X, which is owned by A. So this is that lock, right?
Start to debug because this happens, now doesn't happen all the time.
And again, you want to avoid it.
Because it's again, like for instance, if this happens, you don't have that lock, right?
So this is non-terministic.
It will be a non-terministic bug, right?
And you always need to be afraid of non-terministic bugs because you cannot reproduce them.
If you can reproduce a bug, it's relatively easy to fix it.
If you cannot reproduce it, how you are going to fix it?
Here is another classic example.
Here are four trains and in this configuration, none of them can make progress.
You have a deadlock.
So you have here a deadlock just basically to illustrate the point.
So far, the examples we had, you have two entities which are in deadlock, two cars or
two threads.
But obviously, deadlock can happen between multiple, more than two entities.
And here is an example for four.
So here each train wants to turn to right.
This is real.
This is a real problem which are in different systems, encountering different systems.
Yeah.
Yes, it's exactly San Francisco traffic.
Yeah, that's a good one.
So how you fix it?
So one way to fix it, it's actually for some ordering.
You'll see this as a recurrent theme.
One way to fix deadlock is to have an order.
So for instance, in this case, always go east, west first and north, south, then back first.
Don't go north, south and east, west.
Only east, west and north, south.
Okay.
And as you'll see, like for our previous example, okay, so this is a lot.
So as you see in our previous examples, when you have this kind of deadlock, and we'll
say it a few more times, but it's good to remember, that one way you can avoid the deadlock
in the previous case is to enforce that both threads are going to acquire the locks in
the same order.
So again, if I go back here, if you enforce that both A and B acquire threads in the same
order, first X and then Y, you are going to solve this problem.
And again, we have the deadlock here because we do not have enough resources.
If we have enough resources, it's not a problem.
You wait for a resource that multiple threads compete to.
There are also threads that are blocking waiting for other threads like pipe or sockets or
wait like for instance, I am blocked to wait for a get to get a message.
What I am waiting for, if I am remember about bounded queues, I am waiting for queue to
become to get a free slot in order if I am a producer, I can wait if the queue is full,
I am waiting until the queue is drained so I can put more and more items in the queue.
So it's again, deadlock with space is an example like here.
If you don't have enough resources, you have two threads, each threads want to allocate
two megabytes, but they want to allocate that in two different calls.
And now assume that you have two megabytes of space.
So each thread allocates two megabytes, three two megabytes, but it's doing that one megabyte
at a time.
So you can get here a deadlock situation because if one thread gets one megabyte and one thread
gets another one megabyte, they are deadlocked because none of the thread can get an extra
megabyte in order to finish.
Okay, so here is another very famous problem to illustrate the deadlock.
I think it was called philosopher problem.
This is a little bit of a joke with the lawyers.
But think about this, you have five people and there are only five chopsticks.
Now in order to eat, you need two chopsticks.
So if everyone grabs one chopstick, it's deadlock because no one can eat.
So how do you do that?
Well, in order to break this deadlock, you need to give someone two chopsticks.
So if everyone has one chopstick, we need to get someone to give up her chopstick to
her neighbor.
So now the neighbor has two chopsticks.
She can eat, she can finish, and now she can give the chopsticks to her neighbors.
And now her neighbors can finish.
So this was solving the deadlock after it occurred.
But of course, ideally, you even want to prevent that lock.
So you have to have an algorithm if you want to prevent the deadlock, you don't get in
the deadlock situation in the first case.
We'll talk about those, but keep that in mind.
Now if you remember, when you have these kind of situations, you have some concurrency,
this is also an example of concurrent access to the resources.
We saw something similar with this when we talk about critical section.
We really want to have some to formalize the problem.
And if we formalize a problem and say, what are the conditions a solution should meet,
then we should focus on, we can only focus when developing a solution to meeting these
conditions.
So what are the requirements?
First of all, let's think about when does a deadlock occurs.
Because if we know the requirements on the deadlock occurs, then if we basically break
one of these requirements, then we can break the deadlock.
So there are four requirements for a deadlock docker.
Mutual exclusion.
Only once at a time can use a resource.
Hold and wait.
A threat holding at least one resource
is waiting to acquire additional resources
held by other threats.
Because if you don't wait, you can proceed,
you can finish it.
You can release a resource
and now there are no resources in the system.
So maybe other threats can finish
which you're waiting for the resources you are holding.
No preemption.
If a threat holds a resource,
that threat is not going to release a resource voluntarily.
Okay?
Before it finishes with it.
And then it is circular wait.
There exists a set of threats
such that T1 is waiting for a resource
that is held by T2,
T2 is waiting for a resource
that is held by T3 and so forth.
So this means the last,
the last actually requirement
give us a way to detect deadlocks.
Okay?
So how is that?
So basically you want to detect that cycle.
So let's use the same symbols.
You already use them, but.
The threats are circles.
The resources are rectangles
and you have multiple dots.
So this resource,
each dot represent an instance of a particular resource.
So for instance, you have a CPU is four cores.
You are going to have four dots,
each representing one core.
Okay?
And the pattern of manipulating a resource is very simple.
You request the resource, you use the resource,
you release the resource after you are done.
And now we can have a resource allocation graph.
And there are two types of,
we have two types of vertices,
threads and resources, resource types,
and two types of vertices or edges.
Sorry, and two types of edges.
These are directed edge.
If a thread, you have a edge from a thread TI
to a resource RJ,
if thread TI request the resource J.
And then you have assignment edge,
which it's a direct edge from RJ
to thread TI,
when thread TI allocates
or has allocated resource RJ.
Okay?
So basically here in this example,
this edge from R1 to T2 basically says that T2 own R1.
The edge from T1 to R1 says that T1 request resource R1.
Okay?
So this is some examples.
So you see here,
let's see which are,
it turns out and we are going to learn more about that,
but it turns out that this middle examples,
it seems that that look.
Why?
Because two reasons.
First of all, you have a cycle.
You see here,
T1 was for R1,
which is own R1 is owned by T2.
And T2 ways are for R...
Oh, I'm sorry.
I am sorry.
The cycle is this one.
R3, T2, R2, T3.
So T2 owns R3,
request R2,
which is owned by T3.
And finally, T3 request for R3,
which is owned by T2.
So this is a deadlock because you have the cycle
and the other condition, if you remember here,
another requirement is hold on wait.
Threat holding at least one resource is waiting
to acquire additional resource held by other threats.
So every threat here in this example,
it's in this situation, right?
It's waiting for a resource handled by another threat.
Here is an example,
which is, there is a cycle,
T1, R1, T3, R2.
But this is not deadlock
because T2 and T4 own a resource,
but they don't do it for any other resource.
Okay?
And the reason this is not a deadlock,
again, we'll learn more in the next,
in the remaining of this lecture and the next lecture,
is that T2 and T4 can proceed.
Can run to completion.
And once they run to completion,
they free an instance of R1 and R2 respectively.
I see, yeah.
How does R3 have two assignment edges?
Assignment, good answer.
There are two instances.
Yes, like I said, so you can look about this R3 and R4.
As type of resources.
And the dots within these rectangles
are the number of instances of that particular type.
And typically one thread here
will require one instance of a particular resource type.
Okay.
So we do have also a deadlock detection algorithms.
You want an algorithm.
And the deadlock detection algorithms is very simple.
Okay?
So you keep an array of free resources.
Then you have an array of requests,
threads of the current, you know,
current request from thread X.
And you have also, so for each thread X,
you have the current request of that thread
and the current resources are located by that thread.
Okay?
So you initialize the available resources
to the free resources, right?
The free resources are the one which are available.
Then you look at all the nodes which are unfinished.
You keep all the nodes, which are all threads.
This represents all threads, which are not finished.
And you take one by one,
and you look whether you have enough available resources
for that thread to finish.
In other words, if the requested resources
by that thread can be satisfied
by the existing available resources.
And if yes, you are going to run the thread,
and then now all the resources, once the thread finishes
are going to be added to the availability.
Set, because they are available now.
Okay?
So you do that.
And if there are no longer unfinished resources,
when, if there are no longer items in,
or threads in the finished list, you are done.
There is not a deadlock.
Otherwise, there is a deadlock.
(silence)
So not left in unfinished are deadlocked.
Okay?
So let me, there is a question here,
but T1 and T2, T3 is still in deadlock.
Oh, okay.
So I can say, so, okay.
So let me say here.
So this is a question.
It's a great timing for that question.
So,
so the question here, yes, you know, T2 and T4 finishes,
but T1 and T3 are still in deadlock.
So here is a thing.
If you run this algorithm, what will happen?
You see, T2 actually will finish execution.
And once T2 finishes execution,
it releases the instance of R1.
Now there is one available R1 instance.
So T1 can acquire that instance.
And now T1 has both instance of R2 and R1.
So it can run and complete.
Okay?
So that's a trick because the T2,
whenever you have a threat, which can complete,
think that is going to release, you know,
once it finishes, the number of free resources,
available resources is going to increase,
which will give an opportunity to other threat,
which are blocked until then, to acquire the newly,
the new release resources and to finish themself.
And then they're going to finish,
even more resources are going to be available
for the, in the system for the other threats to finish.
So how should we deal with a deadlock?
There are four different approaches.
Deadlock prevention,
so you write your code in a way that is not,
deadlock cannot happen.
It can't happen.
Deadlock recovery, you let the deadlock happen
and then figure out how to recover from it.
Remember it's those like, you know,
on the bridge, a car which can back up.
You can preempt the resource or things like that.
Deadlock avoidance, with deadlock avoidance,
you can dynamically delay resource requests
so deadlock doesn't happen.
You can order and impose the order and the time
when different threats, they request resources.
Right, so now a very simple example from the beginning,
if you remember, you just say, well, you know,
first you let duty one acquire the resources
and then duty two, and then there is no deadlock.
Well, the last one, you know,
it's obviously not a solution.
It's, you can deny the deadlock and see what happens.
Maybe you are lucky.
What is the difference between deadlock avoidance
and deadlock prevention?
That's a very good question.
Deadlock avoidance is that you can write your code,
for instance, deadlock prevention, meaning that,
for instance, you make sure that you never had
more threats than the resources.
Right, you have plenty of resources.
Then you prevent the deadlock.
Deadlock avoidance is that deadlock can happen,
but you can make sure and you write your,
you know, your code and you are trying to schedule
your threats and you are trying to order
as a resource request so that all doesn't happen.
So like in our examples of, you know, trains,
when you go south, east, west, and then north, south,
then you don't go first north, south,
and then east, west.
But they are related and yeah.
Okay, so many operating systems avoid the deadlock.
You know, they don't, you know, ignore the deadlock.
When can you ignore the deadlock?
To let me, you know, here we are making a little bit of fun
that, you know, denial in this Oistrich algorithm.
So, you know, you pretend the problem is not,
doesn't happen, is not happening.
But when actually deadlock denial, it's okay.
When crashing, freezing isn't that big of a problem, yes.
And when they are very, very, happen very rarely.
When it happens very rarely, okay.
That's what, when it's okay.
And if you were to push a deadlock, you know,
to do deadlock prevention or avoidance,
will require very expensive algorithms,
will dramatically increase the complexity of the system.
Right?
So preventing deadlocks, like I mentioned,
you have enough resources
so that no one ever runs out of resources, right?
But other things, every source can be shared,
like the CPU.
You have 100, you have one thread, fine.
You have 10 threads, fine.
You have 1000 threads, fine.
Everyone will be slower,
but still you are going to get your share of the CPU.
And finally, like you don't allow waiting, right?
And this is what happens in many cases, right?
When you call and the other part is not available
or when the system is overloaded,
you get a busy signal, right?
Failure.
Try again.
The same in ethernet, in the networking.
There are a collision between the packets.
Try again.
Okay?
So it's again, it's inefficient.
And in some cases you cannot do it,
but it can be inefficient in some cases,
but it's a very simple method.
So this is an example,
if you have infinite resources in our case
in which the deadlock happened
because limited resources, no longer a problem.
Another way to, yeah.
Another way to do it is to prevent the deadlock
is to require everything at the beginning.
Everyone requires everything at the beginning.
And therefore, you know,
and you know exactly what everyone is using.
So you can allocate from, at the beginning,
resources to everyone so that you make sure
there is no prevention, there is no deadlock.
And then force all stress to request resources
in particular order, like we discussed.
But here, you know, it's a very, very important thing
is that one thing this happens
when you acquire the locks X and Y and Y and X
is because these two operations of acquiring the two locks,
they are not atomic.
But what if the operation of acquiring these locks is atomic?
Then everything will work, right?
Because only one of the threads will be successful.
And the thread which is successful
is going to run to completion,
is going to release the two resources, two locks,
and the other strand is going to come up and run.
And how do you do that?
In practice?
Well, use another lock to make sure
that acquiring the locks X and Y are atomic.
Okay?
So that's why I do it.
You can also do it, like I said earlier on,
that by enforcing the order.
So in this case, if you both threads A and B
acquire the same order, again, you are fine.
Does it matter in which order the locks are released?
No, because the release is not awaiting operation.
Okay.
So we are going to stop here
and we are going to continue talking about deadlocks
next lecture.
Good luck with project one
and see you all virtually on a Saturday.
Thank you.
(upbeat music)
[ Silence ]