Hello, everyone.
So today, during today's lecture, we are going to finish the discussion on the deadlocks
and then continue to learn about virtual memory and address translation.
So last time, we spent quite a bit on deadlocks.
Deadlocks is a very important concept.
And if you remember, there are four requirements which needs to happen to have a deadlock.
The first is mutual exclusion.
That means that only one thread at a time can use a particular resource.
The second is hold and wait.
That is a thread holding holds at least one resource and is waiting to acquire additional
resources which are held by other threads.
So this means that the thread cannot make progress because it needs the other resources
in order to make to finish the computation, which again are owned by other threads.
No preemptions.
Resources are released only voluntarily by a thread holding the resource.
So a thread cannot preempt another thread to get the resource to finish the computation.
And then in circular wait, so you have a cycle, which is a cycle which is defined by the pattern
that a thread is waiting for a resource that is held by another thread.
And that thread is waiting for a resource that is held by another thread and so on until
you get a cycle.
Also last, there are several techniques we listed last time to resolve a deadlock.
And one of them is to recover from the deadlock.
And some of the things we mentioned last time was to terminate the thread.
So therefore, you can terminate a thread which owns the resource so other threads can acquire
the resource and can finish their computation.
Of course, you don't always want to do that.
In some cases, it's pretty hard.
Like for instance, you can kill a thread which is modifying some sensitive data or important
data.
Then you can, like for instance, updating your bank balance.
You don't want to do that because you may end up with garbage.
Preempt resources without killing of a thread.
This means that the system has the ability to suspend a thread.
And then you can preempt that resource while that thread is suspended or is sleeping.
And another thread can get that resource and again, complete the computation.
And when the thread which are suspended comes back, hopefully there are enough resources
for that type of computation.
Rollback the actions.
If you remember in our example, it's a bridge and you have two cars on a one line bridge
coming head to head in the middle of the bridge.
One way to resolve the problem is a deadlock is for one car to back up.
And when you look at the operating system, some of them use some of these options.
Like for instance, when system hangs, right?
Typically when system hangs and you can't do anything about it, in some cases it's a
deadlock.
In many cases.
So how do you do it?
You reboot it, right?
So you kill everything.
And preempting resources, this operating system is doing that.
You know threads are preempted, are put on the waiting queue.
And yeah, these are a few examples.
So also we talk about another example last time.
Another way, obviously you can solve the deadlock problem if you have infinite resources, right?
If you have infinite resources means that every thread at any given time has all the
resources it needs to continue to progress and to finish its computation.
And this is relevant here as an example about the second part of the lecture when we are
going to talk about virtual memory.
And because virtual memory, it provides you a memory which is much larger than the physical
memory.
You can think about for most applications, the same infinite space, infinite memory.
The one thing though is that as we will see under the hood of the virtual memory, the
virtual memory is implemented.
You are going to load different parts of the virtual memory in the physical memory.
And then you are going to offload to move some of the parts of the virtual memory of
the threads which are not running off the physical memory.
You put them on the disk.
And in doing so, you basically the solution under the hood is to preempt, right?
You preempt the physical memory storage which contains a virtual memory data from one thread
with another, with a virtual memory content of another thread.
We'll talk more about that.
That is something, it's a nice relation between the deadlock solutions and virtual memory.
So the next mechanism of resolving the deadlock problem, it's deadlock avoidance, right?
And this is different from deadlock prevention, which we talked last time quite a bit.
So deadlock prevention, if you remember, it design your program so that you never run
into deadlock, right?
Like all the resources are going to be acquired in the same order by everyone, right?
Things like that.
Now deadlock avoidance is basically is that it's more dynamic.
It's a more dynamic way to avoid, sorry, deadlock avoidance is a more dynamic way to avoid deadlocks.
And this is basically the operating system in this case.
It checks at everyone, you make every resource request, whether it can result in a deadlock.
And if the operating system convince itself that if it grants this request, there is a
way in which you don't get into a deadlock state, then it's granting the resource to
the state which asks for it.
Otherwise, it does not.
Okay.
Let me see the question here.
Oh, sorry.
That's a great question.
The slides is my mistake.
Let me, okay, let me give me 30 seconds to upload them and they're going to be available
in a few moments.
Yeah, I apologize for that.
Silence.
Okay, so I pushed them so, you know, after a bit of time, they are going to be available.
Okay.
Sorry.
And thanks for flagging it up.
Okay.
So let's see how this, you know, in this example, it's like we gave this as a canonical example
we used last time to illustrate the deadlock.
And here, if you remember, you have two threads and both threads A and B acquire resources
or the lock Y, X, and Y, but they acquire them in a different order.
So let's say thread A acquire X and let B acquire B. So thread B acquire Y.
So in this case, it's not working.
You have deadlock, right?
Because if Y tries to acquire, because if A tries to acquire Y, it can no longer do
that because B already holds Y.
Okay.
So this will, this doesn't work, right?
So this is what we want to avoid.
So in this particular case, the point here is that, you know, if you go back, once the
system allocated X to A, then it shouldn't, when B asks for Y, it should not grant access
to that resource.
It shouldn't grant that the resource Y or the lock, right?
Because if you grant it, now there is a potential for deadlock.
Okay.
And now, intuitively, you see, if the operating system doesn't grant Y to B, then A has the
opportunity to request Y, and now the operating system can grant Y to A. So A now has both
X and Y, so can complete this computation and then release both X and Y, right?
So that's kind of what you want to happen.
And this is exactly what the deadlock avoidance is trying to do.
Okay.
Intuitively.
So with the deadlock avoidance, you have two states, a safe state and a deadlock state.
Okay.
And in the safe state, means that there is a way to allocate the resources to the existing
threads such that every thread is going to complete.
So there is no deadlock.
Deadlock means there is a deadlock in the system.
So the four requirements we talk about are all hold.
These are the two main states, and then there is another unsafe state.
There is no deadlock yet, but threads can require resources in a pattern that unavoidable
leads to deadlock.
So basically right now, there is no deadlock.
But the deadlock is imminent.
You cannot do anything about it.
Okay.
You are on the way for the deadlock to happen.
So this is what unsafe state.
Okay.
So with a deadlock avoidance, you just try to prevent the system from reaching an unsafe
state.
Because if you reach an unsafe state, eventually you are going to reach a deadlock state.
Okay.
And the main idea here is when a thread requests a resource, the operating system checks if
it will result, if granting that resource would lead to an unsafe state.
Okay.
If it will not lead to an unsafe state, it's going to grant the resource.
If not, it's not going to grant and is going to wait for the existing threads to finish
and release some resource.
So let again look at the previous example.
And I already mentioned to you the solution, but let's do it again.
So thread A acquires X.
Now thread B ask for Y, but we do not give Y to B until A finishes.
Okay.
Because if we give grant Y to B, as you know, it can, it results in deadlock.
And the classic algorithm for avoiding deadlock, it's a banker algorithms.
And basically what you, you know, the idea here is that each thread is states the maximum
number of resources in its inner bass, right?
And allow a thread to proceed only if available resources in the system minus requested resources
in the system is greater than the maximum number of resources required by a thread.
Right.
And this is important.
You need to stay upfront how many resources you have, because if you don't, the system
doesn't have the information.
And at any given time in the future, you can, you being a thread, ask for more resources.
Right.
So there is no way actually to protect the deadlock in this situation.
So banker algorithms allocate the resource dynamically.
So he's looking at each request, resource request, and then it decide whether to grant
a request, a resource or not, if the resulting state remains a safe state.
And the techniques is very simple.
You pretend that each request is granted.
Then you run the deadlock detection algorithm.
So you remember the last time we are looking, we are, we learn about deadlock detection
algorithm.
Okay.
So it's very simple.
In the deadlock detection algorithms, you are looking whether the requested resources
by a particular thread are, it can be satisfied.
So it's less than the resource availability.
Right.
In this case, we are looking at how many more resources a thread needs in the worst case.
Which is a max node, is a node in the graph.
And you know, that's why it's called node here.
But you can replace node with a thread, but the maximum number of resources that the thread
still needs is a maximum number of resources overall that thread needs minus the number
of resources the thread already owns.
Okay.
So this is again, if you remember, this is the algorithms to detect the deadlock.
So the only change you need to make here is that we need to, we are going to replace request,
number of request resources with the maximum number of resources that node or thread can
still need, will still need in the worst case.
So that's what it is.
Right.
So just to look a little bit more at the code, you put all nodes, again, all threads in unfinished
you have available resources, which is amount of the number of resources which are free
in the system.
And then you are going to look at all nodes in unfinished, which are still computing.
And for each of them, you are looking at that, you know, can if the amount of resources that
thread is going to require in, to ask for in the worst case is less than the available
resources.
And if yes, is fine.
You remove from unfinished because we know that we are looking at those resources with
the thread will finish for sure.
Right.
And we'll never ask for more resources than that.
And then you iterate and it's until you are done.
Okay.
Thank you.
Bye.
Can you explain what a lock means?
A lock means allocate--
a lock is the resources which are already
allocated to a thread.
So say I have a thread--
so let me just go--
let me just--
nothing better than an example.
OK, so in this example, both threads, the max will be 2,
because they require x and y, right?
Or it's a vector.
Depends how you want to look at it.
But in this case, we understand both threads requires x and y.
This is the max, initially.
Now, when the thread A gets x, in this case, x is alloc
in the alloc--
allocated vector.
So the amount is the number of resources
which are already allocated to the thread.
Max is still x and y.
So when you do max, max, x and y, max minus alloc,
in this case, you get what?
You get y, because max is x and y.
Alloc is x.
So you get y.
So in this case, in the worst case,
that thread A still is going to ask for y.
OK?
the system in a safe state means
that there exists a sequence in which your grand request
to the threads which are unfinished so that all threads
are going to finish.
So let's apply this algorithms to the dining
philosopher problem or lawyer's problem.
So what is a deadlock here?
The deadlock here is that when each person picks a job stick
and they have only one job stick,
there is no other job stick available, so no one can eat.
OK?
So what is a safe state here?
Is that when you can grant a request to a job stick?
You can grant one is that there is not the last job stick.
Because if we have still one job stick,
we can give that job stick to someone
who has already one job stick.
And that person is going to finish eating.
And now you get two chopsticks.
So you can give these chopsticks to other people to eat.
OK?
Or this is the last job stick, but you give to someone
who already has a job stick.
Because if you do so, then that person,
you gave the second job stick, can finish eating.
OK?
What happens if you have--
you generalize the problem with K-handed people,
like octopus?
Think about like you have octopuses which are dying.
You can generalize that.
So basically, the last one and no one could have K.
It's the second to last one, and no one have K minus 1,
and so forth.
Right?
Because otherwise, if you allocate--
if you grant the chopstick by violating
any of these conditions, then you can end up in that lock.
So in summary, there are four conditions.
By the way, any questions about Banker's algorithm?
So again, at the high level, the idea is very simple.
Each thread is going to tell you in advance,
to say in advance, how many resources it needs.
And then what you do, the operating system
is going to grant a request to a resource.
If by granting that request, you remain in safe state.
And in safe state means that there
is a way to grant the request to the existing threads,
such that every thread is going to finish.
What is K minus 2?
So here, K minus 2, here you assume
that instead of having two hands, that person or entity
will have K hands.
And in order to eat that octopus, it needs OK chopsticks.
So if you have one chopstick left,
and someone else asks for the chopstick,
you do not give that chopstick to that person.
Unless that person has K chopsticks.
And the same next, if you have two chopsticks, which
are not allocated, you would not give that chopstick
to a person unless at least one other person
has K minus 1 chopsticks.
Because otherwise, if you give the chopstick
to another person, and none of the person
has K minus 1 chopsticks, they have K minus 2 or less,
now you are in unsafe state.
Because you have only one chopstick left,
and no one else has more than K minus 2 chopsticks.
So no matter to whom I am going to give the last chopstick,
no one else can eat.
No one can eat.
OK?
So there are four conditions for deadlock to happen.
Mutual exclusion, hold on weight, no preemption,
and circular weight.
And there are several techniques to addressing the deadlock
problem.
Deadlock prevention, you write your code in a way
that it's not prone to the deadlock.
You set up some rules so that if everyone respects these rules,
you cannot have deadlock, for instance.
Deadlock recovery, you let the deadlock happen and then
figure out how to recover.
You can preempt a thread, you can suspend a thread,
you can roll back.
Deadlock avoidance, this is what we just learned,
the banker algorithms, which then you basically
delay resource requests.
So deadlock doesn't happen.
And finally, of course, deadlock denial,
you just ignore this deadlock because it may never happen.
Or this happens so infrequently, and when it happens,
there is not a big issue.
So announcements.
Project one, congrats for completing your first project.
So we are planning to release the grades for your midterm
by Monday, like I mentioned last time.
And project two will be released today.
So good luck for project two.
So now I am going to switch gears,
and I am going to talk about virtual memory.
And we'll start to remind everyone
to recall about virtualizing resources.
Memory is just another resource which you visualize.
But before then, let me stop and ask you
whether you have any questions about what
we've learned so far or any other question.
OK, so it seems there are no questions.
So let's go ahead.
So remember that what we want in the operating system
was to provide to the application
is the illusion that each application has
its own machine on which it runs.
It has its own resources.
But of course, the physical machines
have limited resources.
So therefore, you need to kind of virtualize
this virtual machine, this physical machine,
to different applications, different processes, which
means that virtualization means that you need--
if you have more application or more processes, which
is a common case, then the physical resources,
the only way you can visualize resources is to multiplex them.
And you can multiplex them in space or in time.
So one classic example about virtualizing in time is CPU.
You multiplex the CPU so that in time quanta,
so for each time quanta, you let another process run.
And therefore, each process has the illusion
that it owns a CPU, a slower CPU than the physical CPU.
The second one is another important resource is memory.
And this is what we are going to start learning about today,
how to virtualize the memory.
And the other important one is a disk or storage.
Now, why memory is important?
Why do you want to virtualize memory?
Of course.
It's very important because the entire state of a process
or application is stored--
or not entire state, but most of the state or the active state,
the state which is used by the process when it runs,
is stored in memory and registers.
And therefore, as you know, you cannot have two threads use
the same memory.
Always use the same memory because it's, again,
like two different pieces of data cannot
occupy the same location.
And you don't want--
sometimes, you don't want threads
to have access to each other memory.
And here, you have memory protection.
And remember, how do you provide memory protection?
You provide them-- we are going to see the mechanics here.
But the abstraction is a process.
Each process is its own memory.
All the threads in the same process share that memory.
Threads in the different processes
cannot share the memory, cannot see each other memory, cannot
access each other memory.
So OK.
Now, going back and recalling the four fundamental OS
concepts, we have thread, which is execution context.
It represents the control state, which
is program counter, registers, everything
which is needed to execute that thread.
Then is the address space, which owns the entire memory,
accessible by the program for accessing means read and write.
Then is a process, which is an instance of a running program.
And the process, it's address space plus one more thread.
And then we have this dual operation,
dual mode operation between the system and user.
And the system has the ability to access
more resources than the user, user programs.
So let's talk then about virtualized memory.
First, let's start with the concept of address space
and address translation.
An address space is a set of a contiguous set
of memory addresses, which are seen
by the process or the application.
Typically, the unit for memory is byte,
and the size is expressed in power of two.
So for instance, if you have 2 power 10 bytes,
this means you have 1,024 bytes, which
is one kilobyte, with capital B. Capital B stands for byte.
A byte has eight bits.
And then you have an address.
And the address is used to access individual bytes
in this address space.
Again, the number of bits in the address
is basically in this case is k or 10 in this example.
It's the exponent of two when you define compute the memory
size.
And this should be very easy to remember.
If you have n addresses, how many bits you need
to encode these n addresses?
A bit has two values, 0 and 1.
So you need log of n.
In this case, n is 2k.
Log base 2 of 2k is k.
How many bits of address each byte--
bits of address-- how many bits you
need to address each byte in a four kilobyte page?
Is 12, right?
Because 2 power 12 is four kilobytes.
And obviously, if you have 20 bits to address,
you can address 2 power 20 bytes.
If you have 32 bits, you can address 2 power 32 bytes
and so forth.
But this is what a process see, a contiguous set of addresses.
And typically, at each address, you have one byte.
You can store one byte.
One byte is eight bits.
And then the process uses this address space
to store various information, code and data.
An accessible address-- accessible addresses
are all the addresses a process can read and write or write,
and the state associated with them.
So what is stored at that particular address?
In some cases, we are also measuring or give
the size of a memory in words.
And a word typically has more than one byte.
So for instance, a four word is 32 bits.
So one question here is, how many 32-bit numbers or four-byte
words you can fit in an address space of--
with 32 bits, right?
Well, you have 32 bits, so you have 2 power 32 bytes.
You need to divide by 4, because a word is 4 bytes,
so you get 2 power 30, which is 1 billion.
Now, we are going to--
more about that, but just for you to know that when you read and write to an address,
there are many things can happen. The most natural thing is that you read and write
that particular piece of data, which is associated with the address that you read and write.
But other things could happen. You can actually, when you write to special designated addresses,
or you read from special designated addresses, you can read and write to some device like display.
And these are memory mapped IO operations, they are called. It can cause a program to abort.
When is a program or do segfault? When this can happen, when does program segfault?
You should know by now. You've done
homeworks, projects, I'm sure that many of you had this unfortunate experience.
And map memory. Yeah, so basically, if I'm trying to access an address, which is not accessible to me.
I'm going to read from and write from an address which is not accessible to me.
So that's one. So some addresses owned by other processes.
OK, so as you know, in the address space, there are four important segments for each process.
You have the code segment, which contains a code you are going to execute.
The stack segment, which you know it's used to push the return addresses when you call a function
and also pass the arguments to that function, is a heap for dynamically allocating memory.
And it's static data, which is for what? For static data, as it implies, like global variables.
You've seen this picture many, many times. I apologize for showing you again.
But if you remember the relation, this shows you again the relation between a process and a thread.
A process can have multiple threads.
All threads in the same process share resources, including most of the memory resources,
including heap, static, and code segments. The only one segment they don't share is the stack
and the registers, obviously. And the reason you don't share the stack, because again, the stack
contains the state of the execution. If you call a function in the thread,
then you have to push the return on the stack. So now that represents the execution state of that
thread. And you can also have a single-threaded process, which has a single thread.
There are three important aspects of memory multiplexing. One is protection. You prevent a
process from accessing the data of another process. The second one is translation.
It's the ability to translate from a virtual address space to a physical address space.
We'll learn about it. Okay. And when this translation occurs, you are going to have
these virtual addresses. And this can be used to avoid overlap or talk next,
provide a uniform view to the program, to the process.
And also can be used to provide protection. And the control overlap is
it's separate state of the thread should not collide in physical memory.
So this means that again, we have only one physical memory in the same
on a single machine. So you have different processes, different threads. They shouldn't
collide. They shouldn't, for instance, share the same data segments.
So an alternative view is to have to look at what is the allowable process behavior,
what you allow process to do. And
this, what is allowed to do, it's regulated by the operating system, as you know.
So the operating system in one way, it's interposing itself. So to make sure that the
processes are well behaved. That's why the processes do not do anything bad.
So the operating system is handling the I/O operations on the behalf of the processes.
It makes sure that every process gets access to the CPU.
And like we'll see, it's going to make sure that each process, it gets its own
physical memory under the hood. Okay.
So the question is, how do you enforce that?
In the previous two cases, the operating system, as you know, is like this requires a context
switch, right? I/O operation, it's a Cisco, it's a context switch. For the CPU, to share them,
to multiplex the CPU between different processes or threads, we need to do context switch, right?
And context switch, remember, it's very, it's expensive. It can be tens of thousands,
hundreds of thousands of instructions. So now the question here is what about the memory?
It doesn't seem that the memory, you can do that on every access to the memory.
It's too expensive. So you need to have another way to make this kind of translation to interpose,
to have this interposition layer between the virtual memory and the physical memory.
And if there are exception cases, like you'll see, like page fault, we'll see that, then you can give
the control to the operating system. You can have the operating system interposing itself.
We'll learn about that, OK?
Please again, this is a previous picture you're seeing in one of the first lectures.
Everything here in this big box, it's hardware in the operating system, and it with this big box
provides a virtualization of the OS and of the machine to the application. That's all
of the operating system. So, and just for big picture, what happens under the hood when you
execute a program, if you remember, you copy the program, it's on the disk, right? You copy the code
in the memory and then you start executing. So let's see what happens when you execute. And here
it's a very snippet of assembly language. And basically what happens here, you load
some from this address data one, you load the data which is there in register R1,
and depending on the value, you are going to jump to this address. Otherwise, you are going to
decrement the value and then you are going to look, you go to until it's not zero, B and Z means
R1 is not zero, you go back, right? So basically, as long as it's not, and when it's zero, you jump
out of, you terminate, right? So basically again, this code, take a piece of data, checks it,
and then you decrement it and then you look, you go back.
So what is in memory for this program or do you store? So in memory, you have only bits, right?
And this is an example here.
And you have two columns for the physical address. The column on the left are the addresses
and the column on the right are the content, is the content of the node.
In this memory layout, we are using four byte words. How do you see that?
You see this number here on the right, 0000, you know, you have one, two, three, four, five, six,
zero, seven, and twenty. So you have eight characters. Each of these characters
represent eight bits, sorry, represent four bits, right? So it's a hexadecimal format.
So it's from zero to F, each of these is from zero to F. So you have eight of them,
eight times four, it's 32 bits. So you have 32 bits word or four byte word.
The things with the red are the addresses which also appear in the program. You have three
addresses, four addresses. One is the address for this data one. This is red. The blue one is
the check it address. And the green one, it's a loop address.
OK. So now, tell me now, I said that, say take with the red, I said that this 00C0,
which is a program refers to this 0300. Can you figure out how these are connected
and why they are connected? Why basically the same thing?
OK, so here it is.
If you address the memory at 32 bits boundaries, so an address as the word granularity,
each of these four bytes. OK, you need four times fewer addresses. OK, that's what it is.
So that's basically what happens here. When the program is going to
do your compiles the program and when you allocate the memory, everything happens at four word,
four byte granularity or 32 bits granularity. So therefore, at this granularity, you need
four times fewer, so to speak, addresses or bits. So this is what happens here. So 00C0 is 0300,
but is at 32 bits granularity instead of at the 8 bit or byte granularity.
Indeed, if you multiply C0 by four, you get 300.
Any questions here?
OK, so the same for the other one. If you multiply 280, you are going to get
800. If you multiply 0242 by four, you get 0908.
And now this is how these values are stored in the physical memory. It's another way,
another representation. Right, so you have the values in these boxes and the addresses on the
side. So now here is a question. Say I am running this program and this program loads into physical
memory. And this addresses, right, because these are the addresses maybe in the program.
On the disk. If I run again this program.
What will happen? Right.
If I run again this program, I don't want to load to be loaded exactly in the same place.
Right, because a different instance of the program.
Like different data.
So that's one of the problems we need to solve. We need this translation. Right.
So one way to do the translation. So instead of I modify these addresses with this nuance,
and now all these other addresses will not overlap with the previous instance. They are going to not
overlap, to be non-overlapping. And you are going to be able to load the second time you run the
same program at a different address space. So the two programs now, they don't step on each other.
OK. So, you know, there are many way to, you know, the possible way to translate. This is
only one possibility, of course. So translation can happen at two times. The link time.
When or before, you know, or execution time. Right. And
well, it's compile time, link time and execution time. But link or load time. So compile time,
you know, it's very hard. We are not going to talk much about it. The link and load time,
we are going to talk briefly and then we are going to focus mostly on the translation
happen and execution time. So before talking about link load time translation, let's remind
ourselves what is the lifetime of a program. You start with a source. You compile, you get the
object modules and then you link with possible other modules and libraries and then you load it
in the memory. And in the process, you are going also to link with some system libraries
and some libraries you can actually link them.
at the runtime after you started executing.
Okay.
But here is our previous example.
Actually what implicitly we've done,
you modify the addresses before loading to memory.
So this is linked load time when you modify the others.
Right? Remember here, we said this is our program, right?
And maybe this is on the disk,
but when I am cooperating system is going to load
this program in memory,
is going to override these addresses
so that it's not going to overlap with other programs
which are already in the physical memory.
So this is what happens. Okay.
Okay.
So,
make sense? It's any questions?
Now, a little bit of history.
Again, the earliest operating systems
for personal computers were very simple.
You have only one address space
and you have only one application running at a given time.
So the application was owning
the entire physical address space.
You have the illusion of a dedicated machine
because you have a dedicated machine.
Okay.
So how do you do this?
Now is the next step.
If you start to work to run multiple programs,
you want to run in the same computer.
It's again, if the operating system
doesn't provide you support,
like we'll see for translation,
the one way you can do it, like we've just seen,
is basically translation.
You translate the addresses of the program
before you load it to avoid overlapping,
conflicting with another program.
And this was the case for early version
of the Microsoft Windows 3.
I mean, the early version of the Windows.
With these things, it's risky.
There is no protection to the buggy code.
And all applications here have access to the entire memory.
So one application can read and write
the data from another application.
So it can also crash another application.
The next level is to provide protection.
You steal one address space,
steal the applications are going to be,
the addresses will be overwritten
when by the loader,
before loading the application, the program to the memory.
But now you do have protection.
How do you have protections?
Base and bound.
You remember about this, we talked about that.
You have a base and the bound
and associated with each application.
And you make sure that when the application
is going to address the memory,
that address, access the memory,
that address is going to be between base and bound.
Yeah, so this was in tray one supercomputer,
one of the first supercomputer.
Okay, this is what we do if you know, right?
We have the address of the program here, 101.
The base you have, base is 100, bound 1100.
So when you use address, you are going to check,
sorry, you are going to check
whether it's between 100 and 110.
If it is, you can access the memory,
otherwise you are going to segfault.
Okay, so you protect and isolate programs,
but it requires you to again override the addresses
of the application before the program, before you load it.
This is also called relocating loader.
A loader like that is doing that rewriting
is called relocating loader.
Okay, can be very fast.
Of course, the base and bounds
are going to be implemented in hardware.
And it's only comparison, no addition or nothing.
Can be done extremely fast.
Okay, so to summarize, we saw uniprogramming, no protection,
one program at a given time,
multiprogramming, no protection,
but you have multiple programs at a given time
in the same physical memory.
And you need a relocating loader
to make sure that the programs, when you load them,
you override their addresses
so that they don't step on each other.
And finally here, we have again, no protection,
one physical memory, no virtualization,
but you have also base and bounds to, sorry.
So in this case, again, you have only one,
again, you have only one address, physical memory,
only one other space, which is shared by the applications.
But in this case, you provide protection
by using base and bounds.
This is provided in hardware.
So now, it's a time, this is a pretty complicated,
like relocating loader and so forth.
It's pretty complicated and it's pretty limited.
So next, we are going to start discussing
about the general address translation, okay?
And the general address translation is happening this way.
You have the CPU, remember this,
because sometimes it's least to confusion.
When the CPU issues an instruction, in general,
the instructions contain virtual addresses.
So these virtual addresses are then mapped
to the physical address.
And they are done typically by chip
or a part of the processor,
which is called MMU, memory management unit.
So the programs, because they are running on the CPU,
they see virtual address spaces.
Okay?
From the memory side, you have only physical addresses.
So,
you know, in translation, it's a generalized technique,
which helps you with many things.
But if you really want,
but if you only want, like I mentioned, protections,
control overlap and things like that.
But if you really want to implement only one of these things
like protection, like we've seen in the past,
things are easier.
And why you want protection?
Because if task A cannot gain access to task B data,
no way for A to adversely affect you.
Now, if you have the translation,
then every program can be linked or loaded
into the same region of the user space.
Right?
So you have, again, you have two application in this case.
Both applications have different virtual addresses,
virtual address space,
because they have their own process.
And each process has its own address space,
virtual address space.
These both applications,
they can see the same virtual memory.
Both of them, they see virtual memory,
say from zero, zero, zero to FFF.
The trick here is that these two address spaces
are going to be mapped to different location
in the physical memory by using translation.
That's what the translation gives you.
Let's consider examples.
Okay?
So it's one way to do it.
It's a very simple change of the previous
Bayesian bound technique.
And here is a difference.
Let me just go back to make sure that it's different, right?
This is a difference.
In this case, the Bayesian bound, right?
Are absolute addresses.
And the program address is also absolute address.
You have one, zero, one, zero.
And absolute meaning I am referring to physical addresses.
So you need to compare one, zero, one, zero
with the base and with the bound.
With translation, the program address is not absolute.
It's relative to the bound, to the base address.
So actually the real address, physical address,
is a program address plus the base.
Okay?
So in this case, the program address is zero, zero, one, zero
and base address is one, zero, zero, zero.
So if you add them up, it's one, zero, one, zero.
And these addresses are translated on the fly.
Right? Very convenient.
So you see now, these program addresses,
they don't need to be changed.
The only thing I need to change in order to make sure
that programs are mapped into different address spaces,
physical address spaces,
is to just change the base address.
Right?
Indeed.
This is, it's harder for location.
It's also called then basically, you know,
a question here.
Can you touch the program?
Can you touch the OS?
But if you are careful, we are not going,
you cannot touch the OS because the OS will be outside
the base address and the bound address of any user process.
Can you touch other programs?
No, if you are careful.
That's how you provide protection.
But it's, again, it's a very simple idea.
Okay. Any questions about that?
Do you see how now I no longer need to override
the program addresses when I load the program in memory?
I just do that as a runtime when the program executes.
Any questions?
Okay.
So what are the issues with this Bayesian bound method?
The issue here is about what is called,
it's about fragmentation.
And this is a very simple example
because each process requires different amount of data,
the different amount of space, memory space.
So they are not uniform.
Okay. And because they are not uniform,
like in this case, process two requires a lot
and you process two goes away.
And as the process nine comes,
you allocate memory space of process nine,
process five goes away.
And now look at this situation.
You have process 11 and you have enough physical memory
for process 11.
But the point that this physical memory is scattered
and process 11 needs a contiguous region of memory.
Okay. So that's a problem.
Okay.
So how do you do it?
What is your solution here?
And there are many solutions,
but one simple solution is to have,
instead of only one segment for each program,
you can have different segments.
And typically you can have code segment, data segment,
stack segment, heap segment, right?
And you do this independently
and this gives you a little bit more flexibility.
Okay.
So also another problem is a solution I showed you here.
The original solution, the Bayesian bound,
is that remember about threads and processes.
You can have multiple threads in the same process
and the thread in the same process shares a code.
But how you are going to do it here?
Okay.
Because, right?
And even like think about actually,
you can think about maybe a better example
than what I said is libraries.
If you have common libraries, system libraries,
and with these libraries,
they are used by multiple applications.
So it makes no sense to load a copy of the library
for each application.
These are, again, shared system libraries.
Right?
How you do that?
Okay.
So again, now we can alleviate this problem.
Like I mentioned that instead of having
one segment per process, you have multiple segments.
Right?
Per process.
A typical one, like I mentioned,
you have code, data, stack, heap segment,
but in general, you can have a segment at one extreme,
you can have a segment for each function.
Right?
And for each segment, you have a base and a bound or a limit.
And now, because the segments are smaller,
you have more flexibility how to place them
in the physical memory.
Let me go back here.
Is this process 11?
If this process 11, maybe it had been consistent
from two segments, then you could have fit
process one in physical memory,
because maybe one segment of process one
would have fit in one of these gaps
and the other one is the other gap.
Okay?
So that's why how multiple segments can help.
And this is one version.
You have then a map.
How would you implement it?
Now you need a map, a segment map,
which needs to reside in the processor.
And then how do you address it?
How do we know which segment we are in?
So one way to do it is to divide the address space,
the virtual address, into two.
The first bits of the address,
or the most significant ones, represent the segment.
Going to the segment map.
And the second, and the other part of the address
is called the offset.
So when the processor issues such virtual address,
the processor takes the first, the segment bits,
its indexes in the segment map,
then it gets the base and the limit.
Okay?
The offset is added to the base.
And now this, you have the physical address,
and then you need also to compare the offset to the limit.
Right? To see that you are within the segment.
If not, it's an error.
And you are done.
Okay?
So now you can chunk the memory in as many chunks
as you have in this map table.
And this is what very early versions
of Intel 86 implemented.
80, you know, 86.
Okay?
So we are going to stop here.
We are at time.
And we are going to continue our discussion
on virtual memory next Monday.
Until then, good luck with project two.
As you know, it's good to start early.
So I'll see you then on virtual, I'll see you on Monday.
If you have any other questions, please let me know.
(silence)
Thank you.
So I'm happy to have you here.