Hello everyone. So, welcome. So we are going to continue our lecture on virtual memory.
And we are going to start discussion on caching and TLBs, which stands for translation lookaside
buffers.
So if you recall, address translation as a name implies, it's about translating the addresses
which are viewed by the application by the CPUs into physical addresses. And there are
a couple of reasons why we want to have these different kind of addresses for the application
and versus the physical addresses. And some of them are about providing the illusion to
each application, it has its own machine, its own resources, including the memory, which
means that then you need to map the address space of each of the application in the same
physical space, which is physical memory. And also another reason is protection because
you want to protect the address space of one application from another. And also sharing,
controlled sharing, if you remember, in which actually some parts of the address space you
want to be shared. For instance, the address space, which contains a code of a shared library,
of a library, which is a code of a library, which is used by two applications like Windows
library on your own Windows machine, you do not want to replicate that code in each application,
you want to share that code. And typically the sharing happens, it's handled by one of
these components, a chip, which is called memory management unit. So this was originally
was a standard on chip, which was you put near your, between the processor and the memory.
But of course, in the modern processors, it's just a component of that processor. And one
of the techniques to do address translation was a segment, we're using multi-segment model.
And in this case, if you remember, each segment is represented by a base and a limit. And
now the virtual address, the address, which is seen by the CPU and as seen by the application,
is split into two. The first part, the first few bits represent an index in the segment
table. And then there is an offset. So when you have a virtual address, you look at the
first field, which is a segment number, the first bits represent the segment number, use
that to index into segment table. And then in that segment table, you are going to find
the base of the segment and the limit. And you are going to compute the physical address
by adding the offset, which is the second field in the virtual address to the base,
the segment base. And of course, you are also going to check whether the address is generated
is less than the limit. So it's within the segment. You also have in some architecture,
actually in Intel x86, instead of having the first bits in the address, in the virtual
address, it's presenting the base indexing into the segment table. You have just a bunch
of segments. You have initially have four segments and these segments are base segments
are stored in special registers like ES, this is S is for the stack and three other registers.
Okay. And then you compute the address by taking the virtual address and you are going
to add it to the segment register. And that's how you are going to compute the physical
address. Finally, there is a bit valid or not valid. And this is one use of this one
is that not all segments of all applications can fit in the physical memory at the same
time. So when you run out of space in the physical memory and you want to load your
certain new application and your program, you need to allocate space in the physical
memory for that new program, the segments of the new program. You may take one of the
existing segments of an application which doesn't run and you are going to store it
on the disk. Okay. And so then for the segment is no longer in memory. So then you can say
it's not, you can use this bit to specify that. So whenever next time when you are looking
for something in that segment, then you are going to get an exception and the exception
is going to be treated by the operating system and the operating system will bring the segment
from the disk to memory before executing that instruction. Okay. So this is some examples.
So here it's a simple, an example of an architecture is four segments. The address is 16 bits. The
first two bits of the address are used to specify the segment number. And because we
have four segments, we need only two bits. So these are bits 15 and 14 and the rest of
these from 13 to zero represent the offset. On the left hand side, you can see the address
space, the virtual address space. So as seen by the processor, by the application. And
we have our traditional four segments, the code segments, the data, the stack segments,
and this is also, we added a shared segment. Think about this is either the data or the
code which you may want to share with another application. So here in green, you have the
tables, the segment table, again, four entries for code, data, shared and the stack. And
you see you have the base and the limit for each of these segments. So now let's see what
happens. So for instance, and on the right hand side, you have the physical address.
For simplicity in this case, the physical address and the virtual address spaces, they
have the same size. Okay. So say you are going from the code, you are going to execute the
instruction in the code segment. And so where is that going to be mapped in the physical
address space? Well, if you look about in the segment table, because the first two bits
of everything in the code segment are zero. So therefore you are going to identify the
first entry in the segment table and you have a base of 4,000 in hexa decimal format. So
therefore you have to add 4,000 to every address, the virtual address is a code segment and
to get the corresponding physical address for the code in the physical address space.
Okay. Then for the data, the data starts in the virtual address space at 4,000. This means
that what are the first two bits of any address in the data segment? Why don't you tell me?
It should be a very simple answer here. So the first, you have 16 bits. When we use a
hexadecimal representation, right? Four bits represent one digit. So now we have four here
first. What does it mean? What are the first four bits representing the four? How do you
write four in binary representation? Okay. So here it is. I'm writing this in our chat.
So four in binary representation, if you want to represent it using four bits, it's what?
0, 1, 0, 0, right? This is it, right? It's 1, 0, 0 is four in the binary representation,
which means that the first two bits for any address in the data segments are one. The
segment number here is what? 0, 1. Now it's not 0, 0, 1. It's 0, 1 because it's only the
first bits. But it is correct, you know, it can move. Okay. So it's 0, 1. This is what
you have, right? So therefore, to translate any address in the data segment, what do you
need to do? You go to the second entry in the segment table, the one which the segment
ID number is one. And the base here is 4800. So what you need to do is that you are going
to add in order to translate any address in the data segment, you need to add to it 4800.
And for the shared segment, this, you know, the things go similarly. For the shared segment,
they started at 8000. So the first four bits is 8, 8. What is the binary representation
of 8? It's exactly. So the first two bits are 1, 0. So the segment number, it's 1, 0
is 2, right? Because you take only the first two bits. And finally, stack C. What is C?
The representation, binary representation of C. You should remember this, right? It's
review. It's 1, 1, 0, 0. It's exactly. Very good, right? So the first two bits are 1,
1. So it's 3, number 3. So of course, it's the last entry in the table. And for the stack,
the base is 0, right? So you add the base offset to the base. So we started from 0,
0, 0. Okay. Does it make sense? Okay. Let's look at this other example. By the way, you
should try. These are some very important slides because you may expect not only to
understand how the address translation works, which is one of the fundamental mechanisms
in used by any in today's processors, leveraged by the operating system to provide virtual
memory abstraction, but also because you can expect problems like this in your next meter.
Okay. So now let's look at this piece of code and see what happens under the hood. And we
are assuming this piece of code is going to run on the previous architecture from I just
showed you in the last slide. Okay. So you have the segment table is the same. And now
is a code. So the code starts at 240, right? So basically the entire address is 0, 2, 4,
0, but you don't show the first four bits, which are 0, right? Okay. So now let's see
what happens. And this is pseudo assembly language code. And let's see what happens
when we type this code. The first instruction is a main. And basically what this instruction
is doing, it loads an address, which is bar X into register A0, right? Now this code is
run in the user process, the user process, see virtual addresses. So all the addresses
you see here are virtual addresses. Okay. But now the code and the data, they are actually
stored in the physical memory. So in order to read the instructions and access the data,
we need to translate the virtual addresses to the physical address. Okay. So the address,
the instruction, first we need to fetch the instruction in order to execute the instructions.
The instruction again is in physical memory. So the address, the virtual address, it's
0, 2, 4, 0, like we discussed. And here it's a binary representation of the address. So
the first two bits are 0. So the segment ID, the segment number is 0. So therefore, in
order to translate this address, virtual address, 2, 4, 0, to a physical address, we need to
add the base address corresponding to the segment. So the base is 4,000 and the virtual
offset, right, is 2, 4, 0, right? The virtual offset. The offset is the black bits in the
address. The bits encoding the segment identifier are the green bits, obviously. Okay. So you
have to add all the offset, which is 2, 4, 0, to 4,000, which is a base. And therefore
you are going to get the physical address 4,240. And now you are going to use this address
to fetch the instruction from the memory. And the instruction is basically, like I told
you, is to load the address, which is VAREX address, which is 4050, this is the virtual
address, into register A0. Now, after that, you execute the instruction, you would know
very well what happens. Next, the program counter, it's incremented by 4, right? Because
here assuming that there are instructions, they occupy 4 bytes. Okay. The next instruction
address is 244. Okay. So let's execute the next instruction. It's again, in the next
instruction, you are going to see, you have now the address is 244, like I mentioned.
Again, the physical, if you look at the, this will also be in the code segment. So you need
to add the base, which is 4,000. The physical address will be 4244. And you are going to
get the next instruction, which is gel, to jump to this string length address label.
And this is exactly what you do it. But before jumping, here we store the return address.
So after we execute the function string length, we need to return where? To the next instruction
after the jump. The next instruction after the jump would be 0x248. Okay. So therefore
we are going to, we assume here that we have a return address registers, which stores a
return address. So we are going to load into the return address 0248. And this is done
automatically by the compiled code, by your application. And then you move in the program
counter, the address where you want to jump. So the address you want to jump, the label
string length is corresponding to the address 360. Okay. So you are going to jump there
and you are going to execute that next instruction, which will be the address 360. 360 is again
is in the segment code. In order to compute the physical address, you are going to add
the base, which is 4,000. So 4,000 plus 360 is 400, 360. And then you are going to read
from the physical memory you are going to read. And this instruction is basically initialized
this account. So put a zero in a register of zero. Okay. And once you execute that,
to the next instruction.
And the next instruction, it's at the address 364.
And this next instruction, it loads
what is at this particular address, which
is stored in A0.
So remember that what we're storing in A0,
it was VARX address.
So this VARX address is 4050.
So now we want to load in register T0
the content of the address VARX, so the address 4050.
So when we want to do that and we want to access it,
to see what is the content at that virtual address,
the virtual address is 4050.
And this is a binary representation.
The first two bits are 01.
So the segment index, which corresponds to this address,
it's 01.
And therefore, the base address of that segment is 4800.
So therefore, you need to add the 4800 to what?
To the offset.
So what is the offset here?
The offset here, notice, is 50.
So the virtual address is 4050.
But remember, the first two bits of this address
represent the segment ID.
That's 01.
And the last, in this case, 14 bits,
represents the offset.
But the last 14 bits is 50.
So now, the offset is 50.
It's, again, offset is a black digits, 0 or 1.
So then you are going to add the offset
to the base, which is 4800.
So the physical address you are going to compute is 4800.
And you are going to load the byte from that address to T0.
And you increment the program count.
So the main thing to note here is
that everything which is in what the processor sees,
everything what is in the registers of the processors,
all these are virtual addresses.
The translation happens only where
you are going to access the memory.
So the memory management units really
sits between the arithmetic logical units
and all the registers and the memory.
OK?
Any questions?
OK.
We spent quite a bit of time on this one.
But this is important.
Please make sure that you understand this example.
OK?
As you will see from the previous years
and previous exams, you are going
to see a lot of problems like this one.
So a few things about segmentation.
The one problem with the segmentation is nice.
It's a very elegant solution.
But you are going to translate on every instruction,
everything.
Even fetch an instruction, access, read some data,
write some data from the memory.
And virtual address space has holes, right?
Because you are not going to use everything in your virtual
address.
And that's why you use a segmentation in the first part,
in the first thing, in the first place.
Because if you think about if you
have the code and the segment, the segment grows.
You put the segment as a high addresses
because it grows to the smaller, grows downwards
to the smaller addresses.
And for instance, the data segment,
you have to be as a lower address
because it's growing up.
OK?
Whilst the stack growing down.
So you need to separate them.
And between them, there is a gap.
So if you have segments, if you don't have the gap,
sorry, if you don't have the segments,
that gap will occupy space in the physical memory.
Space could have been used, empty space
could have been used to allocate to other processes,
other applications.
However, if I have these two segments now,
each segment can have--
one segment can have data, one segment can have the stack.
And then they are going to be mapped on the physical memory.
And the gap, I don't need to map it.
I don't need to just waste the space
on the physical memory.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
So now, the one thing to notice here is I said,
OK, you allocate segments for the stack and the data.
But if I allocate, then how--
allocate the stack at a certain size
and allocate that physical memory for the stack
at that given size, what happens when the stack grows?
And you know that stack grows because as I
call more functions or say recursive programs,
every call puts the arguments and puts the return values
and so forth on the stack.
OK, so how do I do that?
Well, in that sense, when I'm going to browse the stack,
for instance, then I'm going to access an address
outside the limit.
And that will generate an exception.
The exception will be treated by the operating system, which
is going to grow the stack, OK, grow the limit
or modify the base, and provide more room now
so the program can add-- put more things on the stack.
The same thing for the heap.
OK, there is a question here.
Why did we not translate var x in the first line
on the previous slide?
So that's a very good question.
Why didn't translate var x?
Remember what I said?
Everything that's in the registers is virtual addresses.
These are all virtual addresses.
Because the rule is that the addresses are only
translated when I am going to access a memory.
In this case, I am not accessing the memory.
Var x is just a virtual address, right?
I don't need to access the memory for that.
When I need to access the memory,
then I'm going to read the content
as a virtual address.
And then I need to find the corresponding physical address.
And then I do translation.
But everything that is in the process, in the registers,
it's virtual addresses, basically.
OK?
Of course, you need to protect the segment table.
Only the operating system has to be able to modify it.
And also, it provides--
the operating system provides protections
for different segments, for instance,
to make the code segment being read only.
OK?
Now, let's say we do a context switching now.
What do we need to save and restore
on context switching when you have a process context
switching?
So besides, as you know that we need to save a bunch of things
like file identifiers and things like that,
the other thing we need to store now is the segment table.
Because the segment table, as I've shown you,
in the previous slide, in the previous examples,
you have one segment table per virtual address space.
And you have one virtual address space
per process or per application.
So when you switch context switch a process,
you have also to save the segment table
because the next process is going to run.
It's going to have its own segment table.
Also, like I mentioned earlier on,
some of the segments of the process which is no longer
running can be stored on the disk
in order to make room for the segments of the next process
being run.
This again, this is what happens is that again,
if not all segments within memory,
you save them on the disk and you swap them.
So basically, the P1, say process P1,
it's-- we switch from process P1 to P2.
Then we can save the segment of process P1 on the disk
to make room for the segment of process P2
to be brought in the memory.
Of course, if you have to do that,
the context switch cost will grow dramatically.
So you need to be very careful about what you switch off
or what you swap out and swap in because you really
want to minimize your operation on the disk.
And we are going to learn about that the next couple
of lectures.
The problem is fragmentation.
Problems with segmentation, one of the biggest problems
is fragmentation because now you need to store different--
you need to be able to have to store
and to fit segments of different sizes in memory.
And if you remember the last lecture,
we had an example in which you leave a lot of gaps.
And you can get to a point in which you have many gaps
in the physical memory, but none of the gaps
can be big enough to store a new segment,
despite the fact that if you add them, all the gaps--
it's much, much more than what is needed by one--
by that segment.
Think about you have 100 gaps.
Each gap is 1 gigabyte.
And so you have 100 gigabytes in total of available memory.
But now you have one segment which requires 2 gigabytes.
So you have plenty of available space,
but none of the available spaces,
contiguous spaces is large enough
to store that segment, 2 gigabyte segment.
OK.
So if you do that, you can take one
of the segments which are there to addition
to one of these 1 gigabyte gap.
And you are going to store on the disk.
You are swapping out to make more room.
Or you can move segments around.
OK?
So there are two kinds of fragmentations.
Both of them waste space.
Internal fragmentation, you don't need all the memory
within allocated chunks.
And this is also--
and then external, which is free gaps within allocated chunks.
So what in the example I mentioned to you,
I was talking about the external fragmentation.
OK?
And next, we are going to talk also
about internal fragmentation.
OK.
So basically, this is about another view
about the general--
how the address translation happens.
This providing a little more intuition
by showing two virtual address spaces mapped
to the same physical address space.
OK?
And these programs 1 and programs 2,
or this process 1 and process 2, the virtual address
spaces to each of them can look absolutely identical.
Think about you're on the same application, two instances
of the same application.
But of course, the translation, while in the virtual space
are identical, you have in both virtual spaces
the same thing at the same addresses, virtual addresses.
When you are going to map these virtual addresses
to the physical address space, when
you are going to translate them, you
are going to translate in such a way
that they are not going to conflict.
So now, with segmentation, we have
this external fragmentation.
And sometimes, it's harder to allocate storage
to variable size chunks.
So there is a solution for that.
And a solution for that, which is very simple,
is about instead of allocating variable size chunks,
you allocate fixed size chunks.
And these are called pages.
So every chunk of physical memory
is equivalent to the same that it has the same size.
And this can allow you to simplify a lot of things.
For instance, how do you handle allocation?
So one way to handle the allocation
is to have a bit vector.
And each bit in the vector represent one page.
And the value 0 is that whether that page has been allocated
from the physical memory or and 1 if it was allocated.
So if you want to find a page in physical memory you can allocate,
you just find a 0 in this bit vector.
Now, what about the size of the pages?
If the pages are too large, again, all pages
are the same size.
What is the problem?
What is the problem if the pages are too large?
[AUDIO OUT]
Wasty spice, internal fragmentation, excellent.
So I buy it and add it on.
And cost of context switching can be higher
if you need to swap that page out.
That's correct.
But yes, the main thing is about internal fragmentation.
Because if you think about, if you have these pages,
say you have a page of 1 gigabyte,
if your program is only 1 megabyte,
you waste enormous, most of the space.
So you want small pages.
OK?
The problem with the small pages,
what is the problem with the small pages?
[AUDIO OUT]
Any guess?
Lots of accounting, more translation is yes.
Lots of accounting.
I wouldn't say more translations and larger page table.
OK, you already know about it.
Yes.
But it's accounting is hard.
You have to deal with more things.
Right.
And OK, so let's see.
So now, how do you do the translation?
But there are not many more translation because--
in theory, right?
Because you still need to-- every virtual address,
you need to translate your physical address.
The little bit of truth of that, the higher overhead
per translation could be.
But the number of translation is basically the same.
Yeah, works on cache can be that as well.
Yeah.
OK, so how is a translation works with paging?
It's very similar with segmentation,
but with a few differences.
So first of all, you have a page table.
And the virtual address, as again, is in two parts.
We have a virtual page number and an offset.
But there is a difference.
The offset is not added to a base address.
The offset of the address remains the same.
So with translation, when you use paging, what happens,
it's only the virtual page part.
The first field changes, right?
A virtual page number is replaced
by a physical page number.
That's it.
So the same like previously, the first bits, in this case,
the virtual page number in the previous case
was a segment number, are going to index in the page table.
But in the page table, what you are going to find,
you have a page number, which is a physical page number.
And you are going to take that physical page number,
and you are going to concatenate with the offset
of the virtual address.
So the offset of the physical address
and the offset of the physical address
are the same, OK?
Typical page sizes are between 4 kilobytes and 16 kilobytes
are quite small.
4 kilobytes means what?
12 bits, you need 12 bits.
And 16 kilobytes, you need another 14 bits, right?
So if you have even smaller pages, right?
And this is where you see the number,
the problem with the small pages.
So you have a 32-bit address.
And you are going to use 1 kilobyte pages.
So you need 10 bits offset.
This is what you need, 10 bits offset.
And therefore, the virtual page number, the number of bits
there is 22 bits, 32 minus 10, 22 bits.
So therefore, the page table have 4 million sentences.
Huge.
And just think about if you have 64 bits address.
So in order to do that, for instance, you are--
you are also going to not allocate space
for the entire maximum size page table.
So you are going to just grow this page table as you
add more pages to it.
And therefore, you are going to have in addition to the page
table pointer, which represent the start of the page table,
also the page table size, which is, as the name implies,
the size of the page table, which can be increased
as you add more tables, as you allocate more pages
and you are--
so that you allocate more entries,
you add more entries to the page table.
Also, with each page, you are going
to have a bunch of bits which represents some--
we are going to discuss them more a little bit later.
So keep in mind about these bits.
We are going to give an example a few slides later.
So this is a very simple page table.
You have a four-by space, so it's a trivial example.
You have this on the virtual memory.
You have four pages starting from 0, 4, and 8.
And then you have a page table only with three entries,
because you have three pages in the virtual memory.
So assume that the address space here
is has equivalent of 8 bits, so it's 64 bytes.
So the address, if you need for the page table,
again, if you have four bits, you need only two bits
to represent four bytes, to address four bytes.
So therefore, the last two bits represent the offset,
and the first six bits represent what?
Represent the page number.
OK, so if you want A, it's at the address 0 here.
So if you want to translate the address 0,
then the page number identifies the first entry in the table.
The first entry in the table contains four.
So now four is a new physical page number,
so you are going to concatenate these four
with the offset, which is 0.
So you are going to get 0x10.
OK?
The same thing, similar things happen
if you want to access the first address, the address four,
the virtual address four.
The virtual address four now is going
to lead you, because the offset is one,
is going to lead you to the second entry in the page table.
The second entry in the page table contains three,
so you are going to concatenate three with zero,
which is the offset.
You are going to get to the address 0c, physical address,
and so forth.
OK?
Any questions?
So question here, why was space size issues
in between 4 kilobytes and 16 kilobytes?
This is, again, always a trade-off.
The smaller the table, the smaller the page,
the smaller the internal fragmentation,
so the less wasted space.
However, the smaller the page, the larger the page tables
are, so therefore, it's much more context switching,
actually, can be more expensive.
Good question.
OK?
And these are some other translation.
Translating the address five, it's
going to translate to the address in this case
is basically 117, and I think there is another example.
Nine is going-- sorry.
Previous case, the address six was
translating to the address 116, and the second case,
the address nine is going to translate to address five.
No, physical address five.
[AUDIO OUT]
So there is an anonymous question
asking about if the 0x12345678 is the address,
could the first 123456 can be the offset?
Now, again, the offset are the last bits in the address.
OK?
So in this particular case, again, the offset,
if you look at the first one, example here, the offset,
it's one, zero, are the black bits,
and the page number are the red bits.
So the offset is two in this case, and the page number,
it's one.
And page number one selects the second entry
in the page table, which is three, so it's one, one.
And the offset remains one, zero,
so now I have one, one, one, zero, which is basically e.
[AUDIO OUT]
OK.
What about sharing?
Well, if you want to share a page between processes,
these are not RPT-E's, right?
You just-- you have each of the processes
has its own page table, and if you
want to share the same pages, then the corresponding entries
are going to point to the same physical table.
That's it.
[AUDIO OUT]
Very elegant.
Where is page sharing used?
Kernel region of the processes.
So of every-- so for the processes,
you have a kernel region, as you remember,
so every process has the same--
all the processes, they have to see
that you are going to share this code, the kernel code,
across all the processes, because the same code is not
going to change.
You can-- and by the way, this is protected.
It's like the kernel will have--
the process only can access at the user level
when I'm talking about the kernel region.
I'm not talking about kernel region being
accessed by the process.
I'm talking about the kernel regions associated
with the process, which is accessed by the kernel
during the context switching.
During different processes running the same binary,
you don't need to duplicate that because the code is read only.
User level libraries, like I mentioned,
or even sharing the data between--
you can share the data between the processes.
You can use a shared memory.
So this is another example.
This is a summary of paging.
On the left-hand side, you have the virtual memory view.
On the right-hand side, you have the physical memory view.
And in the middle, you have the page table.
You see that many entries in the tables are null,
but this is a full page table.
And here, we are assuming an 8-bits address.
And now, the offset are the last three bits.
So the base size is 2 power 3, so it's 8 bytes.
And the page number is 5 bits.
So you are going to have 2 power 5.
You have 32 entries in the page table up to.
OK.
So now, the one thing--
and on the right-hand side, you have, again,
like the physical memory.
So one thing here I just want to show you, and earlier on,
I said that, well, the stack--
how the stack and the heap grows here.
So now, the stack, again, grows downwards,
so grows going to lower addresses.
And you see here, the stack, it's on the right-hand side.
And with what I represented here, with the gray,
the pages with gray are all OK, are all reallocated.
So only the pages which are white are not allocated yet.
So let's see what happens and how
you are going to grow the stack.
So now, the problem is that, let's say
that I want to grow the stack by two pages.
I decide to grow the stack by two pages
in the virtual memory.
The virtual memory, I can very conveniently grow the stack
because I have enough space in the virtual memory.
However, in the physical memory, if I'm
going to try to grow it, I can allocate another page.
You can allocate another page.
Maybe you have only room for another page
there if you want to allocate contiguously
the pages to the stack.
But the point is a page with a translation
that these pages do not need to be allocated contiguously.
So therefore, the only thing you can do,
the only thing you need to do, you
need to find room for two other pages.
And you are going to allocate these pages for the stack.
But again, they don't need to be contiguous.
Whatever is contiguous in the virtual memory
doesn't need to be contiguous in the physical memory.
OK.
So now the biggest problem and the challenge, the table size,
if you're in the simplest version,
in the simple instantiation, in the simplest implementation,
the type of size repeats.
It's equal with the number of pages in the virtual memory.
And this can be absolutely huge.
So let's give Satek an example.
So you have 32 bits address space.
So you have 4 gigabytes address, virtual address space.
And these are just the units for you to remember.
So the one thing to remember here and one confusion
I've seen often is that when you are going--
when you are talking about the memory,
we are talking about the power of two units.
So 1 kilobyte is 2 power 10.
1 megabyte, 2 power 10.
And gigabyte, 2 power 10.
When we are talking about bandwidth and how much
capacity, network capacity, we are talking in power of 10.
1 kilobyte or 1 kilobit, it's 1,000 bits.
1 gigabyte, 1 gigabit represent what?
It's 1 billion bits.
So now, assume the typical page size is 4 kilobytes.
So it's 2 power 10.
We need 10 bits to address any byte in a 4 kilobyte page.
So therefore, OK.
Sorry, we need 12, what I'm talking about.
If the page is 4 kilobytes, this means 2 power 12.
So therefore, I need 12 bits to address any byte within a page.
So the offset is 10 bits.
And therefore, if the offset is 10 bits,
the page number, it's 32 minus 12 is 20 bits.
So now, the page table size can have as big as 4 megabytes.
Right?
Why is 4 megabytes?
Because each of the entry in the page table
needs to have 20 bits.
And then you are also going to have some other, like you see,
some other flags associated.
So you have 32 bits for each entry.
So it's 4 bytes, and you have 2 power 20 entries.
So it's 4 megabytes total.
So this was a lot of memory.
And now, think about this was in the past
when you have 32 bits was the standard,
but now the standard is 64 bits.
There is no way, right?
If you try to do the same thing here,
you are going to have 30 exabytes, which
is only for the page table.
Actually, you don't have enough physical memory
to store that page table.
This is really a lot of space.
So what is the solution here?
Right?
And by the way, all this space is empty.
Most of this-- no, no, not all of this.
Most of this space is empty because you don't
have as many page tables.
You have very few page tables, right?
So which are actually allocated.
So what is a--
so this is a big problem, and we are looking for a solution.
So a little bit of a discussion about page table
before going forward.
So what do you need to switch on the page table?
When a context switch happens, what do you need to do?
You need to have a page for the table point--
the page table pointer, so the beginning of the page table
and the limit, the size of the page table.
Again, remember about the dual mode operation, because these
space tables can be only modified and accessed
by the kernel.
You cannot let an application access these space tables,
because then they can change the page table,
and they can point to anywhere, to any other address,
including the kernel or the address of other applications.
And now let's look at the pros and cons.
On the pros side, it's a very simple memory allocation.
Remember, you have a bit vector, 0 or 1,
whether the page is allocated or not in the physical memory.
The bit vector contains one bit for each page
in the physical memory.
Easy to share.
The cons we've seen.
If the address space is very sparse,
the page table can be huge.
So again, if the page table is big,
then you need also probably to context switch.
You cannot keep all the time in the memory.
If the process is a page table of a process,
if the process is now switched off
and is no longer using the CPU, you may want--
it was preempted.
You may want to take the page table of that process
and swap on the disk.
But if that is large, then the overhead is very large.
So the TLDR here, the page table,
the paging is a technique with elegant solution.
Very simple to implement.
Provides low internal fragmentation
if the pages are small.
On the downside, the problem we encounter
is because the page tables can be huge.
So what is the solution?
Well, the solution is you know, you
represent the same technique, right?
You recursively do it.
And it's multilevel paging.
Look, if the page tables are very large,
then why don't we have a page table for that page table,
right?
Or you can combine paging segmentations, OK?
So and these are the two solutions.
Segment mapping, you are going to have segments.
And in the segments, you are going to have--
you know, you page the segments.
And then in the page tables, you are
going to page the page tables.
And let's look about how this is working.
So the core, remember that the page table
is a map between the virtual page number
and the physical page number.
This is what it is.
So a simple page table is just a lookup table.
VPN, the virtual page number, it's
an index in this table which contains a physical page
number.
By the way, what other map structures can you think of?
There are many of them, trees, hash table, and so forth.
But obviously, these are more complicated.
More complicated means higher overhead,
even though they can have slower storage overhead.
The beautiful things about the page table
is very quick to access, right?
It's just an index.
If you use the trees and hash tables,
and we'll see about that.
They are much more space efficient.
You don't need to maintain all the entries, which you know, for it, there is no table,
but accessing those is much more expensive.
There's a trade-off here.
So one simple solution is like we mentioned is to have to do the problem of having very
big page tables is to page these page tables.
And basically, here is a two-level page table.
And here is that instead of now the address has three fields.
At the end is the offset like before, no difference here.
But what was previously corresponding to the page number, now you split into two fields,
which corresponds to virtual page numbers or page indexes for the two-level pages.
So the first 10 bits in this case represents a virtual p1 index.
So indexing the first level table, page table.
And this is going to take you-- it's going to contain an address to a page containing
the page table entries at the second level.
OK?
So in order to compute now the entire physical address, use a p1 index to find the address
of the page containing the physical page number, which is stored in the second level.
And this physical page number is going to be concatenated with the offset like before.
And now you have the physical address.
OK?
So it's the same thing, the same thing.
The only difference is that now you split the physical page number into a part which
is going to index into a page table, first-level page table, which contains the address of
a second-level page table.
And the second field in this page number is going to index in the second-level page table.
And at that entry, corresponding entry, you are going to have physical page number.
And you can have many more levels.
So now these are some announcements.
We are just 15 minutes before the class, so ends.
But here are some announcements.
So you release a midterm score.
And please check Piazza for grading policies.
I think you did quite well.
The scores and the distribution is very much in line with that of the past midterms in
the recent years.
The Project 2 Design Document, remember, is due by this at the end of this Friday.
And the Homework 3 is due on Sunday at the end of the day.
So if you want an extra credit point, please feel free to meet semester survey and check
on Piazza for details.
OK?
So it's free, free extra credit.
The next lecture, I'll be out of town.
And Nathan Pemberton, who's a senior PhD student, which is expert both in architectures and
systems, is going to teach this class.
He's a fantastic teacher, fun.
I really urge you to attend his lecture.
They are going to be a lot more fun than my lectures.
So he's a great presenter.
So remember that I mentioned to you now that in a page table entry, besides a physical
page number, we are going also to have some bits.
And here is an example.
So let's take our previous examples in which you are going to have an offset of the-- you
have a 32-bits address.
The offset is 12 bits.
So the physical page number is 20 bits.
OK?
So now for in a page table, what you need, you need the physical page number, which is
these 20 bits.
So what about the rest of the rest of the rest of the rest of the bits?
So for the rest of the 12 bits, you are going to have a bunch of flags, which are used--
so you have different use.
You can use it in different ways.
But here is an example.
And this is from Intel Architecture.
So these are examples about these bits.
And we are going to start from the least significant bits.
0 is p.
This is present.
It's the same as valid.
Is the page present in physical memory or not?
W, writable.
Can you write on this page or not?
If it's 0, then it's read only.
U is user accessible.
Is this page accessible only by user?
OK.
PWT, page write transparent.
This is related with a cache.
Typically you have caches to reduce the latency to access the data.
And when you have caches, the problem, the question is about how you are going to update
the physical memory, the data in the physical memory.
And there are two ways here we are going to learn.
But one way is that whenever we are going to access and we are going to write to the
cache and modify the data, we are also going to modify the data in the physical memory.
And this is page writes transparent.
PCD is page cache disabled.
You cannot cache the pages.
A, it's access page has been accessed recently.
This is used also for caching.
If it's accessed recently, and the next two are the same, also for caching.
You want to know whether the page was accessed recently and whether it's dirty, whether it
was written.
And the physical memory associated with physical memory was not updated.
So you need to know about that.
And then you are going, we may decide to page that to-- this is-- OK, how do I say?
So these two bits, the only thing you need to know now, are used when deciding what page
to swap out of the memory to make room for new pages.
Fundamentally, you do not want to swap out a page of a process which will be accessed
immediately.
And OK, that's a question.
The PCD means-- the question is that PCD means-- it's about what PCD means.
The PCD means that the page is not cached.
And again, the reason you may choose to not cache a page is that, for instance, in multiprocessor
systems, multi-core systems, when you have concurrency on the same page, you have a page
which is shared to different processes which run on different processors.
And they can concurrently access that page.
And if you want to update the page, if it's cached, each processor cached, then you have
a cache coherency problem.
And if you want to simplify that problem, if you want to remove that problem, you can
say, OK, this page is never going to be cached.
OK.
So example of how to use PTEs, invalid PTEs is that-- again, even this one can imply different
things in the operating system besides how to use these flags.
So one-- yeah.
And one we use is that-- which I didn't mention-- is that the address space is actually not valid.
Right?
It doesn't-- it's not allocated.
But another way is basically, say, the page direct-- that page is not in the memory.
It's on the disk.
Right?
In that case, you need-- it's a trap to the operating system exception.
It results into a trap to the operating system.
And the operating system is going to figure out where is the page is stored and is going
to bring it to memory.
And this is going to be used by the main page.
We are going to learn about that.
Another use here is about copy on write for the PTE.
So basically, when you fork, remember that the fork-- when you fork a process, a fork
process copy actually is a parent process.
Right?
It has everything.
And now the question is, do you want to copy it right away?
Right?
And are you going to copy everything?
And it's not smart to do it because, for instance, the code of the process-- of the parent process
is the same code you are-- the child process is going to execute.
The code is read only, so you don't need to copy it.
But the same is also true about the data.
Right?
Do you want to copy-- to move that-- to copy the data from the process address space to
the child address space?
Well, the answer there is that only if the child-- ideally, only if the child accesses
it.
Right?
And writes it.
So when-- so that's what-- so initially, when you are going to create-- because you want
to reduce the overhead to create a deforca process, the fork process can share the entire
address-- the entire address space to the parent process.
OK?
So the reads are very-- the reads are going to the same memory.
It's memory efficient.
It's fast.
Right?
To fork.
And but then the only one you can start doing it is when you write it.
So when you write a page, now, only now, you are going to create a copy of that page for
the child.
And now the child can write and read from that copy.
But as long as you want to read, you can read from the same memory-- physical memory-- which
is shared with the parent.
Another use case here, it's a zero fill on demand.
So say you allocate, say, 10 gigabytes of memory, and you want to initialize to zero.
That initialization can take seconds, many seconds, just to do this initialization.
So you don't want to pay the overhead then when you are going to allocation.
So instead what you can do, you can do zero fill on demand.
So the OS knows that this page needs to be zero, but initially doesn't make them zero.
It makes them zero only when you access that page.
And that's perfectly fine because you amortize zeroing it.
Or even better, maybe the application is not going to ever touch every byte which is allocating
these 10 gigabytes.
So it's, again, some smart ways to use this PD.
So sharing with multiple level pages, you can see here you have two processes.
Each process has its own page table hierarchy.
And the first level page, you can see for each process, it's pointed from-- you have
the page table pointer and page table pointer prime for the two page tables, different page
tables, first level page tables.
And then each of them, they have point to second level page tables.
And what you can see here is that some of the second level page tables are shared.
And obviously, all the pages to which entries in the shared page tables point to are also
shared.
And finally, you remember, we started with solving this problem that the page tables
can become extremely large.
And if we have-- but many of the entries from these huge page tables are null, so contains
no information.
And we said that the two level page table is going to solve that, address that problem,
or at least alleviate that problem.
And here is an example.
So if you remember, this is an example, and let me just try to go back here.
So this is a previous example.
So this is an example in which you are going to have, if you can see, this was a one level
table.
So you have, I think, 72 entries.
Many of these entries are null.
And this is a corresponding example.
This is a corresponding example.
So you can see and you can count.
You have much fewer-- it requires fewer-- less storage for storing these page tables.
And certainly, you have much more fewer null entries.
So let me just continue.
We have just a few more minutes.
And this also shows you about how the translation is done.
So in this particular case, we have, for the first level page table, we use three bits.
For the second level, two bits.
And for the offset, three bits.
So in the best case scenario, the size of the page tables is the number of pages used
by the program in the virtual memory, unlike the previous case in which the number of pages
was the one available in the physical memory.
The price to pay here is that you have one more additional memory access, because you
need to index on both page tables at both levels.
So how about about segments, segments and pages?
This is another way to do it.
We have two level tables, but another way to solve similar problems is to combine segmentation
with paging.
So in this case, again, you have the address is split into three fields.
But the first field represents a segment number.
The second field represents a virtual page number within that segment.
And then you have the offset.
So it's a very similar approach.
Is again here, what do you need to save and store when context switching?
You need to store the segment table, you need to store the page table for that process.
How do you share the data across different segments when you have these both segments
and paging?
It's the same very similar way.
You are going to have from two different processes, they can share the pages by simply having
the base by sharing the segment.
If you want to send a bunch of pages, you are going to put all these pages in the same
segment and you are going to share the segment.
So let me do this one last slide and then I'm going to stop here.
So when you have multi-level translation pages, what are the pros and cons?
So the big pro is that you get to is much less space for the page tables.
That's it.
So the paging themselves, they have the big advantage that it's fixed size, so they retain
the simplicity.
You have no external fragmentation, you have only internal fragmentation.
The cons is that the page tables can be huge because they need to be continuous because
you need to index into that.
And therefore you need to have multiple level of tables in order to get the memory allocation,
to get efficient memory allocation for the page tables.
But the big problem is that now you need to have multiple lookups for translation because
you need to have a lookup for each level, for each page level.
So let's stop here and again, please attend Nathan's lecture on Thursday and I'll see
you next Monday.
Thanks.
So we are done.
Let me just stop recording.