Okay. Cool. So we're recording and I can do stuff.
Okay, great. So I'm going to try and keep my eye on the chat.
But I'm not very good at this yet,
so this is all new to me.
So I'm going to do my best.
Okay. So I'm Nathan.
I'm filling in for you on today.
I'm a grad student.
I work with you on sometimes.
I study a lot of stuff.
I do like kind of cloud stuff.
Serverless computing, if ever heard of that.
I goof around with some hardware,
lots of stuff like that.
But today we're going to be talking about
more stuff to do with paging and virtual memory.
And particularly today, there's a big focus
on how paging actually works kind of in practice.
So a lot of the tips and tricks,
how the hardware deals with it,
and some of the more kind of
advanced detailed concepts around that.
So starting from what you guys saw last week,
and you guys can interrupt me in the chat
if I'm sort of off in sync.
I think Jan told me where he left off last time.
We talked about flat page tables.
We talked about first level, single level page tables.
And so a single level page table is going to have
one entry for every virtual page
that you could possibly have.
So if you have a 32 bit system,
that's going to be two to the 32 entries,
about 4 billion, well, 4 billion divided by the page size,
which is 4K.
If you're on a 64 bit machine,
which is obviously the most popular today,
at least for high end sort of systems,
that's going to be two to the 64,
which is a completely outrageous number.
So single level page tables are just not practical.
You'd have to have an entry for every virtual address.
And the reality is that no program uses anywhere near
all available virtual addresses.
The vast majority of programs use a tiny, tiny fraction
of virtual memory.
So what do we do?
Well, we go back to our data structures class
that we learned,
and we learned about all these neat data structures.
And we remember that there's a thing called a tree.
So what we do is instead of having that first level
page table address everything,
what it instead does is it points to child nodes in a tree.
So this isn't a binary tree.
It's a tree with as many leaves as you need
in order to cover the virtual address space.
But it's the same idea, just like a tree.
And instead of treating your virtual address bits
as an index into a single table, we split it up.
So now there's two parts here.
So you can see there's one part that indexes
into the first level page table.
And then the second half of it,
we're going to use here to index
into the second level page table.
So it's just an index scheme, right?
It's just a scheme in order to structure a page table
more like a tree than a single table.
And then this one here is actually like what you learned
about before, this is your standard page table entry.
We call that a PTE for short.
I'm going to use that word a lot today.
So page table entry is a PTE.
And this is the normal one we saw just like when it was
in a first level page table.
So you've got the physical page number here.
So in Linux, I think they call this a frame.
So they call this the physical frame number or PFN.
So you might hear me say page number.
You might hear me say frame number.
Often frame tends to get used for the physical
just to make it a little more clear
that whether we're talking about virtual pages
or physical pages.
Also, when you say frame, you tend to refer
to an actual literal like particular address in memory.
So either way, we have a physical page number in the table.
So we use the virtual page number.
So that was this part.
This was what you thought the address was.
We use that in order to find the physical page number.
And then because pages have multiple bytes in them
and you're trying to address a particular byte,
there's this offset part you provided.
And that offset is gonna be the same
whether it's physical or virtual.
It's just the offset in here,
whether it's here, here, here, here.
Okay, so multi-level page tables,
pretty sure we talked about this
or you talked about this last week.
But they're pretty cool.
And one of the nice things here is that
I don't actually have to have every one of these.
So I could have, maybe this doesn't even have to exist.
If I haven't allocated any pages,
why should I even bother creating the leaf node yet?
And so what you might do is you might just sort of
mark this as empty, right?
In this entry, you might have some sort of bit
that you set that said,
"Ah, this doesn't actually exist, ignore it."
In which case we didn't have to allocate this other one
and we saved ourselves some memory.
So with multi-level page tables,
we no longer have to store,
we don't have to allocate memory
for all the empty spots in the table anymore.
We just have to allocate memory
for the ones that actually have been assigned.
Or at least, you know, one page's worth
of ones that have been assigned.
We still are gonna have empty slots
in this second level page table,
but there's a lot fewer of them.
So it kind of works out.
Okay, so what are the pros and cons here?
So the pros of the multi-level page table is that,
like I said, sparse address spaces,
address spaces that are mostly empty, mostly unassigned.
This is reasonably good at,
because you don't have to store all the empty ones.
Because we're using paging rather
than something more complicated like segmentation,
then it makes memory allocation a lot easier,
because you have fixed size pages.
You have these fixed size allocation units,
and that makes life a lot easier
when you're writing memory allocators.
Now, I don't know if you guys have a memory allocator project
in this class or if you've done one yet,
but when you do, you're gonna start to realize
how incredibly annoying it would be
to try and allocate variable size things.
It's much easier if they're fixed size and aligned.
The other nice thing is that every process
has its own page table.
And so it makes it really easy to share.
So even though two people
might have different virtual addresses, it's pretty neat.
We can actually just have those virtual addresses map
to the same physical address,
and then people can share physical memory
without even realizing it.
And that's pretty neat.
So we'll talk a little bit more
about that later in the lecture.
It's not perfect though.
I mean, there's downsides, right?
One of them is that because they're not variable size,
because they're fixed size,
we actually have to have an entry per page.
So even though I might allocate you like a gigabyte
in one shot, I actually am gonna have to have one entry
for every 4K in that big four gigabyte section.
So I can give you these big allocations,
but I'm allocating a lot of kind of redundant information.
With segments, you wouldn't have that problem, right?
With segmentation, I could give you a base register
and just a four gigabyte bound
and then everything would work out.
So it's kind of a drawback of this paging approach.
The way people deal with that is they tend to allow
for different sized pages.
They're still aligned,
but today you can do things called huge pages.
So maybe you could allocate a one megabyte
or even bigger page size.
And so that is a trick that modern systems use,
but we won't really go into too much more detail
beyond that for huge pages.
You know, they have to be contiguous.
It's not such a problem
when you have multi-level page tables.
All we do is we make each one of those levels.
So each one of those, you know, let's see.
So each one of these, where are we going?
What happened here?
Sorry guys, still getting used to this.
Okay.
So, you know, we make each one of these happen to fit
precisely in one page
and that makes life an awful lot easier for everybody.
So it's not really that big a deal,
but it does add us another little constraint
that we have to have a very particular organization
of our page table,
because as we're gonna talk about later,
the hardware has to be able to interact with it.
So it's a little bit of a constraint,
but the big one, the one that really screws us up here
is this last point.
So the problem we have is that when you have
multi-level page tables,
then you have to kind of hunt around it.
So you gotta read that first level page table first,
figure out where the second level one is,
and then go read the second level one to find your answer.
And if you have more, right,
like some things have more than two levels,
there's four level page tables or more,
then it's like four hops.
And every time you have to follow a pointer, that's time.
That takes time, right?
Jumping around memory, chasing pointers.
And we have to do address translation
on every single load and store.
So every time you load, every time you store,
including instruction,
so every time you fetch the next instruction,
that's kind of like a load,
you have to do address translation.
So it's important that it be super, super fast
and hopping around is kind of slow.
So this is a big issue
that we're gonna have to figure out how to solve.
Okay, so the next question is,
we talked about how they're organized,
what they're kind of doing at a high level.
The next question is who's managing these, right?
How are you actually filling in these translations?
And so we got to remember that this is an operating system.
The operating system's job, one of its big jobs,
is allowing multiple applications,
like multiple processes to safely share a machine
so they can't screw with each other, right?
So like, even if you have a process
running some sensitive information,
other processes that you're running at the same time
aren't allowed to read that.
So it's security.
And also if one of them screws up, right?
You have a mistake, you start writing to some random address,
you get a segfault, whatever,
we don't wanna be able to screw everybody else up.
So if one badly written program
can take your whole system down,
you kind of have a problem.
So the trick we do with most, you know,
any sort of CPU that really supports
or any ISA that really supports an operating system
is gonna have this dual mode operation.
So instead of letting processes set up their own page tables,
we have kernel mode.
So in kernel mode, you can do anything you want, right?
You have super high privilege to do anything you want.
And then in user mode,
there's a bunch of stuff you're not allowed to do.
And a lot of the stuff you're not allowed to do
boils down to like what memory regions you can write
and which like control registers you can set
and things like that.
So when the system first boots up, it's in kernel mode,
when you first press that power button,
then your operating system loads
and it sets up anything it wants to set up,
page tables, control bits, all this kind of junk.
And then it decides to run a program.
So it's gonna jump into that program.
It's gonna say, okay, let's go and execute some PC
that represents some process.
And when it does that,
it's gonna deselect the privilege bit.
So it's gonna turn off that privilege bit.
And now we're in user mode
and the user's not allowed to do anything.
And the only way you get back to kernel mode
is through a trap.
So there might be some hardware event
or there might be some software event that says,
hey, it's time for the kernel to do something.
And the kernel has registered very specific things
that it's allowed to do.
So it says, if I get trap five,
then you should run this code in my kernel.
If I get trapped six, you should run that code.
So the user can't touch anything,
but they can hand control back to the kernel
in a very controlled way.
It's obviously more complicated than that.
And there's gonna be this caveat
through this entire lecture.
In this class, we're mostly focused on x86
because that's the one you're using in your projects.
And basically x86 is like thousands and thousands of pages
for its instruction manual.
It's old, it's grown very organically.
And so things tend to get a little complicated.
Not too important to know,
but what you can realize is that
we have a lot of flexibility here.
So traditionally ring zero would be kernel mode,
ring three is user mode.
There's a ring one and two that nobody really uses.
And then when they wanted to add hypervisors, yeah, right.
And then there's minus one and there's more, right?
Yeah, like there's minus three that Michael's mentioning.
In RISC-V, what you have are also different modes.
I don't think they call them rings in RISC-V,
but you have machine mode,
which is kind of like this Intel management engine
style thing where you're setting up
very, very, very low level stuff.
It's where you might like emulate instructions
that you haven't implemented or other stuff like that.
And then there's supervisor mode where the kernel runs
and then there's user mode.
And I actually don't know a lot about
how RISC-V handles hypervisors.
So I can't talk too much about that.
But the point is that the CPU has control modes.
They have protection modes
and that's how operating systems work in practice.
That's how they're safe.
Okay, we're gonna just take a quick detour
into segmentation.
I just talked about how Intel's got all sorts
of old stuff floating around in it.
And one of those old, moldy old things is segmentation.
It's not really used a lot these days,
but it does still exist.
So just real quickly, I think this slide will be
mostly good for your reference after.
So I'm gonna go through it real quick.
But x86 supports a bunch of different segments.
You have these registers.
So registers are right in your pipeline.
They're right next to your CPU.
So you can't have very many of them
and they can't be too complicated
'cause you have like limited number of bits,
limited number of wires and flip-flops
and whatever right next to your CPU.
So you can't have too many.
So what they do is they have a register
to represent segments.
And then that register is actually a pointer
to a more rich description of the segment that you want.
And then that segment has a whole bunch of details in it
about the segment.
So it's got permission bits.
It's got a base and a limit,
which is the bottom line for segments.
You notice that the address bits
are spread around in funny places.
You might remember from 61C,
how RISC-V does the same thing for, I think loads,
like certain loads or certain jumps
have kind of a funny layout.
And these are all just micro architectural details.
At the time when they wrote this,
it was easier to put this wire here or that wire there.
It tends to be sort of boring reasons that it's shaped funny.
And you can come back to this slide
to understand what all these bits do.
But let's just quickly talk about
what they're actually used for.
So there's different ways that you can use the segments.
The most common use originally was in
the old, old, old 16 bit version of x86.
The very first time people were writing 16 bit processors,
having more than a few kilobytes of memory
was a ridiculous concept, right?
Nobody, having a megabyte of memory was insane.
Nobody ever thought that could happen, right?
And so they had this 16 bit addressing mode
and they had a lot of segments.
Again, you can't have page tables
if you only have like less than a kilobyte of memory.
So they would use segments originally.
Then, okay, we use the word modern here loosely.
Most application level sorts of processors
are 64 bit these days,
but some embedded low power,
that kind of stuff would be 32 bit.
I don't think there's a lot of 32 bit x86 processors
out there, but in RISC-V,
there's lots of 32 bit RISC-V processors floating around.
So in this case,
they kind of weakened the segmentation support.
It's still there, but not great.
The one exception is thread local storage.
So a process is not like a super precise concept.
I mean, it is in the spec,
but a process is just some sort of logically connected set
of things that all share most of their resources.
So they have one process ID.
They most, for the most part,
they have one set of like virtual addresses,
things like that.
But sometimes it's handy to have a little bit
of private memory space per thread.
The threads in this case are like different PCs
that you could potentially be jumping between, right?
So different program counters into the same basic program.
So on x86, they use segments in order to implement that.
On RISC-V, they do something different.
I actually was looking for that earlier.
I couldn't find it.
So I'm not sure how RISC-V implements thread local storage,
but I'm sure it's not with segments.
And then on 64 bit mode,
which is the most common x86 mode today,
they have been basically nerfed.
So like they work in like the most limited possible way,
except again for thread local storage,
which still gets used.
But otherwise, just keep in mind segments kind of made sense
when you had very, very little memory.
And they make a lot less sense
as your virtual address space starts to get bigger
and you need like more and more flexible management
and you have enough memory where the memory overhead
of keeping a bunch of page tables around
isn't gonna kill you.
Okay, so enough about segmentation.
Coming back to paging,
I mentioned that you could have more than two levels, right?
So if two levels is good, then four levels is gooder.
And there's really nothing different here.
So there's nothing special.
You know, whatever you learned about two level page tables,
just like recurse on that a couple more times
and you've got multi-level page tables.
So you still have your base here,
you have your top level page table,
that is gonna point into some lower level page table,
which is sort of like this one.
And now it points here and then it points here.
And then finally you get your PTE here.
So it's not fundamentally different in any way
than a two level page table.
You just have more hops.
And that's gonna keep shrinking
this top level page table, right?
Every time you add a hop,
that's gonna exponentially drop the number of entries
you have to have here, which can be handy.
But again, otherwise nothing special,
just like you saw before.
You keep going, right?
So, all right, well, we had four, why don't we do six?
It starts to get ridiculous, basically.
I mean, there are drawbacks, right?
We talked about having to do all this pointer hopping, right?
You have to keep following through each level
and that takes time.
There's a point where you're just not saving anything.
It just starts to get out of hand.
So six level page tables aren't really common.
I think Itanium might have.
Itanium was an attempt by Intel to create a new ISA.
It went horrifically wrong.
It's a long and tragic story and somewhat funny
involving lawsuits between Hewlett-Packard and Intel.
And it's a great story that I won't tell you now.
But basically, they did a lot of crazy things
and some of them didn't work out,
including six level page tables.
Okay, so what else can we do?
And then this is, I'm gonna ask for a little bit
of audience thought here, if not participation.
So the problem we're facing here is that
these page tables have drawbacks.
You have to have an entry for every virtual memory address.
So there's still a lot of space.
Every process gets their own page table.
And even with multi-level page tables,
you still have a lot of empty spots.
And typically your address space is way, way bigger
than your physical memory, right?
You might have two for 32 gigs of RAM,
but you've got two to the 64 virtual addresses.
So it's not even a competition.
So the question for you guys is,
let's look at what is the problem we're trying to solve?
The problem is given a virtual address,
I want to be able to map that to a physical address.
So one of the data structures we thought about
for doing that was a tree.
Trees have this login sort of traversal pattern,
and they have these properties,
but we wanna have better than login, right?
We'd like to have fewer pointer chases.
we want a faster look at. So what data structure might we consider that isn't a table? We have a
lot of data structures. Y'all took, I guess it's 61b that teaches you these. So I'm going to give
you 10 seconds to think up what data structure you would use other than a tree. And we got it.
Hash tables are super cool. So hash tables are great. They've got constant access time,
at least, you know, big O constant access time. And we can do some cool tricks with these. So
one of the things we do here is we can have a hash table where it has an entry for every
physical page. Like we don't need more virtual addresses mapped than we have physical memory
because like it doesn't make sense. You can't map, you know, more than physical memory anyways,
because you only have that much memory. So you can have one hash table for the entire system.
And you can use that to look up your virtual page. So you can index into this hash table using
virtual page number and get this physical page number back. And this has been used before,
right? This is nice when you have these big address spaces, these big virtual address spaces.
And so it has been used in a couple of places and it has some nice properties, but it's not perfect
either. So the big problem here, there's two big problems here. Actually probably three big
problems here, but we're going to list two of them here. One is that keep in mind from your
algorithms classes and stuff, the limitations of big O notation, right? We say, oh, constants don't
matter in terms of asymptotic complexity, but like insertion sort is way faster than quick sort
for a small enough list, right? When you were doing merge sort, there was a point where you
bottomed out on merge sort and just switched to like selection sort or insertion sort. And the
same thing applies here. There's a point where the complexity of looking at the hash table,
the constants involved algorithmically and looking at the hash table are actually going to outweigh
the benefits. So that can happen. This is particularly true in hardware.
So because these lookups are happening on every access, we need to do that in hardware. So we're
actually designing a circuit, a digital logic to access this hash table. And so, you know,
it has to be sufficiently simple that you can implement that in hardware. So that's a problem.
The other problem is locality. So hash tables kind of by their very nature, right? That's what
a hash function does is it's pretty random. It's pretty evenly distributed. There's no locality. So
I can't like effectively cache this hash table. Every lookup is going to be in a pretty random
spot in this hash table. So it's not very cache friendly. And that's pretty annoying.
The third problem here actually is that it makes things like sharing really difficult. So this
assumes there's only ever one virtual page, virtual address mapped to a physical page.
But for sharing, we might want to have multiple virtual addresses point to the same physical
address. And so that makes this a lot more complicated if you want to do that.
Nonetheless, it's still pretty handy and people have used them in the past, but they're not
especially popular in processors today. I'm not aware of any, you know, mega really popular
processor. I guess PowerPC might still be around. Okay. So we've got options here. We've got a whole
bunch of options and how we can do paging. At the end of the day, we're all trying to solve the same
problem. You have some address, some virtual address, and you want to map it to some physical
address. That's it. That's all we're trying to do. Right. And these are a bunch of different
algorithms and data structures that we could consider using in order to do that.
So we've got segmentation. Segmentation's great for simplicity in terms of implementing a CPU,
doesn't use too much memory for the metadata, but it's very hard to allocate all these arbitrary
size things. And it really screws with your ability to share memory and allocate memory.
Paging works a lot better. It's a lot more flexible. It's a lot easier to allocate.
But if you have single level page tables, you can really fill up your memory for a lot of empty
space. So we use multi-level paging to get around that. Or you could avoid all of this sort of tree
walking and use an inverted page table, which works pretty great, but has limitations of its own.
Okay. So enough about the high level strategies and the problem we're trying to solve.
Let's get into the nitty gritty. Let's start talking about how you might actually physically
implement this. How does this work in practice? So the thing that is in charge of this is called
the MMU. So this is the part of your architecture, the part of your CPU or your chip that is
responsible for handling this virtual address to physical address translation. So we call that the
memory management unit. Everyone just says MMU. And it's the one that's in charge of all of this.
So it needs to do different things. We're going to focus on paging. So we're going to focus on
page tables probably from now on because it's by far the most common approach, at least in
the sort of high end or medium end application processors that you're likely to see.
So if you have page tables, the MMU is going to have to do the walk. So it's going to walk
that tree in hardware. So it reads the page table entry, the PTE from the first level page table,
checks all the metadata that it needs. And then it goes and finds the address in the second level
page table, looks that up, iterates as many times as it needs, gets the final PTE, and then it can
form the actual physical address and send that request out to the rest of the memory system.
So the MMU is just translating. Logically, the CPU doesn't know about physical addresses.
So the CPU is just issuing virtual addresses and automagically, the MMU is making them
behave like physical addresses. Okay. So it's doing this at every, at least conceptually,
it's got to do this all the time. Every single time you do a read or write, and that includes
fetching the next instruction, that MMU has to do that translation in order to get to memory.
So this is a bit more of a physical representation of it. You can see you've got all these buses
floating around. So you've got your core, your core CPU pipeline, you've got a bunch of buses,
and they're going through these hardware blocks. And if you take 152, you're going to see a lot
more of this, or maybe some of your digital logic classes. A lot of this can take time. So loads and
stores, if they hit in the cache, can be really fast. Maybe they don't stall the pipeline too bad.
But if you miss or you have to go out to physical memory, then your pipeline has to stall and you
get those bubbles. If you remember seeing bubbles, I think in 61c, you hit a little bit of that,
and that can cause problems. So we have to make sure that this translation is really fast. And in
a really naive sense, if we didn't do any fancy optimizations, a single load or store could turn
into like three or four reads and then the loader store, right? So it's multiplying every memory
access by like four if you have a four level page table. So this is a problem and we're going to have
to solve this problem. Okay, so this is really, really slow. I mean, unreasonably slow for any
high performance CPU. So what do we do if we have some sort of data access? We do that data access
multiple times and we want to make it faster. So I already kind of spoiled the answer here by
switching slides. This is caching. Caching is one of those like fundamental core computer science
concepts that just comes up again and again and again. You're going to see caching everywhere.
It's just everywhere. So that's what we're going to have to deal with is caching. That's the trick.
That's the trick we're going to use to solve this. So I'm going to spend a little bit of time now
reviewing caching. I know you learned a little bit about this in 61c. If you've taken like 152 or
something, you're going to see caching in a lot more detail. But I'm going to take some time now
to refresh your memory because caching is super important. And you're going to see just in this
lecture alone, we're going to see two examples of caching, three examples of caching just in this
lecture alone. And then every class you take, you're going to see it. So a cache is a smaller,
faster memory in which we store copies of some original data. It's everywhere, like I just said,
and it really only works if you have some sort of locality. So basically you have to be able to
predict whether you're going to reuse some memory. If you can predict it, then caches are going to
work well. If you have completely unpredictable accesses, then the cache isn't going to work
because what do you store in the cache? Every single one is like totally random.
So they won't work in that case, but as long as you have some locality, caches are great.
Here's a metric. There's a metric that's really important to keep in mind.
This is another one. It's sort of like the iron law. There's a bunch of these equations that seem
really dumb or like Amdahl's law, right? They seem really, they're almost dumb, right? They're just
obvious like, oh yeah, well, of course this is the time. But they're easy to forget and they're
really helpful for thinking and like understanding how systems work. So in this case, we're talking
about average access time. So that is the hit rate times the hit time plus the miss rate times the
miss time is going to be your average access time. So on average, a memory access is going to take
that much time. So keep that in mind. You may be asked to do that on homeworks or tests or things.
It's important. And we're going to, I think we're going to walk through an example here in a second.
Okay. We need to put into context a little bit why we're talking about caching and just how
effective it can be, right? I think humans brains are really bad at reasoning about scale. We just
can't handle things that are like orders of magnitude apart. Our brains just aren't wired
for it. So here's an attempt to put it into perspective, an attempt that will probably fail,
but you should keep these numbers in mind. It's really important to always have this in your head.
So we have multiple ways of storing data in digital logic or in a computer. The fastest
one here is registers and also kind of the L1 cache. The L1 cache might be a little slower
than registers, but it's close. Both of these are about the cycle time. So these are running
about the same speed as like your computer processor cycles. So that means that we want
to interact with these in hardware. These happen at sort of hardware time scales, right? Then we've
got all this stuff in the middle. So we've got all these and they're just getting slower and slower
and slower. And at some point we're going to get all the way to your hard disk. And when you get to
your hard disk to a first order approximation, the amount of time it takes to read from a hard disk is
forever. Like from a hardware perspective, it's not even worth thinking about. I mean, it's an
absolutely absurd amount of time. I was going to need bread, but then I cut my finger, so I
haven't done that recently. Okay, so basically think about hard disks as taking infinite time
from a hardware perspective. If I'm cycling at 4 gigahertz, 10 milliseconds is just a ridiculous
amount of time. And so when we're going to go to these time scales, we're just going to deal with
it in software, right? Because it doesn't make sense for the hardware to even deal with it. It's
so slow. And then there's this stuff in the middle and all this stuff in the middle are going to be
shades of gray, right? And depending on how you want to deal with this, you might have hardware
deal with it. You might have software deal with it. You might have some more complicated mix of
things, right? A lot of my research has focused sort of in this space and understanding where
exactly that barrier between hardware and software can be. And it's a pretty interesting question.
But way over here, definitely want to deal with that completely in software. Way over here,
you definitely want to deal with that completely in hardware. And there's like millions and millions
and millions times difference in the performance here. So that's why caches are important. An L1
cache miss is not a big deal. It's going to happen. You're only going to lose a cycle or something.
If you try and read something from disk, just give up, right? Like go put your laptop away,
go home, come back, right? At least the hardware thinks it's like that.
And then address translation. Because this is so fast, address translation has to happen
right here. It has to happen by the time you get into the core. So it's got to be fast.
Worst case scenario, page tables live here or maybe even here in extreme cases. But for the
most part, your page tables are here. So we need this caching in order to be able to access them
effectively. Okay, so just real quick, because I think it's really important to understand this
equation, we're going to go through an example. So let's take a real example or a made up example
that's real enough. And say that it takes about 100 nanoseconds to get to DRAM. This is about
right. And then say it takes one nanosecond to get to your cache, like your L1. Again, it's about
right. So what's the average memory access time here? I'm going to go through it now just in the
interest of time. But this is something that you guys are going to have to get a little bit
comfortable running. Okay, so actually, I'll let people sort of think about this for a second. And
I'm going to answer this question. Yeah, so what do I mean by letting software deal with it? We're
going to talk about that in a little more detail later in the lecture. But basically, what I mean
is that the hardware might notice that it needs to go to disk, like it might notice that the data
it needs is not available. And rather than some circuit, figuring out how to read from the disk,
so some digital logic issuing requests to the disk, what it's going to do is it's going to
throw what's called a trap. Just like how the user process is able to switch back into kernel mode,
the hardware can decide, you know what, I can't deal with this right now. I'm going to run some
code that the operating system provided. And I'll let that code deal with this. So when we let
software deal with it, that means we hand control to the operating system to make some more
complicated decisions than you could in a dedicated like digital logic circuit. And we'll go into more
details of this later on, assuming we get there. Okay, so we're looking at the average memory
access time. So this is hit rate times hit time plus miss rate times miss time. So the hit rate
plus the miss rate, obviously they've got a match, right? If I didn't hit, then I missed. If I didn't
miss, then I hit. So these are just ratios. So let's assume that our hit rate in this cache is 90%.
That means that our miss rate is going to be 10%. If we hit, then that means it took us a nanosecond
to read. So that'll be 90% times one. And then if we missed, it's going to take us 100 seconds to
read. But I just wrote 101 here. So why did I write 101 and not 100 for the miss time?
I'll give you guys a few seconds to think about that.
So the reason I did that was that in order to notice that I missed, I had to try and hit.
So not quite. So the, yeah, exactly. So I think Brian's got it here. So the trick is that I had
to notice that I missed and that took a nanosecond all by itself. Then I noticed that I missed
and then I could start trying to read from the next level, right? Or actually that might be what
they were just trying to get at too. So that's why. So you have to account for the fact that
missing takes extra time because you have to notice that you missed.
And so we can look at what happens as you change hit rates and miss rates. Notice that a relatively
small increase in the hit rate can have a very large impact on the overall performance. So hit
rates become very, very important. Okay. Again, I talked about why caching works. I'm going to move
a little bit fast here. Well, that's kind of an important concept. We talked about locality. So
caching works because we have predictability. We can guess what memories are likely to be accessed
next. So there's different types of patterns that we might detect. And the most common ones
are temporal locality. So if I read or wrote some address, I'm probably going to read or write it
again. Most likely. Imagine if I have a loop, right? So instructions are memory. If you remember
your whole von Neumann thing, so the program itself is memory. And if I have a loop in my memory,
then I'm going to be reusing those instructions over and over and over because I got this loop,
right? So that's temporal locality. So that's a pretty good guess. That tends to work pretty
well. If I access something recently, I'll probably access it again. The other one is spatial locality.
So this is like, imagine scanning an array, right? If I'm reading an array from start to finish.
So if I read an array from start to finish, if I access one piece of information, it's pretty
likely that I'm going to read addresses that are nearby, right? So that is spatial locality. Stuff
tends to cluster together physically, like in the address space. That's not always true. I talked
earlier about how hash tables aren't very cache friendly. This is why. Because hash tables don't
have a lot of spatial locality. You jump around them a lot. And so things that are physically
near each other aren't necessarily accessed together. But then having an array or a table
lookup or something like that, you have more spatial locality. So they tend to behave a little
nicer. Right. And then the final thing here is that we have multiple levels. And so we can stack
these together in order to keep track of things. Okay. So what is the trick here? Why was I just
talking about caching? Well, translations are slow, really painful. And the trick we're going
to do, the trick we always do, is we're just going to slap a cache on it. Right? Caches are everywhere
and this is no exception. So we're going to stick a cache on the MMU. And now every time we do a
translation, we're going to save that translation in this cache. Now the cache is smaller and it's
faster to access. So we don't have to do all this table locking. We can just look it up in the cache.
And the cache is relatively simple. It's just going to have the virtual page, right? That's what
you're using to look up. Then it's going to have the physical frame number. That's the answer you
want. And then it's also going to cache a bunch of other metadata. So PTEs have a bunch of extreme
in them, like whether this mapping is currently valid or whether you're allowed to read or write
to it. Has it been accessed recently? There's a bunch of little metadata. We'll show you a picture
at the end of the slides, but a lot of little data that you want to keep around to keep track
of extra information. And that's, so that's what you're caching. So keep in mind here, this is not
caching data. So this has nothing to do with what's actually in the page, right? We're not caching the
information contained in the page. All we're caching is metadata. We're caching information about the
page. So that's what we're trying to cache here. And it's going to save us every time we hit in
this cache, we get to avoid walking the table. And that's pretty nice. Okay. So this cache, for
largely historical reasons, is referred to as a translation lookaside buffer. It's just a fancy
word for a cache. Turns out, it's a very old idea. It was, they came up with it quite a long time
ago, before the word cache was really coined. And so it has kind of a funny name. But either way,
it's storing these translations. You know, if we hit in that cache, we get to avoid all these slow
lookups. So that's really nice. Like I said, it was invented actually quite a long time ago,
before the word cache was even being commonly used, hence the funny name. And we call it the
TLB. So you're gonna, I don't think anybody ever says translation lookaside buffer out loud, they
only ever say TLB. So you'll have to get used to hearing that word. But keep in mind, TLB is just a
funny word for cache. It's a cache for your page table lookups, a cache for virtual to physical
translations. So how does this work? Let's go through just sort of a flow diagram, a workflow of
how this actually goes. So CPU is going to ask for a virtual address, it's going to try and find it
in the TLB, or the MMU is going to try and find it in the TLB. If it does, great, immediately,
it's just going to push that request all the way through to physical memory, and everything's on
theory. If it's not, so there's nothing cached, then you're going to have to go to the MMU. And
the MMU is going to have to go back and forth to memory a couple times to walk that table. But once
it's walked the table, and it's looked up the translation, it can save that translation in the
TLB, and then go and do the translation for the CPU, and everything starts back up.
So why does this work? And does it work? It's a question of page locality, right? So is there
locality, or is the caching going to work? Is there spatial locality? Is there temporal locality?
It turns out there is. So it turns out that physical memory, the pages in physical memory,
tend to have quite a lot of locality, actually. The biggest, a really, really big source of this
is your code, right? Code is data. I talked about this before. So when you're reading a program,
like when you're running a program, the instructions that make up that program are
all close together. So that's spatial locality. And they tend to get reused a lot. So you have a
loop, you're reusing the instructions. If you call into functions, one of the whole points of having
subroutines or functions is that you only have one copy of that code, and you call into it lots
of times. So tons and tons of temporal locality in code. You also have other spatial and temporal
locality. Your stack gets reused again and again and again. A lot of the sort of hard data stuff.
The heap is, you know, more variable. Whether or not your heap has locality, it's the same reasons
it has cache locality in your data caches. It's up to you to write a program that has good cache
locality, but it tends to. And of course, all the tricks that we play for caches apply to TLBs as
well. They're just a cache. So maybe they got a few different decisions you might make, but
ultimately they're caches and all the same tricks work. So we can have a multi-level TLB if we want.
Okay, we've been talking for a while. I'm going to take a break. I'm going to get some water and
do a stretch, and I will allow others to do the same. So we're going to take a two-minute break.
So I'll be back at 1.28. Here's a bunch of announcements. I'm just sort of stepping in
for today, so I have no idea what any of these announcements mean, and it's just what Jan gave
me. So talk to your TAs or whatever. Okay, 1.28, we'll be back.
Oh, and while we're waiting, you guys can ask questions and stuff if you want.
Okay. Thank you.
Thank you.
Okay.
Okay, and we're back.
Quick break.
A lot of content to cover.
Okay, so, starting again.
Okay.
Okay. So, we talked about caching a lot.
Real handy to keep this in mind.
This is a concept that comes up again and again.
So, let's talk about, you know, we talked about why caches work.
You know, you talked about temporal locality and spatial locality.
So, let's talk about what makes caches not work.
What makes us miss in the cache.
So, let's categorize them.
So, recall the one of the types of cache miss that you can get is called compulsory.
This means it's a miss that you really just can't do anything about.
Right? Like, I've never seen this data before, therefore I don't have it cached.
So, called, you know, compulsory misses are mostly unavoidable.
There's some tricks you can do with what's called prefetching.
Where you try and guess what you might need in the future.
And that's really the only way that you can avoid compulsory misses.
Another one is called capacity misses.
So, in this case, I basically just ran out of space.
I have cached everything I can cache.
I have no more room.
I had to kick something out of my cache because I ran out of room.
And therefore, I missed the next time you tried to read it.
So, I saw this data, I cached it, and then I ran out of room and I had to kick it out again.
So, the way you deal with capacity misses is you make your cache bigger.
And you make it bigger and bigger and everything's great.
But keep in mind, as you make your cache bigger, it gets slower.
So, there's a point where you don't want to make the cache any bigger.
Another one, conflict.
So, in this case, with a conflict miss, I've seen the data before, so it's not compulsory.
I have enough capacity for it so that I have empty space in my cache.
I could store it.
But because of the algorithm and the data structures I chose, so because of the way I chose to design my cache, I had to kick something out.
So, we're going to go into those details again here in a minute about what sort of algorithms you might choose and why those might have conflict misses, even if there was enough room.
But the bottom line here is that I couldn't store it because of the algorithms I chose.
And there's different ways of dealing with conflict misses.
You can make the cache bigger so that you're less likely to have one of these conflicts, or you can change your algorithm.
You can make your algorithm a little more sophisticated, and then you're less likely to have conflicts.
There's one more, and I don't think this was talked about very much in 61c, if at all.
It's been a few years since I taught that class.
But the last one here is called coherence.
And this is one that's going to come up a lot in TLBs.
So this is kind of a big one for TLBs.
And a coherence one is basically that a cache is a copy.
So I have a copy of data, but the data that's up in, say, main memory, that's the real data.
That's the official, real ground truth of what that data is.
And my cache is just a copy of that.
And so if somebody changes that data in main memory for whatever reason, some other CPU does it, or some other process or circuit or trigger or whatever did it,
if it changes for some reason, then I have to invalidate my cache.
I have to tell the cache, "Hey, you have a copy of this data, but it's not true anymore. You need to throw it out and read the new data."
So that's called a coherence miss.
And this is one that doesn't show up much in data caches for single CPU systems.
But if you have multiple CPUs, it happens a lot.
And if you have things like TLBs have it more often because there's more things that change page table entries.
And TLBs are kind of separate from the data cache.
But we'll go into that in more detail.
So false sharing is a particularly degenerate cause of coherence misses.
So this is a question in the chat.
So basically, false sharing causes unnecessary coherence misses.
But you can have coherence misses that don't involve false sharing.
So if you have true sharing, right?
So let's say I'm sharing -- you see this a lot in locks, when you're implementing locks.
This is really common.
You have lots and lots of entities, lots and lots of different cores.
And they're all trying to read and write the same piece of memory.
Maybe it's to set a lock, maybe it's just to communicate.
That's real sharing.
And that would cause lots and lots of coherence misses.
What happens with false sharing is that caches store an entire line at a time.
So you store blocks.
You store a cache line.
And so let's say that you're not actually sharing data.
Like core zero is writing the first byte.
Core one is writing the next byte.
Core two is writing the next byte.
So they're not sharing data.
But they are sharing the same cache line.
So they're sharing the same block.
So that's why it's called false sharing.
The caches can only detect conflicts or coherence issues on a cache line granularity.
So you're not actually sharing data, but you are sharing the same cache line.
And that's causing a bunch of coherence misses.
So Albert asks, how do we know if there's been a coherence miss?
That is an excellent question.
That is -- so there's a famous quote that I love.
And I'm sorry, I can't think of the originator of the quote off the top of my head.
But he says, there's only two hard problems in computer science.
Naming things and cache invalidation.
So the answer to your question, Albert, is that it is an extremely difficult and complicated problem.
One that makes my head spin when I try and understand it.
And one over which many PhDs have been written.
So cache coherence is hard.
It's very tricky to do.
And if you take 152, they'll go into it in quite a lot of detail.
The different algorithms they use to detect coherence misses.
That's for data caches.
And I particularly think 152 is a great class and you'll learn a ton if you take it.
TLBs are interesting because they tend not to participate in all those schemes.
Because the only time the data changes is when the operating system chose to change the page tables.
And so TLBs tend to rely on manual cache invalidation.
I know RISC-V does, or at least all the RISC-V implementations I'm familiar with do.
And I'm pretty sure x86 does as well.
So in this case, the OS has to tell the CPU, hey, I invalidated this line, go and throw it out.
So in that case, there's like the operating system is manually detecting it.
But for data caches, it gets very complicated.
And for distributed systems, too.
So if you take a database class, you'll learn about dealing with cache coherence in like a distributed systems networked cluster kind of perspective.
It's the same problem, slightly different constants.
So the solutions are a little different.
OK.
So we're going to go through a quick here overview of caching again.
This is, I think, largely a duplicate of what you learned in 61c.
But obviously, that was quite a long time ago and 61c is a ridiculous class where you learn way too many things in one shot.
So it's worth revisiting.
So how do we find blocks? So we're using blocks. Sometimes we use the word cache line.
So how do we actually find them in cache? Most caches are organized this way.
This is definitely by far the most typical way to organize a cache.
I guess in theory, there's other options, but I'm not really aware of anybody that does them in hardware in a way that's different than this.
So what you do is it's very similar to what we've been seeing for virtual to physical translations.
So I've got my address here. So this is the top part of the address.
And this is whatever I'm asking for.
There's also a part and this is the offset within the line.
So I'm storing a block or a cache line. It's some fixed size. It's bigger than a byte.
Right. So maybe it's 64 bytes, whatever it is. So I've got a 64 byte cache line.
So I'm going to need some offset to figure out which byte that is.
And then you've got the block address and the block address is going to help you figure out which cache line it is you're looking at.
And typically we break this block address into two parts. We'll call one the index and we'll call one the tag.
The index is the one we're actually going to use to find the block in our cache.
And the tag is the one we're going to use to make sure it's the block we think it is.
So caches are very, very similar to hash tables.
And a lot of what you can learn learned about hash tables also will help you understand caches.
So this tag is like, you know, in a hash table, you hash the value and you use that to find it.
And then you compare the actual value against what you found to make sure it's the one you wanted and not just like a conflict.
Same thing here. OK.
So one of the options we could do is called direct mapped.
So in a direct map cache, we are going to have exactly one place that we could put any particular address.
So in a way, you're going to use the index to choose exactly one slot.
So let's see.
So if I've got a one kilobyte direct map cache, I got 32 byte blocks.
There's an index and I'm going to use that index to pick a particular line, a particular place in this cache that I want.
So let's say that the index here is one.
We're going to use that to select one of these entries and then we're going to compare the tags.
So I'm going to make sure that the tag I have in my cache is, in fact, same one as the address I'm looking for.
And then if so, I'm going to use the byte select to pick a particular byte out of that cache line to return.
So this is direct map. The important thing here about direct map is that you have exactly one option.
This index has exactly as many bits as you have entries in the cache.
And it's just a direct index. If it's one, we go to the index number one.
If it was two, we'd go to index number two. That's direct map.
Direct map has an issue. The issue with direct map is that it's got lots and lots of conflict misses.
Since I only have one option about where I'm going to put a piece of data,
it's pretty likely that somebody is already there and I'm going to have to kick them out in order to fit the new thing.
So they have lots and lots of conflict misses because you only have one choice about where you're going to put anything.
So what we do instead is we come up with set associative. So in a set associative cache, we give ourselves more options.
So instead of having exactly one place that we could put a particular piece of data, we have in places that we could put it.
So you can think of this as having two direct map caches side by side, sort of conceptually.
So you can think I have two direct map caches, but I've set them next to each other.
So each is half the size of my total cache. But I now have more options.
So we do the same thing. I'm going to use that cache index to pick which line in one of these caches it is.
But I'm going to have to check two tags. So if I'm a two way set associative cache,
then I have to check two tags at the same time. And then I get to pick whichever one matches, if any.
So the set associative caches are giving us more options. We're less likely to have a cache miss.
Right. Because the data could go here, but this is full. So, OK, I guess we'll just put it here since this one's not full.
So we have options and that's going to reduce conflict misses. But there's a there's a cost.
The cost is complexity. So if you remember your Logisim project from 61C, like imagine writing a mux that could handle like a thousand inputs.
Think about how narrowly that mux would look. Right. It would have just bajillions of wires.
It would be huge. It would be like completely impractical to implement on like a physical chip.
So there are a limit to how many ways you can have before this stuff starts getting so complicated that your cycle time goes out the window.
But you can do it. So in the extreme, we could say, all right, well, you know what, I don't care.
My cache is small enough that that multiplexer isn't going to be too unreasonable. So why not have as many ways as I have lines?
In this case, the whole thing is that the the entire the entire address part of your address, the entire selector part of your address.
here is your tag. You just don't even have an index, right? You just search the entire
cache simultaneously to find your tag. And these work if the cache is small enough, you
can get away with a fully associative cache, but it starts to wear out pretty fast, right?
You're not going to have like even a multiple kilobyte cache. You couldn't have direct or
fully associative. It just wouldn't be possible to implement hardware.
Okay, so let's see. So let's put them all together and kind of compare and contrast what would
happen here. So let's say I'm trying to put block number one, I guess, or two, whatever.
I'm trying to put this block here into a cache. So if it's direct mapped, I'm putting block
number 12. So I'm going to look at what the index here is 12. I've got eight blocks in
my cache. So I need to split 12 up into eight potential places. So I do 12 mod 8. That's,
you know, mod in binary is the same as just like picking some bits. Turns out 12 mod 8,
that's I think three or four, that's four. So we're going to find it here, direct mapped.
Set associative. I have fewer slots now. So I have four sets, right? Because I'm two-way
set associative. So I have four sets, each set has four entries, four times four, or
they have two entries. So each set has two entries. I have four sets, you have eight
lines total. So in this case, I'm going to do 12 mod 4 and pick which set it is in. So
in this case, turns out it's in set zero. And then I'm going to compare both tags simultaneously
and pick whichever one it is. And then of course, for fully associative, I'm not even
going to bother looking at the address. I'm just going to compare that address against
every single line until I find it. Okay, so that was a quick kind of whirlwind review
of cache organization. You can go back and kind of follow that along a little slower.
It's worth keeping in mind, it's worth remembering caches are really important. The next question
you have with a cache is about what happens to it when you miss. So for direct map cache,
there's really no choice, right? Like if I have to replace a block, I only had one option.
So that's the one I'm going to kick out. Whoever was in my slot gets kicked out and I go there,
your only option. For set associative, we have a choice. You know, I have multiple ways.
I have multiple sets in my cache, which if every entry in that set is full, who do I
kick out? I can cook out any of them and still be correct. So which one do I choose? Two
big strategies here could do it totally randomly, not the worst idea. Or I could do it using
the least recently used algorithm. This ends up being pretty true in practice. Like the
thing I use the longest ago in the past is the one I'm least likely to use in the future.
So whichever one hasn't been used recently, that's probably a good choice to kick out.
So we can go through some examples here. We don't need to look at these numbers too detailed.
You can come back and stare at these if you'd like, but the trend here is multiple things.
So you can see that as you increase the associativity, so when we go this way, miss rates go down
as you go this way. And as you go this way, as the cache gets bigger, miss rates also
go down. So this is removing conflict misses. This is removing capacity misses. So there's
a question here about how we keep track of LRU. The way you keep track of LRU is you
assign kind of like a shift register. You basically have a few bits. So if I have a
two-way set associative cache, I can have one bit in there. And every time I read from
that line, I set the bit. And I set the bit and I clear the other bit. So if I read from
set zero, then I set its recently used bit to one, and I set way one's bit to false.
So I can just alternate. If you have four, you can do it that way. But you basically
have a counter next to every line and you update the counter on every access. And that
helps you keep track of LRU. There's other tricks too. You can do things with shift registers
and whatever. You can do approximate LRU if it's cheaper. But when you don't have too
many sets, it's pretty easy just to have a couple of counters that you update on every
access.
Okay. So what happens on a write? So this is another aspect of cache design, another
design choice we have. We have what happens when I need to write data to cache. So reading
data from the cache is no big deal. That's what we've been talking about pretty much
this whole time. But what happens when we want to modify that data? So one strategy
is called write through. So in a write through cache, every time I write to my cache, I also
write to the higher levels too. So I write to the next tier of the cache at the same
time. The reason this works is that I can return as soon as the data is sort of being
written. I can stick it in a queue and just have faith that it will get written eventually.
So when we're doing write through, we're not limited by the latency of the cache. We're
only limited by the bandwidth of the cache. And it turns out bandwidth is a lot easier
to achieve than latency. But it still has a problem. It's still using a ton of bandwidth
to do that. We're writing a ton of data. And keep in mind, locality is a thing. That's
the whole reason caches work. So if we wrote to an address once, we're probably going to
write to it again soon. And so why should we be wasting all of this bandwidth writing
over and over and over if we're just like iterating on a line? So the way to avoid that
is called write back. In a write back cache, what we do is we only bother storing the cache
line that we've written to. We only bother writing it back to the higher level layers
in our hierarchy if it gets evicted. So when we come in with a new line and we say, "Okay,
we have to kick this block out, this cache line out, but we've modified it. Oh, great.
Well, now we have to write it back as we evicted." So that's called write back. And the way you
do that is the same trick as I was just explaining for LRU. You just keep an extra bit around.
You set a bit if you've written to it. So if that bit is set, then, "Okay, well, I've
written to it. I need to write it back." Okay, so this is what I just said. But the bottom
line here is that there's issues with write amplification. With a write through cache,
when I evict a line, it doesn't cost me anything. So there's no additional work that's required
in order to evict a line. You get to just delete it right away. No thought. Just, "Nah,
it's gone." Because I already wrote it higher up. So I can just delete it whenever I want
and it won't break anything. But with a write back cache, it's more complicated. If I need
to evict a line, now I've got to figure out, "Oh, was it dirty? Oh, it was dirty. Let's
figure out where to store it now." And it messes things up a little bit. But the real
problem though is that with a write through cache, you could get hung up on bandwidth.
So I could spend way too much time doing writes that didn't even have to happen. And maybe
that interferes with my ability to read or write data that actually needed to be written.
So pros and cons, I think write backs are more common, but depending on the organization
of your cache and the relative speeds of things, write through might be a reasonable choice.
Okay. A lot of stuff here, man. A lot of stuff. Caches are a really rich thing. There's a
lot of different strategies around caches. So coming back to the theme of this whole
lecture, which is virtual memory, we have to ask the question, "What are the addresses
that we're using to look stuff up in the cache? Are we looking things up with physical addresses
or are we looking things up with virtual addresses?" So with a physical cache, the way you would
have to implement that is you'd have to figure out what the physical address is first. And
once you figured out the physical address, then you can ask the cache to go ahead and
look it up. So that would be a physically indexed cache. With a virtually indexed cache,
I could access the cache directly and I would only need to access the TLB if I'm going higher
up in the memory. Right? So I could have a cache that only keeps track of virtual addresses.
And that saves me having to go through the NMU every time. I'd be able to just read and
write from it directly. So that's pretty slick. That seems really nice, but it has problems.
Right? It adds a lot of challenges. One is, remember this whole write through, write back
thing. If I want to write to this, so if this cache needs to write to memory, it then has
to go through this NMU, through this TLB. And that can be kind of messy. The bigger
problem here though, a much, much bigger issue is that this cache, because it's storing virtual
addresses, the cache is only valid for one process. If I switch processes, the cache
is like totally wrong now. Right? Because it was keeping track of virtual addresses.
So that's a real problem with virtually address caches. There's, you know, tricks you can
do. You can store which process that particular cache line corresponded to. There's a lot
of different things you can do, but none of them are pretty, right? They're all kind of
messy and they all have their own caveats and problems. So it's very tricky to pull
this off, but it does make sense if you're willing to write all the complex circuitry,
if you're willing to make those trade-offs and if your workload supports it, maybe a
virtually indexed cache makes sense. I think physically indexed is more common. I wish
I could tell you off the top of my head what RISC-V does, what, not RISC-V, what the Rocket
Core implementation of RISC-V does. I believe that their L1 is some sort of goofy hybrid
where the the MMU and TLB are super tightly integrated into the cache. So it's somewhat
virtually indexed. But I'm not 100% sure how that works.
Okay, but for the most part, we're going to talk about physically indexed because that's
definitely the most common design.
Okay, so all of this talk about caches, all of this that we just spent a bunch of time
talking about was in service of TLBs, right? This lecture still in theory is about virtual
addresses. So let's get back to why we brought this up in the first place. And that is TLBs.
So, again, remember TLB is a cache. It's just a cache of translations. That's it. It's just
a cache that keeps track of those virtual to physical mappings.
What are the properties we want out of a TLB? Well, the first one and, you know, really,
really important one here is speed. TLB needs to be accessed on every single instruction
and sometimes multiple times per instruction. So it's very, very important that the TLB
be fast.
So that means you maybe we want to keep it direct mapped or low associativity or something
like that. But we'll see why that maybe isn't the greatest idea.
The other issue is that we want to keep conflicts down. I mean, we always do. But the problem
is that like, missing in a TLB is pretty painful, right? Walking those page tables is really
slow. So the miss time here is not pretty. And the hit time is dictated by the clock
cycle. So, again, we need it to be really fast in the common case, but we want it to
not miss very often. And, you know, the trade off between those two properties is what hardware
designers and architects spend a lot of their time doing is deciding how to trade off these
goals.
Oops, sorry.
I don't know what I'm doing here. Okay, whatever. Moving on. So the question is, how big do
we make it? And what organization do we use? In practice, people usually make TLBs fast
by keeping them small. So that's the trick that hardware designers tend to use when they
try and make a TLB fast. Because it's small, they get to be highly associative. And because
they're highly associative, their miss rate is pretty low. And this is just a trade off,
right? You can make a lot of different decisions. But the hardware designers who've done all
the math, they've done all the profiling, all the experiments, they decided that, you
know what, this is probably the best way to make the TLB work the way we want it to. Right,
again, because it's a cache, we can do all the same tricks with caches, right, we can
have a multi level TLB. Why not? Right, we have multi level caches, why not have multi
level TLBs? It'll still work. Right. So you know, we can look at this example, I think
I want to just get through more content. But ultimately, a TLB is going to store a virtual
address, a physical address and metadata. Right. And I guess one piece of metadata worth
mentioning here, there's there's two particularly important ones here that we'll talk about
later. One is ASID, that is the address space identifier. So we want to be able to support
multiple processes. And this ASID is what we use to keep track of that. So you can think
of this kind of like the kind of like a pointer or the index of the of the page table. So
it's like a process ID, who's who does this virtual address belong to? And then the other
one that's important here is the valid bit. So the valid bit tells us whether or not this
mapping actually exists. So we might have a page table entry, but that page table entry
might not point anywhere real, or maybe it's been revoked, or maybe it's been changed,
a lot of different reasons why it might not be valid, but we have to know. And that's
going to prevent us from doing the translation if it's not valid. Okay, and just, you know,
so you understand the TLBs are tightly integrated into the core, they have to be really fast,
they have to be very close to the core. And so we have actual different stages, different
designs of the TLB. And there's parts of it that are spread around different parts of
your of your core. So actually implementing TLBs is quite a very interesting digital logic
and computer architecture question. Okay, there's all sorts of tricks you can do. Again,
just just your computer architects are full of this kind of thing where they have all
these little tricks that make things faster. So for example, you know, you can imagine
that you have a physically addressed hash and a TLB. And maybe we can play a trick and
do something in parallel. So we can maybe overlap. So I'm going to, I'm going to show
an example here of how that might work. So you might imagine that I've got this address
here that I'm trying to translate. And it turns out that the say there's these top bits
here, these top 20 bits, that's the virtual page number. And that's the only thing that
TLB needs to look up, right, the TLB doesn't care about this chunk, it only cares about
the virtual page number. So we'll send that to the TLB, it'll start translating. And if
we have the right size of caches, if everything lines up, we might be able to have the index
here be these lower bits, and we can send that to the physical cache. And then so now
the physical cache tries to find the line, the TLB tries to find the translation. And
then once they've actually done it, we can, we can look at the tag and the physical page
number. And if they match, we have a hit. So it's a dirty little trick. And it works
if all the numbers line up. But as soon as the caches don't line up, it stops working.
So that's a little tricks. Highly recommend taking 152 if you're interested in all of
these tricks, because there's a ton of them. Okay, um, so we only have a minute left. So
let's see. Let's talk about context switches, and then we'll finish. So what happens when
I change the process? If I switch processes, I have to be careful to keep track of which
process this TLB entry goes to. So maybe I flush the entire entire TLB. If I didn't keep
track of address spaces, we saw in the RS 3000, which is just an older processor, that
they do keep track of addresses, a lot of tricks, a lot of different ways you could
do it. But you have to you have to pick one, right, either you invalidate the whole TLB
on each context switch, which is slow, but simple. Or you create you keep a process ID
in the TLB, that might slow down the hit time of the TLB. But you know, won't have all these
misses when you contact switch. And then there's this is the last one, this is what I was talking
about, it's possible for the OS to change the page tables on you, right, it does it
all the time. And if you do, then you have to go and invalidate the TLB. So those are
those coherence misses that the TLB is really have to deal with. And this is a really big
design decision in operating systems, operating systems spend a lot of mental energy, trying
to understand this and make this not happen too often. Okay, so um, yeah, so I'm going
to end it there. Because we're out of time. And I'll let the next lecture kind of do this,
this is a great slide to start the next lecture on anyways. So you guys will start with this
overview. And then you can get into more interesting stuff around paging. And you know, people
asked about what happens when software has to deal with the disk, all that stuff, you
can look forward to that in the next lecture. So I'll end it there. I think we're out of
time. And I'll stick around for a few minutes if anybody wants to ask questions, and then
I'll end off the recording. So thanks for listening.
Bye bye.
Transcribed by https://otter.ai
[ Silence ]