Okay. Hello everyone. Welcome to today's lecture. So today we are going to finish our discussion
on demand paging and on memory in general. And we are going to start the discussion on IO
if time permitted. As always, please ask your questions, any questions, anytime.
I will try to answer them as quickly as possible.
So if you remember the last time, we ended with showing this FIFO example policy
for page replacement. Why do you need page replacement? Why do you need to evict
pages out of memory on the disk or SSD? This is a question for you.
Okay. It's exactly. So the main reason you need to evict pages from memory
on the disk is because you are going, the memory allocated by processes is going to exceed
the physical memory. And the memory allocated by processes is there via virtual memory.
So each process has its own virtual memory. It allocates part of that virtual memory for its code,
for its stack and for its heap and data. And then all of these have to be stored in the physical
memory once they are accessed. And because the sum of all this allocation for overall processes
on a machine is going to in general be higher than the physical memory, then sometimes you need
to move the pages from the physical memory to the disk. And because you want to do that, then
the question about which page you are going to decide to evict, it's an important one
because evicting different pages will have a significant impact on performance. So which page
of you are going to choose to evict is going to have an impact on performance. So for instance,
if you evict the page which you are going to access next, then it's not going to be a good
idea because remember then there is a pretty high overhead in bringing the page back from the disk to
memory. And on the other hand, if you remember the optimal replacement policy
eviction policy is basically evicting the page which will be accessed the farthest in the future.
Okay. So, but of course, that's hard to implement. And we discussed, as we discussed,
so we are now going through a few simple cache page replacement policies. And we started last
time with a FIFO one. So the FIFO replacement policy is very simple. You always evict the page,
which was the first one which was brought to memory, right, to brought in memory.
And we went through these simple examples. This is just to refresh your memory. Here we have
the memory. The physical memory has three pages, three page frames. And
we are accessing four pages, so not all of them, A, B, C, D, not all of them are going to fit in
memory at a given time because they are four and the memory has only three pages. And this is a
sequence in which you are accessing these pages. So you remember it's A, B, C. These are all
compulsory misses. The page is not in the memory, so you need to bring the page from the disk to
memory. That's a miss. And now after you access the first three, now the memory is full. Now you
access A is great. It's already in the memory. You don't need to do anything. Then you access B,
the same thing. It's in memory. Don't need to do anything. And now you are accessing D. D is not in
memory. So what you are going to do, you are going to have to choose to evict one of the existing
pages to bring B into memory. And A was the one in this case, because it's five for you are going to
evict A because A, as you can see in this figure, was the first one which was brought in memory.
So you have A, so now you have D, B, C in memory. A comes, so A is accessed again. So
unfortunately, as you can see here, was not a great idea in hindsight to evict A because now
you will need to bring it back. But again, according to the five for policy now,
you are going to evict B, right? Because from the existing pages in the memory, B was the one which
was the oldest. It's the oldest one. Then D again, you don't do anything because D is already in
memory. Now B comes, you access B. B is no longer in memory, so you need to replace the oldest page,
which is C, and so forth. Okay? So as we looked at that, and if you remember again from the last time,
we have seven misses or seven page faults. Three are compulsory misses, A, B, C, and the D, A,
and B, C are capacity misses. We had the miss because the memory was not large enough.
Okay? So now let's look about how this optimal policy mean, or at least recently,
you know, mean will work. Okay? So suppose we have the same reference stream,
and again, the same memory, three, with three pages. A, B, C, the same thing happens. Nothing
changes, right? Until you fill in the memory, because obviously before you fill in the memory,
there is no eviction. A again, nothing happened. B, nothing happened. So now,
tell me without looking to the slides, please tell me now I have B, and now I am going to access
after B, I am going to access D. Which page I am going to replace and why?
So I want to access, to replace a page which will be accessed farthest in the future.
And I'm here, I'm D. So after that, I'm going to access A, B, C, B.
Okay, so the answer C, because A, D, B, C. Yeah, yeah.
Okay? That's correct. So after I am going to access D, you know, I am going,
after that, I'm going to access A, then B, and B, and C. So C is the one which is farthest in
the future. So I'm going to replace D. Now, next, I'm going to access A, nothing happens.
Now I'm going to access D again, and now I'm going to access B, nothing happens. And now I am going
to access C. C is no longer in memory. In memory, I have only A, B, and D, which I'm going to replace.
Which page I'm going to replace now? I'm here, B, then following one are C and B. A. Okay?
Do you see another page I could replace?
Yeah, you can replace A, it's fine. What if I were, if I would have replaced D?
Yes, D is also an option. Okay? Because if I replace D, the following two access are C and B,
so again, I have no miss. No page fault. So now you can see that instead of seven,
now you have only five page faults. Right? And remember, A, B, C were compulsory. You are going
to have them anyway. So from capacity misses, before we had four, now we have two.
Okay? So it's quite an improvement. Now we said that with mean, while it's optimal,
it's very hard to implement, right? Because it's assumed that you know the future,
but you don't know the future. And what people do, it's approximated. And the one way to
approximate it is using list recently used. So they assume basically that the accesses are
local also in time or in any space. And basically they say, well, the assumption is that if I
accessed a page recently, I am also going to access it soon. And if I haven't accessed the
page for a long time, I am no longer to access that page for a long time in the future. Okay?
So by this one, this means that I am going to a big pages, which I haven't
accessed for a long time. Okay. That's what it is. So let's see what happens here.
Again, let's now see this. This is a stream. And let's see, A, B, C, the same, D. Now D,
which one I'm going to replace? I have to replace, remember, the page which has not been accessed
in the past for a long time, for the longest time. So which one I'm going to replace here?
A, correct. Right? Because A has been not accessed for whatever, two time units or three
time units, depends how you count. Okay. So I replaced A, so now I have D, B, C. Now A comes.
Which one I'm going to replace?
B, right? Very good. So now B. A, right? And now comes C. No, sorry, it's come B. B is again.
I need to replace, I'm going to replace C, because he was not accessed for a long time,
for the longest time. Now I have C. I'm going to replace D, and so forth.
Okay. So now, the things about this scenario, it is that LRU for this particular input
doesn't behave very well. Right? And it's again, the reason it doesn't behave very well,
it is because you don't know the future. And this means that the assumption behind
LRU is broken. Right? Again, remember that the assumption is that the pages which haven't been
accessed for a long time, they are not going to be accessed in the future. But this is exactly
wrong. Right? Because after D here, I am accessing A, which hasn't been accessed for a long time in
the future, the longest time in the past, and so forth. Okay? Now, the one thing I should have
said in the previous slide, if you look in the previous slide, let's look in the previous slide
and do the same thing. First, we tried min. Now let's try to think about how will LRU work. Okay?
So let's see how LRU will work for the same string. So now think it's LRU. So this is recently
used. So now I have A, I am accessing A. Right? And now I have B, I am accessing B. And now I am
having D. So according to LRU policy, when I get D, which page I am going to replace?
[silence]
Correct. I am going to replace actually, Allison is correct. I'm going to replace C.
And Brian and Eric, you know, and others. The reason I'm not going to replace
A is A was accessed right here. Do you see my cursor? Do you see my pointer?
Okay. Great. Yes. So you see, A was accessed here.
And B was accessed here, which means that when D comes, C is a page which was not accessed for the
longest time. So the difference is that with FIFO, the time which matters is when the page was
brought into memory. With LRU, the time which matters is when the page was accessed. That's
the difference. Okay? So I have to replace D here. And now I'm going to do A, I'm going to access A,
I am B, and now D, I'm going to access D. Now I'm going to B, right? I'm going to bring B. B is
already in memory. And now I'm going to get C. C is no longer in memory, right? But let's say when
I get C, which page I'm going to replace? So again, it has to be the page which has not been
accessed for the longest time in the past. Right? So B was accessed here. D was accessed here. A was
accessed here. So which one I'm going to replace? A. Okay. And now B, it's already in memory.
So in this particular case, the point here is that mean and LRU behave the same.
But this is not necessary. Okay? Like we've seen in the preview in the next example,
actually LRU can perform quite badly, right? If the assumption is violated. Okay?
So and obviously mean in this case, that's much better. When I'm going to access D,
I am here, I am accessing D, which is along as a page which is not accessed for the longest time in
the future is C, right? So I am going to replace C. Now I'm going to get A and B. I'm going to
A, B are already in memory. Now C. C is no longer in memory. C, but I am looking at C
when it's accessed. If I look in the future, I can look in the future. Then I access D, A, B,
and C again. So the longest, the one which will not be accessed for the longest time in the future
is B. So I'm going to replace B. Okay? And then so forth. So in this particular case, the mean
is going to have, you know, six faults or misses while LRU is going to have 12, double. Okay?
Good. But still, no matter, like you'll see in the rest of this lecture,
still, LRU is considered a very good heuristics because many programs
are exhibit locality in their memory access. Okay? And as you'll see, the problem, it will be then to
approximate LRU because LRU itself is expensive to implement. But before going that, let's look
about a little bit more, take a step back and look about what is, you know, the number of page faults
versus the number of frames. So this is our memory size. So on the X axis, we have the memory size in
terms of the number of frames. And on the Y axis, you have the number of page faults. Okay? And as
you'd expect, as the number of frames increases, so you'd expect the number of page faults to decrease.
Okay? Does it make sense?
More memory, fewer page faults.
However, it turns out there are anomalies to this.
There are certain page replacement algorithms
which do not have these properties,
which means that I increase the memory
and for the same workload, the number of page faults increases.
Very counterintuitive.
You have more resources, you perform worse.
And here is an example.
By the way, this is not for all page replacement policies,
it's only for specific ones, like FIFO.
Like for instance, it turns out that for LRU and MIN,
this is not the case.
For LRU and MIN, whenever I increase the memory size,
the number of page faults is not going to increase.
Either stays the same or is going to decrease.
But now, this is an example in which using FIFO
will result in more page faults when I increase the page size.
So here you have A, B, C, D. I have now five pages.
I am accessing five pages.
The memory has still three frames, one, two, three.
And this is for this particular access patterns,
this is what the page faults are.
And now, there are nine page faults.
But now, assume that I'm going to increase the number of pages
or the number of frames in the memory from three to four.
And as it turns out, again, with FIFO, it's very simple.
FIFO is very simple to look, right?
Because you always, when you have a page fault,
you replace the one which was brought first.
And on this graphic, it's very simple to see the one which
was brought first, right?
You just look on each line, which is a first in memory,
right?
OK.
So you can convince yourself when you get E here,
you are going to replace A. A, you are going to replace B,
and so forth.
And by doing so, if I have now instead of three, four frames,
then I get 10 page faults.
So the memory size increases from three frames to four frames.
And the number of page faults increases from nine to 10.
OK.
Any questions?
It's a cool example, right?
It's like you wouldn't expect that.
Now, the reason for ALERU or MIN, the reason this doesn't
happen for ALERU or MIN is because they
have these properties.
That if, say, I have a memory, the memory size, it's x frames.
If I increase the number of frames by, say, one,
then I'm guaranteed that the pages I have in memory,
when the memory size was x, it's a subset of the pages
I'm going to have in memory when the memory is x plus 1.
And because you have this subset property,
then the number of page faults cannot increase.
OK.
So that's the reason.
So now, as I mentioned, if you remember,
we mentioned that in the last lecture,
that ALERU is not easy to implement.
Because ALERU requires that one way to implement,
at least recently, you used to have a list.
And whenever you access a page in this list,
you take that page and you bring it at the head of the list.
And then when you have to replace a page,
you take the page from the end of the list,
and that's the one you replace.
OK.
But just on every axis, manipulating the list
and taking the page you accessed to bring it
at the head of the list is very expensive.
Multiple memory accesses.
So you do not want to do that.
So next, we are going to talk about some approximations
of list recently used.
And one of such approximations,
the first one we are going to start with,
is a clock algorithm.
OK.
So and we'll have some examples.
So this is imagine that all pages are arranged in a ring.
And you have a clock, right?
A clock hand, which advanced one by one.
And you look at every page.
And when you need to evict a page,
this clock hand will move to the next page.
And you check for pages which are not used recently.
And then you also mark the pages which are used recently.
Right?
And with all this approximation, the way you approximate,
you still replace an old page, but not the oldest page.
OK.
And here how things are working.
So remember that you have a use bit, right?
Or access bit.
So the use bit in the PTE.
PTE is a page table entry for each page, right?
If you remember.
And that bit, whenever you access a page, is set to zero.
Right?
So sorry, whenever you access a page,
you set it to one.
OK?
So if I see a one, this means that the page was used.
Now, this clock is looking at the page.
And if you see it's on one, it's resetting it to zero.
OK?
If it sees a zero, then it's replacing that page.
Because this means that the page hasn't been accessed in a while.
Right?
If it's a one, this means that it was accessed recently.
So you give a chance, second chance, to that page.
OK?
And let's see how it works.
So here I am showing an example.
And I have with all these rectangles, obviously, there are pages.
Or sorry, or frames.
The one with the dashed rectangles represent three frames.
There is nothing there.
And then for these pages, for a few pages, I also put the value of the use bit.
So you have 1, 1, 0, 1.
And this is now, I want to bring a page from the disk.
So I want to find the page I'm going to replace.
OK?
So when I'm going to go through this, you know, the hand is going to move.
Now, remember this first page, the use bit was 1.
OK?
So I'm going to reset it to zero because use one meant that it was accessed recently.
Then I'm going to the next page.
And it's again, the use bit was 1.
I'm resetting it.
I'm setting it to zero.
And finally, now this next page, the use bit was zero.
OK?
And because the use bit is zero, this means that the page hasn't been accessed in a while.
At least it wasn't accessed since the last time the hand visited that page.
So we are going to replace this page.
If the page was written, since it was modified, you save it on the disk first.
And then you load the page and update the PT.
By the way, when you evict the page, you also invalidate the PT of that page and invalidate
the TLB entry of that page.
OK?
And now I just load it.
I'm going to access it.
So the use bit is 1.
And now assume that in the meantime, for instance, when I access this page here, which has a bit
set, which had the use bit set to zero, when the hand visited the last time, I am going
to set up the use bit to 1 again because it was accessed.
And now finally, say that we have another page fault.
And I am going to go to the next page.
It has use bit was 1.
Now I'm going to set up to zero and then I'm going to go to the next page.
And that frame, it's actually a frame.
It's an empty frame.
OK?
And I'm just going to load the page and I'm going to set up to one.
I'm going to initialize it PT and so forth.
OK?
Typically, and this is a little generalized here a little bit, you only the free frames
are in a different list.
OK?
I put it here to have a global example, but typically frames are in different lists just
for you to, you know, to keep in mind.
So I'm stopping here.
And any questions?
So whenever a page is accessed, the use bit is set to 1.
Whenever a hand visit the page, because there was a page fault, if the use bit was 1, you
set it to zero.
If the use bit is zero, you have the page and bring the new page in.
Let me ask you this question.
Say the hand is moving very fast.
What does it mean?
Is that good?
Is it bad?
Yes, Gilbert and Allison.
Yes, it's bad because this means that a lot of page faults.
Right.
And if it's moving slowly, there are very few page faults.
OK?
Good.
The other thing is not is that if all the bits are set to 1,
they're still OK because the handle move and while moving is going to set up each bit of
each page to zero.
So when you come back, when it comes back after one rotation, it's going to find a page
with a use bit of zero that was a page whose hand set the bit to zero first time.
So Allison, it's a question here actually about the hand, whether it's moving fast, it's bad.
If you say that might just mean that we have all our pages being used and so that hand has
to step over a lot of in use pages.
So this can happen, but then it will still be, you know, it's again, there are two reasons
the hand is going to move fast.
One absolutely is because of page faults.
If there are no page faults, the hand will not move.
The other reason it's obviously because you need to step over a lot of pages which are
used, right?
And there used to be the set.
OK, and that can be the case, but it's also unlikely because if you assume
that will happen only if all the pages are very uniformly accessed, which is not the
case, right?
Because you have to have all the pages being uniform accessed, right?
Since the last time the hand visited them in order to be a one.
And if you have locality that it's unlikely to happen.
But it's a good question.
A good point.
Yeah, so this I discussed what if hand was moving slowly, good sign or bad sign.
This is not many pages, false or fine page quickly.
What if hand is moving quickly, lots of page faults or lots of reference bit set, right?
We discussed both of them, but this is what it is, right?
It's like you have a lot of reference bit sets only if you have, you know, it's pretty
uniform memory access.
So one way to view the clock algorithms is that you group the pages into two groups,
one which you're accessed recently or one or accessed longer, you know, longer time
in the past.
And then obviously you are going to pick one from the ones which you accessed longer in
the past.
Right.
So an obvious question, because you think about these two groups, you have these two
groups is why not actually partition it and instead of having this kind of clock algorithm,
just have two groups.
OK, and we are going to talk about that.
But before that, let's look a lot about a version of the clock algorithm.
We generalize it clock algorithms and it's n chance version, right?
And with n chance, think about right now you are going to evict a page, right?
You give only, so to speak, one chance because you set the bit once the hand sets a use bit
of a page to zero is going to evict it the next time.
Unless the page wasn't accessed in the meantime.
So another way is to have more than one bit, and this is about n chance algorithms.
So now the OS keeps a counter per page, which is a number of sweeps, a number of times it
was visited while the page was not accessed.
On page fault, the OS checks the use bit and if it's one, you clear it.
Right, like before, is zero.
And you also initialize, you clear what is this sweep counter.
And if it's zero, you just increment the counter and only if the counter is equal to n, you
replace the page.
Right.
So this means that the page has n chances.
So it can be visited by the hand n times.
Before being evicted.
Of course, here I am talking about the page which is not accessed.
While this n sweeps happen.
Okay.
So obviously one question is how do you pick n?
What happens if n is very large?
If n is very large, you can actually better approximate ALERU.
Say n is 1000, that is really good approximation.
What is the problem with picking a large n zone?
Why wouldn't you pick a larger?
Is less efficient?
Yes, Danny.
Why is less efficient?
Yes.
Sweeping will take a lot of rotation, right?
Because think about, you know.
You need to go, you need to visit a page n times, so n sweeps before you can evict it.
Okay, so if there are a lot of pages, then this will take a long time.
It's exactly so it's not.
efficient. Takes a long time to find free pages. What about modified or dirty pages?
Obviously, it takes extra overhead like we saw in the previous example to replace a dirty page,
right? Dirty page meaning that was modified since when it was brought in memory, right?
Because you need to write it to the disk. So these algorithms had something, some improvement here.
And basically, before a page counter gets to the end, you write it back to the disk. So if
you are going next time to decide to replace that page, it was already written to the disk.
So for instance, one approach is for the clean pages to use n is equal to 1, which is basically
the original clock algorithm. But for the dirty pages, use n equal to 2. And for n equal to 1,
you write it back. So if you look at these algorithms now, right, if it's a page, it's clean,
right? It has not modified. If the counter is 1, you replace it.
If it's a dirty page, then when the counter reaches 1, you don't replace it.
You just write it back to the disk. And when the counter is 2, you replace it.
OK? So this means that hopefully the next time when you come, by the time you decide
for this, you either are going to find a page which is clean. So you don't need to write to
the disk. So you pick that to replace it. Or in the worst case, you come back to the page,
you decided to write back. But by that time, hopefully it's clean. So then the overhead
is always going to be low. Any questions? OK. So this again is a PTE. And this is
the page table entry. And again, these are the bits which are in the PTE. So we have a bit which
is present or valid. This means, if you remember, whether specify whether the page is in the memory
or not. If p is 0, then it's invalid. So it's a page fault. The page should be on the disk.
It's a writable. This is about its access control. This is about whether the page,
you can write to the page or not. Like for instance, if the pages which contains the code,
they are not writable. Right? Because the code is immutable, or it should be immutable.
Then it's access bit or use bit. We talk quite a bit about it. This was what is used in the
clock algorithm. And it's a dirty bit, right? Modified, which is used by any cache replacement,
sorry, by any page replacement algorithms. Because if the page is dirty or is modified,
you need to write it back to the disk. OK? So this is what kind of you have. And here,
OK. So again, just to summarize for the clock algorithms, like the way,
you know, as we discuss so far, we use the use bit and the dirty bit.
But this being said, the p and w are almost always used. They are going to be used by the
operating system, obviously. So now, so here is some interesting questions. So
again, p and w, they are a must in general, right? Because it's protection, w is protection, and p,
you need to know whether the page is in memory or not. You cannot go around those.
So now the question is about these other bits, right? And the question is that, are they
really necessary to implement, for instance, the clock algorithm?
And. Yes, that's great, Harrison. You can use a valid bit and always
set it to invalid to force a fault on each axis. It's super slow, though. Yes, that's correct.
So the trick here is that if you do not have these bits in the hardware, in these registers,
what you can do, you can maintain this bit in software.
And now you need to find a way to modify, to look at these bits and modify them.
And Allison is correct about how you can do it and hear how you can do it in more details.
You can do it also for for now, let's assume we can do it using the read only bit.
OK, so basically when you. We are talking about modify bit, so basically what you have here
is that when you read a page, you mark it read only. No matter whether it's a day,
contain data or code. OK. So and then when. OK, so all of them are read only and then when.
You are going to access it and you want to write it. Then you are going to have an exception.
Right, because you want to write a page which is read only. So it's a trap in the operating system.
OK. And in the operating system, in the software, you maintain this modify bit.
Of course, first time when you bring the page in, you make and you make it read only,
you set this modify bit to zero. When you write it, you get an exception like we discussed.
Trap the operating system. The operating system is going to make the page read right and set the
modified bit one. Right again, modified bit is in software. Whenever the page is written back to the
disk. Right, you reset the modified bit to zero because now it's not is what you have in memory
is exactly what you have on the disk and you mark again read only. OK. So that's pretty cool.
Now, it turns out that actually you don't even need the use bit. Right. And
like again, in this case, if you don't use you have the use bit in the PTE,
you have to keep it in software. So the kernel is to keep it. Right.
And the way you do it now, you can mark all pages as invalid, even if they are in memory. OK.
And then you set the use bit and modify bits, which are again in software, you set up to zero.
You bring a page in. And even if again, now the page is memory, you still do not you still
keep the invalid bit being set for that page. However, in the software, you keep in mind
that you brought in the page and you set up the base for use and modified to zero for that page.
So now any read or write to this invalid page will trap to operating system. OK,
now the operating system then is going to set the use bit to one because you access it.
Right. And if it's a read, you are going to only if it's a read, you are going to set the page
to read only like before to catch the future writes. If write, you also set the modified
bit to one and you mark the page are writable. OK. And when the clock passes and the use bit is zero,
you can again mark the page when the clock can passes, you reset the bit to zero,
use bit to zero and mark the page again as being invalid. OK. Sorry.
So. The modified bit is not obviously you are not going to. You are not going to
write that bit, you are not going to modify the bit, the modified bit,
unless the page is written back on the disk. OK.
Any questions?
So it's very cool. So basically, the TLDR here is that you can get away
by not storing the modified and used by not having the modified and use bits in the
page table entry. And because you don't have that, you need to have them somewhere.
So you are going to keep them in kernel. But now you need to modify and need to look at those bits.
So you need to go to the kernel to do that. In order to go to the kernel, you need to force
that trap to the kernel and the way you do, you force that trap using the other bits like
invalid bits or write only bit or read write bits or writable bit in order to force that trap.
So you force, you are going to give the control to the operating system to handle
the modified and used bits.
Make sense?
OK. So now let's talk about the second chance list algorithm. So it's a variation.
Let's put it as another approximation of all area. And it was implemented in BACs,
VMS. You do not know about that. You haven't seen it probably. Maybe you're only in the museum.
But this is a very popular computer. It was called mini computer. And before the personal computers.
Right. So it was in 70s, 80s. Right. But it was VACs was a very, very influential computer.
And in this case, you have two lists. You divide it into lists.
And the first list is direct mapped pages and they are all marked read write. And
you keep FIFO. Why FIFO? FIFO is very fast. Right. With FIFO is very simple. Right. You
when you bring a page in memory, you put it at the end of the list when you. Well, you
sorry, you can put it you put it ahead of the list when you remove a page, you remove from
the end of the list. Right. Very simple. And while things while things in this list are
accessed, you don't do anything. Right. But then you have a second chance list and they
are marked invalid. And this is Alerio implements Alerio. OK, so this is how you split the memory.
Directly mapped page and the second chance list pages. OK, so let's see how it works.
So if you access a page in this. You know, one of these green pages, they are also called
active list, right? Then you access it. No problem. If you don't access a page which
is an active list, you are going to have a page fault. And on the page fault, always
you are moving the page from the end of the active list to front of the second chance
list and mark it is invalid. Right. This is five. OK. And then. If the pages is a second
chance list. You move that page to the front of the active list and you mark it read right,
because all the pages in the activist are read right. Now, if the page you are looking for
is not in the second chance list. OK. You page it directly in the active list,
as a front of the activist, you mark it as a read right and you page out a victim from
second chance list. I'll let you using gallery. OK, so let's take a step back and see what
happens here. So what happens here and why we do this, it's because we, you know, I'll
let you it's expensive to implement and obviously. Writing back to the disk and, you know, reading
from the disk a page is also expensive. OK, so therefore, what we say, well, let's take
a bunch of pages from memory and organize them in a five. Five is super efficient, very
simple to implement. But the problem is five, obviously, is that they do see and it's not
pretty good in limiting the number of page faults. And now the second thing comes, I say,
OK, I have page faults with FIFO, I know that I'm going to have a lot of page faults, but
let's make them cheap. So the way you make them cheap is that with the second chance
list and because you hope that a lot of times the page you are looking at is still in memory,
is this in the second chance list. OK, so that's the key. And for the second chance
list, you do LRU. You can afford to do LRU because anyway, in order to, you experience
a page fault to get the page from the second chance list.
So increase the number of page faults because you have FIFO and you are using only a subset
of frames in this active list. But you reduce the overhead of the page faults because many
times a page fault will page in a list of a page which is already in memory. Make sense?
OK. Now, the interesting thing to notice here and like, for instance, what happens if the
second chance list is zero and all the memory frames are allocated to the active page, active
list, then you have FIFO. That's the regulation policy. What if active list is zero, right?
And you allocate everything to the second chance list. Then you have LRU, but it's very
expensive. This is what it says. But because you are going to page fault on every page
reference. So you pick an intermediate value, obviously, in terms of how many frames you
are going to have in the active list. And again, this will reduce the number of disk
accesses because fundamentally, if you look from the point of view of the entire memory
now, you use LRU, not an approximation of the real approximation of LRU. So you are
very efficient in terms of the number of disk accesses. But you are going to increase the
number of context switching. You are increasing the number of page faults.
So any question?
And again, a base translation will see that you can adapt to any kind of access to program,
access or any access patterns of the programs. So one interesting tidbit here was that when
VAX was originally designed, the use bit was not part of the PTE. And the story is that Stryker,
the architect, actually went to the software people and asked them.
them.
people say, oh, no, we don't need it. So they didn't implement it. Of course. Eventually,
when they implemented the cash replacement policy, they needed it. And they always use it,
what they did about it, of course, because it doesn't in the PDE, they have to keep it in
software. So they need to make sure that we get a trap to the operating system, to the kernel in
order to modify the bit, like we've seen in the previous few slides. And obviously, he was also,
not obviously, but he was also blamed for this omission. So don't trust the operating OS people.
That's kind of the moral of the story here. The other things which we didn't, we alluded,
but we haven't discussed so far. It's in general, even with the algorithm, with all these algorithms,
even with the clock algorithms, in practice, you do have, you maintain also a free list.
And the free list, it's a list of frames which are available, you can allocate,
they are not allocated yet. And so therefore, if you initially, and the way you do that,
you use it again as a sort of cache. For instance, with the clock algorithm, when you are going to
evict the page, you are going to write this page to the free list instead of writing it directly
to the disk. And then in the background, there is a daemon, which is going to look at the free list
and to look at the pages, which are dirty in the free list, and then write these pages to the disk.
So the advantage of this is that it's again, it's like when I need to replace a page,
even if the page was modified, I don't need to wait for it to be written to the disk,
because it's going to be written quickly, just move in another list in memory.
Okay. So this is very similar with the VAX, the second chance list to just learn about.
Any questions?
Obviously, this is this high level, right? It's the high level pictures.
There are many details we haven't discussed. So let's discuss a few of them.
Remember that when you are going to evict the page, you need to invalidate these PDEs,
because the next time when you are going to access that page, you need to bring this page
in memory. So you need to get the kernel, do that for you. So it has to be a trap.
And you need, so then, therefore, you need to keep the reverse mapping, so that when I am going
to evict the page, I need to know which is its PDE to invalidate. And the same is true also for the
TLB. Okay. So how do you do that? And there are many ways to do it. You can keep a link list of
page entries. And actually, in some sense, again, there are many software solutions here. But in
some sense, the thing when it gets complicated, it's when you have shared pages across multiple
processes, right? Because then remember, each process has its own virtual address space.
And each process has its own page table. So therefore, if a page is shared by two processes,
then like we've seen in the last lecture, you are going to have two entries, two PDE,
two page tables entries, right, in the page table of the two processes pointing to the same page.
So you need to invalidate the two PDEs when you evict that page. Okay. So you need to find both
of those, right? So just keeping the simple reverse mapping is not enough. And one way to
address this problem is like, you can see on this slide, is basically you can have a list,
right, of page table entries for each page. So if there are two or four, say four processes,
we share the same page. For that, then for that, associated with that page, you have a linked list
of the four PDEs of these processes who access that page. Okay. So now you go back to this list
and you validate everything which is in the list. And there are other solutions here. Okay.
Any questions? Okay. Now let's switch gears. And now we are done with, in some sense, with this
kind of low level page replacement policies. And now we are talking about how the memory will be
allocated across processes. But before then, any questions? So memory is a resource. It's very much
like the CPU, right? And we are talking about all these policies or scheduling policies, page
replacement policies, because the resources are oversubscribed. If the resource is not over
subscribed, we don't need to do anything. We have enough for everyone. Right? And we've seen all
these scheduling algorithms about how to allocate the CPU to across multiple processes, threads,
in a fair manner, whatever. And you can imagine we have the same problems to solve. We have the
same problems to solve in the case of the memory as well. Right? And the same questions, right?
If you have multiple processes competing for the physical memory, how you are going to allocate
the memory across processes? You are going to allocate fairly, right? The same number of pages.
Also, we need to keep in mind that each process needs a minimum number of pages to work.
It cannot work without having a certain number of pages in memory. Okay.
So like for instance, this is one case, this is IBM 370, which for one instruction,
you can need up to six pages to be in memory. And this was an instruction to move a bunch of bytes
from one location to another. First instruction is six bytes. So my span two pages.
Okay. And then you can have the region spanning the source region from where you want to copy
can span two pages. And the destination where you want to copy that data also can span two pages.
So six pages in total. Right? And the other thing is again, but here is the only the difference,
and you have to appreciate that the difference between the CPU and memory is that with CPU
actually it's more fungible. The CPU is more fungible. It's memoryless in some sense. It's
like, I am going to decide when to process, to schedule. I'm going to schedule it. And every
time slot, I'm going to pick another process. Right? So every time slot, when I say it's
stateless is that because every time quanta, I can pick another process to schedule. But here,
I am going to start the decision is not for which process to bring a page in. It's already the
memory is full with pages from all the processes. I have to decide which page to evict. Right?
Which is more difficult. And of course, eviction policy can be global, meaning that when I'm going
to pick a page to evict, I'm going to look at all across all the processes, all the pages in memory.
Or another way to think about it can be local. When I'm going to decide which page to evict,
I'm going to look only across the pages of the process, which cause a page fault. Right?
So I'm going to bring a page from the disk for the new or for a process. And I'm going to evict
a page from that the same process. Right? So here are a few policies which are kind of obvious.
Equal allocation. One way to say it is to be super fair, you just divide statically the memory across
processes. You have five processes, you have 100 frames, then each process gets 20 frames, period.
Right? Or you can have a proportional allocation, also fixed scheme, in which you have a weight and
you are going to allocate the memory according to that weight. Now, what is the problem with
a fixed allocation? Can someone tell me what is the problem with these fixed allocations?
Yep, these are very good questions. Very good answers, Michael and Alison. So one problem is
that if a process requires less than its allocation, then memory is wasted. The other thing is that
what happens when a new process is created? Okay, then you need to redistribute all these pages
across the processes. Then it's a priority allocation. You can use a priority and you can
assign priority to each process. You can use the same priority which are used for scheduling.
And then when you need to decide which page to evict, you are going to evict a page
from the process with a lower priority. Right? Or you can use any adaptive schemes.
Another way to think it is about frequency allocation. So basically here you think about
I want everyone to kind of get the same performance and the performance is dictated by
the frequency of the page faults. So I want kind of to equalize the page faults that each process
experience a frequency. Right? So in this particular case, you are going to look, you can
look at, you know, to have some thresholds. And if a process, the number of frequency of the page
faults is lower than this lower bound, then you are going to evict pages from this process. You
are going to reduce the number of pages allocated to this process. If the number of page faults for
the process exceed another threshold, then you have too many page faults. You are going to
allocate more pages to this process. Okay? So that's what you can do.
But still, no matter what you are talking about here, there can be still cases in which you don't
have enough memory. And when you don't have enough memories, what happens is kind of trashing.
And trashing, you can actually identify that in a simpler way, you see a lot of I/O activity and the
CPU very little utilization because trashing meaning that you have a very high number of page
faults. So the program or the, you know, the processes spend most of their time page faulting
than doing useful work. And in that case, no one is making progress. So what is the solution here?
Right? By the way, how do you take the trashing? It's very simple, right? It's like I mentioned
to you, right? It's like you have a lot of I/O activity and the CPU utilization is basically zero.
Right? So what you can do here? No one is making progress. So what you can do?
Well, one simple solution you can do is to
yes, suspend one process or kill a process.
Very good. So we went over this last time and you remember that, you know, we have a similar plot
here and this represent the access pattern of a program, of a process over time. On the y-axis,
you have the page number on the x-axis, you have the time and you have a dot at every position
where you have an access to a particular page, you know, offset at a particular time.
Right? So that's kind of what you have here. Okay. And it's again, when the program executes,
you are going to at different times, you are going to access different location in memory.
And the group of pages which are accessed together at a given time, they are called working set.
Right? And the working set defines a minimum number of pages that a process have to have
in memory in order to work well. So to not spend too much time in page folding.
Okay. So therefore, this means that if you do not have enough space in memory to accommodate
the working sets of all the active processes, then you have a problem. So the solution like
we discussed is to swap out a process. Now, how you define the working set? When you
design a group of pages access at the same time, we need to define the same time. And typically,
this is a time interval. So basically, look at the current time and you are looking in the past
for some time interval about to all the active all the pages which are accessed during that interval.
And this is what you call the working set. Okay. And obviously about how long is the interval,
which is also, you know, is also called working set window is that, you know, it's a good question,
but you need to take a good, you know, because if it's too long, then it encompasses all the pages
ever accessed by the program. Right. So that's not good. If it's too little, it's going to encompass
only the most recent pages and you are going to miss maybe as many other pages that should be
accessed, you know, in a very, you know, very in the near future. Right. So you miss the locality.
Okay. But anyway, so once you set up this window, now you can define the working set. And then the
simple thing is that the sum of the working set of all programs, you let's say is defined by D.
And if D is greater than the memory size, you have trashing. Okay. And if D is less than the
memory size, you are fine. Okay. And this is the last slide I'm going to make about like we
discussed, you remember that when we discussed about this page replacement policies and about
these examples, always we are going to start with this compulsory misses. Right. And obviously
compulsory misses are unavoidable in some sense, but the question, can you do it better? And the
answer, yes, you can do it better. Like for instance, for clustering the pages and when a
page falls, you do not drink only one page in memory. You are bringing a set of pages,
these consecutive pages, because if you assume locality, you assume that if you access say
instructions in the current page, you are also as likely to access instruction in the next page.
So you are more ties the cost of page faults by bringing more pages in memory. Right. And the same
things about the working set. If you know kind of the working set and you have some knowledge
about the locality, you can try to, for instance, when you swap a process on the disk,
you swap its working set and when you bring the process in, you bring its working set,
all the pages in the working set. So we are going to stop here and thank you very much. And let me
know if you have any other questions.