Hello, everyone. So welcome to the 18th lecture of CS162 2021. So today we are going to talk
about general input output. And just to summarize, so far we have studied abstractions, the API
which is provided by the operating system to the application to run a process. We talk
quite a bit about the virtual memory, demand paging, how to manage the physical memory,
and about virtualization. And we also talk about synchronization and scheduling. Okay?
So and how to manage the CPU resources and how to synchronize to have multiple processes
and multiple threads, accessing the same resources and how they can cooperate in order to implement
some more complex functionality. Okay? So now one thing we haven't talked as much so far is about
input and output. And obviously the input output is a fundamental part of any computer system,
because that's why how we interact with the computers through some input output devices
like keyboards, mouse, cameras, and things like that. And also this is how the computer itself
interact with the environment and with us, displaying information on the screen,
printing information, and other things like that. Right? Now the biggest problem, and this is
what also makes this also this lecture a little bit maybe harder, is that
it's there are a huge variety of this input output devices.
Right? Actually, if you think about others, like memory, memory is pretty simple. It's an array
of addressable bytes. Right? That's pretty much what it is. If you think about the CPUs and so
forth, from our perspective, it's a resource which we want to probably time slice in time,
time slice, so then we can visualize it. So we created this illusion that every process has
access to its own machine, virtual machine. Right? But if you look about input output
devices, this is a huge variety. And not only in terms of the sizes, not only in terms of the speed
they operate at, you can have networking, which is hundreds of gigabytes per second versus keyboard,
which is one character per whatever second. But also in terms of reliability, in some cases,
you can lose information like packets on the network can be lost. So you need to recover.
So in all aspects in low dimension, you have a huge variety. And yet the operating system
needs to cope with this variety in a reasonable way. Right? You don't want to be exposed.
And what that means, you don't want your program, when you are developing your program, to think
about each of these input devices in a different way. Right? And this is the role of the operating
system. Again, despite this huge variety to provide us with an interface, which is reasonable,
which is reasonable, you know, scoped, and you can make sense of it. And you don't need to,
you know, think about different concepts or you are going to operate on different IOD devices.
Okay. And this is a, if you remember, this is a figure we have shown a few times in the past.
And here this protection boundary switches down here, it's also abstracts away
this input output devices.
Okay. So today we are going to talk about how you are going to get the impact, you know,
how you are going to get this kind of input from these devices. And eventually,
where do you need to get this input? This input from these devices, you need to put in memory.
Right? Because why? Because your program, in order to operate to the input,
it has to find the input in memory because the program operates only on data in memory.
Right. And that's pretty much it. Now, this is one example, and this is an old example,
many years back. And this is from Sun Enterprise. Again, Sun, it was a big company of workstations
and it was acquired many years back by Oracle. But in the heyday, this was a great company.
And if you think about the devices and only looking in terms of the speed,
you have keyboards, like I mentioned, and the system bus, the system bus, it's learning the
system bus on the machine, which connects different devices, which are on the same enclosure on the
machine, like for instance, this storage and things like that. There are differences,
it's two orders of magnitude. So you need to provide interfaces which can cope with such a huge
variation in the speed. Okay.
So this means that, and you need to have something which works very well
when you have high throughput. So the overhead for transfer per byte should be very low. At the
same time, if it's something very slow, you shouldn't just waste time waiting for the slow
devices. It's like if something happens one per second, you cannot wait once for the entire second
to get one character. Okay. This is another way to look about, and this is to put everything in
one picture about what we learned so far and what we are going to learn today. Right on the left
hand side, you have the processor and the processor obviously has the CPU, but in addition to CPU has
some storage, right? And the storage comes into registers, then a bunch of caches, L1 and L2 cache,
which are the server core. And then you have an L3 cache and the L3 cache typically shared
across multiple cores. And then you have memory and secondary storage and maybe another tertiary
storage and so forth. And the difference between this kind of storage hierarchy, it's obviously
like going from registers all the way from this to disk storage. You have at each level, it's much
larger capacity, but also higher life latency. Right? So we learn about that. And we learn that
about caching, we learned about demand paging and so forth. And in addition to that, here on the top
with the yellow, you have all these devices, which again, needs to be available, the data which is
read from these devices to be available to processor. And then for the processor to write
data to these devices, like to storage, to screen for you to see an image. And typically all these
devices are, they have a controller and this controller is what the name implies, controls
these devices because these devices are different. In some sense, this yellow box provides this
magical interface, which is reasonably uniform across all the devices to the processor and to
the programmer. But in the back is doing this heavy lifting to uniformize these APIs by dealing
with such a heterogeneous set of devices. Okay. So now let's look a little bit into more details
to see how things are on a computer. Right. And this is what you have on your computer. This is
actually on your laptop or iPad. At some level, this is what you have. Okay. And you have processors,
obviously, and you may have other, you may have GPUs, you may have a network card here.
Of course, you have some storage devices, you may have big speakers, internal and external speakers,
you may have a printer, of course, keyboards, you have the monitor, and many more. Right. So again,
you need to take all this information from these devices to get into process, and then to write
back information at least to some devices, some of these devices, of course, you don't need to
write back information to the keyboard, keyboard is only an input device. As a printer, it's only
an output device. And how do you connect them? Right. So first of all, how you wire them.
So it turns out that the way you wire them is through this bus, you have a bus, right? So
everything goes to a bus, everything, including actually even the memory on the machine. And the
data is sent through this bus. Okay. And this is how you get the data into the processor. This is
how you get the data out of the processors through one bus. And more precisely, what is a bus?
It represents the set of specifications. It specifies what are the wires, how many wires
they have, it has, and how you connect to it. And then on top of that, it has to provide an API.
Read, write, how do you read and write from this bus? And you also have how you are going to
address a particular device. And for the particular device, you also have not only data reading,
reading data, but you have also control data, right? Like for instance, for a disk, like you'll
see, you need to tell the disk where a particular block is on the disk to read or to write.
This is happening through the control lines, right? And the controller, like you see the
yellow box, is going to decide and instruct using the control line, a device, what to do,
and where to get the data from or to write the data to. And then there is also the protocol. You
have multiple devices which are going to send the data on the same bus. So what do you need to do?
Right? Not all of them can send the data at the same time, right? In general, you have only one
device being able to send data on the bus at a given time. So this means that you need to
arbitrate. If more than one device wants to send the data on the bus at the same time,
then you need to arbitrate who is going to be allowed to send and who is going to wait.
Okay. And of course, the devices here are, again, remember about they are very different in speed.
The devices which are close to the processor, like memory, things like that, they are very,
very fast. The ones which are very remote, like are much slower, like say, you know,
keyboard or printer. So now why a bus? This is very important. It may seem that this is obvious.
Of course, it's a bus, right? But think about what is the alternative. So an obvious alternative here,
it will be to connect every device to the processor, right? And if the two devices have
to communicate among themselves, you're also going to connect between them, right? The problem is that
then you are going to have, in the worst case, you have n devices and you can have, you know,
n square connection. You don't want that. It's very complicated. Okay? So that's why what you
want, you have this bus and everyone is connected to the bus and then it's beautiful. Then you
multiplex the bus in time. But the problem is that if you multiplex in time, then it may be
very inefficient because remember all these devices have very, very different speeds.
So, you know, like for instance, if I'm going the keyboard, right, it's like a key, right? You
click a key and it takes a gain. It's like every one second. It's like, it's very inefficient way
of that bus, right? Because in the same time, you may send if, you know, from memory, you can send
hundreds of gigabits per second, which means, you know, a few tens of gigabytes per second. Okay?
So it's very inefficient, right? You don't, you know, if you have slow devices,
very inefficient for very fast devices. Okay. And so that's one of the big problems.
Advantage against simplicity, everyone connects to it. The standard bus is today's,
is PCI is called Peripheral Component Interconnect. And it started as a parallel bus. Parallel bus,
meaning that at one device at a time is going to use to be able to send data and it can send data
in parallel. If he sends, you know, and the weights of the bus represents how many bits you can send
in parallel. So for instance, if you have 128 bits, this means that you are going to be able to
send in one clock cycle, 128 bits, right? And you multiply this, this, this bus like we discussed,
but now the problem, if it's a slow device, then you are going to, you know, use, and also it
doesn't have, it sends only eight bits while the bus is 128 bits. You are going to waste on 20
bits while this device is alone using the bus for sending just eight bits. Okay. So I'm going to,
to stop here. Any questions about so far? Okay. So this is a little bit again, it's like very
descriptive, a lot of heterogeneity. So maybe a little bit boring, but it will, it will change.
So now you may have heard about PCI express bus. So what is the problem is that it's parallel.
This is great. You know, it's simple, but only one device can use at the same time. And if it's
a slow device, you waste so much time for the fast devices. So PCI express is pretty smart.
So it's no longer, no longer parallel bus. You still have multiple lines,
but they are serial channels. And you can, now a device can choose how many lines it's going to send.
Do you use to send? Right? So for instance, if you have a very slow device, like your keyboard,
right, you can use to send everything on one line, right? And you leave all the other lines for
others, like memory, right access to memory or the storage. Okay. So this allows the slow devices
to share the PCI bus with fast devices in an efficient way. And again, the beauty of this,
of Linux and Unix behind it, before it was that, you know, the ability to support all of these,
you know, not only to migrate from PCI to PCI express, but again, to provide a pretty uniform
interface across all these devices. Okay. And also the API itself remains the same,
most pretty much the same. And this is quite amazing, right? If you think about it,
because Unix, when it was designed, Unix, I mean, a lot of
things you have today, maybe they are not available then. You don't, you didn't have
GPUs for instance. I'm sure you didn't have a lot of this kind of game, you know, game inputs,
devices, right? And many other things, right? So despite that, you started to connect things
to the computer, which are not envisioned when people designed the operating system in the first
place. The operating system was still being able to preserve the same API. Of course, you need to
implement controllers or drivers, which are going to provide, you know, to support these devices
and provide the same kind of abstraction like before, right? We'll talk more about that. Okay.
Anyway, here is an example of the PCI architecture. Today, you have a PCI number zero,
PCI number zero here. And this is very fast one. This is connected to the CPU
and the CPU is also having a memory bus to the RAM. Then there is a PCI bridge here.
You have another PCI bus. This PCI bus is a little...
bit typically slower. And this connects the storage devices, for instance, a scanner,
and all the webcam, mouse and keyboard. And then you have another bridge here from PCI
to ESA. So ISI, it was an older bus standard. So you may still have devices, for instance,
hard disk drives, which support, which implements this standard and connect to this ISI bus.
And this is a bridge, so then you can use these devices on PCI architecture.
So here, let's go into a little bit more detail. So how does a processor talk to all these
devices? So here is a CPU and you have the memory and you have a memory bus here. And
now you have, this is connected through a bus adapter to get data from this device controller.
Right, remember, each device has a controller. And the device, you send the instructions
about what data to get or to write. And the controller is talking with the device to get
what the program asks for. Now, within a device controller, a device controller is quite complicated.
Actually many device controllers, they have their own processor. So it's like their own
computer, right? They have ARM processor and so forth to implement the program, which is
going to control that device. Of course, we have a bus interface to send the data in and
out to connect to the other buses in the system. And it has a memory, you can, for instance,
for doing, for caching data. For instance, when you send data to the printer, you can
assume that it's not like you send one byte is printed, you send one byte is printed.
No, you send a lot, almost the entire file, or you can send the entire file, which is
kind of stored, that is part of it in local memory, and then it's printed from there.
And then this is very important. You have a set of registers here, which are, these
are the registers to which they are used to interact with this controller. They are used
to tell the controller what to do, right? And, you know, read, write, or configure,
to configure the controller in a particular way. It's also to get the status of the controller.
The status of the controller can be busy, right? The printer is busy, right? Showing
the status, not sorry, this is the status of the device controlled by the controller.
Okay, another important thing, if you remember, we have this kind of interrupts, right? You
remember about the interrupts? And one of the main issues of interrupt is to react when
something happens in the external world. And one of the main use cases there, it's about
when you have some data to get from a device, from the network, for instance, or when some
device needs attention, right? So that's what the interrupt controller and the controller
is going to raise some interrupts. And the interrupts are, if you remember, the operating
system, depending on the interrupt, is going to have an interrupt handler, which is going
to handle that interrupt, right? The network card has, and another controller has new data,
is going to interrupt, to raise an interrupt, the OS is going to handle that interrupt,
and is going to read the data from the controller. Okay. Now, how do I interact? How do I program
these controllers? There are two ways. Port mapped IO, in and out instructions. So basically
here for the Intel architecture in particular, you have say out 0x21. So this is an address.
This is an IO. So each IO has its own address. Each IO device has its own address. And basically
out 0x21, AL means that the content of register AL is a register. So the content of that register
will be written on that output, at that address, to that output, will be written to that output.
And you have the corresponding in and from a particular port address. And then the data
from that port is going to be written in register AL, for instance. Okay. So you have special
instructions here, right? And special addresses for these devices. On the other hand, you
can have memory mapped IO. And this is pretty cool. You basically reserve your, you configure
some addresses in the memory, in the RAM. Okay. And this being are connected to these
input output devices. Okay. And then the only thing you do, you use load and store, because
it's memory. Load means if I am going to put the data there at that particular address,
that data is going to be sent to the corresponding device. Right? If I get, if I read the data
from that, from a particular address, which is memory mapped address, then I'm going to
read data from the corresponding device. Make sense? This is an example about memory mapped,
right? And this is really used for graphics. Right? So typically, typically here, what
you have is that, you know, like your screen is a bitmap. Right? You know that, right?
So the screen, the control of a screen, sees the same memory, you know, have a region,
you devote a region of your RAM, you devote to that, to the screen. And when you are going,
and then you, when you are going to modify this memory, see how, what you modify, you
see immediately on the screen. Right? And so, so from here, display memory is from this
address 800, whatever, 10,000 to 800, 8,000, whatever, F000, this is a display memory.
In addition to that, you may have also a command queue, because you may have, you can provide
some commands to the display, you know, for instance, because you may have, like, higher
level abstractions, rather than just writing and reading, writing individuals in the individual
bits, like, for instance, generating triangles, right, you are going to basically command,
give a command to the controller, the controller, which is a graphic card is going to, to generate
this kind of, say, triangles to create much faster, to render much faster, some, you know,
impressive, you know, objects. Okay. So this is, this is one thing. So again, that in summary
from in summary here, in this is very simple example, you are going to have a region on
the RAM, which is seen both by processor, and is seen by both and also by the controller,
the video controller, right. And when you write, when the processor writes to this address,
to this memory, you see it on the screen. So, any questions? Now, it turns out that
today with this, everyone knows about GPUs, you know, graphical processing units, and
the GPUs, they have actually their own memory. So you don't have the sharing. And the reason
for that, because the memory thing on the because the memory is a GPU, if the memory
is on the GPU, that is much, much faster. So you can, you know, render much faster,
much quicker. That's one of the reasons. This is for you to know. And of course, you can
protect this memory regions using address translation like we know. Now, here is an
interesting thing. So far, we saw it, we told, I told you how it's, you know, that you have
this processor, and you have all these other storage devices and IO devices around it,
and they are connected by the bus. But if a look in the processor into a processor itself,
you see some similar things, because in a processor is not a monolith. In a processor,
remember, you have multiple cores, you have multiple caches, and so forth. So how, and
actually many CPUs today, they also have graphic unit, right? Or neural unit, right, like some
of the Apple chips have. Right? So, and then how do you connect those? Well, the answer
is through a bus, right? Okay. So it's again, it's like what you see is outside, you know,
you know, outside the CPU, it's also pretty similar inside the CPU, you have different
components, like here are a few examples, like I mentioned, and they are connected by
a bus. By the way, HDX is a software guard extension. So this is basically, it's a software,
it's a hardware enclave for people who, you know, for people who took a security course,
a class. And yeah. And then you are going to have, then you are going to connect outside
the CPU, you are going to connect to the memory, DDR, this is the memory. And you are going
also, you see here, you are going to have a PCI Express, right? This is how you connect
to the PCI Express to the rest of your devices. This is another way to look at, this is again,
Skylake system configuration. This is the same GPU here. It's pretty old, but today's
on the ones today are not very different. Okay. And you have, you have here, basically,
you know, you have, this is a core, and this is connected to memory. Then you have the
PCI Express, it's again to directly connect to other I/O devices. And then you have this
bridge, and you have another chip which connects to other I/O devices. And this typically saves
a little bit slower devices in general, right? USB, audio, video, LAN, and so forth. So it's
again the same picture, emphasizing this pattern of multiple components being connected by
bus, fast buses. Okay, any questions? So now I mentioned to you that one of the
beauty and the successes of Unix and Linux, obviously, is that they were able to provide
an API which remain pretty much the same over time, despite a proliferation of I/O devices.
And the reason for that is because obviously, they got abstraction, right, right. And they
already recognize early on, there are different type of devices and they are going to handle
with different with these devices slightly different. So how, how these devices are segmented?
First is data granularity. When I'm going to read and write from a device, what is the
granularity of the data I'm going to use? Lowest granularity is like byte, in some cases,
there is bit but it's rare, it's byte, right? You read one byte at a time, you write one
byte at a time. But there are other devices, many other devices where you write at a higher
granularity, like a block, like to disk, or reading or writing from a disk, or reading
or writing from the network. So it's it's, it's a level of granularity, it's a packet.
So now, let's make a little bit this class more interactive. Why do you think that? Why
byte is not is not enough? Why not just have the ability to read and write only at the
background? Anyone can tell me? It's exactly what's bad. Yeah. And actually,
and this is correct. So if you write and read as a by granarity, then you need to this means
if you if you think about from the perspective, this is an API to the publication. And I want
to read and write a byte, this translates to a system call, a system call, translate
to a context switch. So the overhead, right, to read and write a byte is non trivial. Right?
You cannot sustain keep up with very fast IO devices. Okay. So that's the reason. So
byte is fine for keyboard, right? But it's not going to be fine for sending, you know,
data to a gigabit per second. Because the fixed cost of send operation or receiving
operation is too high. Okay. But they got it right from day one, because they have to
support the disk. Okay. And the disk couldn't do it efficiently at byte level. So they have
to have blocks. Okay, good. Access pattern, sequential versus random. You know, some devices
this must be accessed sequentially if you have a tape and others are randomly. Now,
also there are devices which are under this access pattern beyond it's like, are you going
and we are going to talk more about that? Do you need to monitor that IO device all
the time to see what happens or you are going to get interrupts when something happens?
Right? Like with a keyboard or a card. But now let me ask you again, it's like, for instance,
about sequential versus random. Why not have only one? Forget about tape for now. Right?
Remove tape, you know, because that with tape it's obvious, right? It's like, you know,
it's that, you know, it's, you have to access data on sequentially. But even without that,
tell me, why not have random? Right? Because if I have random access pattern, then it doesn't
make sense. I mean, I can emulate sequential, right? I start from one and then I say one,
now I want to get two, three, four, five, six by three, two, three, four, five, six,
right? After all, in memory, I have only random access. I don't have sequential access. So
why sequential access? Why not random? Yes, Michael. Yeah, it's good. We'll learn. Because
the random may involve some non-trivial overhead to locate that random piece of information.
That's why. Like we'll see with the disks. And therefore, if I'm going to store the bytes
and I can read or write them sequentially, it's going to be much, much faster. So you
see in both these cases, you can do, you can get away only have read/write as a level of
byte and only accessing randomly. But you are going to leave a lot of performance on
the table. So block and sequential, block randomization and sequential access pattern,
one of the main reasons they are used is for performance reasons. Okay.
Now the transfer mechanism, how is this?
Program I/O or DMA, Direct Memory Access.
Program I/O means the processor takes a byte from one device
and transfers to another device.
Like for instance, takes a block of data from the disk
and put it in memory.
It's doing in, out, and low stuff.
It's simple.
You can program everything through the computer.
The disadvantage is that you are going
to use a CPU for doing that.
You are going to consume these resources just moving
the data around, not doing useful work.
The second way is Direct Memory Access.
And now this is a smart one.
In this case, you say you are going to deal with two devices.
And basically, you are going to tell one controller
from one device, well, you have to transfer the data directly
to this other device.
This CPU is going to send instructions
how the transfer should happen.
But then the transfer happens between the devices
without the CPU being involved.
And here is an example.
And typically, this is one of the devices is typically
memory.
And here what happens?
So you have a PCI bus and you have a memory.
And here you have a disk.
And I want to transfer the data from the disk to the memory,
to read the data from the disk into memory.
These are the steps.
The CPU number one.
The CPU is going to--
the program starts to say, I want
to read the data from the disk.
Now, under the hood, the OS is going to handle that
and is going to send a message, control message,
to the IDA disk, the controller disk controller telling it,
OK, you need to get this data to this address in the memory.
Address X. Now, the controller is going to tell this, OK,
I need to--
I was instructed to move this data,
to transfer this data to memory, to this address X.
And now the DMA is doing the rest.
The DMA, not the CPU, is going to handle the transfer
from the disk controller to the memory.
So the DMA is going to read the data from the ID
and then drive the data on the CPU bus to the memory.
Once the transfer is completed, the DMA
is going to send an interrupt to the CPU telling,
I am ready.
Any questions?
Pretty cool, right?
So when do I/O devices are notifying the operating system?
Right?
Two reasons.
When it was-- well, the OS--
think about from the OS perspective,
what do you need to know?
On the other hand, you need to know if you are instructed,
you have instructed a controller,
I/O controller to perform some operation.
You want to know when that operation is completed.
The second is if there is an error.
Right?
OK.
So and like you mentioned, one way to handle that
is I/O interrupt.
Whenever there is one of these events
that OS needs to know about, the I/O controller
raises an interrupt.
OK.
Why this is good?
The CPU doesn't need to worry about.
I'm going-- the CPU is going to--
the device-- the I/O controller is going to let the CPU know
and something worse knowing happens.
But also, you can handle unpredictable events
like a new packet arriving on the network.
The disadvantage is that the interrupts are expensive.
It's a context switch.
You know, when the CPU--
when I raise an interrupt, maybe most likely a process,
a user process was executed.
So you need to do a context switch
to go through the operating system, handle the interrupt,
and then to go back in the user mode
to continue running the process.
The other one is polling.
So this is operating system periodically check
a device specific status to see whether it's ready.
Remember that I showed you in the I/O controller,
one of these registers was called status.
So for instance, it's going to be a printer.
I was always--
I want to know when the printer is done,
when the printing is done.
So I can tell the user, OK, the printer is done.
Whatever you send to the printer is done.
So in that case, the controller has this status register,
and it's going to be updated when
the printer is no longer busy when
the file finished being printed.
And then the OS is periodically going to check on that.
And when it's no longer busy, it's
going to turn to the application.
Now the pro here is low overhead because the OS
is going to check on this between contact switches.
It doesn't need to do a contact switch to just to check.
This one, the operating system gets--
the kernel gets control.
It's also going to check this.
Now the con is that you check and nothing happens,
then that's wasted time, CPU cycles.
OK?
So now, typically you combine those.
There is no right solution.
That's why you have to do both of them.
If you do only one solution, why would
have I told you about both?
But let me take a step back now and ask you,
when are you going to use IO interrupts?
And there is a little bit of an answer here.
But I just want you to give the answer in your own words.
When do you think you should use IO interrupts?
When do you think you should use polling?
Give me another-- this is one example
you have here on the slide.
Give me another example.
[AUDIO OUT]
Let me ask you, keyboard, right?
Are you going to use polling or interrupts?
Human IO for interrupts.
OK, that's good.
Why is that?
Why human IO for interrupts?
Rare and slow and--
you see here?
Oh, sorry.
Unpredictable, right?
It's unpredictable.
If it's something unpredictable, it
doesn't make sense to poll forever, right,
for something rare to happen.
Yes, Gilbert.
So your interrupt for frequent sinks,
polling for stuff we need to continuously check.
Yes, or if something happens--
yeah, this for polling, someone, you
say this for polling, sometimes actually you don't use.
We'll see.
But it's not necessary that you are going to poll the disk.
Yeah.
.
So yeah, for the keyboard, eventually it's again,
you have to use the interrupt because this
is to tell the operating system when some keyboard is pressed.
Because if you watch a movie for two hours
or whatever on your computer, you don't type anything, right?
Or zoom, like right now.
You are listening to this lecture, right?
I hope that you are not doing a lot of many things other
than listening to the lecture.
But still, right, it's like if you are listening,
you don't touch it.
You don't have the keyboard.
So it's very rare event.
Doesn't make a lot of sense to poll.
One of the things, the reason you poll
is like in this example, when things
happens extremely frequent, right?
Once you get, for instance, a packet here,
you get so many other packets one after another.
You cannot afford to have a context switching per packet.
When the context switching is--
the overhead of context switching
is larger than the time between the events,
it probably doesn't-- it's not worth the context switching.
It's not worth the interrupts, right?
Let me put it in another way.
So say context switching gets one millisecond
and picking some random number, right?
And then say an event happens every 10 microseconds.
It makes no sense to do the interrupts for event, right?
You just poll to see for that.
OK, very good.
So this is a structure in the kernel for the device.
So you have the system call interface.
We'll talk more about them.
And you have some for memory--
this is what we learned for all.
We have process management, memory management,
file systems.
And then you have the device control.
This is for I/O devices and then networking.
Networking typically is different in apps.
So the API also for networking is slightly different.
OK, so the device control--
what is-- when we say--
so the device control--
the control for the device, this is typically implemented
on the device itself.
But this device now has to also interface with the operating
system.
The piece of software which--
the piece of software which bridges the operating system
API with the controller API is called device driver.
And it's a piece of code which runs in the operating
system, in the kernel.
And it is the piece of code.
It implements the Unix I/O API.
What is that API?
Well, this is the thing which survived so many decades.
Remember, open, close in order to communicate to a device.
You open, you close.
Then read and write.
And you can read as a program or you can read as a program.
And IO-CTL, IO control, this is a escape patch.
Because each device can have--
is a little bit different, requires a little bit
different configurations.
This is what is IO-CTL is.
It's more for device specific control.
Now, the device driver is two halves.
One, which basically is executed in the user mode,
and the other one which is executed in the kernel.
Sorry.
I'm sorry.
Both top and half--
bottom and half of the device drivers
are executed in the kernel.
The top one, it provides--
it helps to provide the kernel IO API, which
is used by the user program to interact with these devices.
So let's see what happens.
So let's say you have a user program
and request an IO operation, say, to write data to the disk.
First of all, is that--
is the request already satisfied or something like that?
It's like this happens when this happens.
This happens, for instance, if I am going
to read some data from the disk.
And when I read the data from the disk,
the granularity at which the data is transferred from the disk
is larger than what I read.
Say, I read only 10 bytes.
But when I'm going to transfer from the disk,
I'm going to transfer one page is four kilobytes.
So these four kilobytes is already stored in memory.
So now, I am just going to--
if I read those first 10 bytes, then I
can read the next 10 bytes.
They're already in memory.
So I don't need to do invoke to touch the device again.
But let's say now it's not satisfied.
So now, I'm going to send the request to the device.
And well, send the request to the device driver.
The device driver is looking at the request.
And from here on, this code, it's device specific.
I process the request.
And then you send it to the device hardware.
So this is the device driver.
This is on the hardware.
So this part, it's on the kernel.
In the kernel, this part at the bottom
can be in the device driver.
It can be in the device itself.
And the device, the controller, is
going to execute the operation.
Say, for instance, instruct the disk
where to read the data from.
Then read the data.
Once it reads the data, it buffers.
It sends an interrupt.
Sorry.
And the interrupt is sent to the kernel.
The kernel is going to handle this interrupt.
It's going to get the data from the device.
And then it's going to see whether the I/O is completed.
And if it's completed, it's going to let the application
know.
OK.
Sounds good.
So the goal of the I/O subsystem-- so I/O,
it's, again, to provide this interface uniform interface.
And so that uniform interface means--
so uniform API means that the code
you wrote for one particular device
should work potentially with very minimal changes
for other devices.
So for instance, for this code, this switch opens some code
and then prints some output.
It works on multiple devices.
It works on this terminal.
If FD is a terminal, the file descriptor is a terminal.
It works for the disk if file descriptor is a file.
And it can also work on the printer.
The same code.
OK.
So now let's talk a little bit more about this interface
and why the interface, again, has been
so powerful and so general.
Like I mentioned to you, you have block devices.
You have block devices.
And for these block devices, you write the data,
the block reality.
And you have an open read, write, and seek, right?
Then you can have character devices.
And this is the level you read and write the data
at the level of a single character.
And for this, you have also open read.
But you have also for getting a single character,
you get a get input API.
And then for network devices, this
is different enough that you have a different API,
slightly different API.
You still have open and close, but you
have the concept of sockets.
And you still have reads and writes, read, write,
and open and close.
All of them are still--
you still have those.
But in addition, you have other richer API.
If you remember, you have connect, you have accept.
You have also something else, which is select.
Select is when you are going to listen on connection
from multiple computers.
You are going to learn more about that.
But these are the three standard interfaces provided
by the operating system.
And each of the devices falls in one of these categories.
Block device.
a character device or a network device.
Next,
how you are going with respect to timing,
how do you interact with the devices?
Well, there are a few ways to interact.
One is a blocking interface.
The blocking interface,
when you are going to perform an operation,
you are going to wait for that operation to finish.
Right?
When you request, say for instance,
when you read some data,
you are blocking until the data you requested is available.
Then it's non-blocking interface.
You don't, you know, you just write some data
and the call returns immediately before the data is written.
Okay?
Now,
so this is obviously you don't know the result,
but then you don't block.
So you are very efficient.
You don't write cycles on the CPU.
And then it's a synchronous interface.
And then this basically says,
I am going to request the data.
And by the way,
here what you need to do,
and let me know when you are done.
So I wanted to read the data and you need,
so read the data from this device.
And I'm telling you that you need to put the data
after this address in memory.
Okay?
And you put that in the address in memory and tell me,
you tell me when you are done with it.
This is a synchronous interface.
Okay?
So some announcements,
unfortunately, you know,
next week will be quite a week for you.
So the good thing is that after the next,
the following week, after the next week,
it's going to be easier.
And the Thanksgiving is coming soon.
But yeah, next week will be hard.
You have a homework for midterm too.
The review will be,
how all will be on Monday.
The time we are going to let you know the time.
The midterm will be on Wednesday
between seven, nine p.m. Pacific time.
As a project is due on,
at the end of the next week and tomorrow,
unfortunately yesterday, I had, like I mentioned,
a flight which was canceled and then rescheduled.
Between 11, 13 and 12, 13, I'll have my office hour.
Okay, let's move a little bit.
We have another 15 minutes.
So let's move quick now.
Storage devices.
So storage devices are where we store the data
and persistently, right?
They typically have much larger capacities than memory,
but they are slower, right?
And we have magnetic disk and flash memories, right?
There are two types.
Magnetic disks are, you know,
these are traditional ones, flash memories are newer,
but now are dominant.
They are more expensive.
They have provide better performance.
That's kind of the way to look at them.
These are some examples.
This is the disk drive, right?
You see here a platter.
You have here the heads.
We read and write the data.
And then you are going to have,
here is another hard drive.
This is the heads.
You have multiple platters on each drive the data,
and therefore you have heads on each platter,
for each platter.
And here it's a micro drive, this is this, right?
Now, just to give you a sense,
the first IBM personal computer, which was released in 1986.
So that was 35 years ago, right?
It has, the hard disk was $500.
It was 30 megabytes, not gigabytes, megabytes.
The seek time is how long it takes a random access.
It's those 30 to locate, you know,
to write the data randomly, or read the data randomly,
or between 30 and 40 milliseconds.
And the speed, the maximum speed of transferring the data,
what was one megabyte per second, okay?
So how it looks like, this is how hard drive it looks like.
You have the platters, the platter has two surfaces,
the up and down surface.
So you can write on both of them.
On each of them, you are going to have tracks,
and the tracks are divided in sectors.
So the sectors stores a block.
And this is a unit of storing, reading,
and writing data from the disk.
And that is written, reads and writes
are performed by the header, okay?
So let's now show this one by one.
This is a sector, okay?
So you have this ring of sectors.
This is a stack.
And then the corresponding tracks
on all platters represent a cylinder.
What is important about cylinder?
Is that the data from a cylinder can be written
and read without moving the heads.
Because the movement of heads,
which is called SICK operation, is expensive, right?
Okay.
So some numbers, the disk track,
the tracks are around one micron wide.
And this is very small.
The wavelength of light, it's only half a micron.
The resolution of human eyes is 50 microns.
So you have typically 100,000 tracks on a 2.5 inch disk.
And you have these tracks in general,
separated by some guard regions,
because you don't want right on a track
to influence the bits on the others
and corrupt, therefore, the bits on the nearby tracks.
Now, the tracks length varies, right?
The one which are closer to the edges
are larger than the one at the center.
And so typically, we are only using half of the radius,
only the tracks at the edges of that,
because you have more space to store information.
If you store it too close to the center,
the sector is too small.
You are going to get a lot of errors.
And this card, obviously huge right now,
there are terabytes in terms of capacity.
So in general, only a small part of this data,
which is stored on the disk is active, redrived.
The rest is used for being archived.
And this is important.
Before, in the early days, you archive the data
not on the disk, because it is quite expensive.
You archive the data on magnetic tapes.
One note, this is more like a footnote.
There is something which is called
single magnetic recording.
And in this case, instead of having a guard
between the tracks, you remember that I told you
that between tracks, you have the guards.
So you avoid writing, when you write on a track a bit
to influence the nearby tracks, right?
But in order in the race to add more and more bits,
to increase the capacity of the disks,
people came up with this technique,
which actually in some sense,
the tracks kind of almost overlap.
And obviously now you need to be very careful
and need to have much more complex,
digital signal processing techniques
in order to make sure that you avoid a bit being corrupted
by writing a bit in a nearby track.
So, magnetic disk,
it's again, you have the heads, cylinders, sectors,
and tracks, and now let's see what is the time
to read or write data, okay?
So first of all, this is how
the architecture looks like.
So the disk actually has a controller, right?
Like we mentioned many times before.
And you are going to get a request, right?
The controller gets a request, right?
And let me just show you where this request is coming from.
It's here.
You see the request, this is the request.
Okay?
And here we are talking about this device hardware.
(silence)
Okay.
So you get the request, and then you have a queue
because multiple application can request data
to read and write data from the same time.
So you need to queue this request, right?
And then you have the hardware controller,
which is going to take requests from this queue,
and that's going to satisfy the request.
Now, a request, when you satisfy the request, what happens?
You need to figure out and assume that you already know
where the data you need to read and to,
where the data is located, right?
And in order to, once you do that, you need to move that,
you need to, so you need to identify
what you need to identify.
You need to identify a sector.
A sector means to identify the track, right?
In order to get to a track, you need to move the disk,
to move the heads.
The overhead to move the disk is called seek time.
Then once you are above the corresponding track,
you need to wait for the proper sector
to come under the head so you can read and write.
This is the rotation time.
And finally, the transfer time,
the time to read and write the information from the sector.
Here are some numbers from some other magnetic disks.
It's a space like 14 terabytes.
It's pretty eight platters.
Typically the seek time is four to six milliseconds.
This rotation, like rotation speed,
the rotation per minute is like between 3,600 and 7,200.
There are also some of the new, you know,
faster disk at even 1,500 rotation per minute.
Average latency of,
rotation latency is between four and eight milliseconds.
Right?
This is, you know,
if it takes eight milliseconds for a full rotation,
then on average, you need to wait for four milliseconds
rotation latency in order for the sector
you are looking for to come under the disk,
under the head.
And transfer time between 50 and 250 megabytes per second.
The transfer sector is typically between
512 and one kilobyte and things like that.
Right?
They used to drop,
the cost used to drop by a factor of two every 1.5 years.
It's no longer true.
So now let's go through this example.
So assuming that we ignore the queuing
and the controller times.
Okay?
So we ignore this queuing time and the controller time.
Let's look only on the media time.
Assume the average seek time is five milliseconds.
Assume that the rotation, you know,
speed it's 7,200 rotation per minute.
So this means that it takes eight milliseconds
for a full rotation.
And the transfer rate assume is 50 megabytes.
Oh, so then the, sorry.
This is the transfer rate of 15 megabytes per second.
If it's a block size of four kilobytes, right?
So assuming the transfer rate is 50 megabytes per second.
If the block size is four kilobytes,
then it takes 0.8 milliseconds to transfer one sector.
Right?
You divide four kilobytes, the size of a sector,
on the transfer rate, right?
To get that by.
So then reading the block from a random place on the disk,
you need to seek first to the track.
You need to wait for the sector and then you read it.
So it takes nine milliseconds,
a little bit more than nine milliseconds.
Is equivalent to 450 kilobytes per second speed,
you know, transfer speed.
If you read the block from a random place
in the same cylinder, then if you do that,
you don't need to incur the seek time.
So now the latency is only 4.08 milliseconds,
which means that the data now rate
is one megabyte per second.
But now assume that you just need the same,
next sector on the track.
You sequentially read.
Then you don't need to incur the rotation delay either.
So it's 50 megabytes per second.
So it's 50 times bigger or 100 times bigger
if it's purely random.
So now you see why you have seek.
Also you have sequential access
and versus only random access, right?
If you can sequentially access the data,
it's so much faster, at least for the disk.
So the key to use a disk effectively
is to make sure that you, as much as possible,
you access the data sequentially, okay?
So now there is a lot of intelligence
in this embedded into this controller.
So the sectors, for instance,
you have sophisticated error correcting codes, right?
Because, you know, to avoid data corruption.
And this is very important
because if you store the data on a disk
and you trust that disk because it's stored persistently.
So if the data is corrupted, you know, you lost the data.
Sector sparing.
So it's again, it's like,
sometimes some sectors becomes bad.
You can no longer read and write data reliably from them.
So in that case, you remap them.
You forget about those and you remap that
to transfer it to another spare sector on the disk.
And this is done by the controller
transparently with the software.
Sleep sparing.
Now, if there is a bunch,
if the sector goes bad,
now the problem is that, you know,
now you no longer have sequential access.
If you want to preserve sequential access,
you may want to remap multiple sectors
to preserve the sequentiality.
And the last is track skewing.
And here I have a figure for you as a mean track skewing.
So this means that if I want,
if the data is stored sequentially on nearby tracks,
then I want to make sure that when I move
from one track to another, I don't waste time.
So here, you know, these are the sectors on track one.
So say I'm going to read on track one here, the head,
you know, I'm just finishing reading everything
on the track one and I want to move to track two.
The track two is the one inside.
Now, when I want to move,
then the first sector on track one, I'm going to shift.
So then this time,
when I'm going to move the head to track one,
by the time I moved, now sector zero comes,
is ready to be read.
If I don't do this, then while I move this head
from one sector, from one track to another,
I miss a sector zero and I need to wait
for an entire evolution of the disk
before I start reading it, right?
So, and I'm going to end up with this slide.
So this is an example of current hard disk drive.
It's like 20, 20, 18 terabytes is a hard drive,
nine platters, 18 hertz.
Each platter has two sides.
So one head for each side.
Four milliseconds, every six time.
A sector is four kilobytes, 7,200 RPM and so forth.
And 270 megabytes per second maximum transfer rate
costs 562.
Now let's compare with IBM personal computer drive,
the first drive.
This was 86, okay?
So the seek time is 10 times better, okay?
The transfer time is 300 times better.
But the capacity is 600,000 times better.
And the cost, it's almost the same, 600,000 times better.
So this is a progress we were able to get in 36 years.
Okay, so it's quite impressive.
Okay, so we are going to stop here
and next time we are going to start talking
with about solid SSDs.
Thanks everyone, okay.
Okay, I'm going to stop here
and I'm going to answer the questions.
(silence)
.
you