Hello everyone. So today we are going to continue the discussion about the storage devices.
In particular, we are going to talk about SSDs or solid state devices, and we are going
to start the discussion on queuing theory. So last time we talked about disk drives or
the spinning disks, and these are the main technologies used to store data for the first
few decades of personal computers and computers in general. And we are starting with kind
of two decades ago, a little bit more than that. We started to see the emergence of another
technology to store data persistently, and that was memory-based. And the first efforts
was in 1995, the emergencies of you have DRAM, but how you make it persistent? Well, you
have a battery, you have DRAM powered by a battery. And then as long as the battery lasts,
you are going to store the data persistently in that memory, even when the computer is
unplugged. But after that, things change with this new technology, NAND, multi-level cell.
So basically this allows you to store, it's like a memory, but it allows you to store
data, to store information, even when it's not powered. So that was kind of the key technology
innovation at a high level. Of course, there are many details, we don't have a lot of time
to go into details, but the big thing was about having this commercially available technology
to store data in this new kind of memories without needing to power them on.
And these SSDs, they store information, granularity of a memory block, and the memory block consists
of four kilobytes, between four and 64 kilobytes pages. And remember that 40 kilobytes pages
is basically more or less like a sector on a disk, disk drive. And it's also making the
size of the page for a virtual memory implementation. So you have virtual memory, the pages in the
virtual memory are typically four kilobytes, the same, the size is a sector size. And then
when you translate those to the SSDs, you are going for this four kilobytes page are
part of a memory block and the memory block consists of four between four and 64 pages.
This is an important detail. There are no moving parts, just like memory. So this has
a certain advantages, big advantages. First of all, eliminate the seek and the rotation
latency. Remember from last time, there's a seek and rotation latency, where is the
biggest culprits of a long latency to access data on the disk, at least randomly. That's
why we have a huge difference between the throughput of a disk when you access the data
sequentially, because in that particular case, you do not need to pay for the seek and rotation
delays, versus when you access the data randomly, when you need to pay for both of these delays,
seeks and rotation. They also have requires even very low power and anything, and they
are lightweight. It's not just memory. It's not like a disk metal with platters spinning
and heads and things like that. On the downside, it does have limited write cycles. So this
means that limited write cycle, it's when you modify a cell, when you modify a bit,
if you modify it too many times, if you write the same bit too many times, then it works
out. You can no longer write that bit reliably. So that's one of the challenges you need to
deal with. And obviously, since you already introduced, there are rapid advantage and
the capacity have increased. And today, to give you a sense, obviously today is that
I'm not sure any of your devices you are working with still has a disk, unless you are working,
you have a big workstation home or you are using. But certainly your laptops, obviously
the phones, the IP or iPad, they no longer have disk drives to store data persistently.
They only have SSDs. So here it's again how SSD architecture look like. This NAND is where
on the right hand side is the memory, the banks of memory, and each of these could present
a block. And then you have a flash memory controller, which basically decides where
to write and what to read the data from. And you have a buffer manager and the software
queue. And this is about when this is where you buffer the reads and writes requests.
So if you have many reads or writes requests at the same time, and you cannot serve at
the same time, you have to buffer them and serve them one by one. It's also a DRAM here.
So when you cache some of the information, right, when you read, if I read only a few
bytes, the granularity, if you remember to read and write from this SSD, it's one of
these memory blocks, which can be between 16 and 256 kilobytes. So you have to read
that granularity. And once you are reading it, you are going to cache it, because if
you are going to read again the next few bytes, then it's already in DRAM. You don't need
to go and fetch it again. And now, this is the SATA, it's bus technology,
and or can be PS, which is connected through a bridge to the PCI bus, like we discussed
last time, and then it's connected to the processor and to the memory.
So here are some numbers for you. To read a 4 kilobyte page, it takes around, say, between
10 and 25 microseconds. Again, there is no SQL rotation latency. So now the transfer
time for a 4 kilobyte page for the SATA interface, you have between 300 and 600 megabytes per
second. Actually, the best interface is today you have 2 gigabytes per second, so a few
times larger than this. But even for, say, 400 megabytes per second to take a number,
then the transfer time, so the time to read 4 kilobyte pages is 10 microseconds. And the
latency, if you remember, what is the latency? The queuing time, so the time the request
has to wait in the queue for the request to be satisfied, and plus the controller time,
whatever the controller needs to do and to make the decision, it's a fixed time, and
the transfer time. And because this is a memory, basically you can randomly address, there
is not such a big difference between sequential and random reads.
Now this was about the read. Now the writing is much more complex. And you can only write
empty pages in a block. So there are three states of these pages. It's written, no, two
stages, whether it's written or whether it's erased or empty. And you can only write empty
pages. So if you want to overwrite a page, then before doing that, you need to erase
a page. And now the page becomes empty and then you overwrite it. Now, the problem with
that is that this operation is far more expensive. Remember, it's like the read was say 25 microseconds.
The writing data on an empty page is 200 microseconds. And now if you want to erase a page, if you
need to erase a page, if you don't have an empty page, erasing the page takes 1.5 milliseconds.
So the rule of thumb you can think about, the write is 10 times more expensive than
the reads and the erasers are 10 times more expensive than the writes. So 200 microseconds,
it's around eight times larger than 25 microseconds, which is a time to read a page. And then 1.5
milliseconds is what? 7.5 times larger than 200 microseconds is the time to write an empty
page. So therefore you need to be very careful about that. So this is the thing, the two
constraints you have to operate with. And the two constraints which are different make
this SSD different than the DRAMs, the traditional memory. It's one, it's about you can only
write empty pages and read and writes are asymmetric, are not taking the same amount
of time, eraser take even longer. So this is one. And the other one is that you can
only do a limited amount, a number of writes. Typically it's like 10,000 writes or something
like that. Okay. So you need to be careful. So now in order to avoid the cost of erasure,
when you need to write, so to erase first before writing, what the controller is doing,
it maintains a pool of empty blocks. So you bring the use pages, put them in a, you know,
put together in a block and then it pulls, you have these pools of empty blocks and then
you can write them and then you can pay only 200 microseconds per page instead of 1.7 milliseconds.
SSDs provide the same interface as hard disk drives to the OS, the same API, which is great
because you can just swap a disk drive with an SSD and the computer will work, but it
will be much faster. Right? Like I said, when you override the data, when you, the chronology
of writing, it's a, it's a block and the block can be 16 times larger than a page, sorry,
64 times larger than a page. So you have a page is four kilobytes and you have 64 pages
in a block. Then 64 by time of times four is 256 kilobytes. So this is what the 256
kilobytes is coming from. Okay. So I, we already discussed about it. Why not erase and rewrite
new version of the entire 256 blocks? Because erasure is extremely slow. And then each block
has a finite lifetime. Like I mentioned to you, you cannot erase and rewrite all the
time. You can only do that for say 10, a few tens of that 10 thousands of times. Okay.
So therefore if you have heavily used blocks, you do a lot of writes, they are going to
wear out quickly. Okay. So now you have this problem, right? It's like, you know, you,
you have if you have, how, how do you are going to solve it? Right. And again, the problem
is that, you know, I cannot, I can do, I am allowed to do only a limited number of writes
and now I have some heavy blocks. So what I'm going to do about it, do you have any
suggestions here?
Remap. That's exactly, that's very good. So basically when you are going to rewrite, you
are not going to rewrite in the same place. You are going to write to another page, which
is not, was not so used in the past. And then you are going to remap the, the page to the
new block. You're you're you're used to write the new information. And this is a layer of
indirection. It is called flash translation layer or FTL in SSD. I assume maps, the virtual
block numbers, which is uses these are the blocks actually says a page numbers, the physical
page numbers, which flash memory control uses. Okay. So that's the way it's it's working.
Right. So from the OS perspective, you still have the same page as the same page numbers
and everything, but now on the physical pages, you have a map and the page number as seen
by the CPU is going to map to a physical page number. And the mapping is, it's, it's, it's,
it's managed by the controller. So the controller can remap and basically say page number one
is go to physical page number 10 and next is going to go to physical page number 15.
Right. So that's why, how I'm going to load balance the writes for the same page as seen
by the CPU. Okay. So this is pretty much it. It's again, copy on write. This is, or should
be obvious, right? Again, I do not want to copy to rewrite the same page. You know, even
if I want to modify a page, I don't rewrite it because I need to erase it first. And if
I need to erase it first is expensive. So what I'm doing, I'm going to just create a
new version of the page and I'm, then I'm going to remap it. Isn't the lifetime of 10k
eraser writes quite small, consider that we can use a laptop for multiple years. It's
not really, I mean, because if you really do load balancing, really load balancing,
this means that you need to write or update, you can read and draft and update. Like say
you have one terabyte of disk, right? So one terabyte of disk, then you can write the equivalent
of 10,000 multiply with one terabyte. So 10 petabytes, right? I think this is right. You
can write 10 petabytes and you don't, you know, it's hard to write 10 petabytes. Yeah.
So yeah. But it's again, this works if you are going to be able to load balance, right?
And this writes, right? And this is what the controller is doing.
Okay. The flash translation layer also ensures that there is no need to erase and rewrite
the entire 256 blocks when making small modification or changes. SSD controller can assign mapping
to spread or load, it's what we talk about. So you want basically to load balance the
writes. This is called where labeling, and you are doing that by remapping and doing
copy on write, creating new versions of the page or hopefully using a page, a physical
page which was not written many times. If you old version of the pages, which are, you
know, you delete a file, what happened? Then they are very garbage collected in the background
and in the background you are going to erase them. So to maybe to prepare them to be written
again. So you, they are ready to be written again. Any questions?
This again was something, some of the most, you know, now how they compare like hard disk
drives with SSDs. We'll have that in the next slide. But about SSDs themselves, you know,
you can buy, and these are two years old, some of the data, but you can buy 16 terabytes.
You remember that we have 16 terabytes, the disk we considered last time, was this kind
of the hard disk drive was having the same size, 16 terabytes, the same capacity. But
that was, if I remember correctly, and you can check, that was around $500, $550 or something
like that. This is $5,000. Okay. So it's 10 times more expensive. Okay. For the same capacity.
However, if you look at reads and writes, the number of sequential reads and writes,
it's 800 or 900. In that case was, if I remember correctly, it's 800 or 900.
sequential writes it was 260 megabytes per second. So this is up to four, almost four times faster.
And random reads and writes, there is no comparison. Okay. You can have 100,000
reads per second. While a read in the case of a disk, if you remember, can take a few milliseconds.
So if you if you take even a few milliseconds and in a second, you can read a few hundreds
or a few hundreds reads and writes. So in order to write it better. Okay. And if you go and if
you really want to go to the top ones, you have 100 terabytes. So SSD 100 terabytes, and you have
500 megabytes sequential read and writes, the same kind of IOPS 100 kilobytes. IOPS means
or input operation per second. Unlimited writes for five years, so you get these guarantees.
But it costs 4000, $40,000. But more, far more expensive, right? It's like a quarter of dollar
per gigabyte. Why would random versus sequential have different performance? This is this.
If you read at the level of pages, there is no difference. And you can do probably you can do
the math here. Or it's very little difference. But still, if you read at the level of page,
you know, because you transfer from the SSDs as a level of page or block, right,
block granularity, if you read only one byte, or from that page, you are still going to lose
in terms of performance or throughput. And the difference between random, the different reads
and writes, the reason is different here is because remember that the writes are slower,
10 times slower almost.
Okay, so here is a comparison between hard disk drives and SSDs. And this is a nice,
interesting plot. Because, you know, why wouldn't use SSDs? They have all they are faster,
they can have bigger capacity, they consume less power. So they are probably, you know,
they are more reliable. So why in the world you wouldn't use them? Well, the answer is simply
it's cost, right? And however, and here what you see is a blue line is a flash cost. It is for
and for the same capacity for the terabyte is a flash cost or a terabyte. And here is
orange is hard disk drive cost. So the hard disk drives cost much cheaper than SSDs. And with green,
and the green is the most important curve, is basically what is the ratio between the cost to
store one terabyte on an SSD versus the cost to store a terabyte on a hard disk drive.
So it was 37 times in 2013. Today it's around five, six times. So it's much smaller. And many
people predict that sometime in the future, these predictions are almost always wrong. But some in
the near future, the SSD will match the cost of hard disk drives. And at that point, there is very
little reasons to use hard disk drives at all. Okay. So in summary, SSDs, they have low latency,
high throughput, no moving parts, more reliables, lower power consumptions, and read much faster,
read, you know, read at memory speeds. You can read even faster if you have a wider
bus by the way. That was one of the main limitations of how fast you can read and write.
The cons before the R2 is expensive, between 3 and 20x more expensive, but in a few years back,
like certainly 10 years back, the SSDs are much smaller than hard disk drives. So that's why
here it's smaller storage. And the people back then, they are combining the hard disk drive
with SSDs, using SSDs as a cache to get the performance of SSDs and to get the capacity
of hard disk drives. But now it's no longer needed. Because as you've seen from the data,
now the SSDs can have higher capacities than hard disk drives. Quite amazing.
So this says, tells you, this technology, if you are to build a company based on that,
it wouldn't have been a great idea because the trends are not in your favor.
Because your product to use SSDs to speed up the hard disk drives would have become obsolete.
There's still a reason to do that, because if you want to get the cost of the hard disk drives
to do cheaper, right, to be cheaper and still have almost performance comparable to SSDs.
But that's probably true today. But in a few years, again, if SSDs are going to drop at the
cost of hard disk drives, this is really there is no reason for these optimizations.
You have asymmetric block rights performance. We know that. And we learn about that. And you have
the where, the limited lifetime in terms of writing rights. So you need to be careful.
And average failure rate is six years. Life expenditures between nine and 10,
11 years, are actually better than hard disk drives. So it's again, the TLDR here,
SSDs are better in almost every respect. You need to be more careful. It's more complex.
The algorithms are more complex to go around these limitations. The erasures are very expensive and
you need to erase a page before writing it. And the where, you need to take into account the
wearing of pages. And it's more expensive, but the costs are dropping. So the prices are dropping.
Okay. So there's a question here. Just wondering how much overhead generally is there for the
hybrid alternative system involving both SSD and hard disk drives? It seems like it would be a lot
more complex keeping track going between both in the same computer. It's more complex, but the way
you buy that, you buy this like, you buy that like, it's like, it's the same enclosure. The
hard disk drive, they are not two different devices. You buy like, it's like a device which
you plug into your SATA bus. Right. And like, you'll buy a hard disk drive or SSD and you buy
this kind of hybrid device. And inside the device, you have the, you hide all the complexity. You
have a SSD, you have the hard disk drive and you have complex logic to deal and to use SSD,
basically like a cache for the hard disk drives. Did I answer your question Gilbert?
Okay. So yeah, it's complex, but it's hidden. The complexity is hidden. Okay. So announcements.
Homework 4 is due on Mondays. You're now, midterm to review. Now we have a time between 5 and 6,
7 PM on Monday. Admitter 2 is Wednesday between 7 and 9 PM. And please read the updated proctoring
guide. You can have an additional cheat sheet for this exam. Remember that this exam will cover
everything from the beginning of the semester, but we have more emphasize on the materials in the
first midterm. And the project is due next Friday. So next week it's a hard week,
but it's again, after that, it will be easier.
So now let's switch gears. Any question now about storage devices, what we learned over the last
and this lecture, hard disk drive and solid state drives?
Okay. So right now, let's, we are going to switch the gears and we are going to talk about
performance and how to model performance. If you saw this kind of, even like device drivers are
pretty complex. You get a request, you enqueue the request because you may have multiple requests
arriving at the same time, you serve the request. And by, from the point of view of the program who
made the request, it cares only about the end-to-end latency, but it's end-to-end latency
is divided or support is divided between multiple components. So we are going to learn a little bit
about how to model those and let's try first to define what are the metrics we care about.
So the response time or latency is time to perform on operation is end-to-end time. And you have the
bandwidth or throughput is a rate to which you can perform operations, operation per second. And for
different devices, the operation can be different. Like for instance, it's a different metric here,
but all the metrics are over second, it's some quantity over second. Like files,
for files when you read and write is megabytes per second. For network is megabits per second.
When you say megabytes, it's power of two if you remember. Megabits for the network is power of 10.
This is how you, for instance, one megabyte for files is 1024 kilobytes. One megabit
for network is 1000. Sorry, one megabit for network. What I'm saying? One megabyte for files,
yeah, it's 1024 kilobytes I said correctly. One megabyte per second for network is 1000
kilobytes per second. And then you have gigaflops operation per second, floating point operation
per second for automatic computation and things like that. Then you have a startup or overhead.
It's a time to initiate an operation. This can be think about something like context switching.
And most of your operation are roughly linear in the number of bytes. So basically what happens
in bytes. So basically, for instance, if you are going to,
the way you can model this operation, there is an overhead or a fixed cost to initiate the
operation. You pay on that operation no matter how much you transfer. And then it's a variable cost.
And the variable cost is n, how many bytes in this case you transfer over the bandwidth.
So if you remember, we've seen this pretty much in the last lecture for hard disk drives. You
remember you have the overhead, which was the seek time and rotation latency. No matter how much you
read or write on a disk, you need to pay for that cost when you do that read and write.
And then once you locate and you do the rest is sequential write, read and write,
then it's about how fast you are going to be able to read bits from the disk. And that is given by
how fast is the disk rotating and the rotation of the disk. And that is a variable part. You
read more, it's going to take more time. So this is a way to look at it again.
Basically, you have the user thread, which is going to initiate an input operation.
Then you have a queue and you can have queue, this can be in controller or it can be in the
operating system. It depends on the implementation, it depends on the device,
but there is a queue along the way where the requests are queued, if there are multiple
requests at the same time, then it's a controller and then it's finally the I/O device. So I/O
device service time. And this is how long I got the request, how long it takes to satisfy that
request. So the metrics here are response times and throughput. Response time we saw in the previous
slide is S plus N over B. And what is the bandwidth? Now, the bandwidth is that one of
the bandwidths we really care and it's from the user thread perspective, it is, we call the
effective bandwidth. And the effective bandwidth is what we, when we are saying like, for instance,
if you remember, like how this drives, the throughput is very different when we are reading
randomly, random reads or sequential reads, right? It's very different if you remember.
And that's effective bandwidth. So effective bandwidth for random reads is much lower than
effective bandwidth for sequential reads. And the reason is, and effective bandwidth basically is,
it is how many bytes I'm sending, I read or operation I performed over how long it took me
to read this and bytes, right? Or perform an operations. And the time it took to perform
this operation, you know, this latency, you know, from the previous slide, it says plus N over B.
Or you can also, you know, a little bit of refactoring is B over one plus S B over N,
right? So now you can see exactly, right? It's like, if you read only one byte, this is,
you know, the denominator will be dominated, this will be dominated by S by the overhead, right?
And which is include controller time, queue delay, and things like that. And if you are going to have
read a lot of bytes, this will be dominated by N. And actually the effective bandwidth
becomes similar with the bandwidth of the I/O device, like what in the case of a hard disk drive
with a bandwidth of sequential access. Any questions?
Okay. So this is, we'll talk more about that plot you see on the right hand side.
The only thing, and I'm going to repeat that a few times. The only thing to keep in mind is that
this is the kind of curve you are going to see. And this is on the X, Y axis, you have the
utilization, right? How much utilization is about the load, which is offered to the device, the
system over the capacity of the system, right? How much I can handle. And if you on X axis, you see
the response, the Y axis, you see the response time. And this is how it looks like. Initially
it's going, you know, when the system is not very loaded, you have very little load,
you get very good performance. The response time is very good, but you try to growth. And after
some point it's going to shut up. And if the load is equal to the capacity of the system, actually
the response time can go to infinity, right? Can grow extremely fast, right? This is the same,
like, remember, it's like highway. When the highway is free very late in the night or very
early in the morning, if you know, you'll go very fast, right? As a speed, like legal speed,
hopefully, right? And if, on the other hand, if you start like rush hour, right?
The delays can be shut up, right? And that's a big, obviously is a big problem. And then you
are stealing now is the capacity of the system, right? Because you've still added the capacity
of the system because eventually all the cars still get home, right? So, none of them is
stuck indefinitely. So, yes, let me give me one second. I think it's the sensor light.
Let me just start the light again.
Okay.
Sounds good. I need to move more.
Contribute, so the factor to latency, you know, I can mention this kind of S,
it's about hardware control, the IO service time, device service time, and so forth.
And, but the most interesting part, one of the most important things here is a queue, right?
Because queue here, you have a lot of requests coming in, you queue them. So, you can spend a
lot of time in the queue. Actually, the reason response time shuts up is not because the device
the IO device time, service time, serving a request still takes the same amount of time.
Okay. So, this is very important to remember. The reasons is response time shuts up is because
a queue, because you have more and more requests as they have to wait for the previous request
to be served. It's like you go into a grocery store. So, the time it takes a clerk
to serve a customer doesn't depend on the queue size, right? It still takes the same time.
Maybe, you know, if the queue is long, maybe it's going even takes less because it's going to be
hurry. But it's, you know, ideally it doesn't depend on the queue size. However, if there are
many people in the store, you are going to wait more. Why? Because the queue is longer. Okay. So,
one of the most interesting and relevant aspects is a queue, of a system is a queue. And this is
what you are going to analyze a little bit. Okay. So, this is a way you typically present, you know,
you can model the system. You have arrivals and the arrival is a request which arrives,
like read request, write request, packets. These can be packets which arrive at the router and
things like that. And then you serve, you serve this request, like the server, right? You send
the data out, you serve the reads and writes and things like that. And then you have two times,
DQ, which is a queuing time and TS is a serving time. And the response time is very, very,
basically TQ plus TS, the queuing time plus the service time.
And now you have another one, it's TA, which is, this is obviously you have here in this
figure, it's on the x-axis, you have the time, and the TA is interarrival time. So basically
the difference between two consecutive, between the arrival of two consecutive requests. Okay.
And this is the arrival. And now on the y-axis, which is not shown, I should show here, if
you go down, you move from down, is the time it takes, it's basically it's a response time.
Right. So what this shows here is that, sorry, it's yeah, what it shows here is basically
you have TQ is like, it's a time you spend in the queue. And then TS is a time you spend
to service TS, to service that request. And after a while you have another request, which
is queue is very little. Here the queue is empty, but it's still probably a time because
you still need probably maybe to, even if it's one element in the queue, you need to
enqueue it and then get it out of the queue or just checking whether the queue is empty.
So there is still a little bit of time you are going to spend. Right. But here you are
dominated by the service time. Right. And you see, whenever you have a new request,
at least in this example, you are going to the queue is empty. Right. So every response
time, the response time on February request is going to take the same time. Okay. But
now let's do, okay. So let's introduce a few more metrics. So a few more metrics here are
basically the service rate. The service rate is basically is like how many operation you
can perform per second. Right. And basically this is one over TS. Right. It's like if,
for instance, if it takes me to serve a request, it takes 10 milliseconds to serve a request.
How many I can do per second? One seconds over 10 milliseconds is 100. Then it's arrival
rate. And this is one over TA. Right. This has a request per second. The request per
second it's the same. Right. It's like if I am getting every one request every 20 milliseconds,
then the Lambda, which is request per second, it's one over 20 milliseconds. One second
over 20 milliseconds is 50. Right. And then it's utilization. Utilization is your arrival
rate over the service rate. Or if you plug in in this equation, the formula for the service
rate and the arrival rate, you are going to get the service time over the arrival time.
Right. So basically what is this saying is that for instance, if you have the arrival
time, it's 20 milliseconds and the service time is 10 milliseconds, then you are going
to have 10 milliseconds over 20 milliseconds. It's 0.5. So utilization will be 50%, which
kind of makes sense. Right. If I have one new request arriving every 20 milliseconds
and one request, it takes me to process one request 10 milliseconds. This means that for
each request, I'm going to spend 10 milliseconds and I'm going to wait another 10 milliseconds
to get the new request. And I'm going to be free half of my time. Right. Make sense? So
what happens when Lambda is greater than the Mu and the arrival rate is greater than the
service rate? What do you think it happens? It's a good question. If it's a for short
interval of time, what is the burst? Then you are going to have the queue to absorb
that burst. So the queue delay will going to increase. If it's long, it's for a long
time, and it's just average arrival rate is greater than the average service rate, then
the queue will grow indefinitely. The system is called to be in an unstable state. In general,
what we are going to analyze now in this lecture are systems which are stable. Means that the
arrival rate is not greater than the service rate. Okay. Good. So this is basically tells
you is about if TS over TA is small, then we are fine. And the queue time, the queuing
delay is slow. But after some point, if you are going to get one, this is load, you see,
the load is for this plot from zero to one. This is TSA over TA, right? So before one
is fine. It grows, but it grows a little bit. But if you are going to go over one, then
it's going to shut up, right? This is a queue delay. So it can be unbounded. So this is
the answer to your question. Gilbert, if the arrival rate is greater than the service rate,
then the queue will grow unbounded. So now let's see how the requests arrive in a burst
and let's see what happens. And here on the vertical axis, I have queue depths. On the
horizontal axis is again the time. And here basically, I see here the queue depths. I'm
going to have the first request in the queue. It's empty. It's going to be serviced immediately.
So this is where it's going to be the server. This is the server, the timeline for the server.
So I get the request. I'm going to serve it here. But now I get the second request. So
if I'm getting the second request, I am going to have to queue it because the server is
satisfying the previous request. And now I get a new request. So new request again, I
need to queue it. Now I have two requests in the queue. Again, on the vertical axis
down, you have the size of the queue. So I have two in the queue right now. And now I
get another one. So it's again, the first request has unfinished being serviced. So
the queue is increasing by another one request. So I have three requests in the queue. Now
I don't get anything more. So if I don't get anything more, I'm going to start serving,
say it's a five order. So I'm going to serve the first request in the queue, the wide request.
Now while I serve the wide request, I still have two requests in the queue, the light
blue one and the orange one. And then when I finish serving this request, I'm going to
serve the orange request and finally the light blue request. Okay. So this is what happens.
And now I have a new request and things like that. Any questions? So the point here is
that even the utilization is low, even if the average arrival rate is lower than the
service rate, much lower even, you can still have occasional burst. So a lot of events
or a lot of operation arrive at the same time. It's like rush hour, right? Over the entire
duration of a day, the arrival or the number of cars on the highway is significantly lower
than the capacity of the highway. But there are some bursts in rush hours, when the number
of cars, it's almost at capacity and then you experience large events. So how do you
model the burst arrival? Now there is a lot of mathematical models, but one of the most
elegant one is Poisson distribution or exponential distribution. Exponential distribution, and
this is f of x is lambda, where lambda is the average arrival rate in this case, or
average mean for that distribution times e power minus Lx. And this is how it looks like,
this f of x. And this is a lambda, it's actually the mean arrival rate for this distribution,
it's one over lambda. So actually lambda, I'm taking back, so lambda represent the interarrival
time between the events, so mean arrival time is one over lambda. And the nice thing about
this exponential distribution is it is what is called memoryless. Memoryless means that
the future doesn't depend on the past, right? And it's counterintuitive because you are
not used to that. This will say, and maybe sometimes this happens, if you arrive at the
station, right, Bath station, how long it takes for the next train to arrive doesn't
depend of when the previous train arrived, whether it arrived the last minute or whether
it just leaves the station where it was 15 minutes ago. Okay. So this is what, but because
it's memoryless, it's much easier to model, right? It also says, if you look at this plot,
that this means that the lot of events which are arriving in bursts, the interval between
them is short, and there are some also very long intervals between events. So if you look
at the events on the timeline, there are bursts of events arriving together, so interarrival
between these events is small, and then you have long pauses, right? Long gaps. Any questions?
You did learn exponential distribution, I hope in some of your math classes, right,
your statistics classes. Okay. And now with this distribution, what are the main metrics?
One of the most important metrics is the mean, obviously the mean of the distribution. And
you know how to compute the mean. It's like it's an integral or the sum, depending on
the discrete distribution of the P of t. So what is the probability that that event happens
at time, you know, at t? What is the probability that you are going to have in this case, for
instance, an arrival after exactly t time units, and then you are going to multiply
with the t because the interarrival time, right? So, and this is the mean, right? If
you have this variance of the square of the standard deviation, which is you multiply
its sum of P of t multiplied by t square minus m square, and m is again the mean, and t is
about, you know, how long, you know, the interarrival t, which happened is probability P of t. And
then you square coefficient of variance, which is sigma square by the mean square. Okay.
So I'm not going to derive this to you. I'm going to derive something more interesting
to you. This you are supposed to know from some of your previous classes, you know, if
not, this is just the formula you can write on your cheat sheet. But typically we are going
to give you, if I am going to, we are going to ask you in a problem. But the most important
things here is to look at the value of C. The C captures the burstiness, it turns out.
So if C is zero, there is no variance. This also means the variance is zero square, square
of standard deviation, which means that you have the interarrival between two events,
between two requests is the same. Then if C is one, this means that you have exponential
distribution. It's a memoryless distribution, completely random, doesn't depend on the past.
If C is 1.5, you have even a burstier distributions, the majority of C, say, for instance, or the
majority of the interarrival times are much smaller than the average. So the more C increases,
the more bursty you have the distribution, meaning a lot of events coming, a lot of requests
coming together and then long gaps. And obviously the more burstiness you have, the larger the
queue will be, at least during these events. If there is no variance and if your furlough
is lower than the service capacity, then you have no queues.
So let's talk more about queuing theory. And the queuing theory is very simple. You have
to make some assumption about the distributions. You have to make some assumptions about how
long it takes to serve the request. What is the distribution to serve a request? What
is the distribution of arrivals? And based on this, then you are going to get some formula
which will give you the service response time and the queuing delay. That's what it is.
So before talking more about this queuing and giving you those formulas about response
time and everything, let's go through this little law. And it's a very powerful law.
It's very simple, deceptive simple and very general. And this is what it says. It says
you have a bunch of arrivals and which are served by a system, a bunch of requests coming
to a system, they are serving the system. And you know what is the average mean of,
what is the average arrivals for the request and what is the average service for the request.
And what little law is giving you is how many on the average, how many requests are waiting
in the queue to be served. That's all. And the formula is a number of requests. Here
I pick jobs. It's equal to the mean arrival time, lambdas, time, the response time, mean
response time. Okay. So this is what it is. That's it. And the beauty of it is that this
is true regardless of the structure of the arrivals. How what is a burst doesn't depend
on the distribution. Doesn't depend on the distribution of the arrival, doesn't depend
on the distribution of the service time because the results holds for the means. Right. It
does assume though that the arrivals are not larger. The arrival rate is not larger than
mean arrival rate is not larger than the mean service rate. And here is an example just
to give you the, to capture that intuition. On X you have times, and let's say you have
a new job or request for some reason here, you know, I put jobs coming to the system
and being serviced. And you have one job every second. So this is deterministic arrival.
Every second you have a new job, exactly every second. Any job takes to serve five seconds.
Right. This is what you have, right? You have the first job starts here, you serve five
seconds. The second job starts, serve five seconds and so forth. So now how many of the
jobs you have in the system? At any given time, you can draw a line and the number of
jobs you have in the system, it's the number of jobs this line is going to intersect. And
how many have? Five. Right. And what is the formula saying? Number of jobs, average number
of jobs in the system is equal with average or the mean arrival rate, which was one times
the mean service response time, which is five. So it's five. Okay. So let's, let me try to
derive this formula for you. Okay. So let's talk, let's say now we are going to be general,
right? The jobs can arrive at any time. They can take any amount of time to be, to be,
they are going to be in the system and yeah. So let's talk L of I is the response time
of job I and N of T is a number of jobs in the system at time T. Right? So this is N
of T at this particular time. So you want to see what is the system occupancy? How many
on the average? What is the number of jobs in the system? This N, the average of N of
This is what you want to compute. The average of N of T. OK.
So before, so this is the remember is what I want to get.
Now, let's do some a little bit of math. Let's assume for simplicity that the height
of one of these things, jobs, which I represent here, it's one.
OK, so really the N of T represents the height of this shape, right, the blue shape.
So in this case, the height is four, so you have four jobs in the system. Right.
Now, the area of each of these boxes is what? It's I of I, it's I of I, the length,
it's how long it takes the job response time for that particular job I times one,
because we said that by convention, we say that the height is one. So the area S is S1,
the total area here for this all the jobs within the time capital T is S1 plus S2 plus say SK.
It's and it's equal to is L1 plus L2 plus LK because SI is equal to is LI times one,
which is equal to is LI. And why do I do this? Right. Now, what I want to compute is to remember
that average fuel occupancy is what it is. It's this area over T. Right. This is what I'm doing.
I have this shape, which I have this area, and I need to divide on the length of the area,
which is T in this case, to get to the average height of the area. Right. The N average,
the average number of jobs in the system is the average height of the shape, which is S over T.
Right. But now we know that S is L of one plus L of two plus L of K over D now. And now the
beauty of it, I need to do only the one thing. I need to divide by N total and multiply with N
total. Right. And N total is a total number of jobs which arrived during this time T
and are serviced during this time T. Right. So it's the same equation, the equation from the
previous one, but I'm going to divide by N total and I'm now going to multiply by N total. N total
in this example, it will be K. Right. Because it's what I showed here, like K. Right. But now
I just reverted one, but it's the same thing. It's N total over T plus L1 plus LK over N total.
But here is a thing right now. What is N total over T?
So I have N total jobs arriving during time T. So N total over T, it's an average,
it's how many, it's N total over T, it's arrival rate.
I mean arrival rate. If I tell you, I have 100 jobs and they arrived in 10 seconds. Right. And
I ask you, what is the arrival rate? What do you do? You say 100 over 10 seconds. Oh, it's 10 jobs
per second. This is Lambda. And what is L1 plus LK over N total?
L1 is the average response time for first job.
L2 is the average response time of the second job. If I add all these jobs up, the response
time of all the jobs, if I sum up the average response time of all jobs and I divide by the
number of jobs, what do I get? The average response time. So here you are. The average
occupancy or the average number of jobs in the system is equal with the average arrival rate
of these jobs plus times, sorry, the average response time of a job. Make sense? Any questions?
Okay. So again, I want to emphasize like this is a great,
very elegant law and because it's so simple and yet is so general. It doesn't make any
assumption of distributions. You need only to know the average arrival rate and average response time.
Okay.
Any questions?
Okay. So now let's do a little bit of queuing theory and unfortunately, and I apologize here,
I am going to give you some results. I'm not going to derive anymore. So hopefully you enjoyed
the previous derivation. But let's talk a little bit about that, about this to give you some,
you know, queuing results, queuing theory results. First of all, like I mentioned,
here we only assume that the system is what you call in a queue level, which is
basically the number, the arrival rate is not larger, is no larger than the service side.
We also assume that the queue has no limits. So therefore we don't drop requests.
Okay. Let's assume that the time between two arrivals is random and is memoryless,
it's exponentially distributed. When the time, inter-arrival time between
successive requests, it's exponentially distributed. We are saying that that arrival
is for us all, by the way, if you hear that. So arrival rate, Lambda, service rate is Mu,
one over the T service. This is a TS. Previously, it was denoted by TS, it's a time to serve
the request. Okay. So you have Lambda, mean number of arriving, request, customer, jobs per second,
mean time to serve the customer, it's say M, square coefficient of variance, this is one,
in the case, remember, in the case of exponential distribution, Mu is a service rate, you know that,
one of the TS, time to service that request. Utilization, again, you know that,
your SOSA formula is a number, is arrival rate over the mean arrival rate over mean service rate.
Which is Lambda over Mu or Lambda time deserve, right? Here, I just
replace the Mu definition, which is one of the service time. Now, and if you do that,
you get the utilization, it's arrival rate times the service time, I mean service time.
What do you want to compute? Time spent in the queue, that's what I want to compute.
We also want to compute the length of the queue, which is, what is the length of the queue?
The length of the queue is Lambda of TQ, right? Because the system here is a queue,
this is what I'm saying, the system here is a queue, right? So you can apply little,
low to the queue itself, or you can apply to the entire system. Here is for the queue itself.
Okay, so let's see. Like I said, when you have exponential distribution for the arrival rate,
inter-arrival rates for the requests, this is also called Poisson arrival process.
We assume here that we have one server, right? We can have a, there are scenarios in which you have
multiple servers and you send the request to, if one server accepts a request, you can send
the request to another server. And it's memoryless service, so again, let's assume that the service
distribution is also exponential, so it's memoryless.
So this system, which Poisson arrival process, memoryless service time,
and one server is called MM1Q.
It's again, one server, inter-arrival times are exponentially distributed, service time
are exponentially distributed. And in this case, the queuing time, it's equal with the service time
times U over one minus U, where U is the utilization.
Now for general distribution, if you have the service distribution, so if the service time is
a general distribution and you know for that one only the variance, the square root of variance,
the C, then this is a formula. It's very similar formula. It's
one over, let me just move the, it's service time times one over two plus one plus C,
this is again square root of, square of variance, times one over one minus U.
Okay, so the important takeaway from this equation, it's a very important aspect here,
is this fact, this is one over one minus U. Why is this important? Because this tells you
when the utilization is small, this factor is small, right? It's
basically U over one if U is very small. But what happens when the utilization approaches one,
which is equivalent with a service rate, arrival rate approaching the service rate, what happens?
It gets very large, the Q becomes very large. So another important aspect here is,
and this is food for thought, is something which is not intuitive either.
If U goes close to one, although it's not yet one, the queuing time grows to infinity.
And then we ask, well, but hey, wait a minute. If U is one, we should be fine,
because the arrival rate is not greater than the service rate. But if U is one,
the queuing is infinity. Why is that?
We'll talk more next lecture and you are not going to be asked this during the exam.
But if the system is very bursty, there can be gaps.
And during these gaps, there is nothing in system.
And you lose that time, you lost, you never comes back. Because the bursts you are going to get in
the future are going to, then if you eliminate that gap, the number of arrival you are going
to get in the future is going to be greater than the server capacity. Right?
So because this kind of this gaps where the system doesn't get,
doesn't do anything, when you have a very bursty arrival,
this is a wasted time, it's a wasted capacity. So that capacity you cannot get back.
So that's why you can... you fall behind in terms of capacity and you remain always behind.
Okay, so it's... I'm trying to give you an intuition, so it's like...
it's not easy to get the intuition and... but this is good.
Okay. What else I wanted to say here? Oh, by the way, you notice that for the general service time
distribution, the formula for the queuing delay, if exponential... you remember for exponential
distribution, what was C? One. So if C is one, the equation, the queuing time for the general service
distribution is going to reduce to the formula which you should expect for the exponential
distribution. Let's take now simple examples and then we are going to conclude the lectures.
Let's say the user request, you have 10 requests of... you want 8 kilobytes disk,
write 10 requests of each for 8 kilobytes data, and the request and the service are exponentially
distributed. Average service is 20 milliseconds and this is controller six times, rotation, latency,
and transfer time. And how you utilize this is a disk, right? So utilization, this is a formula,
remember, it's lambda times the service time, these are the formula. Average time to spend in
the queue to queue, average number of requests in the queue. Now this is LQ denoted here. What is
the average response time for disk request? So this is the average response time. It's very simple
that the sum between the time you spend in the queue and time to serve is a request.
Okay, so let's do the computation. Lambda, you have 10 requests of 8 kilobytes disk per second.
So lambda, you have average arriving number of customers or request is 10 per second. Average
time to service a customer or request 10 milliseconds. It was given here, if you remember,
this is one average service time. Server utilization is lambda times the service time
is 0.2. Queuing time, now you are going to apply because everything gets exponentially distributed.
Then you use a formula, which is a TS, service time times utilization over one minus utilization,
and you get five milliseconds. Average length of the queue is lambda times TQ is 0.05.
And average time the customer spend in the system is a queuing time plus the service time
service to 20 milliseconds plus 5 milliseconds. Here is 25 milliseconds.
There are a lot of materials here. You have some pointers if you are interested more in the
queuing theory. It's great. This is a fair game. This is a mistake. You are going to get this in
midterm 2, not 3. Sorry for the typo. So this lecture is included for midterm 2. And with that,
I am done. So in summary, and remember about, we look at this, how we are going to model the
systems. And these systems are modeled, they have a queue. And you spend some time in the queue,
plus have a fixed overhead, like rotation latency and so forth, and you have a transfer.
Then this will impact the effective bandwidth. Effective bandwidth is not like the device
bandwidth because of this fixed overhead. Then we learn a little bit about this queuing theory.
And in particular, I gave you the formulas for the queuing delay for MM1 queues, everything is
exponentially distributed, interarrival time and the service time. And MG1 queue arrival times are
still interarrival time, are still exponentially distributed, but the service time has a general
distribution. And remember, this is a formula for the queuing time for the general distribution of
the service time. And remember that in both cases, both MM1 and MG1 queues, when the utilization
approaches one, then the latency goes to infinity, the queuing delay and therefore the response time
goes to infinity. So I'm stopping here. Good luck to at the midterm and really good luck for the
next week. If you have any questions, please don't hesitate to ask on Piazza. And yeah, I'll see you
next week.