Welcome everyone to the second lecture. Today we are going to learn about the four fundamental
OS operating system concepts. And as always, please ask your questions on Q&A channel.
I will stop from time to time to read the questions and answer them. First, let me start
with some announcements. So I will have for now one office hours on Mondays between noon
and 1 PM. And there is more demand, I'm going to add more office hours. Of course, next
Monday is no office hours. Actually, that should be Monday, not Wednesday. It won't
be an office hour on Memorial Day. And we will add, it will be office hour will be via
Zoom. And I will add the link to the Zoom on the class webpage.
Just a reminder that the drop deadline is this Friday, early drop deadline. Please,
if you are thinking about dropping this class, do it right away because this will let other
people from the waiting list to enroll in the class. Finally, please, after the drop
deadline, start to sign up for the groups. Remember, we ask you to have four people in
a group and try that all people to attend either the same sections, this is preferable,
or maybe if that's not possible, if there are two sections taught by the same TA. This
is in order to have consistent feedback for your projects during the semester.
Yes, there are some, again, there are some quick questions on the chat. Please ask question
on the Q&A channel, not on the chat, but now one question is, are we going to have today's
lecture slides posted to Piazza due to website being down? Well, hopefully the website will
come back up, but yes, we can post them on Piazza. And a second question is when will
the TAI section preferences form will be released? I'm not sure any TA, head TA, Eduardo, if you
are here, please answer this question. If not, Alan, you ask this question, please also
post it on Piazza and we'll get the answer there.
What do I mean two section by the same TA? So what I mean here is that if not all people,
if there are TAs, there will be TAs or some of the TAs have two sections. So if not all
of you in the same group can go to the same section, pick two sections which are taught
by the same TA. Will the class expand to get all the people on the wait list? This class,
again, although it's online, it's limited because of TA resources and the staff of the
class doesn't actually have any kind of, you know, it's not, we do not decide who we're
going to get from the wait list, who is going to get enrolled in the class. This is a department
decision. So please ask them. We can't do much about it. When I say we, I refer to the
staff of the class, myself and the TAs and the leaders.
Okay, let's move on. So, and last thing I want to say is that please avoid private Piazza
posts because in many cases you are not the only one to have a question. Many other people
will have the same questions. Of course, if it's a personal questions, you should use
a private Piazza post, but otherwise please try as much as possible not to use it.
Okay, so let's go and start with a lecture. So what is an operating system? We discussed
a little bit last time during the last lecture. And this is one slide from the last lecture,
basically saying that, you know, the operating system is a software layer we see between
hardware and the applications. Okay. And it implements and provides to the application
a bunch of very useful functionality, provides easy, convenient abstraction to the applications.
So make it much easier to write the applications and using the raw hardware, protect access
of between the application and between the application and the operating system to the
shared resources, provide security and authentication and provide communication among logical entities.
And if you remember, you also have this slide which basically says about how you can look
at the operating system between, you know, based on the functionality it provides, on
a certain functionality it provides. So in one way, one way to look at is like a illusionist.
And this is when the operating system magically abstracts the hardware to the application
and it provides a illusion that the application use a dedicated machine with an infinite memory
and has access to all the files and other resources on the same dedicated machines.
Okay. So that's a very convenient abstraction for the users and for the application developer.
In reality, an application, sorry, the system, the hardware is shared between multiple applications
and multiple users. So therefore you need to arbitrate the access of the resources,
the shared resources between these applications. And this is when the operating system plays
a role of the referee. Okay. So it needs to provide isolation between the processes and
the applications. And you need to protect one process from another and the operating
system from processes. And finally, this application and these processes often to implement more
sophisticated functionality, they need to communicate with each other. They need to
share resources and they need to use the same services. And this, the role of the operating
system to provide the services, you can think about providing the glue, which keep together
and make this application to work together. So it provides a storage, right? Which can
be used by every application. It provides a window system and it provides networking,
which helps the applications communicate with each other. Okay. So that's pretty much where
we are. And next, let me just stop here to see whether there are any other questions.
No new questions. Yeah. Okay. So let's go a little bit through the operating system
history. Again, the operating system abstracting away the hardware and making the job of the
application developer easier, making it much easier to develop this application. This was
from very early on since the first computers have been developed. Okay. And there are several
distinct phases. The first phase, which I alluded last time, is that when hardware was
very expensive and humans are cheap. So this picture shows a room, you see a pretty large
room. Well, that's the room which hosted the entire computer, right? You need a big room,
almost like a warehouse room to host the entire computer, right? These are extremely expensive.
These fairly early computers, maybe you heard about like ENIAC in '50s, millions or tens
of millions of dollars in today's money. And then this was a age in which you have very
expensive computers and humans are relatively cheap, right? So what means that is that you
want to optimize, to use very efficiently the computer and you don't want to necessarily
to optimize the time of the humans because they are cheap, remember, right? So if they
need to, humans need to spend more time to optimize their programs and to make the hardware
usage more efficient, then so be it. It's perfectly fine. And this was again the age
when Thomas Watson, the founder and chairman of IBM in 1943 was saying that, "I think there
is a world market for maybe five computers." So, and Thomas Watson also called the world
market greatest salesman by the time of his death in '56.
Then the next big stage is in '80s, '70s and '80s, and it's the rise of the personal computer,
right? In mid '70s, when the first Apple was released, I think it was '76, and then you
have IBM PCs and compatible computers being released. And this was when hardware was becoming
cheaper and human more expensive. Now everyone was having access wanted to a computer and
you have a computer on every desk in every home. That was the vision of Bill Gates, the
founder of Microsoft. And finally, we are today when the hardware
is really cheap and humans are really expensive. And here we are talking about, you have not
only about your phone or tablet or your PCs, but we are talking about more and more of
devices around you. They have processors, your TV, your thermo type, your car, and each
of these platforms and devices, they do have an operating system on which you implement
or developers implement specialized application to control your thermostat, your TV and so
forth. The other thing, what happens, and we'll see that this kind of different phases
led to different requirements on the operating systems. The other thing is also was driven
and also these distinct phases is by the hardware becoming more and more plentiful, faster,
and faster, and cheaper, and cheaper. This led to from computers who are hosted in one
huge room to computers, which can be on your watch. And so this led, for instance, in the
early days of the big computers, the main way to use them was batch processing. And
what batch processing means is that you put your job in a queue. You went there to some
punch cards on which you write your program and you give the program to the operators
and you come the next day to get the results. This is what we mean is that the time of the
program was not that important then because it was cheap and the computer time was very
expensive. So you want to have very high utilization and one way to have high utilization is that
always you have a program to run. So you have a queue of programs which are submitted and
you run it one by one and then you are going to get the results when it's finished. It
takes hours for it to run, sometimes days. Then it's going to be multi-programming and
the multi-programming means now you have, they are a little bit cheaper and then you
want to start to use the computers in a more interactive way. And multi-programming means
now that instead of one program at a time, you have multiple programs running at the
same time. You have that one. So the time you wait for the program to finish can be
reduced. And then it's time sharing, which now you are using the computer in a more interactive
way. You have terminals which are connected to the computer. And in that case, the computer
wait after the human to type in, to write the program and then to execute the program.
And then you have obviously the personal computers where you have a computer dedicated per human.
And in that case, the computer now is idle 99% of the time because it's waiting for you
for the humans to take some action. So for the computer to respond and so forth. And
then ubiquitous devices are obviously the devices I mentioned for you, like your thermostat
and devices in your car and things like that. The operating system is a huge variety of
operating systems in terms of complexity. You can imagine that the operating system
to control on your thermostat is probably much simpler than operating system to control
a supercomputer. And a small OS can be just have hundreds of lines of code while larger
ones can have tens of millions lines of code. And they are very, very expensive to develop.
And because of the cost of development OS from scratch, it's very high. Actually, most
modern operating system have a long lineage. You can trace back the lineage long, long
tens of years, decades ago. So they are in linear. So therefore, the operating system
from today are some improved version of some very old operating systems. So this is one
lineage which is mostly extinct now. This was from Multics. It's one of the most, the
first operating system which was multitasking, multiprogrammed and time shared. And this
is an ancestor of Unix. And this is then you have AT&T Unix, Berkeley, BSD Unix, Altrich,
SunOS and BSD. Then you have actually from Mac, this is a micro channel we are going
to learn a little bit about it. This was developed by Carnegie Mellon University in the '90s.
And this is plus Unix BSD. You see it here up. So this is Berkeley Standard Distribution.
This is what BSD stands for. Then this source used to develop Nextstep. I'm not sure how
many people heard about Nextstep. This was a company that Steve Jobs founded after he
was pushed out from Apple the first time around. And eventually Nextstep was acquired by Apple,
I think in 1997. And this is how Steve Jobs came back to Apple. And then like they say,
there is this history. And this now is Nextstep is at the basis of Apple OS X and iPhone iOS.
Okay. So then is this other lineage from Linux, Linux. This was developed by Andrew Tannenbaum
from Rije University or Free University in Amsterdam. Again, I think in '80s. And this
is lineage then Linux and Android operating system and many flavor of Linux you know and
you use today. And then finally this lineage from, again, this is operating system developed
for home computers very early on. This is first on the CPM, again in '70s. And this
is then evolves to MS-DOS. This is Microsoft DOS. This is Microsoft first operating system.
And the reason for why Microsoft is a company which is today. And then Windows. So this
is a Microsoft lineage, Microsoft operating system lineage. Okay. So it's again, a very
few obviously, all the operating system you are going to work today, you can track down
back to probably two or three ancient operating systems. Okay. So here is a question. What
are examples of?
tasks that computers will be used for in the batch scenarios. So even today, even some
of the separate computers, which are again very expensive today, they are using the batch
mode. So for instance, today you can submit a job which perform a very expensive simulation,
fluid dynamics, for instance, you want to simulate airplane engine, or you can submit a batch
to process some huge amount of data, which will take hours. So these are some examples
of batch scenarios.
Okay. So this is another figure by basically showing how in time, some of the you have
on the x-axis is at time and then on the y-axis going from very large mainframes or very large
computers to handheld and ubiquitous devices. And you can see here also showing you different
functionality provided by the operating systems and the progression of the operating system
here from Multics to Unix.
Okay. So the main thing we are going to learn in this lecture is these four fundamental
operating system concepts. And we alluded to them in the last lecture, but now we are
going to go in more depth. The first one is Thread. This provides you execution context.
It fully describes the program state, which means it's all the state which is needed to
run the program. Then is Address Space. The address space is the program, the set of addresses,
memory addresses within which the program executes. The code of the program has to be
stored in memory. The data of the program is going to be stored in memory. The output
has to be stored in memory.
Then is a Process. So a process is basically consisting of this address space and a thread,
right? So it consists of all the resources which are required by a program and all the
state which is required by the program to run.
And finally, the Dual Mode Operation and Protection. And this is refers about how is your operating
system co-exist on the same hardware with the processes and how is your operating system
protecting, protective from the processes, right? Because the user processes, if there
is no such protection, it can change the state of the operating system. The operating system
can crash. So everything halts, right? So how you are going to avoid that?
So let's look a little bit about all the journey from writing the program to executing the
program. So as you know, you are writing the program, which is you already wrote many programs
by now. So you edit the program using your editor, Emacs or your favorite editor or PyCharm
or Visual Code or things like that. Then you compile the code and as the code is interpreted
like Python. But if you have C code, as you know, you compile it and you get an executable,
which is a code. Executable contains a code which can be interpreted and it can be around
by the processors. The processors understands, right? And now this executable is loaded in
the memory of the computer and then it's executed. But when it's loaded in memory, there are
several segments of the memory or several partitions of the memory where different kinds
of data is stored. One part is where you keep the partitions. One partition is where you
keep the code, the instructions of the program. Then you have where you keep the data and
the data you statically defined. For instance, you say, and when you create an array or variables,
and you see static. Then hip is where you define and you create dynamic data structures.
Like for instance, this is when you allocate memory. When you allocate memory, this happens
as a runtime after the program starts executed. And therefore, the heap is going to change
during the runtime, depending on how much dynamic memory you are allocating for your
dynamic data structures. Finally, you have a stack. The stack is used and it's used for
instance, to store the variables you are going to declare within a function. And it's also
used to store the return address when you call a function. After the function is done,
you need to know where you go back in the program. Again, we'll discuss a lot more about
each of these different types of data and memory. And finally here you have the operating
system memory. So that's pretty much it. Let me stop and see. Okay. No new questions. Please
again, keep the question coming. Great. So how do you execute the program? If you remember,
and this is from 61c, if you remember, you basically have a bunch of instructions which
are in memory, and then you have a program counter called SoPC, which point out to the
current instruction being executed from memory. So what happens when you take the instruction,
you fetch the instruction, which is pointed to by the program counter, and then this instruction
is decoded and then it's executed. And this is basically down here, you see the processor,
like a core. And a core typically consists from an Alu arithmetic logic unit, which performs
the operation addition, subtraction, and things like that. And a bunch of registers, what
are the arguments of these operations in many cases. And registers are very fast to address
because they are very, very low latency. And then after you execute an instruction, the
program counter is incremented and you are going to the next instruction. So very simple.
So this is another view here about on the right hand side, you are going to have the
memory with a bunch of instructions and a bunch of data. And on the left hand side,
you have what is a processor, which is fetching the instruction and execute the instruction.
And there you have on the left hand side, a bunch of registers R0 to R31. And you have
another set of register from F0 to F30. The difference typically between the set of register
because the second set of register is for floating point operations. The R0 to R31 typically
are for fixed point operations. And then you have the program counter. So it's again, you
fetch the instruction as a program counter, you decode it, you execute it possibly using
the registers. Some of the argument of the instruction can be addressed in memory and
write the results to the registers or memory. And then you go to the next instruction. Okay.
And repeat. Okay. So let me see the questions. The question is there one program counter
per thread. The program counter is typically a register in the processor. So it's typically
only one program counter. It's maybe two if you have a user program counter, but it's
one. What happens, and we are going to see later in this lecture that when you are going
to do context switching, what is called when you go to another to start executing a thread,
the first action you do, you take is to load the program counter, which is say somewhere
in memory, the current program counter of the thread corresponding to the thread into
the processor program counter. Right. So, but the program counter from the processor
point of view, it's only one, it's not per thread. So, okay. Let me just. So the thread
of control, again, this contains a state required to run the program. Right. So what does it
mean? It's basically, it contains, sorry. It contains a program counter and then it contains
also pointers to where all these other kinds of regions in memory start. Like for instance,
it contains the, for the stack pointer, the stack pointer, it's basically where is a stack
starts from. It contains a heap pointer, it's an address from the where the heap starts
growing. And so, and it contains also what it's in registers, right? Because the state
in the registers is used by the instructions. And a thread is executing, like I mentioned
earlier, when it's resident on the processor, when the state is, the thread state is loaded
in the processor. PC Regis program counter holds the address of the executing instruction
in the thread and again, register holds some of the root state of the thread. It's called
the root state. Okay. So that's kind of what the thread is about. So all the state which
is needed to execute that program. Program counter, state of the registers, heap pointer,
stack pointers, and a few others. Now the address space is basically the memory addresses
or the memory regions where the data and the code of the programs are stored. Okay. The
addresses are typically it's the size of the memory addressable memory, which is very important
of the size of the memory. The size of the addressable memory is given by the number
of bits of the processor typically. So if you have a 30 bits processor, there are two
power 32 or 4 billion addresses, which means four megabytes of memory. If it's byte addressable,
if it's 64 bits, it's two power 64, which is a huge amount of memory. Okay. This is
addressable memory. Like we are going to see, this is different from the physical memory.
The physical memory can be smaller and typically smaller than the addressable memory. But then
you are going to have a process you are going to learn in school of virtualization and address
translation. We are going to even talk about this lecture, which is going to create you
the image and the illusion that you have access to the entire addressable memory in a smaller
physical memory. Okay. And of course, what happens when you read or write to an address,
maybe nothing or you act like a regular memory. A regular memory means that you read the value
from that memory and you write the value to that memory. Perhaps you can ignore writes.
For instance, if your process is writing to an address which doesn't belong to that process,
then maybe it's going to be ignored. Or maybe it causes IO operations. So as you'll see,
there are memory mapped input output designs and architectures in which, for instance,
if you want to communicate to a device like a keyboard, you want to read from a keyboard
or you want to communicate to the printer, there are certain predefined memory addresses
where you have to write. For instance, it's a predefined memory address you read from
and that's what you are going to get the input from the keyboard. There is another predefined
memory address or a range of addresses where you can write and that data is going to the
printer. Or perhaps it causes an exception, like an example I gave to you earlier on when
you are going to write to a data to an address which doesn't belong to you or say to the
address owned by the operating system. It can be ignored, but in many cases you get
a segmentation fault. You cannot cause an exception. And one exception, the offending
program is going to basically stop, crash. So again, you have a bunch of region or segment.
You have the code segment. The code segment I already mentioned to you contains the instruction
of the program. You have the stack segment. I told you how, again, earlier what it contains,
it can contains the variable you are going to declare within a function and also the
return addresses from a function. And the stack grows from high to low. So grows, so
to speak, downwards. And because you add, when you call a function, you add things on
the stack. And then you have the heap, which is for dynamic data. When you allocate data
during the program execution and you're growing from low level of low addresses to high addresses.
So let's see, there are some questions here. Where does the OS save all the state and the
registered values when changing a task? So it's a threat control block PCB. This is where
it says it stores. So you have a data structure which associated on each thread and which
is managed by the operating system. And in that block or region, you save all the state
associated with the thread. So when we say that the process has a virtual address space
zero to FF, it doesn't imply that it has free reign to write to those services. Absolutely.
Well let me, sorry. Let me, there are two views of the memory. And again, this is very
important to, and this is about virtualization. It's about creating the illusion. It's a memory,
it's a physical memory and the physical memory is partitioned between different processes.
Okay. Now there is also what the illusion actually of the process, the illusion of the
process is that it has an address from zero, zero to FF. It has an entire address space.
And the application in principle can write at any of these addresses. Okay. And, but
typically the operating system takes care for, so that the application does a shooting
its foot, right? For instance, you cannot write on the stack because if you can't write
on the stack, the program will crash, right? So the operating system will impose some restrictions.
So you don't have a free reign. You do see the entire address space. Again, you don't
have free reign, but I just want to, and to plant the seed now, and we are going to do
this, to say this over and over, because there are two views of the memory. You have physical
memory, which is partitioned between different applications. You have data code from different
applications residing in the physical memory at the same time. And then you have the virtual
memory, which is basically what is presented to the application. And there you create the
illusion that each application, each process has access to the full address space with
some constraints, like I explained. Okay. So, okay. So, so here is exactly what I mentioned
earlier about the physical memory. So you see on the right hand side, you have the physical
memory.
memory, as you can see, you have, and on the left hand side, you have the operating system
with N processes, green, yellow, orange. So now in the physical memory, you can see that you have
instructions, the code and data from different processes. And they are all residing in the same
physical memory. And each of these processing is only going to see only its own data. They
shouldn't see the other process data. So now what is the multi-programming about? Multi-programming
about is about having different processes, like I said earlier, earlier I said about jobs, but
the process is the same thing. You have different processes running and running at the same time.
On the same, on a single machine. And now how do you give the illusion? Because the operating
system provides the illusion that despite you have different processes running at the same time,
on the same hardware, each process believes that it is allowed. And the only way you can give that,
you have to share, you have to multiplex the resources. And there are multiple resources. One
is the CPU. And if you have a single processor, how do you provide illusion of having multiple
processors, one for each processor? Well, as we discussed last time, you split the processors in
time quanta or time slices. And we give a time quanta or a time slice to a different process.
So say it's 10 milliseconds, the time slice is 10 milliseconds, for 10 milliseconds you run process
one, then we switch for the next 10 milliseconds to process two, for the next 10 milliseconds to
process three, and then come back to process one. This is one way to do it. So you multiplex it in
time. And each, this kind of virtual CPU needs to hold this program counter, stack pointer,
registers, and things like that. So this is a state which is associated with the thread.
And because when you run something on this virtual CPUs, it's a thread.
And obviously the question now is about how you switch from a virtual CPU to the next one.
This is what you do. You save the state of the virtual CPUs and here running the state of the
virtual CPU is the same as a state of the thread running on that virtual CPU, in that time slice.
And you load the state for the next virtual CPU or the next thread you are going to execute.
And then you execute, you run the next thread. So it's again, just only to make sure here,
since I'm not confusing, you have only one CPU and in this particular case, and you want to
multiplex it. So you are going to multiplex it in time. And therefore each process is provided with
the illusion that it owns a processor albeit a slower processor. And by virtual CPU here, we mean
that time partition part of the CPU, which is kind of owned by a particular process.
Right? And when you, from the process, when you have each process, if you remember has a thread
and will again repeat that soon. And that thread is a part which is running on the processor
or the virtual CPU. Okay. Let me, you said a program can write on the stack, but when you
write assembly, we often move the stack pointer and write. Yes, that's true. So basically you
said a program can write on the stack, but when you write assembly, you often move the stack
pointer and drive to the stack and you are a bit confused. So when you write an assembly,
you don't go through the compiler. So you don't have anyone to put any kind of constraints of what
you are going to do. So you can indeed do almost everything. You also need to, so you need to do
that. But when you write a typical program, like in high-level languages, you compile it and the
compiler is going to put additional constraints about what you can do. Who's the program knows
that the CPU is time-partitioned? No. In general, no. What is exactly slower when in reality it is
multiplex? What I mean slower is, when I mean slower, I mean, imagine that you have a CPU
and it's, and if the CPU is partitioned between two processes, then each process and each process
will alternatively use a 10 millisecond, run for 10 milliseconds. This means that each process will
see a processor, which is half the speed of the original processor. Right? Because for instance,
out of one second, each process will use a CPU only for 500 milliseconds. Okay? So it's
half slow, as slow as the real CPU. What is done differently for context switching between
strength of the same process versus different processes? Oh, this again, this is probably too
early. We'll learn a lot, but you know. So in short, the answer here is that
when you change, when you switch, do context switching between the thread, you only need to
switch, context switch is a state of the thread, which is a bunch of registers and pointers.
It's very light. When you are going to switch between different processes, you need also to
switch the state about all the resources. For instance, memories, there is a memory table
to ensure the translation between these virtual address space and physical address space.
There is a file descriptors. So it's a lot of more state you need to switch when you switch
between processes. Where are the state blocks stored? So, the thread control blocks or all
the state is stored, is stored in the operating system, by the operating system and managed by
the operating system. Isn't there overhead with switching from one virtual CPU to another?
Yes, absolutely. There is an overhead when switching from one virtual CPUs to another,
because we need to save in those states like the person who asked the question correctly
identified. Is it just necessary inefficiency we accept in order to multiplex? Yes, it is.
How about those programs that are time sensitive? Well,
when the programs are time sensitive, typically you may have an operating system which has real
time support. In these operating systems, you can specify by when a particular task should be
executed and they are going to ensure that that task will be executed by that time. Or you can,
other ways you can specify in the operating system will guarantee that you are going to get a minimum
share of the CPU. So, if you get a minimum share of the CPU, then presumably you are guaranteed
that you can finish some of the operations or your operations in time.
For instance, this is a continuation. This is a question from Yufeng. For example, some programs
receive data from network. Wouldn't context switching the program during the transmission
cause trouble? No, well, it's the other way around. Actually, when you get something from
the network, there is an interrupt and you are going to interrupt the processes, which are
actually application processes, which are actually running. And then after you do the work, you get
the data, you return from the interrupt and you are going to continue the processes. Typically,
so it's a little bit the other way around. It's not like a process interrupt the transmission
or receiving data. Where is the current start block information being stored for each virtual
CPU? Like I mentioned, this is in the operating system. Following up on the assembly, giving you
free-running questions, are segmentation faults a C-Sync or will you also be prohibitive on the
assembly level? Yeah, the segmentation faults are the C-Sync. It's like an assembly level
because it gives you a lot of more flexibility. We see you can write all over the place. But again,
when you have, like for instance, if you run Java or things like that, you cannot do it.
And this is enforced by your compilers. It can be type, if you probably heard about being type
safety, type safe. So then they verify that actually when you write the program, you cannot,
for instance, overwrite on the stack, write on the stack. So in short answer, assembly language,
C language, you can do it. Higher level languages, you cannot do it. The compilers will take care of
that. What is the state block? Maybe if I say state block, this is not the correct term,
it's a thread control block and this process control block. And this is again, the state
control block contains all the state which is associated with a particular thread, program
counters, stack pointer and registers. What was the difference between a thread
control block and process control block? Well, like I mentioned, the process control block
has all the state associated with the resources associated with that process.
Like file descriptors and base translation information and things like that.
Okay, let's move on. But thanks for the question, this is great.
And if I don't answer a particular question, you can repeat it. Feel free.
Okay, so let me see. Now, when you have multiple processes running on the same hardware,
you need to multiply the hardware and the basic problem is what is called this concurrency.
And concurrency meaning, again, multiple processes wanting to access the same hardware.
Okay. And because you want to multiplex single CPU, memory, IO devices and things like that.
And remember, again, the role of the operating system at the same time is to provide the illusion
that each of these processes own a single machine. It's the only one executing on the machine.
So the operating system is in charge to arbitrate, to coordinate, to manage all these concurrent
activities while providing this single machine abstraction to the processes. Okay. So that's
kind of hard. So one of the main abstraction and okay, so one of the main resources needs to be
multiplexed is a memory, is a physical memory. And the way this is done, it's using the concepts of
virtual memory and we can extend that concept to the machine, right, to the entire machine.
So what we call when I said that we provide the illusion to a process that it owns
is dedicated machine, that machine is called virtual machine,
or we also refer to it as a virtual machine. Okay.
And then the question then it's about how to multiplex these virtual machines.
And the virtual machine has these virtual CPUs, virtual memory, and so forth.
The first system doing this was the system, short and interesting name,
and really was a few thousand lines of code. The OS 360, which arguably was one of the first and
probably the first successful commercial operating system created by IBM was having at that time,
1 million lines of code, which was huge. Today, probably you have Windows has tens of millions
lines of code or even more. And it's again, this just show you another data point about
how complex this operating system grew over time. And this is a funny thing, right? It's like
probably the number of bugs in OS 360 were probably the same or larger than the number
of lines of code in the system. Okay. So, now what are some of the consequences of sharing?
If you have only threads, the threads are going to share the same address space.
Okay. Which means that the threads can have access to the other threads data, for instance.
So they can share, but this means that they can also change the data of a different thread.
So that's very important to keep in mind. And here is a question, can a thread overwrite
operating system functions? We are not in the class to ask the class and people to answer,
but the answer here is no, because the operating system doesn't run in the same address space.
Okay. But it's again, all the threads in the same address space, they can see each other beta,
they can read each other data, they can write each other data. Okay. And actually there are
systems in the past which have this mode like Windows 3.1, which was the first really successful
Windows operating system from Microsoft and the early Macintosh operating systems. This is before
OS X, in which you have this kind of threads are in the same address space. Even more,
the operating system didn't actively share the CPU among the applications. Okay. Instead,
the application have to use this kind of common yield to relinquish the CPU so other
application can wrap. Right. So misbehaving application who never use yield can monopolize
the entire system and hang every other application. Okay. So this kind of... And so therefore,
what we want though, we want to have protection. Right. We want that we have two processes and this
is a concept of process is kind of encapsulate the protection because the thread in each process
can see each other data, can modify each other data, but threads from different processes cannot
have access to the data from the other process. Okay. Because the process contains the address
space and the address space, it's a unit of protection of the address space in the memory.
And here it's... So here again, you have two programs of two processes, the brown one and
the green one, process one and process two, and here process two shouldn't have access to the
memory of process one, shouldn't have access to the operating system memory or shouldn't have
access to the file descriptors of other processes. Okay. Typically, when they try to access
resources, they don't own a process to operating system will cause a segmentation fault and will
crash this offending process. Okay. Let me just... There are a few more questions.
How are operating system tested in development when the complexity is very high?
Well, that's why there are so few operating system being developed or new...
operating system because it's fundamentally extremely hard.
You know, it's just, you know, good software engineering practices.
You are very aggressive during unit testing, end-to-end testing and so forth.
And even so, with all of these, because they are so complex, many operating systems still
have bugs.
And I'm not sure I have that plot, but it was a plot in which you can see like, you
know, when people debug the operating system, initially you are going to have a lot of bugs.
And then after a while, the rate at which new bugs occur, it's reducing.
And it's kind of when that rate flattens, then you shield the operating system.
This doesn't mean that you have zero bugs.
It just seems that the number of bugs, it's rare enough.
So the operating system is usable.
Yeah, all the CPU's share the same resources.
Is this, yeah, I was saying, probably I misspoke there by saying the question is by saying
the all CPU share the same resources, is it referring to stress within a single process
or process sharing resources and so forth.
And I was referring at basically all threads in the same process share the same resources.
Then all processes also share the same physical resources in terms of the CPU and in terms
of physical memory.
How are address spaces allowed?
It seems inefficient to allocate large blocks or have many small blocks.
Yes, there is a big trade off here between having small blocks and large blocks.
You have what is called internal fragmentation or external fragmentation.
For instance, with large blocks, if you don't use an entire block, you allocate it, then
you waste memory and something like that.
And so, but yeah, so you need to be smart about it.
Today's operating systems allocate the memory in what is small blocks or pages which are
a few kilobytes, four kilobytes, 16 kilobytes or 32 kilobytes.
And then you have many, many of these small blocks.
Then you need to manage them efficiently.
And we are going to learn how this is done.
Ideally would application use yield when they are performing?
Absolutely.
That's a great point.
Sorry.
To read the full question, ideally would application use yield when they are performing IO operations?
Yes, that's exactly the case.
When you are going to send some data, then you can do yield because you can wait for
hours, excuse me, or when you are going to execute the yield or you can, when the interaction
on the application is interactive, like an editor, when I click on the keyboard, then
you see the characters appearing on the screen.
In that case, the editor will do yield after each time after it displays a character.
And it's going to wait for the next character to be typed in to arrive to get from the keyboard.
What does threads can share instruction mean on the previous slide?
So this means that, again, the threads are in the same address space.
And for instance, and even between processes, you can share that.
But if you have the same user, same libraries, and multiple thread user, same libraries,
you are going to have only one copy of the library, which is going to be shared by the
threads.
You are not going to have multiple copies.
Okay, so here is another picture showing the boundary, protection boundary and how the
raw resources, access to the raw resources is protected from the processes.
And like we discussed last time, and we already said a few times in this lecture, the OS operating
system isolate processes from each other.
So make sure they don't read and write data from each other.
The operating system also isolate itself from other processes.
And again, the challenge here, because all of those run on the same hardware.
This is again, some again, summary and repeating what was in the previous slide, maybe with
a little bit more details.
So the operating system has protected itself from the user programs, from the user processes.
And what does it mean?
And why is that needed?
This obviously for security, if the operating system is not protected, then it's easier
for an application to break into another application and read the confidential data or private
data.
I just mentioned about the privacy in the same example.
And the one of the main thing is reliability.
If the operating system fails, then the computer is unusable.
So the operating system, it better runs at all times.
And fairness, it's again, the operating system is the one which ensures that the processes,
different processes get a fair access to the hardware.
Program of course, like I mentioned, the operating system is to protect user programs from one
another.
And one of the primary mechanism of protections, it's translation.
And we'll see that next.
And the translation ensure that the process can only touch its own address space and cannot
touch the physical addresses of another process.
And there are a few of other mechanisms like privilege instruction, which can be only executed
by the operating system.
And there are some special registers only operating system has access to.
The third concept so far, we talk about threads, we talk about addresses.
We also talk quite a bit about processes.
This is again to make it explicit once more.
The process is basically another space plus one or more threads.
So processes allocate resources and then it has a thread, which basically is a unit of
execution.
And why do you have processes?
Because the processes protects from each other.
Threads do not protect from each other.
They share a same address space.
They share all the resources within the process.
However, threads are more efficient like we discussed.
The context switching between the thread in the same process is much quicker than between
threads in different processes.
Also communication between threads is in the same process much faster because you can use
shared memory.
You can use the address space, which is already shared between the threads to communicate
between the threads.
Between processes, you need to communicate through other means and you need to context
switch between the processes, which is far more expensive.
And typically an application consists of one or more processes, a process consists of one
or more threads.
And here you can see in this figure, on the left hand side, you see one process with a
single thread.
And you can see what belongs.
You have the process, you have the memory, address space, you have the code, data, file,
descriptors, register, stack.
So this belongs to our process.
And now on the right hand side, you have different thread in the same process.
And here you can see, notice at the top, the code and the data and the file descriptors,
all these resources are shared across all the threads in the same process.
What is not shared is the execution state of each thread.
So each thread comes with some registers, comes with some stack.
Right?
Registers includes the program counter, the stack pointer and things like that.
And the address encapsulate protection, right, it's a passive part of the process.
The thread is an active part, concurrency, encapsulate concurrency.
Why multiple threads for address space?
Yeah, too bad we cannot, it's hard to have this question answered if you have in the
class on this webinar.
But you want to have more because you want to build higher performance applications.
Like for instance, if you have an application which is doing, you have waiting from the
keyboard and they're doing some processing like rendering graphics and things like that,
and as a result of what the users, it's user's input, then you are going to have two threads
and you want this to communicate between others to send the user input to the thread which
is doing rendering.
And you want these two threads to be in the same process.
If they are not in the same processes, then you're going to be in a different process.
You need to incur context switching and things like that, which is going to be much less
efficient.
That's one example.
Okay, some examples, some questions now.
How can an application have multiple processes?
Is it if it needs multiple instances of a CPU or something?
What is the practical reasoning for this?
I thought it was one to one.
There are many reasons an application can have multiple processes.
And let me give you an extreme example and then you can imagine that will happen also
on a single machine.
An application like Facebook has obviously multiple processes because it runs on different
machines.
You have one part which is running on your machine, it's a front end, and then a part
which is running on the backend.
So you can imagine many of these applications like that could be client and server.
Some part of the application is handling, say, an access to the database and some part
of the application is handling the front end.
And then you can have a multi-user application and then you want to isolate the user from
each other in the same application.
So for each user you are going to provide a different process.
Or you want to have a stronger isolation, like for instance in your browser.
In your browser you have different tabs.
And if every tab you run it in the same process, then you have no protection and therefore
a misbehaving webpage can crash your browser.
If you have a stable process then you have strong isolation between processes.
So these are quite a few examples.
Now we are not going into details but there are more things between processes and threads
that are actually other ways people try to maintain the efficiency, to preserve the efficiency
of the thread, but add some protection which you have from processes.
We are not going to discuss about this though.
But hopefully I answered that question.
So that attack doesn't depend on waiting, can take over while the other is waiting,
even if the CPU is multiplex.
I'm afraid I don't, this is a statement I guess.
But what this statement said is correct.
The task which doesn't depend on waiting can take over.
The task which depends on waiting is going to be suspended to wait for some part.
So a task which, a process which waits for an event to happen, like getting an input
event from getting some data from the network, is suspended and waiting for that event to
happen and during that time another process can run.
The operating system can take care of that.
And finally the fourth operating system concept is dual mode operation.
So dual mode operation is fundamentally concerned about how you are going to share the hardware,
the machine between processes, the user processes and the operating system.
And typically this happens, you have two modes for that.
You have a user mode, which is used when you run a user process and the kernel mode, which
is used when the operating system runs.
And the reason for that is the operating system actually has access to a lot more resources
and even to processes, resources during when it is running.
And the way to differentiate between these two modes is you have a bit and it's a user
system mode bit.
So when you set to zero, for instance, it's a user mode and you set one is kernel mode.
So how the transition happened from a user process to a kernel happens from the user
to kernel, you set the system out.
So now, and then save the user program counters and all the state of that particular thread
and execution state.
And then from the kernel to the user transition, you clear the system and restore the appropriate
user program counter.
And you can return from the interrupt.
And here how the user mode and the kernel mode interact with each other.
So on one hand, from the kernel mode, you have EXACT.
And this is how you run a process.
The kernel and the operating system is launching a new process.
Then when the process exits, you return to the kernel.
The kernel is taking care of freeing all the resources allocated to that process.
So these resources can be used by other processes.
Then it's a system call.
And this is when the user process requires some functionality, some services, invokes
some services from the operating system.
Example of some services like accessing a file, sending some data, reading information
input data from the keyboard.
And this is returned.
This is after the operating system satisfies this request.
Then it's returning control back to the user.
And then there are user interrupts.
And the user interrupts.
One example is basically you can have a SQL.
You can actually kill a process.
So that's one example of a user interrupt.
And there are also interrupts which come from the hardware.
Like when a packet arrives, where when you click on a keyboard and then you have an interrupt,
so the operating system needs to read the symbols.
And then you can return from the interrupt.
It's a user-level interrupt.
You return from the interrupt.
You return the control eventually to the user.
And finally, there are exceptions.
And exceptions are when the user somehow the program is doing something which is not allowed.
Like for instance, you can have division by zero.
Okay.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>>
[ Silence ]