Hello, everyone. Welcome to today's lecture. Today we are going to wrap up the discussion
about the performance and then we are going to spend the main bulk of the lecture on file
systems. So let me start. So just to recap from last week, last week we talked a little
bit about performance and this is one way to model the performance in particular for
something like a network. And we are talking then that, for instance, if you send a packet
with a certain number of bits, say small b, and the network capacity is capital B bits
per second, then this is a formula for latency. You have a factor S, which is overhead to
send that packet, for instance, of the system call, and then plus a variable part, which
is b is the number of bits in the packet over the capacity of the link, capital B. This
formula also works reasonably well for transferring data from the disk. In this case, the S, it
represents the rotation latency plus seek time. So this is one and this is a formula
for the latency and you see here is shown on this plot with a blue line. So the intercept
of the blue line with the y-axis represents the S, so in this case it's 1000 microseconds
and then here the slope represents the bandwidth of the particular link. So in this particular
case, we are going to have a link of 100 Gbps, S was 1000 microseconds or one milliseconds,
and then b is here on the y-axis. So on b it's 5000 bits, then you are going to get
the corresponding 5000 over, I think that should be bytes, it's 500,000 divided by
125 megabytes per second, that will give you 4000 microseconds or four milliseconds. And
if you add to S, which is one millisecond, you are going to get five milliseconds or
5000 microseconds. Okay, and then the other important metrics here is the effective bandwidth,
which is basically, okay, if I'm sending a packet of this length, what is the effective
bandwidth for sending that packet? And that obviously is a packet size, in this case b,
over the time it takes to send the packet, which it does include S, the fixed overhead,
and this is a formula B capital B times S over b small b plus one. Okay. You notice
that if S is zero, then the effective bandwidth is equal with capital B, which is expected,
right? Because there is no fixed overhead, then the effective bandwidth, you can send
data as fast as the capacity of the link. And one important metric here is about, it's
a half power bandwidth, and half power bandwidth is a way to think about it, is basically what
is the size of the packet in this case I need to send such that the effective bandwidth
to be half of the capacity of the link, right? So the overhead is not that very high. Overhead
just cuts my capacity to half, right? And here is red, you can see the curve, this curve
is red, is the effective bandwidth, again versus the capacity of the link. And when
the number of bits is zero, obviously here you have effective bandwidth, it's zero. Okay.
And on this plot here on the right, this is a plot which has two y-axis on the left hand
side is the latency, the blue one, the blue curve, the blue line, and on the right hand
side you are going to have the bandwidth, effective bandwidth, which is a red line.
Any questions? So next, remember that we also did a little bit of queuing theory, mostly
providing you some formulas, so just summarize them here. And as you know, this topic is
covered. This is part of the exam, the midterm topics. And so you may get the problem, which
is about queuing theory or about performance, cyber performance. So anyway, so here you
remember that this is a queuing model, obviously it's called a queuing model, so for a reason,
it has a queue. So you have a bunch of requests here with the arrival rate lambda, lambda
is the number of requests, average number of requests per second arriving to the queue,
and the requests are removed from the queue as fast as they can be processed by a server.
And the server processes each request at the service rate mu, and mu is one over the service
time, how long it takes to service a particular request. So the way to think about if the
server takes 100 milliseconds to serve a request, then obviously mu is one second over 100 milliseconds
is 10 because you can serve 10 requests per second. So then another important parameter
is square coefficient of variance to characterize the systems and the server utilization. The
server utilization is basically the average arrival rate over the average service rate.
And fundamentally you do want these parameters to be less than one because this would mean
that the system is in the stable regime, that any stable regime, if the arrival rate is
lower than the service capacity about how fast the request can be served. If you send
more, obviously the system will not be in a stable regime, which means that the queries,
the queue will grow indefinitely, right? As more requests come in and the system cannot
keep up with serving these requests. And all the results typically in the queuing theory
assumes that rho is less than one. And then the parameters you want to compute is the
time you spend in the queue, right? We know how long it takes a request to be served.
So it's t serve. So now we need to understand how long it takes a request to spend in the
queue. So then by adding the do, we know the service time for the queuing time, we know
how much a request spend in the entire system, which is what matters from the user perspective.
And then we also want to learn about the little law and the little law allows you to compute
the queue length by just multiplying the mean arrival rate plus the time average time spent
in the queue. And this is some of the results we went over last time. So it's again, this
is a recap, which may help you for the tomorrow's midterm. And t queue is for MM1 queue, which
is remember an MM1 queue is one of the simplest queues out there. It has one is for means
that it has one server, m, the first time refers to the distribution of the arrival
rate. So this means that the intervals between two consecutive requests arriving is exponentially
distributed or it's also called Poisson distribution of the arrival rate. And also the service
time is exponentially distributed. It's again the time it takes to serve it's exponentially
distributed. And the formula here is this serve times row over one minus row. And for
a more general queue where the serving time, it's general, it's just characterized by the
C, we know only about the square coefficient of variance. You have a very similar formula,
only the second parameters is a formula it's different. But the real main point to notice
about this formula are this last term, which is row over one minus row. And this capture
what I said earlier, that if row is should be less than one, that if it's equal or greater
than one, then the system will not be in a stable region. Right? And this is a plot showing
you roughly how the response time and the service time is looking versus throughput
or utilization versus row. So on the x-axis is basically row is from zero, say to one,
and this is a response time. The response time is a queuing time plus the service time.
And as a time, as a row goes to one, this is going to be dominated by the queuing time
because the queuing time is going to grow one row. It's close to one, then this goes
to infinity. Okay. So any questions? Okay. So now let's talk about how we are going to
optimize the performance and what are the ways to optimize it. And this is what we are
going to discuss over the next several slides. And again, if you look about for an IO device,
you are going to have the user stress. This is where the program is running. Then you
are going to send requests, say read or write from this particular file, which is from that
particular one particular device. And these requests are queued and then are submitted
to a controller and the controller is going to program the IO device to read and write
the particular data. Okay. And so how you are going to improve this system? Well, there
are a few ways. One speed, right? You can make everything faster. Each of these components,
you can make it faster. You reduce the overhead of the context switching. You have also some
context switching here of the controller and of the device. You buy a disk which rotates
faster with a lower seek time. Another way is parallelism. It's basically, you know,
you can parallelize. You can have, you know, inside, you can have multiple queues if the
queue observations are expensive. Or instead of an IO device, you may have multiple IO
requests. You can, for instance, as you know, probably you can have two disks and then you
are going to strive the data across disks. So therefore, or you just partition the data
between disks. So when different requests can run at the same time on if they are going
to request data on different disks. Then is overlap, right? So this applies to different
parts of this kind of pipeline. So for instance, for the thread, you send a request, you are
waiting for the request, you can do some useful work instead of just waiting. The same thing
here is like for the controller, as you program the current request and you program the IO
device to ask to satisfy the current request. Once you do that and you send the request
to IO device, then you can process the next request. The one important aspect here is
that one way to look at this pipeline, say you want to improve the performance here,
what you are going to do is the engineering way to look about and or software engineering
way, the sound way to do it is to look what is the bottlenecks are, which is a bottleneck,
which is a slowest part in this chain. And then you are going to focus on that bottleneck
part to improve the performance, because if you improve the performance of something which
is already fast, not the slowest link in the chain, then the end-to-end performance will
not improve much. And remember, the queues are here to absorb the burst. The queue sees
that because the requests are not going where, you know, are equally distanced in time, they
can arrive in a bunch of requests at the same time. So the controller cannot serve on this
bunch of requests at the same time. So you need to then queue them because if they don't
have a queue, you need to drop on the floor of the request, you are going to fail satisfying
the request. And finally, another thing we didn't discuss last time, it is one other
techniques in this kind of systems, it's admission control. The admission control basically says,
look, and in admission control, why you have admission control in general, is that you
basically admission control says that I refuse to, I'm telling you this request I cannot
handle. Okay? So the thread wants to submit a request and I'm saying, you know, the controller
or the queue itself saying I can no longer enqueue this request, come later. And this
also typically happens if we want to ensure to limit, to provide guarantees in terms of
the end-to-end latency of end-to-end response time. Okay? In order to provide, so basically
saying if I'm going to accept the request, I'm going to guarantee that I'm going to serve
this request in say 100 milliseconds. Right? If I cannot, if there is no admission control,
then I cannot make that guarantee because if there are a lot of requests coming, which
exceeds the capacity of my system, I cannot guarantee that each request is going to be
processed within 100 milliseconds. Okay? So admission control place is hand in hand with
limiting the delay if you want to have guarantees on the end-to-end delay. Any questions? Can
you give an example from real life where the admission control is employed?
Any? Example? Any? Example? Any? Example? Any? Example? Any? Example? Any? Example?
Okay. Yes. Red lights on the entrance of the highway. That's exactly, that's a great example.
And real time systems, yes. Although I was, that's, I wouldn't call it real time life.
Red lights on the entrance of the highway. That's a great example. And there are many
other examples. Like for instance, in during when there are more restriction on during
COVID during the pandemics, you know, some shops, you limit the number of customers who
are inside. So in order to make sure that they can keep distance among themselves, there
are even more obvious examples. Like when you fly on a plane, here is admission control.
It's your seat, right? You cannot, it's not like in a bus in which you, you know, there
is no admission control anyone can get in. Well, I guess it's a natural one. No longer
people who are no longer fit in a bus and you know, it's, that's a natural pushback
mechanism. But yeah, there are many examples in real life where you are having this so
to speak admission control. Ha ha, Berkeley course waitlist. That's a great one. Yes,
Richard, that's great. Okay. Thank you. So any of these performance highest, remember,
obviously, when there are sequential reads where, and this is subtle and we are going
to see this is a, for, you know, the next, for the next few slides, there is another one.
There is so much work. You get so many requests. You can piggyback, you basically, you can
have so many requests, but can reorder the request says that you can serve this request
much more effectively. We'll, we'll, we'll see that in a, in a bit. Now, if the system
is mostly idle, it's perfectly fine to be inefficient. No one cares. Right. And, but
First, this is an important point, right?
When you have a burst,
meaning that you get more requests
than the system can handle.
So you need to queue those.
It's both as threat, or it should be threat there,
because they can increase the latency, right?
Because you can queue these requests.
But it's also an opportunity
because you can do this piggybacking.
You can, again, reorder the request,
as you'll see in a few slides,
or you can do batching.
Batching meanings, you can, for instance,
you have many requests,
you can do one context switching or function calls.
You can think about, you can do one context switching
to handle multiple of these requests at the same time.
So you amortize the context switching
across multiple requests.
You can also waste the space for speed.
Like for instance, you can,
you know, when you write on the disk,
like, let's see, what will be a good examples?
Yeah, you can have, for instance,
like for instance, for page tables.
For page tables, you can have additional hash maps,
which you are going to keep in order to locate,
to map the pages, the virtual pages,
to the page numbers, to the physical page numbers.
Another way to do it is to increase the size of the TLB.
Another way to increase the performance
in what you learn, we learned in the past,
is to increase the cache size.
In order to reduce, to also improve the performance,
system performance, program performance,
you can also increase the memory size.
Of course, there is a Belladia anomaly,
which as you know, for certain page replacement policies,
increasing the size of the memory,
or the size of the cache,
doesn't necessarily reduce the number of false, page faults.
But in general, for many of those page replacement policy,
like ALERU, that's increasing the memory size,
always will likely decrease,
most likely will decrease the number of page faults.
These are a few examples where you can have
increase the number of the space,
to increase the space and to improve the speed.
And other techniques are reduce the overheads
through user level drivers.
So basically, if you can implement the functionality
as a user level, you may avoid the context switching,
because you don't need the operating system
in order to handle these requests.
And the other one is like I mentioned earlier, the overlap.
So while you are waiting for an I/O to complete,
you are doing the useful, more useful work.
And this can happen at multiple, in multiple levels.
It can happen in your, the operating system,
as you now, when operating system on a thread
is blocked on an I/O device, on an I/O request,
is going to switch it out,
it putting the thread on the waiting queue,
and is going to schedule, the operating system
is going to schedule a new thread,
which is on the ready queue.
Okay, so now we're going to look into a bit
into the disk scheduling, right?
The disk remember is quite complicated, right?
You has multiple plates,
and each plate has two surfaces, up, down,
and then you have cylinders and sectors, right?
So when a request comes in from the operating system
to read or write on the disk,
is going to tell you, typically is telling you
what is a cylinder, the face, the surface,
and what is the sector, right?
Here we are talking, we are considering a simpler example
where you have the, just the cylinder and the sector.
And this is, this is how the request look like.
So in this case, you have two numbers,
for each request, a cylinder and the sector.
The request also is going to specify
what is the read and write.
And because this disk is slow,
more likely you are going to have some requests
which are queued, okay?
So now the interesting aspect here,
the requests are in general are independent,
are in general independent.
So now the question is how you are going
to serve these requests.
A simplest way is five, right?
You serve the request in the order in which they arrived.
This is fair among the requester,
that is fair with respect to the order
in which they submit the request.
But it can be very long six.
Why?
Because the head can go, you know, randomly from, you know,
from one cylinder or one track to another, right?
You don't run that because you remember
the seek time is very expensive, right?
As well as, you know, rotation latency.
So you don't want to go, you know,
you want to be smarter than that.
So that'll be a smart way to do it, right?
If you want to minimize the seek time,
once you serve a request and you are in a certain position
on the disk, you look, you want to look in the queue
and take the request which is closest to you,
because if the request is closest to you,
you are going to minimize the seek time.
And this is shorter seek time first, right?
You pick the request that it closes to the head on the disk.
Okay?
Of course, in general,
you also need to include the rotation delay,
not only the seek time,
but for now let's simplify it only to seek time.
Okay?
So now the seek will reduce the time if you look,
but it's not good.
What is not good is that may lead to starvation.
Like for instance,
if a lot of requests come and they are clustered close by,
then according to these disciplines,
you are shorter seek time first,
you are going to serve this request.
And the request which is farther,
a lot, you know, which is farther,
like for instance, at the edge on the disk,
may wait for a long time to be serviced.
Make sense?
So you don't want that.
Again, the rate of a seek time, but it's unfair.
Can cause starvation.
So one solution to that is scan.
It's a pretty nice solution.
These are what you see here, these numbers.
Think about these are tracks or cylinders, right?
A cylinder, it's all the tracks
which are under the heads on different platters.
So scan is basically you start going into one direction,
either to the edge of the disk or to the inside of the disk.
And you are only going to serve the request
in the direction you are going, right?
So you serve the request on say track 53,
then you look in the queue and you have multiple requests.
Say you pick the one which is closest to you
in the direction you are going, it's 37.
Then the next one is 14 and so forth.
And in this time, so for instance,
if when you serve the request 53, you get the request 65,
this is closest to you.
So according to the shorter six time first,
you'll serve this request.
Because it's not in the request on track 65,
it's not in the direction of your movement,
you are going to ignore it, right?
So you go until the last request in your direction
and then after you reverse.
So here I say no starvation,
but still retain a flavor of shortest six time first.
Why is that?
Tell me, why is that?
Why do we still have a problem with this one, with scan?
By the way, it's also, it's called elevator algorithm.
Can you think about, does scan exhibit any unfairness?
And why, if yes.
(silence)
Yes, I just want to say you may never reverse
if tasks keep arriving at the same spot.
So basically on the same track, that's true.
That's a pretty edge case.
It's a good answer, but it's a little bit edge.
What else?
Can you think about some other requests
which will get preferential treatment
if they are in some region of the disk versus others?
(silence)
Oh, Karl asked a question.
How do we define the initial direction for scan?
I guess, I mean, it's a good question.
I don't know, but I don't think it matters.
You can choose anyone initially.
Yeah.
There is more data on the outer rings.
So traveling is disfavored.
Yeah, you are right.
It's like, let me see, it's also a question here.
Okay, it's the same question.
So Karl, it's again, the answer to your question,
how do you define the initial directions?
I think it doesn't matter.
You can, but I do not know,
and I don't see a reason that's very important.
And going back now,
it is going back about when this scan is not fair.
So here, when it's not fair,
which requests are fair,
for which requests does scan provide advantage, favor them?
So here, the request in the middle,
you get quicker to the request in the middle,
right?
Like for instance, I can go to a request,
say it takes one millisecond to go from one end to another.
If I missed a request arrives here,
just after the scan has passed in that direction,
just I missed it.
So I say, okay, it goes 0.5 milliseconds to one end,
and I wait for another 0.5 milliseconds
to come to me back.
So I wait for one millisecond.
But if this happens when I'm at the edge,
so I just missed the head,
which now goes towards the inside of the disk.
Then you have to wait for two milliseconds.
You need to wait one millisecond
to go all the way to the inside,
and one millisecond to go back.
Okay, now I'm oversimplifying things here,
but just to give you a sense.
So scan favors the requests which are in the middle,
right?
And not the request which are at the edges.
What is the solution here?
Well, the solution is circular scan or C-scan.
And this basically just go one direction.
So say you go all the way to the,
you send the request only in one direction.
And when you are done with those,
you immediately go to all the other edge
and start serving them again.
Okay?
So that's kind of what it is.
But I'll say if I missed, if I request,
I just misses the head,
no matter what the request is,
on the average is going to wait for the same time
for the head to come to be back to be served.
Okay?
This is not biased towards the pages in the middle.
Finally, I mentioned that you can hide the latency.
How do you hide the IO latency?
If the blocking interface is a wait, we already discussed,
you have a block read and write system call,
you put process operating system,
put processes to sleep until the data is ready,
the request is served.
And during this time, the operating system schedules tasks,
ready tasks, which can use a CPU.
Non-blocking interfaces don't wait.
So basically this, you remember,
this is the interface in which you are just going
to issue the request, but then returns immediately.
You just, after you return, you do something else.
Right?
And then later you need to go
and see whether you got the data.
Okay.
Or you wrote the data to the kernel.
And asynchronous interface is then later,
again, it's like in the non-blocking interface,
it returns immediately the request,
because in this case, for instance,
when you get the data, you allocate the buffer,
you give the pointer as a buffer,
and tells the operating system basically,
put the data when available,
starting from this pointer, right in the buffer.
Okay.
And then let me know.
And when you send the data, it's the same, right?
You are going to create a buffer,
you are going there, you are going to,
you know, where you put the data,
where you want to send,
and then you give to the kernel, to the OS,
in the right operation, in the right system call,
you give the pointer of the buffer
you want to be transferred.
Okay.
So now recall the entire error here for the IO.
This is a top part, which provides the API
and the abstraction to the applications,
whether it's streams or it's a block API,
plus the system calls open, read, write, and close.
Then at the bottom, we also covered last time,
this is about IO drivers, controllers, right?
These are the drivers which are interacting
with the physical device,
read and write the data to the physical device.
And the middle is a system which kind of
makes a conversion in some sense
from the API, which is provided to the application
by the operating system and the API of the IO driver,
which is a block interface in general.
Right?
So more precisely for the API,
for the higher level for the application,
you typically have a variable size buffer.
And for the file system,
which you are going to talk more about this,
you are going to have blocks,
but the blocks are logically indexed.
These are where the data is stored, right?
Logically indexed means that the index
in the operating system is not the same index,
which of that block on the physical device.
This is done by the hardware device
and by their controllers mapping from this block device,
from the operating system to the blocks
or the sectors on the hard disk drives.
Remember that the blocks in the operating system
are typically have like 24 kilobytes
and sectors on the hard disk drives are smaller.
They are 512 bytes.
So you have typically, you can have eight sectors for each
or a block requires eight sectors.
And you have an SSD,
you remember you have these flash translation layers,
which again maps the logical index of the blocks
to the physical blocks.
That's pretty much what you have.
And also you have your agent pages.
So let's look now,
we are going to start looking more,
a little bit more depths to the file system.
And one way to define it, like I mentioned,
it's a layer of the operating system
that maps the API provided to the application,
which is files, directories, stream of bytes
into lower level API of the IO devices,
which is a block interface.
Right.
[Silence]
And there are a few things, you know, this needs to be done, the operating system.
And that's naming.
You need to find file by name, you don't give to the OS a block where the data is.
You let operating system worry about mapping between the file name and the block.
And this is part of the organization.
Also part of the organization is about the file names are typically within directories.
So you need also to locate the file name within a particular directory.
Also need to provide protection.
We enforce access restriction.
When do you do that?
When you open the file typically.
And those finally reliability.
Why do you store the data on the disk?
Because it's durable.
You want to survive data to survive when there are crashes or when your laptop is powered
out.
So from the user perspective, then I have some data structures which I want to store
those data structure view.
That's what I want as a user.
And that was a file system should offer me.
Now from the system view, and I'm talking here about the call interface, the API as
a boundary between the operating system and the user space.
It doesn't have any idea about what data structure the application has.
It just see a bunch of bytes, a collection of bytes.
So the system needs to take this collection of bytes, this bunch of bytes, and write them
on the device hard disk drive.
Then the system view that it's inside the kernel.
This is the one which interfaces to the devices.
It takes a collection of block and it sees a collection of bytes and maps them to a collection
of blocks.
The collection of blocks are still logically identified.
Logically again means that these are their identification.
It's not the physical identification or these blocks are on the disk.
OK.
And like I mentioned, the block size is typically greater than sector size.
So let's see what happens when, for instance, the user says to the operating system, I want
bytes between two and twelve from this file.
Well, the operating system has to face a block corresponding to those bytes and just return
the correct portion to the operating system, to the application.
What about when you write bytes between two and twelve?
You fetch the block from the disk, you modify the relevant portion and you write down the
block, back the block.
So for writing these 10 bytes, you get the block.
Which is four kilobytes.
Update these 10 bytes and then write back the four kilobytes.
So everything between the operating system and the devices is a block ground-large.
So therefore, you always are going to pay the overhead of reading and writing blocks
as a block ground-large.
OK, so it's again a file system.
You have directories and files.
Directory, you can think about that user visible index mapping names to files.
And the disk is just a linear array of sectors.
You can look at it.
It's a sector on you have a bunch of sectors on a track and you have a bunch of tracks
on a face of a platter.
And then for each platter, you have two faces and then for a hard disk drive, you have multiple
multiple platters.
So therefore, a sector is defined by, like I mentioned earlier on, by the cylinder, the
surface and the sector.
Now the main point to take from this slide and it's reemphasizing what I said earlier
on, is that the operating system doesn't track at the level the sector using their physical
identifier.
The physical identifier again here is a cylinder, surface and sector on the disk.
Instead you have a logical block addressing and typically now the controller translates
this logical block addressing to the physical block address.
It's something similar with virtual addresses.
The way that the operating system is responsible for translating the virtual addresses to the
physical addresses.
Let me answer this question from Alison.
Why don't we build devices that let us do lower, basically, I guess lower granularity
of reads and writes?
I guess, you know, this is a very good question.
And the answer is the overhead.
So you are correct.
Alison, this is because efficiency.
Remember again, just think about the hard disk drives.
If you remember the hard disk drives in the last lecture, there is some example.
The seek and rotation latency were like eight, nine milliseconds.
And the time to transfer a block, even if the block as a sector, even if the sector
is 500 terabytes, it's not only one byte, was much less than one millisecond.
So the time to transfer to random the access and transfer a sector is dwarfed by the rotation
latency, by the fixed overhead, rotation latency and seek back.
So is that because there is always an overhead?
Another way to think about is here it is another way to think about and maybe let me just connect
the dots here.
Remember this slide?
Look here at this formula.
OK.
The smaller the B is, the less the effective bandwidth is.
If B is very small, S will dominate the fixed overhead.
This is just overhead.
It's useless work.
And the smaller the B is, the lower the effective bandwidth is.
Look at the red curve here.
So that's what you have.
Each request, processing each request has a fixed overhead.
Even if this is on, let me go here, even if this device is solid, it's SSD, not disk drive.
There is an overhead for controller.
Is there an overhead for context switching and things like that?
OK, hopefully I answered your question.
OK, let's go back.
So what do you need for file system needs?
What do you know if you design a file system?
What do you need to be careful about?
You need basically to track which for a file, which are the blocks containing the data from
that file.
You need to track it.
You need to for a particular file, you need to know which directory contains it.
And then you need to track the free disk blocks, because if you write something new in a file,
you need to know which blocks are free, are empty.
And then you also need to decide how to maintain this information.
The answer is the information has to be persistent.
So because it's persistent, you have to maintain it on the disk.
So it's again, data structures on the disk is different from the data structure in memory.
The application, you have a data structure.
The disk or even the operating system is unaware, completely oblivious about the data structure
you have in your program.
It just sees a bunch of bytes and later a bunch of blocks.
That's what it is.
Again, because you access a block at a time, it's not very, these things, accesses are
not very efficient for when you access just a byte.
And obviously, like I mentioned, when you write to a disk, you expect to be durable.
That's why you write to a disk, otherwise you keep the things in memory.
But here you need to be careful.
You cannot assume that if you write to a disk, if you say, I call the write operation, everything
is fine.
Why is that?
Tell me why if I just call the write operation to a file, I cannot be completely sure that
this, the data I wrote has been stored durably on the disk.
Yes.
If you remember, we discussed early on about buffer cache.
So the data is not stored directly on the disk, it's stored in a buffer.
So if after you submit the request, the application fails, the operating system fails, the data
may be lost.
You need to call.
You need to call in order to make sure the data goes to the disk.
What system call you are going to invoke?
Flash.
Very good.
Although I would wish also to have more people answering these questions.
So it's again, it's not a wrong answer.
It's about discussing it and you'll remember much easier if we have this kind of discussions
rather than me just talking and talking and talking and being boring.
So OK.
A few announcements, you know very well tomorrow, this is 11.3.
Let me just find.
Tomorrow we have the exam.
I wish you the best of luck.
All the materials is up to and included the last lecture, not this lecture.
And the project deadline, it was pushed.
So now you have a little bit more time.
So hopefully this really helps you.
OK.
Again, let's go even deeper talking about the file system.
So again, a few core elements.
The file system design, if you are talking about the performance, the dominant factor,
you are talking about this bottleneck, the bottleneck is a disk performance.
The disk works better, provides the best performance when we sequentially read and write data because
we avoid seek times and rotation latencies.
So you want to maximize these operations.
Remember we can, it's a file system abstraction provided in Unix.
You need to, it's open, close and in between you read write.
You cannot read and write to a disk without the file system, without the file, without
opening and closing that file.
The cool thing about this is that you can perform the protection checks, admission control.
And all at the open, when you open the file, otherwise you would have to check for protection
every time you access that file.
The size of the file is variable.
When you start writing, you start with one block.
We need more than one sector.
We need more.
You are going, the file system is going to allocate more.
So you don't need to predefine.
This is very important.
You take it as a giver.
But it's not.
Another design is like you would just allocate space on the disk and before you start writing.
And why is that natural?
It can be natural because how do you do it in your favorite programming language like
C, right?
How do you manipulate the memory?
How do you manipulate the storage of memory?
Before you read or before you write some data, what do you need to do?
You need to allocate memory.
Malloc or Calloc.
So you allocate first and then write.
Here is not needed.
You just write and the operating system and the file system in particular will take care
of growing the size of the file as needed.
The files are organized in directory.
You have a directory structure and this directory structure, the directory is a file.
It's also stored on the disk.
And then you need to allocate.
When you allocate, I think we are going to see that in the next lecture.
When we allocate more sectors on the disk, you want to allocate them contiguously.
Why is that?
Because when you read the data, if the data was written on a bunch of sectors, which is
contiguous, you maximize the sequential accesses, right?
Sequential reads in this case, which improves the performance.
So here how things look like under the hood a little bit.
On one end, I have the file path, which is the file path is a name of the file prefixed
by the directory path name where the file is residing in each directory path.
At the other end, you have data blocks which are stored on the disk in sectors.
So you need somehow to map from the file path to the data blocks.
And this is what the operating system file system is wrong.
Right?
You take the file path, which is going to point some in some directory structure.
You are going to find the file and the file is going to be as you are going to identify
by a number.
It's called I number.
And this I number is going to point to a data structure, which is called I node, which contains
all the information about that file, like for permissions, protection permissions.
And also information about the blocks or the data in the file is stored.
This is the I node.
OK, here is another view.
You remember about this.
We had many lectures ago.
This is a view from the process perspective.
So here you have a process, you have threads, registers, and you have the address space.
And then when you open a file, you get a file descriptors.
The file descriptors points to a data structure here, which is in the operating system.
It's really at the end of the day, you are going to have the I node.
But anyway, the file description here, you know, in this case, you have a file name.
And you have position, what's the position in the file?
What is the position you are going to read and write?
from. Right? And then you are going, this is going to read from file descriptor 3 and
into this buffer and you are going to copy the data from position 100 in the file. So
from position 100 of file identified by descriptor 3 read data into this buffer. But really the
way you need to think about this, that instead of this file, you are going to have inumber.
Like I mentioned from here, you just need to point directly to this and inumber points
to an inode. But let me tell you, let me ask you this question. Why do you think instead
of food or text here, I should just keep the inumber. Right? Which is how an identifier
by the operating system of that particular file. Why inumber and not food text? Let me
help you a little bit. Look at this picture. While I number and not file or text. I don't
want to name my files with random numbers. It's again, yeah, it's again, you don't name,
you know, it's let me let me very, very clear here. So from the operating system, from your
application perspective, you open a file and when you open a file, you open food or text
and back, you don't get a file descriptor. So the file descriptors points to a data structure,
which is open file description. This is in the kernel. You see everything which is below
this dotted line, it's in the kernel. So and here on I shown you this example, I will show
you that this file is a food or text, right? Because this is what you open. But what you
are saying here is that we really don't want to keep in the open file descriptor food or
text. Instead, I want to keep the I number of the food or text. And the question, why
do I want to keep I number here in this data structure instead of food or text?
File dot text is directory directory independent. OK, that's a very good point. Let's say it's
not food or text is entire past name. Yes, Jasper. Jasper, it's correct. Save the first
translation step. It's exact. You see. I opened the file. And I get the file descriptor, so
then. I want if I keep the I number instead of file pass, then I'd save this translation
step. Otherwise, whenever I'm going to access a file. I need to do this translation because
I have filed a text, I need to do the translation because the I number. So I save this on this
step. Very good. OK, let me just go a little bit quicker. So, yes, you have a file name
and in a particular directory, so in a particular directory, you are going the file name is
going. You can think about it's a it's a bunch of entries in these directories of the file
name offset is by going, going to tell you the offset is going to tell you all the particular
what is the entry for my particular file. And then for file number, you are going to
have file number offset. Basically, this is what it's I number. The I number is you have
an index structure which is indexed by its of I note each entry in this index structure.
It's an I note which represents all the information associated with that file and the index in
that index structure is the I number. Right, so you have and the open. Operation performed
this name resolution, basically translating the file name into the file number and the
read and write operation are all referring to the file number. So you avoid the first
translation step and use a file number as an index to locate the I node and the I node
is going to lead you to the blocks. We'll see a few examples. So you have three comp
for components is a directory, the index structure, the storage blocks and free space map. Remember
about that. How do you get the file number? You have to look in the directory structure
in the directory structure. I told you that in directory structure you have entries associated
with each file. Each entry I didn't tell you what each entry contains, but each entry I'm
telling you now each entry it's a it's a tuple. And which contain its maps the file name to
the file number. Again, when I'm talking about file number, I am also file number is the
same like I number. Okay. This file number can be a file or another directory. Okay.
So the operation system stores the mapping in the directory and interprets this format.
This tuple or the mapping between file name and file number is called directory entry.
It's very important to understand like again that the way we manipulate the directory,
although in Unix a directory just another file is different despite the fact that at
the lower level it's, you know, directory just another file. The way you manipulate
the directory is different than the way you manipulate a file. Right. You cannot just
use the read operation on the file. You can you need to have special operation, redirectory,
create directory or make directory and so forth. But let me ask you this question. Why
don't I want why don't I, you know, again, since as a low level, the directory is just
another file. Why don't I allow the application to do read and write some directories? It's
dangerous. Right. You can override if you override these mappings. You're messing up
because these mappings are maintained by the operating system. Right. It's for the same
reason you don't allow the process to arbitrarily modify kernel data structures. That's the
reason. This is how the directory looks like. Everyone knows that. So directories are typically
organized as trees. Directory trees. The leaves in the trees are files. The interior nodes
in the trees, including the root are directories. OK. And like I said. You do not allow the
application to manipulate, read and write directly on the directories instead to manipulate
directories, you have special function called system calls. Right. Make dear or remove dear.
Create a directory or read dear to traverse the directory structures. This is from the
command line you can use from the command line, but you also can use them. You have
libc support. You can have also use a library so you can use this programmatically. From
your application link and unlink. This allows you to actually break actually this hierarchy.
And actually you can have a name of a file. You can have a file, a name pointing to an
existing file. Right. So you have a file with a name say foo.txt. Now I can have another
name called foo1.txt pointing to the same file. We'll learn more about that. So just
to give you a sense now, let's assume that about the overhead which are involved, let's
assume that we want to access to resolve this. To get the I number of the file count. Right.
And then to access the file count. So what do we need to do here? First of all, we need
to locate the root of the directory. We need to start searching from somewhere from the
root of the directory. And the root, how do we do that? Well, fortunately, by convention,
the operating system puts the file system, puts the root directory, the root in a fixed
position on the disk. So you access this block, data block for root. In the data blocks, the
root you have, you have this kind of directory entries, file entries in the directory, in
the root directory. So you are going to have to locate my. Right. How you do that? You
can linear research. Typically, the number of entries in the directory is small. Now,
once you locate my, you read the file header for my, because how do you know that? Because
the entry for my tells you what is the file number for directory my. So from that, you
go and read it. Read again the first data block in my. And you search for the book.
The third my is going to gain, it's a directory, it's going to keep a bunch of directory
file entries. You read the header for the book again, you find book. The book entry,
the book entry is going to have the file number associated with the book directory. You use
that in order to read the header for book. And then you read the first data block for
book. You search for count. You find count and the count is you get the file number for
count. There is a file header for count and now you are done. So how many accesses? One,
two, three, four, five, six, seven. Just to do this resolution. So now you see how important
is to keep in the description of the file to keep the number, the number or the file
number instead of just the file name. Because I save the next time after I open it, the
next time when I do a read and write, I save seven accesses. And that is that expensive.
So as you know, you also have the notion of current directories and the current directories,
if you just refer to the file name without ignoring the past name, you are referring
that you assume that in the current directory. The current directory, it's already cached.
So it's one way to reduce this number of counts. So this is how happened, you know, the file
structure in the memory. And this is a user space, a kernel memory, and it's a secondary
story. This is what happened on the disk. So you have read, when you read a file descriptor,
this file descriptor paying points into this per process open file table. Each of these
entries, it's information associated with that file. And what you are going to get here
is a file number and the position, the seek position of the current position in the file.
You see this gray thing here, it's again this entry. Let me show you just to connect the
dots. Oops. Is this one? The information in that gray area is this open file description.
Right, the I number and the position in the file. Okay, so this is what is here. So the
I number points you to the I node. This is the open file tables and the I node has protection
bits and then also has all this, maintains all these data blocks. And all this is maintained,
is maintained also on the disk. The I node information is maintained on the disk because
it maintains the association between that file number and the blocks, data blocks, where
the data of the file is located. So it must be on the disk, it must be durable because
it must persist after you finish your program, after the program ends. Okay. We talk about
all of these things. I'm going to end up with this, a few interesting data and then we are
going to continue next time with the file system. So this is a study which was 13, 14
years ago, but it still is very relevant. And this is the point here is the following.
So what this study is looking, it's looking over five years and it's looking about how
the distribution of the file lengths and other information about statistics about the files
in a file system. The first important one is basically show you what is the size of
the file, the distribution of the file sizes for a file system. And basically what this
tells you, this is on the X axis, the file size and the number of files on the Y axis.
So this is for different currencies for different years. So you have something similar, although
as years pass, you have more and more files. And the main point here is this is showing
that most of the files are small, not that the X axis is log scale. So these are very
small, right? For instance, most of the files are 512 kilobytes or less. There are very
few large files. So most of the files are small files. However, if you look at, if I'm
taking some piece of data and I'm asking the question from the files, from all the file
system, I'm taking a piece of data and I'm asking the question, what is the size of the
file? Which contains this piece of data? Then this is the answer I'm going to get. I'm going
to get, and basically you see now that most of the data is contained in big files. So
yes, the majority of files is small. But the big files are responsible for most of the
data. Okay. And I am going to end up with a question to you. It's a fun question. You
see, you see here that on this kind of distribution, you have two peaks. You have a peak around
two megabytes and another peak around one gigabyte. Right? So you have, why do you think
you have these two peaks? Why do you think this one gigabyte? What do you think causes
it? And by the way, in 2000, it wasn't such a peak, but as the time goes on, passed, you
have this peak. Yes. Let's see. Yes. That sounds very good answers here, right? Yes.
Video, right? It's like, especially that was peer to peer system and you read about it.
Yes. This is one reason it's media. The other reason this is a lot bigger and bigger files.
These are also binary files. So the executive become bigger over time. That's excellent
answers. Okay. So with this, we are going to stop here. Again, good luck to the midterm
tomorrow and I'll see you again on a Saturday. Thank you.
[BLANK_AUDIO]