Hello everyone.
So today we are going to continue our discussion about file systems.
And in particular, we are going to go through a few examples to see how some of the most
popular file systems in the past have been implemented.
Just to recall, these are the main data structures which are maintained by a file system.
First of all, we are going to have directory structures, which is, as you know, it's a
radical.
And here you are going to use a file path to locate a particular file in this directory
structure and an entering the directory structures associate the file with an inumber.
An inumber is an index in an index structure called file header structure.
And this index points to what is called an inode.
And the inode contains all the information which is relevant to the file and which helps
the operating system to locate the data for that file on the disk.
So the first case we are going to go over, it's FAT.
FAT stands for file allocation table.
And this was the first file system employed by Microsoft Disk Operating System, which
is the first operating system released by Microsoft all the way in 1977.
And it's still quite used today, despite after what, after 50, 44 years.
And the FAT file system is quite simple.
So first of all, what you have here on the right, it's blocks on the disk and the disk
blocks.
And you have a file for each file you have where the block is located.
Each file has a bunch of blocks.
And like you say, for file system 31, this is where the disks are located.
And then you need to maintain in the FAT table a pointer or the identity of where the disks,
the blocks are located, therefore to the index of that block.
So the disk block, you can think about of an array of blocks.
Each block has an identifier.
Typically it's a logical identifier, which is mapped then on a physical identifier to
the disk.
And the FAT maintains a mapping between the files and the list of blocks identifiers,
logical identifiers.
So how does FAT maintain that?
It's again, this is maintained in the inode.
The inode is indexed by the inumber.
Let's assume that the file number here is 31.
And the FAT is just basically a linked list.
Each entry in the linked list corresponds to a block of a file.
And each entry will maintain the index of a block and then a pointer to the next entry,
which points to the next block.
So here, assume that you are going to have in three blocks in this file, 0, 1, and 2,
you have three corresponding entries in the FAT table.
And each entry will have an index to a corresponding block and then a pointer to the next entry,
to the next entry corresponding to the next block in the file.
Also as you know, when I am opening a file, another important data I need is basically
the offset.
So what is the current position in the file?
The current position in the file here is given by a tuple.
The first tuple is a block in the file.
And the second part of the tuple, it's basically the offset within that block.
Yeah.
So the question is, where does x, the second element of the 2x tuple, comes into the place?
Again, x, it's offset within the block 2 in this case.
So that's why in order to access the data here from block 2, you start from block 0,
then you have to follow the linked list to block 1, then to block 2, and now block 2,
this is a block I care about.
Now I can retrieve block 2, and then I'm going to the offset x within the block 2.
So it's a very simple technique.
So now you read the block 2 in the memory and then you access offset x within that block.
So again, it's a collection of blocks, and each entry in this linked list, in the fat
linked list, corresponds to a block.
And the file number, it's basically the file number for simplicity in the case of fat,
it's exactly the index of the root block in the file.
So in this case, 31, it's also the index of the root block on the disk.
Okay, so what about, obviously, what about free blocks?
So you need free blocks in order, obviously, to extend the file.
Remember that the file expands as you write more in the file.
So there are four new files you need to follow.
If you want to write a new file, you need to look at, to find these free blocks.
The free blocks, typically there are two ways to manage these free blocks.
One is to have a list of free blocks.
The other one, you can have a bitmap of free blocks.
So basically, in this bitmap case, you have for each block, you have a bit, one or zero,
one if it's, that block is not free, it's used by a file, zero if it's free.
Okay, so this is how you find it.
In this particular case, for instance, if you are going to write, if the file for now
has only three blocks, and you want to write more data, like in this case, I want to write
in file 71 in block C, so this means the fourth block, then what happens again, the file,
the operating system, the file system expands the file and finds them by finding a new block
in the empty list and then allocating that block and now that block is part of the file
and it's also part of the linked list of all the blocks which belong to that file.
So now, what is fast thought?
So it's again, this is persistent storage, all these modifications needs to persist after
I am going, I write a file, for instance, I modify the file, and then I close the application
because next time when I open the application and I want to read the files, I want my changes
to be reflected.
So therefore, by default, this, all this information is a fact, not only the data, but also the
metadata, it has to be on persistent restored in this and the obvious place to restore it
is on the disk.
How do you format a disk?
Do you know what formatting a disk means for people?
So, formatting meaning, you know, I want to make the disk as new, right?
I want to basically erase everything and the way you do it is basically you zero the blocks
and in the fact table, you mark everything being free.
There is a question here from Gilbert.
Do the blocks not have to be in order in the linked list?
So I'm afraid I don't understand that question.
Can you be more precise Gilbert about this question?
So are you asking that because the linked list is fundamentally ordered.
Ah, like block three is before the block two.
That's exactly why we have a linked list because when you are going to read from a block, we
are going to go along the linked list.
Okay.
So that's the main point, right?
So in this particular case, we are going, again, if you follow the linked list, the
linked list will link the blocks in the order, you know, it's all written.
Okay.
They are appended to the file.
That's exactly why I need a linked list.
To preserve that, to store that order.
What happens if we try to insert something in the middle of a file for FAT?
Do we insert a new block into the linked list or is there something more clever?
Well, if you insert, you see in any file system and most file systems actually, you cannot
insert a block in the middle, right?
Because from the file system, think about what is the interface.
You can just write to the block.
So or read from the, sorry, you write through the file and read from the file.
If you write from the file, if you write in a place where already contains data, you override
that data, right?
So you write in an already existing block, right?
And if you write at the end of the file, then if you run out of existing, the block at the
end of the file, you are going to add a new block.
So you are going to expand the file.
Good question.
How to quick format a disk?
You can mark all the FAT entries to free.
And this can be easily implemented.
The main point here, it's again, it's like you can actually, and there are two ways to
format it.
And again, format meanings in, it just, you want to have the disk as new.
Now if you just remove all the information in the FAT without doing anything with the
disk blocks, the disk block still remains, you know, you don't zero them.
Then from the point of view of the operating of the file system, the disk is free.
You can allocate everything because you removed, you just mark all the FAT entries being free,
right?
So you are going to allocate from the previous blocks, which you'll return for a different
file, so just override them.
No problem.
Now, obviously this is not a hard format because it maintains the information from the previous
files.
And typically when people format, they also want to erase this information for security
reasons.
So you need to be careful about what kind of format is going to happen on your formatted
disk.
If you care about the information from your previous files to not be visible.
Again, for instance, you hand down, you hand back your computer to your employee or something
like that.
The FAT directory is again, it's like, you know, directory you have to remember, you
have this and it topples.
One is a file name.
The first part is a file name.
The second one is a file number.
And here is a FAT we also have, it's a linked list, right?
It's like we know.
And all the directory, you know, what you see in a directory, which is basically a list
of names, what happens here, you are going to have each of these, what you see entering
this directory is going to be linked, all of them, you know, in a linked list.
If you remove a file, then you are going to update the pointers so that you are going
to step over that file, which was over that entry, which was deleted.
So that's how you have here.
So it's very simple.
So one, there are a few things about the FAT directory, which is worth mention.
It's where do you have the attributes, the attributes for a file?
The attributes for a file is like protection and permission attributes.
You know, who has access to the file to read it, to write it, to execute that file, if
it's a binary file.
And in the FAT, these attributes are maintained here in the directory.
Like we'll see in other file systems, these attributes are associated with the file itself.
The other question, which in general is, it's an important question for all the file systems.
Where do you find the root?
Where do you start from?
Right?
To get the root.
If I give you a file name, you need to go and get the root directory and then go through
the path names in that directory to find the particular file name and then the I number
for the file.
And typically this root, it's a well defined place on the disk.
For instance, in the case of FAT, it's block two.
So what else here?
Obviously, because this is maintaining a link list, then in order to read a directory and
to display the content of the directory, you need to go over this link list.
You need also to go over, which is called "conf" defined because when you do a display,
like all the entries in a directory, you want to display all the files in the directory.
But when you want to find a file in a directory, you still need to have to go over this link
list, which can be expensive.
Any questions?
Okay, so here are a few questions.
So suppose you start with a file number, the file number is everyone, like in our previous
example.
And here you see also yellow is you have a file too.
Let's see, what is the time to find a block?
What do you need to find a block?
Yes, you take this, it's O(n) where n is the number of blocks.
Actually, in this case, you say root then traverse to the desired number.
Here you already have the file number, the 31.
So you don't need to do the directory traversal.
But yes, this is correct and Gilbert.
So basically in this particular case, you need, it's a linear search, right?
You need to find a particular block.
You need to follow the pointers in the link list.
And everyone knows that link list to find something in a link list is linear search
in the ER file.
So what is a block layout for files?
It was a previous question, do they need to be contiguous?
Not...
Yes, it's correct.
Actually, they don't need to be contiguous, they can be random because then we are going
to have our link list in the fat table to maintain the order, the logical order of the
blocks, which provides you a lot of flexibility about where to allocate the blocks and which
is good.
Sequential access.
What do you think about sequential access?
Is that fast, slow?
Yes.
The directories are linked lists also are presented in the fat in the...
And yes, they are also linked lists, but with directories is a linked list between the entries
in the directories.
Here for the files themselves, you have the linked list basically between the blocks of
that file.
Now the answer to the question sequential access can be somewhat slow because we need
to linearly scan for every access because we do not have a guaranteed order.
It's correct.
So the sequential access can be slow because if you look at how block 0, 1 and 3 are located
here, block 0 and 1 are consecutive.
And because they are consecutive, you do not need to incur a seek latency or rotation latency
if to go from block 0 to block 1.
But now to go from block 1 to block 2, you have to incur a seek latency or rotation latency.
As you know, this is huge.
So yes, you have a lot of flexibility where to put the blocks on the disk, but if you
are not careful and you put them randomly, then it's going to hurt your access time.
Random access.
How is random access?
Yes, it's even slower since you have to incur, you need to sequentially search for the block
which contains the data you want to read or write.
So it's quite slow.
Fragmentation.
How is fragmentation?
Yes, fragmentation is pretty good.
It's not much fragmentation because remember you can put the blocks anywhere.
So if you have just some free blocks, you are going to get it.
No problem.
It's okay.
It's going to hurt your performance, but you can have very, you know, your fragmentation
will be very low.
Small files.
Is this a vision for small files?
Remember, what if you know, if the file fits in one block is very efficient.
It's very good.
If a file fits only in one block.
Why?
Because you already, the file number, it's indexed into the block, the first block.
So you find it immediately.
Right?
As you have, you know, more blocks in the file, then it becomes more efficient for the
reason I mentioned.
Right?
We mentioned.
Yes, it's even more inefficient is again, because the blocks can be layout, their layout
on the disk can end up being random.
And then you pay a lot of sick time, rotation, latency to read and write from the file.
Okay.
So this is fat, right?
Very simple and very influential.
Right?
This was for many, many years, for decades, this was a file system for personal computers.
Because obviously 90% of the personal computers were running Microsoft operating system.
Okay.
Now, let's switch gears and talk about Unix file system.
And the Unix file system, this is Berkeley standard distribution, 4.1 is what we are
looking to now.
And yes, this is a part of your heritage.
And the similar Linux today has very similar file structure.
So it's again, a hugely influential file system.
The file number or I number is again, it's an index into an array of inodes.
And the inodes corresponds to a file, right?
Inodes contains the indexes to the blocks on the disk.
And in this case, it also contains other metadata associated with a file.
It's pretty good for both little and large files.
And all the assumes that still all the blocks have the same, are the same size.
And the trees, what you are going to see is asymmetrical.
So here is how it looks like.
So you have an inode array, the file number, it's an index in this array.
The inode in this array is basically, this is the inode data structure.
The first part, there are a bunch of attributes.
Like for instance, nine basic control bits you have here.
You have typically owner or user, group and others.
So it's basically whether the owner of the file, and for each of them, you have three
bits, read, write, execute.
So for owner of the file, for the group and for others, right?
Basically for everyone else.
And typically, obviously the owner has the most rights than the group and then everyone
else.
And also you have a few other bits, which basically you can execute only at the owner
permission rather than users and to execute at the group's permission.
So it's again, it's pretty classic.
And the more interesting part is after this.
Okay.
But remember this permission bits and information is associated with the inode, with a file
in this case.
In the case of FAD, it was this information was maintained in the directory.
And then you have 13 other entries in this inode structure.
Each entry points to a block.
The first 10 entries are called, each of them, they are pointing to one block.
The 11th entry points is called indirect pointer and points to a block, which each element
is a block.
It's a pointer to a real block.
And you have double indirection pointers where this points to a block, which is full of pointers
or each pointer points to another block, which is full of pointers to finally two blocks.
And then you have triple indirection pointers, which is again going three levels.
So in this case, you have, if you have four kilobytes blocks, it's efficient.
You have, here you have, yeah, sorry.
I said the first, the direct number of direct pointers was 10.
It's actually, sorry, it's 12.
And then you have three other ones, one for indirect, double indirect and triple indirect.
Okay, so you have 12.
And if you have 12 pointers, this means that if you have 4k blocks, you can have, you can
store using only direct pointers, you can store 48 kilobytes.
And if you remember from last time, when you're looking at these results from this paper,
which are looking at the statistics of the length of the file system or the size of the
file systems, in that paper, in the plots we presented last time, we are seeing that
most of the files are small files.
So therefore, for most of the files, you are using only the direct pointers.
And then for the bigger files, you are going to use the indirect pointers, double indirect
pointers and triple indirect pointers.
So just to give you a sense, you can get, for double indirect pointers, you can get
to four megabytes.
Why?
Because in this particular case, it's again, this pointer here is a certain pointer.
It points you to one block.
A block has four kilobytes.
Each pointer in this case is four bytes.
So therefore, in a block you have 1024 pointers.
Each of these pointers points to a block.
A block has four kilobytes.
So now you have 1024 times four, you have four kilobytes, you have four megabytes.
This is level two.
It's one indirect.
Then double indirect is going to add another layer and it's basically you have four gigabytes.
And then for if you have triple indirect pointers, you have four terabytes.
So it's a lot of storage.
Now the disadvantage for this one, what is the disadvantage with going with indirect,
double indirect and triple indirect blocks?
What is the disadvantage here?
Yes, longer access times.
Because right now, if I'm going to have, if I'm going to go to this, you know, the first
level pointers, I'm going to get the inode and then from inode I get the pointers, all
the pointers to the block.
So I have another access to get to the data, one extra access.
If I'm going to have triple indirect in order to get to these data blocks, I have to get
one other access to get the first level block, which contains pointers at the first level.
Then another pointer, another, I need to access another, they get another block at the second
level to contain against pointers and another block at the third level contains again pointers.
And finally, I'm going to get to the data block, to the real block.
So here I have for each of these levels, I have an extra access.
On the other hand, it's pretty cool design, right?
Because for the small blocks, you know, it's pretty efficient.
Small block less than 48 kilobytes.
All these pointers here are to data blocks.
At the same time, you can store huge files, like up to four terabytes in this design.
Yeah, it's a question here.
This seems really similar to page tables.
Do file systems have the equivalent of super pages or huge pages?
It's very similar to the files, you know, it's similar to the page table in some respects,
right?
One is that the unit of allocation, it's a block, it's a page.
It's also they are connected, right?
Because the reason for which you have pages when we do demand paging is why?
Because these pages need to be stored eventually on the disk when they are evicted, right?
And they need to be read from the disk.
And the unit, again, it has to be the same unit, it's a block, right?
So block and the pages are basically the same unit.
Otherwise, it makes things much more complicated.
And you'll see towards the end of the lecture, hopefully we can get there, where you'll see
the similarity even more because we are going to talk about memory map files.
So then you are going to map the files into memory, and then you'll see even more of the
similarity.
So in terms of file system having the equivalent of super pages of huge pages, you do have
that not in Unix, but you do have that in the Windows, the more modern Windows file
system, Microsoft file system.
And in that case, you have what is called extents, what we are going to learn later
in this lecture in which the blocks can have variable size.
Great questions.
So let's take an example here.
So right now, and that's why I was a little, you know, in this particular, it's a different
example and we here assume that each block is one kilobyte.
And we assume that there are 10 direct pointers and in indirect block, so these 10 direct
pointers, so directly you can access only one kilobyte, 10 times, 10 kilobytes files.
And then because you have only one kilobyte, if each entry, each point there is four bytes,
then you have only 25, six indirect blocks at the first level.
And then you have 256 power 2 double indirect blocks and 256 power 3 triple indirect blocks.
So that's kind of the layout in this case.
And now the question is that how many accesses you need, how many accesses to get to the
block 20 string?
Assume the file is everything is open.
Now I'm just one process block 20 string.
How many accesses?
So is this 23 in a direct pointers part?
It's not right because I have only 10.
Is 23 in a, yeah, yes, 23 will be in the single indirect block.
So you need two accesses, right?
You need the first access to get to the root of the first level indirect blocks.
And then from here, once you get there, you are going to read the data block.
What about block five?
Block five is in the first 10.
So you are going to have only one access to read the data block number five.
Blocks are 340.
That's 340 fits in the first level indirect blocks.
Does it fit?
How many you have there?
You have 2556 plus 10, which are direct.
It's only 266 indirect blocks or direct blocks.
So therefore, it has to be in double indirect.
So then you are going to have how many accesses?
Again, one access per level, each level.
So you need, you have double.
So for each level, you need one access or two and the third one for access to the data.
Okay, some announcements again.
Many congrats for finishing the second midterm.
We are making progress here.
Block five has been released.
It will be due on Monday, November 22nd.
And the project two, obviously now is due on Sunday.
So hopefully everyone here is in a good state with that project.
If not, please feel free to ask any questions.
We are here to help you.
Okay, so that was the initial file system in Unix 4.1.
Now people, obviously after they use it for a while, they figure out there are some limitations
and they try to address these limitations.
And the address is limitation in what is called Berkeley FAST file system, FFS, which is BSD
0.4.2.
Right?
This was released in '84, so still a long time ago.
And it's very similar with 4.1.
The differences are that while in 4.1, typically the block size of one kilobyte, in 4.2, one
to four kilobytes.
Why?
Because obviously the discovery has increased in size.
And it's a very good paper.
I recommend you to read it in the reading material.
If not, you can search on the web and you can get it, but it's very interesting.
And there are a bunch of optimization and we are going to go briefly through these optimizations
and compare with 4.1.
And so let me go through, I'm not going to go now through this list.
I'm going while I am going to explain this optimization, but the middle things about,
first of all, let's talk about what are the motivation?
What are the problems with the file systems in Unix BSD 4.1?
Okay.
So, the one thing is that the file system, the FAD table and all of these inode data
structures, right?
They were in a fixed disk, in the fixed place on the disk.
Okay.
So, and the problem with that, if you have all these inodes on the disk in one place,
then it's very likely that they are going to be far from most of the data blocks, right?
The data blocks are all over, obviously, and the inodes are only at the edge.
In order to access the data blocks, you need the information from the inode of that particular
file, right?
So, you need to read an inode and you are almost guaranteed that the place where the
inode was stored on the disk is far away from where the data is located on the disk.
So it's seek time, you are going to pay for the seek time.
The other thing is reliability.
If somehow the outer edges, tracks of the disk are destroyed because sometimes when
some of the failures happen is that when you have a power outage and the disk was rotating
and sometimes the heads were kind of scratching the disk in that particular case.
Then if you lose this kind of the inode information, you lost everything.
So that's a problem.
The other thing, it's hard to allocate for performance, right?
Because in Unix, most writes, in many writes are by appending.
It's again, when you write, either you write to existing block because what the existing
data is, so you override the data.
But if you append, in many cases, you just append to a file, then you are going to add
new blocks.
And the problem here is that you want to allocate in some sense, obviously you want to allocate
blocks which are contiguous, right?
But that's kind of what's difficult.
In the case of 4.1, you need to be able to do 4.1, you have a link list for the free
blocks like in the FAT table.
And then the way you allocate, you go through this list and well, you allocate always the
first block which is available.
But going through the list of the free blocks, all these blocks can be all over the place.
So what have they done?
So here what have they done?
Basically, they define this kind of block groups.
So the tracks which are nearby are in the same block and correspondingly also they define
the cylinder group.
All the blocks which fall under block groups, which are falling under the head, the drive
heads on all the platters are in the same cylinder.
You imagine a cylinder which are going to contain all these data blocks which are overlay
one over another.
So right now, then instead of having these inodes and only at the edge, stored at the
edge of the disk, you are associating these inodes to the files, the inodes which for
the files whose data is stored in the same block are also in the same block.
So you see, this is the inodes information for the files which are stored in block group
one.
And these are the inodes information for the files with data, it's in block group two.
Furthermore, instead of maintaining the available free blocks in a list, you have a bitmap.
And I'll tell you, I'll show you next what you can do if you have a bitmap.
Right?
But this is what it is.
Now, in terms of performance, if you have this kind of layout now because the inodes
are in the same block groups with the files, with the corresponding files, what do I gain
here?
What do I save here in terms of performance?
What is the big deal about this?
Again, for a file to access a file, I need to get its inode and then I need to access
its data.
Because once I get the inode, I have the information or the blocks of the file are located, I'm
going to read or write.
So that is a big deal about this layout.
If the inode is near the file blocks, then it will be much faster to read, especially
for small files.
This is good.
It's a sick time.
It's exactly, Alison.
And it's basically the sick time will be smaller, will be much lower.
Because the sick time, it's about how far the two tracks are from each other.
This is a sick time, it is given by.
And now the blocks are on tracks which are closer together.
So this is what it is.
It's not only that I read the inode and I'm going to read these files, but also all the
blocks of the file are in a block group.
If they're in a block group, then going from one block to another, even if they are not
contiguous, the sick time is going to be low.
Also, here, one thing which I didn't mention is that the inode for files and the entire
directories with the files, the file system tries to put them on the same cylinder.
So on different corresponding blocks on different platter of the disk.
So it's again to minimize the sick time.
In this case, going to do an alias from directory, all the information is within the same cylinder.
OK, we discussed about this data block metadata and free space are within each block.
A voice huge sick time between user data and system structures.
And you also put the directory, like I mentioned, and these files in the common block group.
So basically, you try to preserve some locality between the metadata of the files and the
data blocks of the files by being careful how you store them on the disk.
But I try to be close to each other.
Like I mentioned, the list of free block allocation, here we use Bitmap.
Before, we used List.
And by using Bitmap, you can actually avoid some fragmentation.
One important thing which is true both for the Unix file systems in Unix DSD 4.1 and
4.2 is that you need to keep some 10%, 20% of free space always.
Because if you don't have any kind of free space, really, really you have no freedom
about where to allocate the new blocks.
And they are going to become pretty very random.
So the performance of the disk will slow down to a crawl.
But I'll say a few more words about that.
But now let's see what is the big difference and what is the advantage of maintaining a
Bitmap for the free blocks instead of linked lists.
So here is the difference.
So and we'll go over the summary here.
So here is a Bitmap.
And the dark shades, each rectangle, it's a corresponds to a block, each square corresponds
to a block.
And the shaded one represents blocks which are in use.
And the white ones represent free blocks.
So here is a very nice characteristic.
So let's say that I am starting to add, to expand the file, and I'm going to allocate
new blocks.
I have to allocate new blocks.
So what I'm going to do here, I'm going to go through this Bitmap.
I'm going to start reading from the beginning.
And whenever I'm going to see a free block, I'm going to allocate it.
So this one, the blue one, starts the one which has been allocated.
So so far, so good.
Again, it's like I'm going to allocate what I see and encounter first.
So these blocks actually, in terms of the location, can be quite random if they are
not one near each other.
However, when I am going to start allocating, the more I allocate to a file, the more I'm
going to start looking for bigger gaps, for more contiguous regions.
And I think that's basically the key.
So initially, I am allocating as I find these blocks available, empty.
But then after a while, when I start to allocate more and more new blocks to a file, I'm starting
to look more and more for contiguous blocks.
And because I have a Bitmap, it's much easier to look for contiguous blocks because I know
I just look at the Bitmap.
In the case of the linked list, it's much harder because I need to pop up to go from
one to another entry with a linked list.
And with a linked list, really, I'm going to look in the order in which I am going to
see to find in the linked list the free blocks.
Does it make sense?
So the PLDR here is that if I have a Bitmap, then it's much easier for me to identify contiguous
regions of free blocks.
It's as simple as that.
More efficient.
And then as I have larger and larger files which allocate more and more blocks, I'm going
to start using and allocate more of these contiguous blocks.
Yeah, it's a Bitmap.
So the question here, the blocks here are in an array rather than a linked list.
Yes, it's a Bitmap.
A Bitmap is by definition an array.
But it's very efficient.
A pointer, how many bits you have.
For a pointer, you have four bytes, like 32 bits at least.
Here you have for one block, you have one bit.
Right.
Okay.
Now let's go back and...
So a summary for these fast file systems.
I now layout.
If you have a small directory, you can fit all the data of the files in the directory
in the same cylinder.
There is no very little six.
And so if the file headers are smaller than the whole blocks, you can obviously fetch
many of those at the same time.
And the last one, remember that one of the disadvantage of 4.1, it was big reliability,
because all the inodes are in one place.
If that place is corrupted, you lost all the information from the entire disk.
But here, it's basically if some part is corrupted, and maybe you lose some inodes, the information
about some files, you can never access those files.
But many other files, they are still going to be accessible, because their inodes are
going to be intact because they are stored on different places on the disk.
Okay.
So here is another very interesting aspect, is the rotation latency.
We talk about the seek.
So the block groups are intended to reduce the overhead for the seek time.
What about rotation latency?
Okay.
So here is one interesting thing.
Initially with Unix, a lot of these blocks, you know, the block, a lot of functionality
of the file system was implemented in the operating system.
The controllers of the drive, this drive was very simple.
So now the operating system was getting a block.
Right?
So the block, say, and then needs to transfer the data from the block.
But while transferring the data from the block, the head was on top of the next sector.
Okay.
And then you don't know, right, and then you are going to miss reading the data from the
next sector.
Right?
So basically, think about this.
I want to transfer the data from sectors one by one.
Assume that the data is on contiguous sectors.
So it's great.
Right?
But now the problem is that I read the data from a sector and while I'm transferring the
data from the sector to read it, the head is on the next sector.
Right?
And then I missed that.
I missed the beginning of the next sector.
Right?
And then I need to wait for the entire rotation of the disk to get the next sector.
So one original techniques to address this problem, it was when I am writing data on
sectors is to interlink, to not write data on subsequent sectors, but skip one sector.
So that when I read the data, then I'm reading the data on a sector.
And while I'm transferring the data from that sector to the operating system, I am not going
to the next sector.
It's fine if I'm skipping it because it doesn't contain the data from the file.
And by the time the head is over the next sector, which contains the data from the file,
I am ready to read it.
OK, makes sense.
So basically here you overlap the transfer time, right?
With the rotation.
This is pretty cool.
But it turns out that actually the other solution was you just read ahead.
I read a sector and while I am transferring it after that, I'm not sure whether I need
the data from the next sector or not.
But it's OK.
I'm just assuming that I'm needing it.
So I'm going to read ahead.
OK.
And if I don't need it, I'm going to discard it.
And I'm just going to buffer it.
I just need a buffer to push more data.
OK, so that's another solution.
It's more flexible solution.
And this is actually what today it's used.
And this is implemented mostly in the controllers of the disk.
The disk has a RAM, has a buffer, if you remember.
So you read in that buffer, and then you transfer to the operating system.
Any questions about this?
So the first solution is implementing your rewriting, while the second one is implementing
your reading.
It's a question.
No, not really.
In both cases, you can think about this optimization for reading.
It's again, the problem here is that you read a sector, and then I want to-- I am going
to send the request for reading the next sector, and the next sector, and the next sector.
So I'm reading the sector, and then I need to transfer the data from the sectors.
And by the time I am going to issue the request for reading the next sector, the head, it's
already over the next sector on the disk.
Right?
Okay, so I'm reading this sector, and then I am-- by the time I am going to issue the
request for reading the next sector from the file, the next-- I'm already over the next
sector.
So I'm going-- so if it happened that actually the sector I want to read is just after the
sector I am reading, then I'm going to miss it.
Right?
Because I don't get in time the command to read the next sector.
So therefore, I am going to-- I have to wait all the way for the disk to rotate once to
read the next sector.
So what this first optimization says that I am reading a sector, and now I am transferring
and giving some time before I get the next command.
And if I get the next command, then I am going to know-- I'm going to be close to this next
sector after I skip one.
Okay?
So if I want to contiguously in this mode to have maximized performance, I need to interleave
the sectors when I write them.
So when I read them, I am going to read once, and while I am transferring and getting command
for reading the next sector, I have enough time.
So I am ready to read the next sector.
This makes sense?
How big does a track buffer usually need to be to store the entire track?
That's a very good question.
So you can read ahead the entire track.
I don't know on top of my head what is how much.
Yeah, I'll probably-- I'll try to get back to you, but I assume a few tens of megabytes
depending on the disk.
But yeah.
So Gilbert, did I answer your question?
Okay.
So it's again, remember that the disks and this controller do a lot of things under the
hood, right?
Like, remember we did last time, we learned about C-scan and other scheduling algorithms.
You should order the request so therefore you reduce the six-time rotation latency.
Okay.
So the pros of 4.2, you have efficient storage for both small and large files.
And this is because you have these direct blocks, indirect block pointers, and double
indirect and triple indirect.
So you can accommodate both small files and large files.
You have locality for both small and large files to try to do that because you try to
store them within the same block group or cylinder group.
And you also try to-- you have the locality between the metadata and data because the
metadata that is inodes, we try to store them on the same block group where the files themselves
are stored.
We didn't talk about this when we say non-defragmentation is necessary.
Non-defragmentation is necessary here because we have the bitmap.
In what happens with-- and I remember that when I used it a long time ago.
When you use FAT and when you-- or this Microsoft, early Microsoft operating systems and the file
systems, what you have from time to time, you need to defragment the disk.
Defragment the disk, what meant is this to rewrite the information from the disk so the
files are more contiguously stored.
Because the disk was fragmented.
As you delete disks, as you delete files and you write more files, it's more and more fragmented,
meaning that the data of the files is stored more and more randomly.
The blocks are more and more randomly.
And from time to time, you do defragmentation.
So you are going to try again to rewrite the files.
So to move the blocks around, so to speak, so that the files are stored on contiguous
blocks and the performance will be much better.
Here is not really necessary because I told you about these heuristics in which you try
to find a large bunch of free blocks for large files to store the data.
The cost is inefficient for tiny files.
It's a little bit unfair because it's not-- you still fundamentally need a block to store--
so you need to have storage, it's a block.
So even if you have one byte, you still are going to read or write an entire block, which
is 40 kilobytes.
And in addition, also you need an inode for this data block.
Most of the file systems will have this big advantage.
And inefficient encoding when a file is mostly contiguous on the disk, this basically says
that you know you are going to have this bitmap to tell you what the blocks are.
And if you have, you have one bit for each block.
But for instance, if the file is contiguous, stored on the disk, then you need only two
pieces of information, what is the beginning, the pointer to the first block, and the pointer
to the last block, right?
Because everything in between is contiguous.
This is what it means it's inefficient encoding when files is mostly contiguous on the disk.
And still in order to avoid this defragmentation, you need to have this kind of sprees space
on the disk.
So you cannot allocate the entire 100% of the disk space.
You need to leave around 10, 20%.
Okay, Linux is pretty similar.
You have 12 direct pointers, like in our previous examples, if you remember, when I was a little
kid, I was confused between 12 and 10.
In this case, you have 12.
And the other thing you can configure is the size of the blocks to be different sizes,
right?
You can have one kilobyte, two kilobytes, four kilobytes, eight kilobytes, and so forth.
It's again, you don't have in the same system, blocks of different sizes, but when you configure
the system to start with, you can choose different blocks sizes.
And this X2 and X3 are different versions of Linux in terms of particular or disk layout.
You also have journaling.
We are going to talk about journaling later, but it's a particular way to store the files
to provide fault tolerance.
Okay, we'll talk more about that.
And other than that, it's the same kind of organization here.
You have, these are the pointers in the group descriptor table.
You have pointers to the blocks.
In each blocks, you have inot tables.
And then the inot tables are going to go, going to go to directories.
This is how the directories are organized in EX2-3.
Okay, it's setting up.
Hard links.
Okay, sorry.
So here, we remember last time, we looked through this directory structure and the directory
structure, it's an ROG.
And what you have, typically what you can do in Unix, you can have a different, you
can have another hard link, it's called hard link, another link to the same file, right?
You can have the same file, which is basically, you can have two names for that file and these
names can appear in different directories.
When do you want to do that?
Well, obviously when I want to share a file from different directories, right?
And I want to appear to be local to that directory.
It's like, for instance, library files or things like that.
And in this case, again, I'm going to have pointers, the same, two different file names
are going to point to the same file.
And in the inode, I'm going to maintain a reference count.
Why I need that?
Because only when all the references to the same inode, to the same underlying file are
removed, I can remove the file.
In addition, I have also soft links.
The soft links provide the same kind of behavior.
It's again, they are used to create another entry in my current directory to a file which
exists in a different directory.
But this is symbolic link or soft link.
In this case, it's actually a symbolic link, it's another entry in the directory, which
basically it's about, it has a file name, the new file name, and then it's linked to
the destination file name.
So it's a symbolic link, just an entry, just something you write in your directory, which
basically links the file name, the new file name, with the destination file name, the
one which I want to link.
And in this particular case, though, if the destination file name is removed, the openings
are filed using the symbolic link name, it can fail.
Because there is no one under the hood to keep the reference counting how many other
file names are pointing to the same file.
But this is easier to implement.
So this is what it is.
And you can create both command line, the symbolic links, also hard links, also you
can have a system call to programmatically manipulate the symbolic links.
So let's look here as an example, and we are close to the end of the lecture, about what
happens under the hood.
And let's say we want to access this file staff.txt and the path name is home/cs on
c2 and then is the name of the file staff.txt.
So first of all, we need to start from the root.
So you need to have the ID number of the root and say that's the position 2.
And this one is going, obviously, is going to have here an inode.
The inode is going to contain a pointer to the data.
And this data in this case contains the directory data, directory entries.
Remember a directory entry maps a file to a file number.
Let's assume that the file number is 8086.
So now, and this is what you have in memory, what you have here down, it's in memory.
Now you read the block 8086, right?
And what do you get there?
You are going to get the I number of the file.
You have the I number and the I number for this, the subdirectory cs162.
And you are going to get from that I number, you are going to get data in that directory.
And data in the directory is going to maintain the entry and mapping between cs162 and its
I number, let's say 732.
So you go to 732 now with the I number and you are going now finally to get all the information
which is in cs162 directory, which is also you have file staff.txt here.
And once you read the data in the directory, you are going to find the mapping between
staff.txt and its I number.
So the number now is 9909.
So finally, I have 9909, which is the I number of staff.txt.
Now I can start reading the data from staff.txt.
This may require to read additional blocks before I get to the data blocks.
If this file is large and we need to have single indirected or double indirect or triple
indirect data blocks.
This is pretty much what happens.
And this is the data blocks from the file.
And that's pretty much it.
So let's stop here and we'll continue next time.
Oh, so here the question is that what if there was also a file in /.home called cs162?
I'm going to answer this question.
So basically if it was in home another file, that will be cs162.txt.
Also it will have a different extension.
So the file system will differentiate.
If the file system would have exactly the same name as a directory, that cannot happen.
You cannot have a file name and a directory of the same name in the same directory.
You can try it.
You cannot create it.
You will get an error.
Okay.
With this, thank you and I'll see you next time.
[ Silence ]