Hello everyone.
Welcome. Today we are going to continue our discussion on file systems.
And if you remember last time, we are discussing about, we ended our lecture with a discussion of
the fast file systems. And we are, which was the version, the next version of the file system in
Unix BSD after original version. And this has a lot of, quite a few innovations. And we went over
a few last time, mostly the innovation or about improving the performance like different block
sizes, you know, basically improving the rotation latency and a few more features to again, to
improve the performance. The one thing we haven't, we didn't go over is the organization of the
directories. So what is the, what is the problem here? So assume that you have a very large
directory with many entries. Now, if you remember the early file systems organized directories as
lists, this was in the case of FAT, the Microsoft DOS first file system,
or arrays and of entries or an entry is a file name and the inode corresponding to that file name.
And I know if you remember contains the entire information about where,
which are the blocks of that particular file, as well as other information about that file, like
access rights and things like that. The time was on last updated and other information.
So the challenge with that is that say, I want to locate one file, right? And whenever you are going
to, and there's a common line, or you are going to write a file names to say, see the contact to open,
you need to find that file name because in the directory, because the entry in the directory of
that file name, because that entry will give you the inode and the inode will tell you where are
the data blocks on the disk of that file. But if the directory is organized like a list or an
array of entries, then the only way to locate that file is linear search. If the directory is very
large, this linear search is expensive. Even more, you may need to read the entire directory just to
find the file. And again, if the file, if the directory is large, you may have to load all the
blocks which are storing this large directory, again, just to find the file. Okay. So what is
the solution here? Of course, the solution is to find a better structure than a list of an array.
And if you want to search, what are some better structure to search than a list or an array?
You learn about many of those. Can you give an example? What would you do if you were to design
the directory data structure, which is much more efficient in terms of search? It's a binary tree,
right? Okay. Yeah, that's pretty good. And it's even better here, we can have a B-tree. Okay. And
when you have a tree, a search tree, the depth of the tree is what gives you the complexity of
locating that particular, in our case, file, which is a leaf in that tree. So this is for you,
just a B-tree, it's a more sophisticated search tree. And if you remember, this is just a reminder
for you to refresh your memory. So here, a node is pointing out at a lower level to an array. And
that array contains values, which are smaller than the value of the pattern node. So in this case,
100 points to this array of values, and all these values 48, 50, 79 are less than 100.
Also the following node, the sibling node of 100, 155, now is going to point to a set of values,
to an array of values, which are lower than itself, but higher than its sibling on the left,
right? So these are numbers between 128 and 140 and so forth. Okay.
Eventually, you need to get to the leafs and let's see how to find a value at the leaf.
So let's see how this is used in the context of directories. So in the context of directories,
how do we get a number? Well, the number is easy to get, you just hash the name of the file. So now
we get a number and hopefully the hash is good enough. So the probability of collisions is very
small. Okay. But this is what it is. It's exactly, it's a binary search tree, sorry, it's a B-tree,
in which the values in the B-trees are the hashes of the file names.
And you can see here on the leafs, you are going to see to have the entries in the directory,
which again is a name of the file, the name and the file number or inode.
Any questions? Okay. So in this particular case, you see that the hash to out to it's C194,
and you are looking through the B-trees. First of all, you are going to look at the values,
which are, you are looking to the values, to the consecutive values as that the value on the left
is lower, the value on the right is higher than C194. And then you are going to pick the node
corresponding to that, which is for the range. And then you are going to go on level down. So for
instance, in this case, C194 is smaller than the first value at the first level. So you are going
to go take and go to the arrays pointed out by that value node, AD1102. Okay. Because remember,
AD1102, which is a leftmost node here at the top level is going to point only to values which are
lower than itself. Okay. So you are going to go to the next level, the next level, the second level.
Again, you are going to look at the values at that node, and the values are going to go from
the smallest value is C195, which again C195 is greater than C194. So you are going to go again
to the next level, it's going to be a node, which is pointed out by the first,
corresponding to the leftmost value. Okay. And finally here, you are just going to see that
you are going to have to find C194, you'll find a match, and that match will take you to the
entry in the file directory, which is the name of the file and the file number.
Okay. So Michael here has a great question. Why do we want to hash the file names? Wouldn't using
the file name themselves in lexicographical order have the benefit that it's easy to enumerate files
in lexicographical order? Anyone wants to answer this question?
Yes. The file names can have arbitrary length, so it's going to make the implementation a little bit
harder. Someone says also perhaps to distribute the hash is uniform, that's a great point,
as well. So you get a more balanced tree. If you have a hash, a good hash is going to give
you pseudo random numbers. So you are going to easily get a balanced tree once you build it.
But the other thing is that if you use a file names, it's strings. So comparing two strings
is much more expensive than comparing two numbers. Okay. So again, remember we are doing building
bit trees because we want to improve the performance. So hashes give you values,
which at the end of the day can be our integers. And just comparing integers is much easier,
it's much faster and also much easier to build data structures where the fields have
unique with the same length. Do different file systems use different bit tree types or is some
standard like 2-3-4? That's a great question. Actually, I do not know the answer to that
question. I should look around. But it's a good question. I would assume that there are some
rule of thumb here about what are the good numbers for this application.
While directory can be large, it doesn't compare with the number of rows you can have in a table.
As you probably know, bit trees are coming from database field to index the rows in a table.
So I guess you can have hundreds of millions or even billions of rows in a table.
I don't know the number of files can be large is not going to reach that value.
But yeah, that's a good question. Okay. So now we switch gears and we are going to look at
another file system and file system is Windows NTFS. What NTFS stands for?
New technology. So it's called New Technology File System. It's an interesting name because
it's always going to be called new technology. But of course, now this is like 30, 20, 30 years old.
So it cannot be that so new technology. And this is still the default on modern Windows systems.
And if you are using a Windows machine, most likely you are using an NTFS file system.
And let me just tell you what is the main idea here. The main idea here, one of the main ideas
is that instead of fixed blocks, we have variable length blocks. And these variable length blocks
are called extents. Okay. And then instead of the FAT or INOD array, we are having here what is
called a master file table. And the master file table is almost like a database. And it's in the
database because it has attribute value pairs and these attributes and the values can be different
things. So and each of these entries, which is attribute value, can have one kilobyte size.
So it's more general than the name, file name pairs, which you are finding in traditional file
systems like we learn so far. And let me show you a little bit how this is organized. But the point
is that the reason it's more complex, but this complexity buys you efficiency and performance.
And you'll see how. One is if you can find enough room on the disk and you can have an extent,
let's say of 100 kilobytes larger than any block. So 100 kilobytes extend or even higher
and just contiguous. Right. So it's very fast to read that block. There is no seek that extent.
There is no seek time. You have only one seek time you need to waste in order to get to that
extent. But then you read 100 kilobytes. With blocks, it's again, it's like they may not be
contiguous. So you are going to have more seek times and it's more complex. And not only that,
but as you'll see, like for instance, if you have a small file which is more than one kilobyte,
you can actually put in this master file table because one of these entries, you remember,
it can be up to one kilobyte. OK, and let's look. So this is a master file table
and then you have a bunch of records and these records are content depends on how large is a file.
You also are going to learn next lecture about journaling, which is a way to provide
file reliability for the files. OK, so this is a very small, it's a small file, a tiny file.
So the file is less than one kilobyte. So one of these entries is one kilobyte. So what do you have
here? You have in one of these entries in the master file table for these small files, you have
standard information, which is the usual, you know, that when the file was created or modified
the last time, maybe you want to access the last time, owner ID, some security specifiers, flags,
whether it's read only, hidden, whether you can see, like if you do like a user,
Alice, whether you see the file or not, and or it's a system file and things like that. Right.
So this is what you have in the standard information. Then you have the file name.
OK, so in the file table, master file table, you have the file name. Remember that
in the case of inode array, you do not have, you have only inode, the inode, which is the file
number. The file name is in the directory only. And then like we discussed, if the data is a
file is small, you may be able to put the entire data in this entry. Right. And then it's free.
And you are going to just read all one of these, all this record in one go. Right. So you're with
one disk access. You can read everything about that file, including the data. So it's as fast
as you can get. Right. So now what happens if the file is a little bit larger? If the file is larger,
then instead of having the data here, right, you have a bunch of pointers, attribute values.
Remember the same attribute values. So you are going to have and each of those is going to point
out to a data extent. Again, remember data extent, it's a variable size block. So in order to refer
to a variable size block or extent, you are going to have a start, a starting pointer and the length
of the extent. Right. That's enough. Okay. So this is what you have. Now, if you have other even
larger files, then what you have, you can have pointers to other extents. Remember, to the other
MTF records. So and remember at the end of the day, extent is a contiguous region on the disk.
And so these are, you know, this leaf now, so to speak, in this hierarchy are where the data
extends. Okay. So in this particular case, the attribute list is going to point to have to point
to different entries in the master file table. And this is for a huge file. It's again, you are going
to have a lot of more empty MFT records. So here we go. Right. So basically at one level to summarize,
if the file is very small, the entire file can fit into an MFT record. And if the file is a little
bit larger, then you still have on one of the MFT record, but instead of data, you have a bunch of
pointers to data extents. So it's one level of indirection. Right. And the extents are referred
by the start and the length. If the file is even larger, then you are going to have multiple MFT
records. And if the file is even larger, you are going to have more MFT records.
Okay. Directories are implemented as bit trees like we learn. The file numbers identify its
entry in MFT. It is similar with the inode table or array. And MFT entry always has a file name
attribute. Right. Remember here, right. So you can check it. It's human readable as well. How do you
implement hardlink? Very simple. The way you are going to implement a hardlink, that will be another
entry in the MFT table, which is going to point to the same data extents or is going to point to
another MFT which represents the file. It's attribute list part of the data. This was a
question. Very good. I assume that where it's attribute list, I think it's next.
Yes. The attribute list, it's again, it's part of the MFT record.
I'm not sure what you mean, what the question means about asking about whether it's part of
the data. It's part of an MFT record for that file. And it's again, you have this attribute
list if you cannot fit everything in a single MFT record, where instead of data, you are going
to have pointers to the data extents. So you cannot have this one. So here in the data part,
you do not have enough room to store the pointers to all extents.
Okay, that's great. So it's a question here from Akshay. What are the pros and cons of this,
I assume NTFS over Berkeley FAST file system? The list of extents seems similar to the list of
direct and direct pointers in the inode. So the data part is replaced with an attribute list of
larger files. Yeah. Do you want to, anyone would like to answer?
So Gilbert, you mentioned about the data part is replaced with the attribute list of
four large files. I'm not sure is that an answer to Akshay's question?
So anyway, who would like to try to answer this Akshay question?
What are the pros and cons between NTFS and FFS?
So one thing is about, remember, what is the difference between extent and blocks reviews in FFS?
Okay, so with extents, you can have any size blocks.
What FFS gives you is the ability to configure the file system with different block sizes.
But once you configure the block sizes will still be the same,
the same size, all the blocks are going to be the same size.
Right? And with a data extent, with arbitrary size, you are going to be guaranteed that in
order to retrieve and to read all the data from one extent, you are going to have only need,
only one access, only one SIC to get access to that data.
The blocks are going to be in general smaller than one extent. So you are going to have multiple
blocks and multiple blocks means that you may have to, if they are not contiguous and you are
not guaranteed to be contiguous if they are blocks, you may have to pay multiple access times to
read the same amount of data. NFS is also better for small files, exactly, Michael.
And because like you see here, for if the file is very small, it's less than one kilobyte,
then it fits in one MFT record. Well, in the previous case, you need to have multiple accesses
to load a small file, at least, you know, you need to go to read from inode,
you need to go to read the data block, which is separate. Like this is equivalent,
like the data itself will be part of the inode. Right? But with FFS is not. So you need to read
the inode, which is access. And then even if you don't have very tiny file, you still need to read
another block where the data is located. Okay. Okay, excellent. Okay, now let's move and do
something even more interesting. Memory mapped files. And let's, what are the memory map files?
You see, and why do we need those? You see, when you access a file, and what we learn,
things are getting quite complicated. And the data is replicated multiple places from that file,
you need to the operating system has to have a buffer, we are going to learn more about the
buffer a little bit later, to store the data in that buffer. And then there is another buffer to
put the data at the application level. Okay, so you have multiple copies of the data plus system
costs. Okay. But what if we could map an entire file directly to the memory? Right? And when you
are going to read something from that file, it just is like you read from that region of memory.
And when you have to write it, you write it like in memory. And eventually the operating system
will take care to write back your changes to the disk. Right? By the way, the executable files are
treated this way when we are executing a process. So now, to see the differences, let's refresh our
memory about what happens on a page fault. So you have an instruction, the instruction provides a
virtual address, the virtual address goes through MMU and you are going to get the physical page
number. And then you are going to put the page number, the physical page number is going to index
into a page table. Right? And the page table is going to give you the frame number.
And the frame number is going to be, depending whether you are going to have paging or segmentation,
you are going to concatenate the frame number with the offset and you are going to get the address
of the physical number. Okay. So you go virtual address, you get the page number from the virtual
address, it's going to point in the page table, it's going to give you the frame number, and then
you are going to get the offset of the virtual address and you are going to get the frame and
offset concatenating, it's going to give you the address in the physical memory. Right?
Now, if you are going to have a page fault, page fault means that you do not find the entry
corresponding to the page number in the page table. So what we are going to do is there is an
exception, which is going to be handled by the operating system in particular by the page fault
handler. And that is going to locate on the disk what the page and is going to load it in memory.
Maybe for loading that page, you need to pick an existing page because maybe the memory is full.
And then you are going to update the page table to point to the page, which you just
loaded in memory. And then you return from the page fault and the operating system will reschedule
that process, which causes a page fault, re-execute the same instruction. And when
you re-execute the same instruction, now you do have page table is correct. So you are going to
be able to read the page from the physical memory.
OK, so we did that in the past. This is just a refresher. So now what happens is the memory
map files. Well, very simple. It's exactly what you would expect. Here is a file on the disk.
So you are going just to map the file in the memory and you are going to map to initialize
the page table. You are going to allocate page table entries for each page of the file.
And then when you have in this case a page fault, basically when you are going that the page is not
in memory, which represent a file, which is part of the file, then you are going to load directly
the file, the portion of the file into the page. And now you are just going to read files when you
access it, when you access a physical memory, you basically access the content of the file.
OK. So this is a and I'll give you an example, some of which will clarify things.
This is a system call to create a memory map file. And this basically you provide the file descriptor
of the file and the offset from where you want to get to map the data from the file. Right.
So, for instance, if offset is 100, this means that I want to map starting with a byte 100
from the file into memory. These are some flags and protection. The other very important fields
are the address and the length. The length is how much from the file you want to map in memory.
And the address, you can even give an address. And if you give an address, then the file system
is going to try to map the file at the address it is given. But if it cannot, then it may find
another place in the physical memory with enough space to map the file, which basically is a
contiguous region of length length. And in either way, the function returns the address in the
memory where you map the file. OK. In most of the cases, you can use also this memory map
also to communicate between processes. We'll talk briefly about that later.
But here is an example of a program to just give you a sense of what memory map files
means and what is there in effect. So here is a simple program. And just for the sake of it,
we are going to type three addresses to bring three addresses. One is something, is the address
of something, this variable something. And that something is when it's a data, right?
It's a data segment, right? Then we are going to allocate something. And everything which is
allocated, you know it's on the heap. So this is address for the result of MLK. It resides in the
heap. And then the last one is you have this my file here variable, which is a local variable.
And we know that the local variables of the functions are put on the stack. So this address
refers on-- it's an address in the stack segment. Then you open a file. And this is a file we want
to map in the memory. And now we map the file in the memory. So basically, we are taking this file
descriptor. We are going to pass to a map the file descriptor my_fd. And zero, meaning that I want to
start mapping from the first byte in the file. And here there are again some flags about read,
write. And this is about whether this can be shared between different processes.
And the other important thing is that I am the first address where to map
this program passes as being zero. This time, the operating system, you are free to choose a region
of memory in the memory where to map this file. And most of the cases, this is what you are going
to give. This argument will be zero, right? Because you don't know better than the operating system
where you should put this file in memory. And my file is a return the starting address
allocated for that file to be mapped, where the file is mapped to.
So now, and then you print the file, right? So you pass the file. This is an argument of this
program and you print it. And then you write something at the address of the file in memory
plus 10. Let's write over it, okay? So let's see what happens. So first of all, when I print it,
this is when you print the file. Let's say this is a question. This is the content of the file,
right? So it's mapped. So the first three lines, so I'm invoking this program with argument test.
The first three lines are the print-ups I talk about, printing addresses, the data segment,
heap or stack. And then the next five lines are written by these print-ups. And it's basically
the content of the test file. So the content of the test files, there are four lines. This is line
one, line two, line three, and line four. And now here, I'm now this file, every content,
the content is mapped in memory. And now in memory, like I mentioned, I'm writing at the
address plus 20. Let's write over it. And then I close the file. And then I want to see what is in
the file after I close it. And I do cut.test. And this is what I find. This is line one, okay?
And then this, and then you can see, let's write over it. Because this means that, obviously,
I wrote, starting from the character 21st, the 21st character in the file, I wrote the string,
let's write over, which is exactly, and then I close the file. And obviously, everything was saved
and including the changes in this file. Does it make sense?
It's pretty cool. You should try it. Okay.
So, it's like I mentioned, you can share the files between two different processes.
So here, I have the same file and I have two virtual addresses from two processes.
And you can share, you can map the file in memory and can be shared this file
between these two processes. It's exactly like a real file, the file on the disk can be
shared between different processes. Also, you can use this map to share the data,
or to share memory and use the memory to share the data between the parent and the children
and your four children. You can also create an mf file, it's anonymous file, because there is not
a real file. And you can share to the children and then you can use it to pass data between the
children and the parents with this anonymous memory mf file. Of course, this is not backed
by the disk. Okay.
Yeah, the question here, is a file printed by the printf or the
foots? So here it's printed by the printf, this file. Puts is a special case
of printf. With printf, it's formatting, you can print different values in the same instruction.
So here, you can see the first argument you are going to print.
Because you are printing the map address and the second argument, you are
printing what? You are printing what is the address of m file. And there what you have,
you know, a bunch of, you basically have a bunch of characters, you have a string,
right? And you bring everything what you find there.
Okay.
So,
so now spans the project three design document, remember is due Saturday, this Saturday, and the
homework five is due on Monday. Basically, almost two weeks from now. So any questions about memory
map files? Okay, the next thing we are going to go over is a buffer cache. So remember, we discussed
that when you read from a file, you will create different copies. And one of these copies is in
the buffer cache, it's in the operating system can maintain a cache of the data from the file.
And in this case, you can put the data, you can put inodes, directory, directories, and so forth.
And some of these pages which are cached can be dirty, obviously. And then the operating
system has to take care that to write back eventually the dirty pages to the disk.
And really what you want the key idea, why do you want to cache the disk data into memory again,
this is an operating system memory, right? It's not in the user space memory, like memory map files,
you copy directly in the user space for this is in the operating system. So to get this data,
even if it's in memory, it's in the memory of the operating system, you still need to make a
system call to get that data. And obviously you cache it to exploit the locality,
right? There are many accesses to the same blocks. So if you have them in memory, it's much faster
than accessing the disk. So you need to do this translation between a pass,
name of the file and the inodes, and then from the block address to the disk contact, right?
The logical block addresses. So let's see how the buffer cache is working. And here it's setting up.
So this is on the right hand side, you have the disk. This is like FFS layout on the disk.
And now this is a buffer cache and the buffer cache has a bunch of blocks.
And the blocks typically are the same size as pages, memory pages. And then you are going to
cache the blocks and you can have data blocks, like I mentioned, they can be inodes and they can
be directory blocks. In Avishon, you have a free, also you can have the free bitmap. Remember,
you do have the free bitmap on the disk to maintain data about what are the available
blocks, free blocks. Okay. So this is what you have. These blocks are
the cache is organized as an array of blocks and the color represent different kinds of types of
information. And here you have a state, whether in this case is free or dirty or
things like that, or what happens, whether you read or write a block.
So let's see what happens. So let's say I am reading an inode, sorry, I am reading a data block.
So I am reading a data block, a new data block from the disk.
I am going to find an available block in the cache.
And then I am going to write, now you see the state is read. This means that now I am
reading the data from the block on the disk into this available space. Right?
And then once you read it, you are going to mark that it's no longer free. And if you write it,
you have to mark it that it's dirty because now this is modified and it's no longer the
same content as a page on the disk. So now you say you are going to read a
directory. Right? It's the same thing. You are okay if you look, you find an available block and
you read it there. Right? And you say what it is, inode.
Okay. And this is if you do it, the data is the same thing. Right? If you write it,
now you say dirty, the data is dirty. This is what if you write in the block.
Right? If you write to a block, you first, if the block is not in the cache, you bring the block in
the cache and you write in the block on the cache in memory and you mark it as dirty.
Any questions?
So discussion. So the buffer cache is entirely implemented in the operating system.
Right? It's in the software. There is now TLB. Okay. And the blocks go through transitional
state between free and use, being read from the disk, being written to the disk and so forth.
And blocks contain all this variable, you know, variety of information like I mentioned,
inodes and data and directories and the freemap.
And the OS is going to maintain the management, to maintain the pointer into them.
It's also the OS is going to manage this buffer cache when the process exits, when writes reads.
And for instance, on the process exits, you are going to flush to write back all the modified
data from the buffer cache to the disk.
Now, this is a cache, it can fill up. So what happens when you fill up? Well, there is a
replacement policy. Like we know, like demand paging, if you remember. Replacement policy,
what can you do? You know, you can do allerio. It worked pretty well for demand paging. So I
want to do something like this. And this works well. And if the memory is big enough, especially
it can accommodate the working set of the particular
applications, the working set in terms of the data which is accessed from the file.
Now, the disadvantage is that it's for some access patterns, allerio is not good.
So for instance, if I'm just going to scan the file, I'm just going to read
and to read to need, I'm going to read a block only once.
So with allerio, that block is going to displace another block in the buffer cache.
But then the block was loaded into the cache. I am no longer to access again,
because I got it later. And I'm just doing a scan. So that's a problem.
So what is the solution here? It's a smart solution. The solution here is that the operating
system allows applications to request other policies. So the application knows more about
what is the access pattern. So if the application knows that it's only going to scan the file,
it can specify as a replacement policy used once. And this means that the file system can discard
the block as soon as they are used. They don't need to operating system doesn't need to maintain
that block in the buffer cache.
Now, the cache is obviously stored in the memory. So one question is that how much memory
you should give to the operating system for the buffer cache versus the memory for the map,
the processes virtual address space. If you give too much memory to the file system cache,
the access can be fast, but you may not have enough room left for the applications.
If you give too little memory, you are going to have a lot of accesses to the disk,
because you cannot cache the blocks which are going to be used frequently. So the solution here
is the operating system adjusts dynamically the boundary between the OS cache and the
application memory so that the amount of the rate of paging in are roughly the same.
Okay. Any questions so far?
Okay. Another thing about the file systems you see a lot is prefetching.
Prefetching you remember is read ahead. And we discussed that also in the case of demand paging.
Demand paging is to avoid compulsory misses. If the access is sequential, you know that if you
have one, if you access one block, then you are going to very likely read the data from the next
block. So why not bring both blocks right away in memory, right? And avoid to have another access to
the disk, which is very expensive. Right. Of course, you have a question here, how many,
you know, how much you are going to read ahead? How many blocks are you going to prefetch?
If you do too many, then it's fine, but you are going to be wasteful. Right.
And if you are going to do too little, then you are going to have a lot of more accesses.
So notice two things though. So one is prefetching is easy if the blocks are
sequentially arranged on the disk. Right. Because it's one sick time and you just
read multiple blocks. Right. The other thing is
if you are going, even if the blocks are not sequential, then you are going to provide
the disk controller a bunch of blocks you want to read. And you remember the elevator algorithm
two lectures ago? The elevator algorithms reorder the request, if it gets more requests at the same
time, so that it uses the sick time. It puts them in the order along the direction that the head is
moving. Excuse me. So the head doesn't go back and forth. It's just going in one direction and is
going to get small sick times to the next request, minimizing the sick time.
So the more prefetching you do, the more requests you are going to give the disk,
the more potential for the elevator algorithms to be efficient and to minimize the sick time.
So how much to prefetch? You just discussed. Too much. It's going to be wasteful,
both because delays, because it takes maybe a little bit more time to prefetch multiple blocks,
but also because you are going to bring this data in the buffer cache. And maybe you are not going
to use it. And this data, the blocks you are not going to use it, maybe replaced some blocks you
are going, which are used frequently. And too little prefetching, many more sick. If you have
the limit, you prefetch only one, you prefetch nothing. And then you are going to have a sick
for each new block you are accessing. This was about reading, reading multiple blocks.
The same you can also about writes. It's called delayed writes. So delay writes basically means
that it's again, when you write the data and you modify the data, the data is modified only in
memory in the buffer cache. So it is not written immediately on the disk. So therefore the writes
are very fast, they are on to memory. The writes to the file are writes to memory, if the block is
in the buffer cache. The read is going to first go to the buffer cache to see whether the block
they want to read is in the buffer cache. And if it is in, it's going to get the most up-to-date
value. Even if that block was not written yet on the disk, it's still the writes, previous write
updated the block in the memory. So we are fine here. So when does the write, the changes made
by a write reach the disk? There are a few cases. One is the operating system is flashing it
periodically. I think like say 30 seconds. Every 30 seconds, you go and scan the buffer cache and
you look at the blocks which are dirty and write them on the disk. Or obviously, when the cache is
full, then you may want to flash them to write on the disk. So what are the delay writes advantages?
Why don't you tell me here? What do you think are the delayed write advantages?
Compared with you write back every time you modify a block.
Yes, you do not have to go all the way to the disk for changing every time.
That's very good. Can you think about anything else?
So one is, again, if you don't need to go to the disk, you are going to have a performance advantage
obviously, because you're like I said, you just write to memory, you don't write to the disk.
It's also you can accumulate multiple writes. You can write to the same block multiple times
before you are going to write the block to the disk. So you have only one write to the disk
corresponding to many updates of that block. The other thing is for the reads.
If you are going to write multiple pages to the disk at the same time, you are going to
send all these requests to the disk. And the disk, the elevator algorithms on the disk,
again reorder these requests so that they are going to write close together
blocks one after another and again minimize the sigma.
Another thing is that for the layerized, you also may want to allocate multiple blocks at the same
time for a file to keep them contiguous. You can make room when you write. So you write multiple
contiguous files. So what I'm trying to say here is that when you are going to write
data and I have multiple blocks who are modified from or the new blocks, because you can create
new blocks which are in memory, they are not on the disk, if you expand the file. If you
write at the end of the file, the file on the disk is smaller. But now you are going to write,
you are going to allocate more data in the buffer cache. So now the file in memory is larger
than the file on the disk. So now if I wrote, say, worth of 10 blocks in memory, then if I delay to
write these 10 blocks to the disk, when I write them, the disk now are these 10 blocks and I'm
telling them from the same file. So maybe you can find a contiguous place on the disk to place
all these 10 blocks, one after another, which again is convenient when you read the data from
these blocks because it's there, you know, one after another. So it's contiguous region of the disk.
Again, you avoid in that case, we are going to avoid the seek and the rotation like this.
And here is a fun thing. If you have some files, you open a file during your application,
and you close it, you just use from some to have a file to create a file to share some data
between two applications. If that file is very short duration, it may never make on the disk,
right? Because it's going to be removed and it's going to be deleted, closed, right? And deleted
before you have the operating system have a chance to write it on the disk. Okay, so here I have a
question for you. So with demand paging, remember with demand paging, we have an ALERU and the same
kind of algorithms, but we are very paranoid then about the performance of the ALERU. And we
implemented some approximations and like, you know, clock algorithms and things like that,
second chance algorithm. With buffer caching, it turns out that people do not implement exact ALERU
in the operating system. So people are not as concerned about the performance of ALERU caching
for buffer caching versus demand paging. Why do you think is that?
So why do you think that in the case of the buffer caching is fine to implement the exact ALERU,
while the context of demand paging is not and we need to implement approximation?
It's in software, so not that much of a performance hit.
Well, paging is also in software, so demand paging is implemented in software as well.
Anyone?
I think it's a subtle question and it's okay, you know, if you do not
know the answer to this question. So one reason is about, think about the following thing.
Demand paging, the expectation of the application is going to, you are going to read and write from
memory. So this is what you are against. You are against in the latency provided by memory because
that's the expectation of the application, it accesses memory. So you need to be very fast.
In contrast, when you access a file, you don't have a, you know, expectation to be that fast.
Buffer cache is improving the latency, but the baseline is accessing the disk, which is slow.
And sometimes, yeah, you have to access the disk because it's a buffer, you know, that
the data is not in memory and so forth. So, you know, so that's kind of one reason,
right? Because the expectation when you access a disk is not to have the fastest
operations, right? So therefore it's okay if you are, you know, if you are a little bit slower
and actually with being a little bit slower, you can manage the cache even better, right?
Because it's no longer an approximation algorithm.
Eviction policy, demand paging.
Remember, you have big non-recently used pages when memory is slow, close to full.
With buffer cache is different. You write back dirty blocks periodically,
even if used recently, right? And why is that? The reason for that is again, different expectations.
When I read and write to memory, I don't have any expectation about the ability of the data,
right? You do expect that the computer crashes or even the program crashes.
You lose the data in memory, right? But if you write on the disk, if you think that you write
in a file, you do assume that what you wrote is persistent, right?
So now, and we'll talk about this quite a bit for the remaining of this lecture and the next lecture.
You need the operating system to try pretty hard to provide that persistence. So one way
is going it is by periodically writing the updated modified blocks from the buffer cache to the disk.
Yes, the marginal difference between ALERIO and non-ALERIO isn't that big in this context,
since this baseline, since the baseline is a disk operation which takes super long anyways.
So this is a comment by Gilbert and yeah, it's exactly correct, right? So in the case of the
buffer cache, the baseline is a disk. In the case of demand paging, the baseline is a memory.
Okay, so it's like we mentioned, in order to improve the persistency,
the operating system writes data to the disk from the buffer cache periodically.
So it flashes it like in the case of Linux every 30 seconds.
However, obviously this is not bulletproof, right?
What if the operating system or you have a failure, the machine fails
and you have dirty blocks into the buffer cache? Obviously, this information is lost,
right? And now you have the case you have from your application, you wrote something in the file,
it was open and now machine fails after you wrote. And what you wrote is not in the file.
Although as a programmer, you may believe that, well, I wrote in a file, the file is persistent,
it must be in the file because it happened before the failure. And things can be pretty ugly.
If you, for instance, you only modify a directory, if you don't modify, then you may lose entire
files because you lost their dangling files, which have no presence in the directory.
Or there are many others. You may lose inodes and so forth. So the file system needs some
mechanisms to ensure the persistence, including some recovery mechanisms to recover
kind of inconsistent state. So there are three important properties of a system when it comes
to its, so to speak,
performance availability and so forth of a system and the file system in particular.
So there are three things. One is availability and availability really tells you
percentage of time while the system can accept and serve your requests.
Okay. So three lines, meaning in this case, meaning that the probability you send a request
to the file system and you don't get a reply or it is not resolved is 0.1%.
Then durability. The durability means is that if the data is on the disk,
then it's durable, meaning that if a disk fails, there is still a way to recover the data.
Availability and durability, they are not the same because availability means that the data
is somewhere, but doesn't mean necessarily that it's accessible. And then is reliability,
which is usually the strongest one, is the ability of a system to perform its required functions as
it is defined and its application level definition, what that means to perform the function.
And it's typically stronger because it implies availability. If it's not available,
the system cannot perform its functions and also includes durability because the data has to be,
any persistent data, should be able to get access to it.
Okay. So first we are going to look about how to make this system, the file system durable.
How do you make a file system durable? What I said that what I want to ensure here is that if
I wrote the data on a disk, in a file, I want to be able to read that data at a later time,
no matter what, no matter what kind of failures were happening.
Right? So say the one classic failure is a disk failure. I wrote the data on the disk,
it made it from the buffer cache to the disk, but then that's dispelled. I wrote the data.
How do you avoid that?
Redundancy, you back up. Absolutely. It's what you are doing for your show or you should do for your
own, the most important data you have. Write to more than one disk, totally.
Okay. And there are many ways to do it. And we'll see, you can do it, read Solomon,
you're correcting codes. There are other things you can do. It is like you can have battery backed
RAMs or non-volatile RAM. So it doesn't necessarily need to be on the disk, but you can also write it
in RAM as long as it's powered as in the own battery, so when the machine fails, the RAM is
not wiped out. But to really to have the data surviving more, a lot of more long term,
we need to replicate it. And again, when you replicate it, you need to be very clear about the
assumptions, failure assumption you are making. Because if you have two disk drives
and both are on the same machine, if the machine fails, then you lost both copies.
To avoid that, you need to put copies on different machines. But if the machines are in the same rack
and the rack fails or the data center experienced a catastrophic failure,
you lost access to those copies. Now you can put the copies on several different continents,
you are going to be safer there. And you see that, right? Because typically, many of you assume
that when they back up their data, where do you back up the data? Do you back on the same machine
now? Where do you back it up? Actually, I'm curious. Anyone back up the data?
Yes, cloud. Many people bring their phone to clone the cloud.
Yeah, and Michael has a good point. Maybe also as a medium,
you want to write on different media to protect against some catastrophic failure,
which is going to involve only on media or degradation over time.
But many people write to the cloud. And the cloud actually can replicate the data
across different regions in different continents.
But now, getting back, and this was many years back, and this was
people who developed first the technology called RAID, actually developed at Berkeley
by David Patterson, Randy Katz and their student Gar Gibson, who was faculty at Carnegie Mellon,
now it's at Toronto. And you just have a replica for each disk and one you call recovery
group. And you double the capacity you need. And when you write, write is done only if you write
both at the primary and the recovery group. And that's it, right?
Now, the problem here is that the writes can be quite expensive because each write
it needs to go to two disks. And you remember when you write, you have rotation disk latency.
Well, you are going now to finish and you are going to wait for the slowest one to finish disk,
for the slowest disk to finish. That was a performance is worse for writes. Of course,
you can synchronize the disks, right? So then all both of them finish at the same time.
But that's very hard.
What about the reads? Well, it turns out that with reads you are better, right? Because
with reads you can actually, you can have twice the bandwidth because you can read for
any replica. Right? Or you can send the same read to both replicas and you get the one which is
arrived first. So it's good for reads, both in terms of latency and the throughput is bad for
writes. And also you need to double the capacity. What happens on the recovery when a disk fails?
You need to buy a new disk and then you are going to copy the data to the new disk.
Write all data to the new disk. So now you have again two replicas.
Now that was again pretty expensive. And that was RAID 1. Again, RAID
means redundant arrays of inexpensive disks, as opposed to much more expensive, presumably more
reliable disks. Here you have cheap, less reliable disks, but because you do this kind of replication
or now you see razor coding, you are going to achieve a much higher reliability, given a much
higher reliability than an expensive disk. So, and there are different again levels of RAID.
And you can look in the textbook. But RAID 5 and more, what they do, they basically,
they stripe the data across multiple disks and they add also a parity disk. A parity block.
OK, so basically say in this case, you know, in this figure that each D, D1, D2, D3, these are
disks and these are the blocks which you could, so D0, D1, D2, D3, sorry, these are the blocks,
the name of the blocks, D0, D1, D2, D3. And then to this one, you are going to add a parity block,
P0. And the one you can do it, the P0 is the XOR of the values of the data blocks. Right?
So therefore, you have four data blocks, you are going to add another one, which is a parity one.
So the overhead here is 25%, not doubled. Right? And what happens here, you can, if one disk goes
away, you can still reconstruct the data. And how do you do it? You reconstruct the data of the lost
block by simple XORing. All the remaining blocks, the three remaining blocks, plus the parity block.
It's as simple as that. Okay? And you can also spread the information not only across multiple
disks in the same server or in the same data center, you can also do it across the internet.
Right? So you can use the same technique. Okay, so I'm going to stop here. We are going to talk
a little bit more about this, how to make this durable. And next time. Okay, thank you. And this
Thursday, as you know, it's Veterans Day. So I hope that you are going to enjoy a well-deserved
lighter day. And you can take, you can get some rest. Okay, I'll see you next week. Bye.