Hello everyone. So today we are going to continue our discussion on file system reliability
and we are going to talk a little bit about transactions and start talking about networking.
So if you remember from last time, these are the three notions which are characterizing
a system's ability to function. One is availability and refers to the system's ability to respond
to the requests, to process and respond to the requests. Durability refers to the fact
that it's reflected as storage. It means that if you successfully store a piece of data,
you are going to be able to later retrieve that piece of data. So it's not going to disappear
or it's going to be lost despite maybe some storage device failures.
And then reliability puts the two together, both availability and durability, and basically
the ability of the system to perform the required function according to some specification.
For instance, if you are going to send a request, you are going to get a response within a specified
time period. And obviously that should be correct. And last time we discussed a little
about durability. And let's go again back and we discuss about this is basically a summary
of the last few slides from the last lecture. So one way to provide your ability, so it's
again the ability that once you store a piece of data, you can later retrieve that piece
of data. It's basically replicating the data. And if you replicate the data, then it provides
you the ability to survive to one failure because if one fail, you still have the other
disk storing the replica of the data. So the data is not lost. And we also discuss what
are the characteristics of this system, of this RAID 1, where you replicate any piece
of data on two different disks. One is that when you write a piece of data, you need to
write on both disks. So therefore you sacrifice the bandwidth of the write because each write
now becomes two writes, two different disks. It's also you need to wait for the slower,
slowest disk to do the write. And if you want to really optimize of how long this write
latency, you probably want to synchronize the disks. So therefore both writes take the
same amount of time, more or less. On the other hand, for reads, things are a little
bit different and are better because now you have two replicas and when you read, you need
just to get a piece of data. So you can get from either disk. So actually you can improve
or can even double the throughput in this case. And finally, if you remember, when a
disk fails, what you are going to do, you are going to buy another one and then you
are going to copy all the data from the primary disk to the secondary to the new disk. And
now you have again two replicas. Now this assumes that while you're doing these recoveries,
the primary disk doesn't fail. And that's something to keep in mind. And actually this
is a problem in general because if you do this write one and you build a write one and
your application, presumably what you want, you want this disk to be from different batches
of production. And this you need to be careful, right? Because when you buy this, you buy
all the disks at the same time to build the system. But then if these are from the same
batches, batch of production, they tend to have the same failures and the same kind of
failure pattern. And then when one disk fails, it's pretty likely that other disks also from
the same batch will fail. So you don't want to do that because you want to reduce the
minimum of the disk that during the recovery and other disks will fail. So that's why you
use different product batches or use even maybe different disk manufacturers.
Of course, the problem with write one is very expensive and so forth. So high overhead and
we discuss about this write five and more, you stripe the data. So you have a parity
block. So in this case, you have, you know, you take blocks, you store successively in
this case, four blocks on four disks and then on the five disks here, you are going to have
a computer parity block. And the parity block, one way to compute it is XOR like we discussed
last time. So D0 here is D0, XOR D1, XOR D2, XOR D3. Here is an example. If one disk is
destroyed, you can still recover. This is an example. So here is an example. Here, each
block is one bit. So let's say D0 is 0, then D1 1, D2 0, D3 1. So if you do the XOR here,
you are going to get 0. This is the content of the parity block. And now suppose this
to fail, if you do this to fail, then what you do, you are going to do the XOR or everything
which remains, which is including the parity block. And then you are going to get the content
of the last block. So in this case, D2 was 0. So you get D0, XOR D1, XOR D3, XOR P0,
the parity block, and you get 0. So you recover. It's a great question. Why do we store parity
staggered? Yeah, Gilbert answers that if they are in the same row columns, then we might
have trouble recovering if that specific row column got lost.
So basically, it's about load balancing the load when you have failures. For instance,
if the parity block fails, then both the disk or the parity block fails, at least the reads
will not be affected because all the blocks are there, the data blocks. And in the background,
you are going to reconstruct the parity blocks. So that's one reason. So it's again, it's
like if you put all the parity blocks on a disk, then if any other disk goes away, then
all the reads have to reconstruct using the parity block. So it's expensive. All the reads
are for the data from the failed disk. If the parity blocks are staggered, then again,
when the disk is a parity, when you access the data whose parity block was on a failed
disk, you don't need to do anything because the data is available.
Of course, this is the same solution in principle is going to work over also over the internet.
It doesn't need to be in the same data center or in the same rack. And then it's again,
this RAID 5, it provides durability in the presence of a one disk failure. What would
you have? What if you want to have more disk failures? There are other versions of RAID
5X and instead of parity blocks, they use erasure codes. So for instance, RAID 6 allow
two disks in replication to fail. In the replication, it strives to fail. And many of these use read
Solomon codes or erasure codes. So in this case, you have M data fragments. So you can
think about blocks and you generate N minus M extra fragments. So now to store M blocks
of M fragments of data or blocks of data, you are going to need N blocks out of which
N minus M are newly generated blocks. And this can generate N minus M failures. So basically,
you can, if as long as you have M disks are still up, then you can reconstruct any M disk
out of N are up, you can reconstruct all the pieces of it. It's again, so like for instance,
if you want really to have extremely something extremely resilient, extremely durable, you
can have like this example, you can have M is four fragments or blocks and N is 16. So
then you are going, the overhead is quite high. And by this system will be extremely
durable. And like mentioning, you can have the device, all the disk drives in the same
room or you can have them across the internet. And obviously when they are across the internet,
you are going to have a much more durable system. Because the correlation of failure
is lower. If all the disk are in the same room, if you have a earthquake or you have
a fire, all the disk may be destroyed. And here it's a very interesting aspect. And at
a high level, so say you are prepared to pay an overhead here in this example, you say
an overhead of 4x. So for each piece of data, I am going to require four times storage.
So if I store one gigabyte of data, I am going to use four gigabytes of storage. And one
thing is to have four ways of replication. So each piece of data, I am going to replicate
on four different disks. And then you compute here, this is fraction block loss per year.
And this is on the y-axis, x-axis is the repair time, I'll tell you more. But then you compute
the probability that you lose all the data, right? This means all four disks are going
to fail before you have a chance to repair them. Now, the other way you can do it is
the following thing. And that's why it's called fragments, I'm saying. I'm taking a block
and instead of replicating on four disks, I am going to take, assume that I have say
64 disks, smaller disks, the total storage is the same. But then I'm taking a block and
I'm going to divide it into 16 fragments. And for each fragment, I am going, you know,
and then for the 16 fragments, then I'm going to compute using greater codes, another 64
minus 16, 48 fragments, right? So the overhead is the same, but now I have a lot of more
fewer, a lot of more fragments. And in this particular case, this will be a much more
durable system. Let me say a little bit about this plot now. On the x-axis, you have repair
time and on the y-axis here, you are going to have probability of block failure per year.
So this basically says that as you expect, and different lines are for the number of
fragments, 48, 16, 32, 64. For four fragments is basically you have a replication on, you
know, basically on four, you can see this way, on four of the boxes. And obviously you
can expect that the repair time increases, then the probability of failure will increase,
right? Right? Because if it takes one day to repair, there is a chance that other disks
will fail within one day is much smaller than if the repair takes six months. And then now
you have in six months, the probability obviously for the other disk to fail is much higher.
But this basically, you know, and this again, this is simple probability. And this basically
tells you that the probability to have, say in this case, to have four disks to fail,
so you lose all the copies, is much higher than the probability to have all four disks
to fail, to have, you know, in this case, 49 of disk of 64 disks to fail.
Okay, so Michael asked this question, in practice, are error codes, I mean, you know, all the
parity codes ever used instead of your regular codes? If you have only to tolerate a failure,
I think you are still going to use the parity codes. It's just easier, or you are going
to use replication. The other one, but in general, you do use eraser codes. And eraser
codes actually they are using all these distributed file systems, also like Hadoop distributed
file systems, there are versions which are using eraser codes, and eraser exactly to
improve reliability.
Tayo asked the question, what does it mean to repair for six months? Oh, so, so think
about this is, yeah, depends on how difficult it is to repair, but in the past, you know,
you have the disk homes, and you lost some disks, so now you need to order those disks.
And you know, the delivery, you know, it may take three months, right? Because you need
to order, you need to order your order to be approved, if you are a company, and all
of these things, right? And then your disk have to be shipped. And maybe you have older
disk and your similar disk, so it just takes time. So the time, the mean repair time is
the time it takes, if you lost some copies, you lost some copies to recover these copies,
and because and for that you may need to buy additional hardware to replace the one which
has failed.
Okay.
Make sense?
Okay, and here is an example about using and storing the fragments over the internet.
Right.
Okay. So again, just wanted to make sure here to go back that what we are saying here, when
you do the replication, again, you have one block, so say one block is one kilobyte, so
you replicate, you have four copies, one kilobyte on different nodes. When you do the fragmentation
here, you take one kilobyte and the divide is out block, you divide in 16 fragments.
So for 16 fragments, you are going to have what? It's two power. Yeah, it's one kilobyte
divided by 16. And this is, I believe it's what, 128, something like that bytes. So now
you have this kind of, it's not, you have, sorry, you have 64, right? 16 times 64.
Yep.
So divided one kilobyte in 16 fragments, and then you are going to, each fragment now is
going to have 64 bytes. And now you are going to generate another 48 fragments, each of
them of 64 bytes using great approach.
And now in order to read the data, you need to read 16 fragments. Any of these 64, any
16 fragments out of 64 fragments will do it. And you can construct and construct the original
block. Make sense? Just, I need to make sure. We are on the same page.
Okay. So this is about your ability, but this is not enough. The fact that the disk, the
data is still on the disk. It doesn't mean that you can access it. Also, it doesn't mean
that, you know, you are also able to write the data on the disk in the first place. Right?
So that's why we care about reliability. Reliability is looking at the end to end. It is not, doesn't
care only whether data is on the disk, but whether you can put the data on the disk and
you can retrieve the data from the disk.
So next we are going to talk about reliability, but let's see, let's, let's talk about what,
what can go wrong, right? And which is orthogonal to durability, right? So say a disk loses
power, or you have a software crash. Now you have a read operation or write operation.
What happens with that write operation, which is in progress? Maybe can be lost, right?
Or maybe it's interrupted in the middle. You just wrote half a block, not the entire block.
Okay. So RAID doesn't do, doesn't protect any of, against any of such failures, right?
RAID basically says, well, if you are successful to write data and you have so many replicas,
if you're, once you've done that, I guarantee that you find the data when you come next
time, it still be stored. Right? Right. So yes, you need your ability, but this is not
the entire story. So this is what we are going to talk next. Right? So and why is this, this
a bigger problem? This is a bigger problem because when you write data on a disk, when
you write a block of data in a disk, it's not only that piece of data. You need maybe
to update, you need to update the inode data, right? Because you have a new block now. Maybe
it's an indirect block, the pointer to the indirect block, you know, the indirect, interaction
pointer. You need to update the bitmap of the, which files are now available, oh, sorry,
which blocks are available, availability bitmap, right? If you're writing a block on a block,
that block is no longer available. So I need to update the bitmap. Right? So for each of
these writes, you need actually to touch and multiple, you need to touch multiple pieces
of information from the disk. And if some of them make to the disk, but some of them
do not make the disk, you are going to leave the disk in an inconsistent state. Right?
So that's a problem, right? How do you do that? Not only when you have this kind of
multiple operations, which means all to succeed in order for the write to succeed. And, and
by the, you know, so, so that's kind of the problem, right? And of course you also, there
are other complication because if you aren't concurrency for improving throughput, so you
want to, to perform this operation in parallel and think in sensing like that. Make sure
it makes sense. Any questions? So what are the stress to threats to reliability? Like
we discussed is interrupted operation, crash of software crashes, power failures. And when
this happens, then you can get into trouble. This is a classical canonical example about
the bank transfer. You know, you transfer from one bank to another, from one account
to another. What happens if you have a failures after you withdraw some of money, but before
you have a chance to deposit the sum of money in a different account, then you lost that
money if you are not careful. So it's also this one, the failure of non-volatile storage,
right? Storage media may cause previous store data to disappear or be corrupted. Like we
are going to see. So any questions about what problems you are trying to solve here? So
you are trying to solve here, the biggest problem is that when you are going to write
the data on the disk, the biggest problem you do not want in the presence of failures
to leave the data on the disk in an inconsistent state. That's what, that's a problem. There
are two ways to do it, two general ways. One, you are just careful, you carefully order
the operations such that if you have failures, when you restart, you can clean up the mess
and leave the disk in a consistent state. That's one. The other one is copy on write.
The copy on write, you can think about the data you wrote is immutable. And when you
write, when you try to modify some piece of data, you basically create another copy and
you modify the copies. You don't modify the original. So original is always there. And
when you are done, you are pointing to the modified copy and maybe you can garbage collect
the original. Okay. So this is what it is. So the left hand side, the careful ordering
of recovery choose by fact and fast file system, the Unix. This is a file check, file system
check. It's a command you run when you reboot the system. This command runs to clean up
the disk if there are problems in consistent data. And really you are carefully about the
order in which you are doing these operations. Like for instance, you create a new file,
you need to update the directory, you need to update the free bitmap, to update the inode
to update the data book. Okay. So this is a careful ordering approach. So as a high
level is again, problem I want to solve, a failure shouldn't result in the data of the
disk being inconsistent. The solution you need to order carefully all the writes to
the disk, which are needed to store that the piece of data, such that when you are going
to restart, you have enough information so you can clean up the disk from any partial
and wrong information. This is also used at the application level by say editors like
ORB or Emacs. So let me ask you this question, because this is the core to understand this
technique. Assume you need to store a piece of data and the directory entry to point to
that data or a point of the data. And assume that each of these operations is atomic, but
there are two different writes, one to update, to put the data on the disk and the other
one is to update the directory. And tell me now, this question is the following. Which
one you should write first, the data or the pointer? Data. Why? That's very good. Why
is the data? It's exact. You don't want the pointer to point to the bogus data. You don't
want dangling pointers. Excellent. Right. And then say, so this is correct. First you
write the data and then you write the pointer. Now say you have a failure. You're successful
to write the data, but not the pointer. What do you do when you restart the system? Because
now you have inconsistent state. Yes, you need to garbage collection. Yeah. Collect
somehow. So basically you look at all the data on the disk, all the blocks, and you
see whether there is a pointer, there is a directory entry in this case for that. If
it's not, you are garbage collecting it. So this will appear like the write has failed
in the first place. Didn't happen. Which is okay. Yes. If we write data, but no pointer.
So Michael is asking if we write data, but no pointer, is that the same as writing nasty
at all? Yes, it is. But now that space may be used. So you need to garbage collect. Yeah.
This assumes that is very good point. It's assumed that you also update the free map.
That's why I make, I simplify the example. In general, you need to update the free map.
You need to update the inode like we'll see next. But in this case, I assume that when
you write a piece of data, that block is already allocated. So therefore you need to garbage
for it. Okay. So now it's very easy for you to understand. So here are the normal operations
for Berkeley FAST file system. You allocate a data block, you write a data block, you
allocate an inode, your IZINode, which is pointing to the data block, you update the
bitmap of free blocks and inodes and update the directory with a file name pointing to
the inode number. And then you update modified time for directory and you update the modified
time for the directory. Right? So you start from the data and you go backwards all the
way to the directory. And what do we do on recovery? Like we discussed, you scan the
inode table and there is any unlinked files, not in any directory, you delete it. Right?
Or maybe you put in lost and found directory if you have one. And then you compare the
free block bitmap against the inode tree and to see whether they are consistent. Right?
It's again, we just scan directory are missing from the bitmap. They are not reflected in
the free map. You garbage collect. Right? And then you scan directory for missing update
and access times. So now you do all of these things. It's again, it's a more involving
procedure because you are here, you have to write more pieces of data and which are associated
or linked with a data block when you write a data block. But fundamentally the same idea
like we discussed earlier on. When you have only data block and a pointer to the data
block. Obviously the problem with this one, if you want to do it is the time is proportional
to the disk size because they need to look at all blocks. Any questions? So this was
the first solution. How do you recover a failed recovery? Well, for the fail, that's a great
question. For a fail recovery, you make sure that when you are going to take the actions,
you are taking the same actions that when you recover next, you can still clear clean
up everything. Okay. So that's what it is. You apply recursively the same idea. The second
one is copy on write. So this is also called cow. And you fundamentally create a new version
of the file. This is a simple implementation of this is that if I'm going to update a piece
of data, if I want to update a piece of data, I don't update in place. I create a copy and
I update the copy and later I can delete the original. And it seems expensive, but the
updates can be bad. If you have multiple updates, you can do it at the same time. And if you
remember, if you send a batch of writes to the disk, the disk can be smart. This controller
can be smart to reorder them. So to minimize the seek latency and even the rotation latency.
This is a network. This approach, copy on write, is taken by a few other systems. ZFS
is Oracle now, and there is also an open ZFS and NetAppliance. It has this write anywhere
file layout or waffle. They use the same technique. And here how it is. Assume that you have the
file is represented as a tree of blocks. And you are just updating what is called here
as a fringe block, as a block at the end. You start with all and you are adding more
blocks to this file structure. So now assume that you update these blocks on the right
hand side, the one which is half blue. So what you do actually in this particular
case, you write in a new block, a copy. That's all you write. You took this block, you replicate
it, and you update the replica. The original block remains untouched. So now what you do,
you just basically generate a new bunch of pointers, a sub-tree, and then you are going
to connect these new nodes in the new version of the tree to the corresponding existing
tree nodes.
So now if you are successful in updating all these pointers after you updated the data,
then the old version, the version of the tree and of the file move from the old version
to the new version. And once you do that, you can do garbage collect the rest. You see
all the blocks, data blocks from the old version of the file, as well as interior nodes in
the tree, again, which are not pointed by the new version, they've been garbage collected.
So any block, any interior node to which there is no black arrow pointing, this can be garbage
collected. And now you have a new version. So this again, it's like you are going to
move from old version to the new version only in the last moment, once you update all the
interior nodes of the tree and obviously the data. You updated the block after you copied.
If you are not successful, if you fail during this process, it's okay. You have the old
version, the old version is still consistent. It don't reflect the new update, but again,
that's okay. The main problem when you try to solve here is to not leave the old story
system in an inconsistent state. Any questions? Oh, is this better or worse on SSD? It seems
like we are writing a lot more, but don't have to erase as often. Well, yeah, it's worse
for SSDs because you are going to wear the SSDs more. But again, we have other solutions
like you'll see. But in general, this is worse. You still need to erase because you need to
garbage collect. Garbage collection means you're a rater. But a great question. Okay.
So this is, like I mentioned to you, ZFS, ZFS has variable size blocks, is a symmetric
tree. So basically the tree you are building is symmetric of a certain depth. So basically
you know because symmetric is like how large or small is. If you know the depths of the
tree and you know what leaf, the leaf where you are at, you can estimate the size of the
tree pretty accurately. If it's balanced, right? If it's symmetric. If it's not symmetric,
then you cannot do that. You store the version number in the pointers. So you know the pointer
to which the version number belongs to. And like we saw before, you can create a new version
by adding new blocks and new pointers. And as the tree expands, you are going to garbage
collect the old data, the old pointers to make room for the new data.
So and in this case, you try to batch everything. You try to batch the writes. You try to batch
the updates to the free space and so forth. OK, so now let's talk about more general solutions.
So one solution which you are going to talk about also next time, now it's just briefly,
this transaction. So fundamentally, what we want here is remember, we want to avoid to
have to remain in an inconsistent state. And we remain in an inconsistent state because
we have multiple related updates. So if only part of the updates happen, then you have
an inconsistent state. So we had this problem before. And if you remember, and we talk about
critical section, we talk about that when I talk about atomicity. Right? With atomic
operation, we want all of the operation to happen or none or so. The same idea is this
transaction for the story system. This is called some transactions. They are more than
atomic operation because they also require durability and other properties. But the idea
is the same. A transaction contain multiple operations. And the semantics should be either
all the operation in a transaction are going to happen to be successful or none of them
will happen. So if you are failure in the middle of the transaction, then it looks like
none of the updates in the transaction ever happen. The entire transaction fail. So we
discuss about this and it's again closely related to this critical section and with
the concept of atomic update for memory. So in some sense, the first file system, which
approach to carefully ordering the sequence of updates and then recover from inconsistent
state when you restart, it's a primitive form of implementing this idea.
So again, we discussed that just to draw home the point, a transaction is a bunch of operations
which take a system from a consistent state to another consistent state. And therefore
we want all the operation in the transaction to happen or none of them to happen. If none
of them will happen, you remain in the previous state, which is consistent by definition.
If all will happen, you are going to move to a new state, which is again will be consistent.
So in one way, transaction extends the concept of atomic updates to multiple data structures
from memory to persistent storage. So what is the typical structure of the transaction?
You have a begin transaction, you have a commit transaction or end of the transaction, and
then you do a bunch of operations. If you fail during these operations, you are going
to roll back to undo the effect of the operation who have succeeded. So this way you are guaranteed
that if you fail during the transaction, then all the operation will be undoed. And from
an external observer, it appears that the transaction, nothing from the transaction
happened.
So these are examples in which you are going to transfer $100 from Alice account to Bob
account. There are a bunch of operations here to update the account of Alice and Bob and
to account the branch, how much money is in the branch, assuming that Alice and Bob are
in different, their accounts are in different branches of the same bank. For operations,
all of them should happen in a transaction.
So this is what you do. You have these operations, you know, here is on the exercise, it is a
time. This is how it appears. And then there are these operations that can be interleaved
these operations from other transactions. So they are transaction actually, like we
are going to see next time can overlap. And then you have start transaction and end commit
transaction. So any questions?
So let's see how transactions are used for file systems. You can see a little bit about
how they could be used. And basically the changes are treated as transactions. And there
are two kinds of file systems here, two types of file systems, log structure and journal.
In a log structure, the data stays in the log and logs are updated using transactions.
In a journal file system, log is used only for recovery. The data is still on, you know,
in the traditional data format on the disk. We are going to look to journal file system
in the next couple of slides.
So it's the same idea a little bit, always, like is that you don't modify data structure
on the disk directly, this idea. You put some of the changes on the log. And only after
you are done, we so to speak, the transaction with all the changes, you push the changes
to the disk. And it turns out that as long as the log is persistent, even if you have
failures, you can always recover. We'll see, we'll show some examples.
So this is exactly what I said. You write the updates of the transactions, the related
updates as a transaction in the log. Once the transaction is committed in the log, you
can now start applying those operations in the transaction on the storage. If you fail
in between, it's OK, because when you come back, you have enough information to continue
to update the disk, the data on the disk.
Once the log, all the updates in a transaction are successfully applied to the disk, you
are going to remove the log. So this is Linux, use Jarnold file system and basically took
of FFS like file system and applied Jarnold's. OK, and there are many, many systems using
journaling file systems. OK, so let's before to see, you know, to get a sense about how
journaling is working, let's look again, what are the typical updates you need to do when
you are going to.
Write data on the disk. For now, there is no journaling. So you need to do what you
need to find a free block, the yellow block, there is a free block. Good. You need to find
a free entry, in the inode entry. You need to find where you are going to insert and
in the file directory where you are going to insert the entry which associates the file
with the inode, the file name with the inode. And then once you update, you find all these
free available spaces, you start to write. You write in the free map space, you say,
you know, you mark that you allocate the data. You write an inode entry to point to the block,
you route and you write the directory entry to point to the inode. This is what you do.
Right? And remember, if something happens, wrong happens, it can leave the disk in the
inconsistent state. So now let's see how we address this problem in journaling. Journaling
is locked. So instead of writing journaling to the disk, you write to the lock. It's non-volatile,
it's on flash or on the disk. So what do you do? You find the free data block. Again, like
these are the operations, right? Find free data block, find free inode entry, find a
directory and insertion point in directory for adding the directory entry to map the
file name to the inode. This is what you do. You start the transaction and you write this
operation. Okay, so now you don't write directly and to update the free space map. You put
the operation to the updates, that free space map in the lock. You don't update the inode
table to point to the new block. You write that operation in the lock and the same, the
operation to update the directory entry, you are going to write in the lock. And now you
commit it. So all updates, all operation to update information on the disks are in the
lock. Nothing happened so far on the disk. And then once you are done, you are going
to go through all the operations in the locks and you are going to update now the data or
the information on the disk. So you copy all the changes and you advance the tail of the
lock. And now when the tail goes over the commit, after you execute all the operations,
modify all the operation from the lock on the file system, you can discard that lock,
that transaction in the lock. Okay. So let's say that I was only successful to write to
the locks only the operation to get to the free space to modify the bitmap, free space
bitmap and the pointer to the inode. In this case, if I am coming back and assume that
after these two operations are returning the lock, but before the transaction ended, I
have a failure. So at the second in this case, if I come back, right? The only thing I need
to do is to remove this operation to remove from the lock because it is fine. It's fine.
Still nothing has been applied on the disk. You apply the changes on the disk only after
the transaction is succeeded on the lock. So after you, after the commit. Okay. There
are two questions here. Can you have a fail when while writing the lock? Absolutely. But
then everything will be cleaned up. Like in this case, you can fail while you're writing
on the lock. And then when you come back, you look at the incomplete transaction, you
clean them up because you know that nothing from the transaction, which was not finished
for me, it has been all applied to the disk. What is the big difference between writing
directly? The big difference from writing between writing directly and writing in the
lock is very simple, right? It's basically because I have a lock and I have, you know,
then I can easy reconstruct the state to make it consistent on the file system. Otherwise
it's more difficult. Remember like with a files check for the fast file system in order
to make the state consistent, you need to go and to sequential look over the entire
disk. This is extremely slow. It's again, here in the log, we assume that we know that
a write has been completed. Assume that we know that. The disk eventually will tell you.
If the disk doesn't tell you, then we assume that it doesn't. Yeah. So the question here
is that basically see how do you ensure the sequentiality? Well, you make sure that the
controller for the log is not going to reorder the writes. This is an excellent question.
Very good question. Okay. So you saw how this happened. If you, and now we saw that what
happened if you just a log was partially written. When you come back, you just remove the entries
from the partial logs and you are done. But now let's assume that, let's see what happens.
But now we committed the log, the transaction. So now we need to apply all the operation
in the log. We need to apply them to the disk. So what do you do? You start from the matching
commit and then you are going to, what you are going to do here is basically is again,
every of this operation is idempotent. Meaning that if you apply it multiple times, you are
going to get the same result because it just writes. The writes one write is particularly
idempotent. If you write the same value at the same location over and over again, you
are still going to get the same value no matter how many times you wrote. And here is what
happens here. It's about, again, if you are going to successfully apply all the operations
to the disk, you are done. You can garbage collect like you've seen. But now assume that
you have a failure in the middle or you're applying the operation from the log to the
disk. So what do you do? Simple. When you come back again, you'll go from the beginning
and you apply all the operations. And because the operation are idempotent, it doesn't matter
how many times you apply them. Eventually you are going to finish. Right? And then you
are going to garbage collect the transaction. So the question, how does discard the log
work again? When the machine started writing the logs, the disk, that it's already updated
partially. How do we undo the only part that is not permitted? So maybe I was not, it's
a great question. Maybe I was not clear. There is nothing you are going to update on the
disk unless the transaction is being committed. Nothing. You see this operation, let me just
make that very clear. These green things, they are not modified. I just found these
entries. Right? Nothing has been modified on the disk. You start only modifying once
you route the transaction has committed. Now you can start to go back and you apply all
the changes in the transaction on the disk. Only now you update the data on the disk.
Not before. Did I answer your question? Another question, can we even tell which portion of
a committed log is finished? It's again, you don't need to know, right? You don't know
which is finished because you are going to repeat from the beginning. Every time, if
you didn't, you know, when you go back, when you restart, you are going to redo all the
operation from the log. It doesn't matter whether I already done previously, I've done
a few. See, I have three operation in the log to apply one to three. I applied this
operation one and two, then I failed. When I come back, I'm starting again with one,
two and three. And then hopefully I'm successful to apply three and then I'm done. And I can
apply one and two again because one and two are writes and they are immutable. They are
going to write the same value. So it's okay. Okay. So, you know, why goes through all this
because it makes it easy to reason and be quite efficient to make sure that the state
on the disk is persistent, it's consistent in the presence of failure. Isn't this expensive?
Yes, from one perspective it's expensive because you are going to write twice. You may write
the data, you know, you are going to write on the log and then you are going to write
data on the disk. However, you know, the modern file system is, I forgot to mention, they
have different optimizations. So to do it, you can have different optimization. Like
for instance, eventually the data, you can write it directly and if you fail, then you
eventually recover at a later time. But there is one actually I want to ask you, can you
see one reason actually journaling file systems can be also, can journaling can be good for
performance? If I tell you that journaling can also help with the performance, why do
you think that will be the case? How is the log organized?
the sequential rise are fast. So all the rise in the log are sequential, so they are
very fast. And then later you can actually batch the updates from the logs to the disk.
So you can do them as efficiently as you can. That's the reason. So it's not all bad when
it comes to performance. Okay. Announcements, projects three, design review this week. This
is the last round of design reviews. We are close to the end of the class. Homework five
is due Monday, next Monday. And as you know, we have the midterm grades were released.
I think you did congratulations. You did very well. The first exams, I mean, was around
50 percentile, 50 percent. Now it's almost 60 percent. So great job. Okay. Now we have
another a little bit more than 12 minutes and we are going to switch the gears. So we
are done with file system reliability and with file system in general. And we are going
to start talking about distributed systems. So why are talking about distributed systems?
Because they are everywhere. Because we need to scale all these workloads. And they require
a lot of machines, a lot of resources. Which means distributed systems. Because any application
today you are using almost, it has a backend, which is somewhere in the cloud. Connecting
your app, the front end of your application, which runs on your device with a backend,
is another distributed system. Okay. So you have everywhere in your car, there are 50,
100 microprocessors. They are connected by a bus. That's also a distributed system. There
are two kinds of distributed systems. One is centralized and in which you have a coordinator,
a server, for instance, all the machines are connected to one particular server. It's called
also client server model, this one is on the left hand side. The right hand side is peer
to peer model. The peer to peer model, it's more, every other node can communicate with
every other node. The communication is less structured, it's more general. The kind of
client server, it's also implemented by some of the distributed systems like frameworks,
like Hadoop, Spark. Okay. And this is, yeah. Okay. So, and like I mentioned, distributed
systems can be on the same car in the same, you can have, the context can be widely different.
You can have a distributed system in your car, in a room, in your home, in your building,
data center, or across the globe. So there are many reasons again for being distributed
systems. Some of them, because the applications, the users, you want to connect the users and
the users at different locations. Some of them, because like I mentioned, one server
cannot do, is not powerful enough to support all the workload, to perform all the workload.
Okay. But there are also other reasons. Sometimes it's cheaper and this was the truth, like
it used to be that if you want very powerful computers, you build supercomputers, you can
still build two great supercomputers. These are very expensive, takes a year to build,
to deliver. And then with the rise of the internet, and in particular, Google drove
the charge and that was based on some research which was done at Periclei, network of work
people started to replace supercomputers with a bunch of servers, commodity servers, servers
you can buy online or whatever. And then you connect the servers and now you have a much
more powerful intelligent software on top that on the aggregate, they can provide you
a lot of power, computation power and storage space. Okay. So what is the promise of these
security systems? One promise is higher availability. If one machine goes down, use another one.
Right? Despite some failures, actually all the services in the cloud are pretty reliable.
Your Facebook, Google and so forth, they are pretty reliable, more reliable than your laptop.
Better durability. You can store like we saw the data in multiple locations across the
globe. And also in principle, more security because you have multiple pieces, you split
your application in multiple pieces and now you need to protect only one piece at a time
and securing one piece presumably it's easier than securing the entire system. However,
you need to be very careful and it's not easy to deliver on that promise. And in general,
there have been many systems, real distributed systems, which provides worth of everything.
Worth availability, worth reliability, worth security, worth availability. This is Leslie
Lamport during our winner. You'll hear more about him before the class ends. But he was
having this quote. It's like a funny quote. "A distributed system is one in which the
failure of a computer you didn't even know existed can render your own computer unusable."
Okay. You know, you can think about, you know, if you have your email and email server, right?
If your email client works on your computer, but the email server is down, you know, your
computer is pretty useless for email. Worth reliability. If the data, you are not careful
of the data and you don't know where the data is. If the computer crashes or storing the
data crashes, then you lose the data. And worth security because, you know, if you compromise
a component, maybe you can compromise the entire system. Also, coordination is more difficult.
Remember, we have all these challenges to coordinate on the same machine between
different threads, critical section, deadlocks. Remember that? Now, this is much more complicated
because not even on a single machine. It's across the network. And you remember to address
these challenges, we have this kind of very convenient primitives like test and set or PNB.
Well, these are atomic operations, you know, based on atomic operations implemented in hardware.
Well, how you are going to implement this in a distributed system? When machines can be
thousands of miles away. And fundamentally, the security, the trust, it's more difficult
because you need to be careful that even if a component of the system is compromised,
then other parts of the system are not compromised. And this is corollary to Lamport quote.
A distributed system is one where you can't do work because some computer you didn't even
know existed is successfully coordinating an attack on my system. So it's again,
a compromised part of the system. You can bring that down the entire system if you are not
careful in designing these systems. So now when you design a distributed system,
what are your goals? What are the requirements? And simply the requirements you want to have
is to be as transparent as possible. It's to be almost maybe like your laptop, more or less.
Right? You don't want to be aware about there are so many machines. When you get this transparency,
like for instance, when you use your Facebook application, do you know how many machines are
involved in answering some of your requests, in sending the news feed or, you know,
messages, chat, videos, you know? No, you don't. That's transparency, good transparency.
And the transparency as you can imagine has multiple dimensions, location.
You don't know where your servers, the servers handling your Facebook account are located.
Migration. Sometimes you need to move the data from one place to another to scale up the system.
That should be also transparent. You are not aware about replication. You don't know in how
many places your data is replicated. Concurrency. You yourself, you cannot say, cannot tell how many
other Facebook users are at the same time on the system. Still your experience is the same,
whether there are 1000 or 5000 or 5,000, right? That means transparency. And you also want to be
parallelized. I mean, if you want to have a big job, you want the system to somehow transparently
split it ideally, and then execute multiple pieces as possible in parallel on different machines,
so it is running fast. And fault tolerance for sure, like we discussed. If there are failures,
you absolutely do not want those to see these failures.
So any of these things requires the nodes to some computers to communicate between themselves.
And this is what protocol exchanges. Okay? So the protocol, it's an agreement about how to
communicate. It has a syntax which describes the commands, the syntax of the send message,
for instance, receive message. What are the fields? What are the type of fields?
Name of the commands. And then in semantics, when you send some packets, what really happens?
What actions are taken? In general, this is a description of a state machine,
a protocol. You receive a message. You are in a wait state to wait for a message. You receive
a message. You go into a state to process a message and things like that. So,
okay, we are on the top of the hour, so we'll stop here, and we are going to continue next time.
Next time, it's going to be an exciting lecture. We are going to talk about protocols. We are going
to talk about the Byzantine general problem, consensus problem, and we're also going to talk
now about real transactions and to see how they are implemented under the hood.
Thank you and see you on Monday. Good luck with everything else. Bye.