Hello everyone. So today we are going to talk about a few things, I think all very interesting
topics. In particular, we are going to talk about transactions, how in general, how do
different computers can agree with each other. And then we are going to talk quite a bit
about networking. So let's start. So if you remember from last time, we discussed about
retouching the protocols. And protocol is a fundamental concept when two parties are
communicating. Because you need a protocol to see how everyone is going to perform the
communication and how it's going to interpret the communication. And like we discussed last
time, there are two parts of a protocol. It's a syntax, and the syntax is basically described
as a structure, the commands of the communication protocol. And then there is a semantics which
describes the meaning of the messages, the meaning of the commands. And these are typically
implemented by state machines. So you send a message, what is a state machine means here
is that you are going in initial state and from initial state, you are going to send
a message and then you may transition in a state in which you are waiting for a reply.
That's the difference. If you wait for a reply, the reply doesn't come, then you may have
experienced a timeout and you are going to go into another state and you are maybe you
are going to resend the original message. Just to give you a sense. And also if you
want the protocol to be fault tolerant, one way to do it is to store its state, the current
state of the protocol, so that when you are going, when you come back up after the failures,
you know where you left. And here it's a very simple classic example. So this is about,
for instance, when you talk with someone who is by telephone, by phone, you pick up the
phone, you open it and listen for dial tone. Today on the cell phones, there are no longer
dial phones, but if you used one of these older phones, you know that it's a dial phone,
dial tone. And dial tone, meaning that the phone is available, you can dial in the number.
If it's busy signals, then you cannot. Well, you can, but nothing will happen. So you dial
a phone number and then you hear the ringing. This means that the other person, the phone
rings to the other person and then colleagues is going to answer hello. And then you are
going to start the conversation. And then typically there is some kind of protocol.
This is again, describe the protocol. Then typically when you wait for an answer, what
do you do? You pause, you don't continue speaking. You ask a question and then you are pausing
or when you want to give the other part of the chance to talk. And then when the conversation
ends, you say something like bye or see you soon and then you hang up. So this is an example
of protocol. And we are going to talk about some of the most important protocols in networking.
Next lecture in particular, we are going to talk about TCP transfer control protocol.
Any questions? Okay. So again, these are red lines represent basically the communication
exchange of the information between the two parties. The first group of arrows exchange
represents setting up the connection, setting up the call. You ring and then the other party
answers. But from that point you can start communicating. Then the second group of arrows
represents the communication after the connection has been established. And the last group,
it's obviously closing the connection. Last two arrows.
So now, so fundamentally now we are having an network and we are having different machines.
And like we discussed last time, many of the applications are running on different machines.
All these, your client, Facebook client and backend of Facebook is the same application.
The backend of Facebook or Google consists of many machines. On Serana queries, there
are a large number of machines which are going to contribute to provide you with the answer.
So these machines somehow needs to communicate, needs to synchronize among themselves. And
the biggest challenge here is that it's again, it's like you need to, on a single machine,
we have the same problem to synchronize multiple threads. But in the case of a single machine,
we've done that at the end of the day by using this kind of hardware primitives like test
and set, which are atomics, right? Checking a value and setting a value and that operation
is atomic. So if you remember, it's all very, very helpful to build also the higher level
of communication, synchronization primitives like PNB and things like that, or locks and
semaphores. The problem in a distributed system, that's the only way to application processes
running on different machines can communicate is through sending a receiving message. That's
the only thing you have. And sending and receiving a message is atomic in the sense that typically
the receiver gets the entire message you send by the sender, you don't get half a message.
But you don't have more than that. Anyway, if you can think about this, about what the
abstraction looks like to exchange information between two processes running on different
machines, sending and receiving message abstraction is like a mailbox, right? You put a letter,
you send a letter, the recipient gets a letter and sends you back, right? So you have a send
primitive and a receive primitive. That's pretty much what you have. So now let's think
about how we are going to use these primitives to build higher level primitives. And one
of the most basic primitives is about consensus. So basically what consensus is about is that
you want multiple nodes, multiple parties to agree on a value, right? So this is what
consensus means, to agree on something, right? To pick one choice from multiple choices.
So you need to do this in an environment in which different nodes may fail, stop responding
and messages can be lost. And also the message, how long it takes a message to be delivered
can be unbounded. Okay. So this is a problem, right? And just to simplify the problem, actually,
you just think about there are two parties which wants to choose between true and false,
right? And if they choose the same, have the same choice, they commit, otherwise they abort.
Okay. And again, you need to do that in a globally scalable system and the decision
shouldn't be forgotten, especially when there is a failure, right? So you need to have some
sort of durability. So here is the example. The example is this general paradox. This
This is the one formulation of the problem.
To just illustrate the point.
So here's assume that you have two generals
who want to attack, who must attack the enemy.
In this case, the red enemy,
the red castle in the middle.
Now, if both of these armies on each side
attack at the same time, they are going to win.
If they attack at different times,
they are going to lose.
Because the enemy is more powerful than a single army,
but it's less powerful than two army put together.
So as such, in this case, the two armies need,
and the generals of the two armies need to agree
when to attack.
Now the biggest problem, and obviously here,
think about all times, you need to send messengers.
But the messenger can be intercepted by the enemy
because the enemy is in the valley,
so say in this case, between the two armies.
Okay?
And, you know, this is, it was a real similar situation
like this caster in the history of United States,
that was a battle, little big horn when he arrived earlier,
and he engaged earlier, and I believe he died.
But it's a problem.
So the power, you know, what we need to do here
is to develop a solution in which, you know,
the two generals are going to agree on the time
when to attack.
Okay? That's a problem.
So can you develop such a protocol in an environment
in which the messages can be lost, can be arbitrarily late?
It turns out that the answer is no.
And fundamentally it's, again, say one general say,
you know, I want to attack at 11 AM.
The other one say, okay, yes, 11 AM works.
But then the second one who says that,
how he knows that the first general got his message,
the confirmation, because if he didn't, right,
if he didn't get the confirmation,
then he's not going to attack, right?
And the second general will attack alone, right?
And so forth.
So I told you that there is already no solution.
Now I just want you to think a little bit,
and here is an example about an instance, right?
But can you think about, and can you argue convincingly,
there is no protocol such that under these conditions,
in which the messages can be lost
and can be arbitrarily delayed,
the two generals can agree on the time to attack.
Why don't you take, you know, a few seconds,
maybe half a minute?
To think about this problem.
And during this time, I'll get some other.
(clicking)
Okay, any idea?
Yes, there is always a final message required, Allison,
answer, there is always a final message required
to terminate the protocol,
and if that message is delayed or does not arrive,
the protocol cannot terminate.
(clicking)
Okay, yeah, this is a pretty good answer.
Anyone wants to chime in?
So the more formal proof is the following.
Assume that the protocol, a protocol exists,
and assume that the protocol has m messages, right?
Any protocol has to terminate, right?
So it must have a finite number of messages, right?
Otherwise, if it never terminates,
the general by definition will never agree.
But now think about the last message.
I am sending the last message to you, so you want to agree.
So I send the message, but that's the last message.
And I have no idea whether that message
was received by you or it wasn't received by you.
So from my perspective, that message, it's useless.
Okay?
And it shouldn't be needed for the agreement.
So then this means that the protocol
doesn't have a messages.
It's, you know, it's a protocol with m minus 1 messages
is going to be good enough.
Okay?
But then you go, so now the protocol
has m minus 1 messages, right?
And you kind of go recursively because now m minus 1,
the last message doesn't have any value for you.
So it should be m minus 2 messages.
Okay?
So that's kind of the way to think about it.
But yes, it's, Allison, it's correct.
It's about thinking about the last message.
Right?
So there always the last message for the person
who is going to send it, it's useless
because they don't know whether it was received or not
by the other party.
So now this is a hard problem, right?
It's really hard problem.
And of course, in real life, you can use other things,
but how do we get out of it?
Right?
Because we still need different parties to agree
to build any useful applications, right?
And this is where it comes,
the two-phase commit protocol.
Because we cannot solve this general problem
or general paradox, we solve a related problem.
Before going here, any questions so far
about the general paradox, the general problem?
Okay.
So the way to do so is that,
to get around the problem is that,
and now the challenges of the general paradox,
is that you still have the same problem,
which you have more than one parties agree on something,
but you remove that time during which they must agree.
So you basically say there are no constraints on time,
they just eventually will happen, eventually will agree.
Right?
So that's kind of the big deal.
And this is a two-phase commit protocol.
It was developed by Jim Gray, who has huge influences.
He was the first Berkeley PhD student,
computer science PhD in '69,
and has a huge impact on databases.
And many important database breakthroughs
are going back to Jim.
Unfortunately, he disappeared several years back
while sailing.
So what is a two-phase commit protocol?
commit protocol is very simple.
First of all, you do have a persistent storage,
so you can save the state.
And then you have two phases,
prepare phase and commit phase.
Also, not all members are equal.
You have a coordinator and you have a bunch of workers.
And the coordinator executes a protocol.
It basically sends to every worker a message,
basically asking to agree with something
or not agree.
If every worker responds that they agreed,
the coordinator is going to tell in the commit phase,
all the workers to commit.
If at least one worker says abort,
then all the workers will abort
and that entire operation is aborted.
So again, to take a step back here,
we want here that another way to think about
it's all workers, they must execute an operation.
Is that all of them execute the operation
or none of them execute the operation?
In the case of databases, that operation is a transaction.
So is that all of them execute transaction
or none of them?
So if all of them are ready,
are they going to execute the transaction,
say we are ready,
we then coordinate, they sent that to coordinator,
the coordinator will send back commit.
So everyone will commit the transaction.
Otherwise, the coordinator will send abort
and everyone will abort the transaction.
Make sense?
And like you'll see,
the logs will be fundamental to guarantee
that this protocol is going to work correctly,
which means that either all workers commit
or abort the transaction.
So again, you have one coordinator in summary,
you have N workers,
the high level algorithms is the following,
the coordinator asks all workers if they can commit.
If all workers reply, yes, we can commit,
then the coordinator broke us to everyone commit.
Otherwise, the coordinator broke us abort
because there is at least one worker you cannot commit.
And the worker just obey these global messages
where there is commit and abort.
That's it.
And we use persistent log in order to make sure
that the protocol will work correctly
when machines fail.
Now, here we assume that the machine fails
is going to eventually come up,
look at the log and continue the protocol.
But again, we don't put any bound
in terms of the time that this protocol it takes to finish.
So it's again, there are only two possible votes
a worker can make and can do, commit and abort.
And commit, it only happens if anonymously
everyone says commit.
So in the previous slide,
in the preparing phase, you remember the preparing phase
is a phase in which the coordinator asks every worker
whether they can commit or they are going to,
they can commit.
If a worker says that it can commit,
then it can do that only if it should commit.
And it's also to ensure that can accept the transaction.
And this assurance, this vote must be recorded
in the stable log.
If the worker votes abort, it must guarantee
that it will never accept the transaction.
And this is also going to be recorded in the log.
And finishing, it's all the machines have agreed to commit.
Then if all the machines have agreed to commit,
you record the decisions to commit in the local log.
And this is for the coordinator.
And then the coordinator inform every voter to commit.
Otherwise the coordinator logs the decision
to abort and send the rest abort to every worker.
The machines remember the workers from the previous slide,
they cannot take back its decision.
So we are guaranteed that exactly one of this will happen.
So basically if a worker says,
I can commit this transaction,
it cannot let later say I cannot accept the transaction.
And the other way, if the worker says,
I abort this transaction, it cannot later say,
oh, I changed my mind, I am committing this transaction.
Here is another way to look at the algorithms.
You have coordinator on the left, worker on the right.
The coordinator sends vote request to all the workers.
The workers are waiting for this vote request message.
If they are ready,
they are going to send to vote commit to coordinator.
So this means that they can commit.
Otherwise they send vote abort and are going to abort.
The coordinator collects all the votes.
If all the votes are commit,
they send the global commit.
If at least the vote is abort,
then the coordinator sends abort to every other worker.
And if the worker then receives global commits
and commits, otherwise they abort.
Any questions here?
Pretty simple problem, right?
(silence)
Okay.
So now, although despite the fact
that this protocol is simple, it's yeah.
Okay.
Two questions.
Allison question is that,
so it's okay if the algorithm stands forever.
In theory, theoretically it can hang.
It can take forever.
I'll show you how later.
Actually, let me give you an example.
One example in which you can hang forever
is that a machine fails before getting the global commit.
It says commit everything,
everyone votes for commit.
And the coordinator is going to send everyone commit.
But that machine or the coordinator,
the coordinator gets, let's do this example.
The coordinator collects all the votes.
But before, and write the result of the vote.
But before going,
replying with a global message
or sending a global message to every worker, it fails.
Now we come back,
we're looking at the global storage,
is a log that it has,
as a result of the vote, says commit.
But before again,
can has a chance to send a global commit, fails again.
So this can happen indefinitely, right?
For the coordinator.
Come up, see the results of the vote.
But before has a chance to broadcast
the global message to everyone, fails again.
Now, this is unlikely to happen.
So in life, everything is probabilistic, right?
So the probability for this to happen every time
is extremely low,
unless there is some persistent bug in the program.
Okay.
Since messages are unreliable, does the worker...
is the next question from Michael.
Since messages are unreliable,
does a worker keep sending his vote
until it gets a global procedure?
Yes, the workers can do that,
but if the messages are unreliable,
the coordinator, like we will see next,
if the coordinator didn't hear from the worker
for some time, the timeout,
then he can declare that the worker
who is not able to accept the transaction
and is going to log the result of the vote as being abort
and ask everyone else to abort.
That protocol is still caught.
What about when the worker doesn't hear from the coordinator?
So, in that particular case,
the worker has to wait for the protocol to be correct
because the worker doesn't know whether,
especially for a worker,
I hear you are talking about a worker
who said that it can commit.
We cannot finish the protocol
until it gets a message from the coordinator
because it doesn't know what to do.
It doesn't know whether the vote is commit or abort.
Yeah, so in this case, you have to ask to retransmit.
The coordinator for to retransmit is a global commit
or global abort.
But it's again, the probability this to happen is very low.
And in practice, it's working.
It's a very good protocol.
We'll go through a little bit of these questions next.
So, here is a failure-free example.
This is a timeline on the horizontal axis.
You have one coordinator, three workers.
The coordinator sends vote requests.
Then, say every worker sends vote commit,
and then the coordinator sends global commit.
Very simple, no failures.
Easy.
Remember, you are discussing in these protocols,
you have a state machine.
This is a coordinator state machine.
You are in a unique state, you receive start.
When you receive start, the next thing
what you are going to do, a coordinator, what it is.
You send the vote request.
When you send the vote request,
you go to a different state because you need to wait
for the votes from the workers.
Okay?
So, you receive all vote commits, right?
And if you receive all votes commits,
now you are going to go into different,
you are going to record.
Now, this is the result of the vote is commit.
And you send the global commit,
and now you go to the commit, the commit state.
Right?
Otherwise, you log the results of the vote as being abort,
and go send a global abort and go into the abort state.
So, while you are in this state,
if the worker blows a message,
like we discussed earlier,
and wants to get,
sends a request for the coordinator
to resend the decision,
the coordinator knows exactly what to send
because based on what state it is, it's commit or abort.
The workers is similar.
State diagram, state machine.
It's again, it says, "init," I am in it,
and I'm starting.
In the init,
I am waiting for receiving the vote request.
And from here, from the vote request,
I can do two things.
I can say, I want to abort,
case in which I am going directly into the abort state
and I'm sending vote abort,
or I'm going to go to commit.
And then I'm going to vote to commit.
Then I'm going to go to the, in the ready state,
I'm ready to commit.
And here I'm going to wait for what?
To receive either global abort or global commit.
I'm going to receive global abort.
I'm going to go to abort state.
I'm going to receive a global commit.
I'm going to go to the commit state.
So, let's see dealing first with worker failures.
So when I can be affected, if I am the coordinator,
when can I be affected about a failure?
It's really only when I am waiting for something
with the wait state,
because for init, I'm just sending a vote request.
And for commit and abort,
I just send the transition to go to the states
by sending a message.
So here I am, when as a coordinator,
I'm going to be impacted when I'm in the wait state.
Okay.
So in wait, if it doesn't receive N votes,
like I mentioned, you can timeout,
the coordinator will timeout and send global abort.
This will work perfectly fine.
It will be correct.
Right?
So here is what the examples.
Coordinator send vote requests,
but somehow worker three didn't send vote commit.
What is the message of the most?
So coordinator waits for some time
to get the commit, the vote from worker three.
But if he doesn't get it, when the timeout expires,
he sends global abort to all workers.
Okay.
And that's ended.
Now let's look at the coordinator failures.
When you can be impacted as a worker,
it's again, you are impacted by the failures
when you are waiting for something from the party,
which can fail.
And you are waiting as a worker from coordinators
for two messages, vote request, this is in any state,
and global commit or global abort.
So here where you can be affected.
So here you need to look at, right?
And now this is the answer I gave to the question
of what happens on coordinator fails.
So if coordinator fails, worker must block waiting
for the coordinator to recover and send the global message.
Right?
Like we discussed before, the worker has no choice
but to wait for coordinator.
Anyway, so let's see as a failure happening in it,
the coordinators somehow doesn't send the vote requests
because it fails before the vote request is sent out.
The workers will timeout and they can now send vote abort.
They can timeout and send vote abort.
Now you are in the ready state.
In the ready state a worker waits for the global messages.
Okay, so vote request, and somehow you have vote request,
vote commit, but now the coordinator failed.
So now the worker in this case have to wait
for the coordinator to restart
and to send the global abort in this case.
And in this example, and only then they can finish.
Okay.
But it's again, the reason for the worker,
why the worker needs to wait for the coordinator,
it's again, it's very simple
because if the worker decides, he says, I can commit,
he doesn't know what to do
because the both choices are valid.
He either has to abort or he has to commit.
And he must know exactly what has to be done, has to do
because he has to be consistent.
The decision has to be the same decision
as all the other workers.
So obviously you need to keep the lock in a stable storage.
You need to provide your ability
so when the coordinator or say he's going to restart,
he's going to find the state,
the accurate state in the stable storage.
Okay.
So that's basically what it is.
And open recovery, you have the set of rules.
if the coordinator recovers a board,
if it's in the init, wait or abort state,
the coordinator commits,
he sees the commit state, right?
So if they have, right?
The worker aborts, if it's in init and abort state,
and commits in the commit state.
And if it's a coordinator,
if the worker is in ready,
so he's asking for,
which is exactly the question we had before,
if the worker is in the ready state,
when it fails and it comes back
and you see how it was in the ready state,
it has to ask again,
the coordinator whether to commit or to abort.
Any questions?
Okay, so Miles asks the following question,
if only one global commit message
from the coordinator to worker fails,
we'd be in trouble.
Yeah, so let's see what happens.
So assume that the worker,
so the coordinator said again,
in the previous example,
we had three workers.
So assume that two messages gets through,
but one global message,
global commit message doesn't get through.
Say third worker didn't get it.
What will happen in that case?
What do you think it should happen?
If you design the protocol,
implement the protocol,
what do you do?
What do you think we should do?
Third worker blocks for how long?
A certain amount of time,
or that amount of time expires,
what you are going to do.
If you are to implement it.
So what is the natural thing to do?
Maybe it wasn't in the previous diagrams,
but that is the natural thing to do.
I don't know as a coordinator,
decide it, what I'm going to do.
Don't do anything, you are blocked.
But what else can you do?
That's something you can do that.
No, don't ask it.
It's a valid option.
Another thing you can do
is ask against the coordinator.
That's good action, yes.
You can ask against the coordinator
what you decide, that's correct.
That's what you'll do
if you implement this protocol.
Okay, so let's go for,
have this short discussion.
So why do you need DCBC decision-making?
Well, you need it because you want
in four different programs,
you want different parts of the program
which run on different machines to agree.
A very simple example is that you want
to replicate the state for durability
on different machines, right?
So you need, for instance, that's one example.
And by the way, a group of machines can come to a decision
if any one or more of them fail during the process, right?
In that particular case, if some process fails,
the other can still come to a decision, right?
Because they are okay to record,
say to commit the transaction.
So if the third worker fails,
two can still commit the transaction.
And maybe the other one, the third worker,
when it fails, it comes back and as a coordinator
and the coordinator says to commit
and it's going eventually also to commit the transaction.
So, and we said, we discussed that just to reemphasize
why 2PC is working and Generals Paradox doesn't,
is because 2PC relaxes the problem
in that it doesn't require the nodes to commit the transaction
and the nodes to agree by a certain time.
They only say that eventually there will be agreement.
And it also allows us, that's why, to reboot and continue.
Okay?
Announcements, homework five is due on Monday.
Midterm pre-grades will close on Sunday
by the end of the day.
Okay.
Any more questions about consensus,
General Paradox and the 2PC protocol?
Okay.
If not, we are really going to switch gears now.
And we are going to talk about networking.
Networking is obviously a fundamental part
of the operating system,
especially today where everything is connected.
Like we discussed so many times.
So here are the main concepts you need to keep in mind.
First is the network interfaces.
Each of your machines, the machines you are watching now
has a network card, some network or a network chip, right?
And that's a chip which communicates with the outside world,
sending physical signals, radio signals and so forth,
or signals through the wire.
Okay.
These are the physical, you know,
these are the network cards.
One computer can have multiple network cards
because a computer can communicate multiple ways.
Can you give examples about a few ways
the computer can communicate?
How can your computer communicate with some other computer?
Land, wireless optical copper.
This is good. This is good.
Right? Wireless, wifi, right?
Sounds is good.
It's a good one.
Bluetooth is another one.
Bluetooth, wifi and so forth, right?
Ethernet, you may have heard.
So therefore it's again,
one machine can have multiple cards.
Remember that.
That's network.
Okay.
So, typically each network card is associated two addresses.
One, it's a media access control address or MAC address.
This is a physical address.
And this is burned into the card
by the company which produces these cards.
So when a card was produced,
it comes with a MAC address.
Like we'll see it's 48 bits.
And then there is an IP address,
the internet protocol address.
And this is the address to which, you know,
when we send a packet, operating system sends a packet,
is going to send to one of these IP addresses,
not to the MAC address.
We'll learn more about how they bump to each other.
Okay.
So this is what you have.
MAC address, like I mentioned, is 48 bit unique identifier.
And it's assigned by the card vendor.
IP address used to be 32 bits.
It's assigned by the network administrator
or is dynamically when you connect to the network.
Typically today, almost everyone is dynamically connected.
Your laptop, your phone, when you get an IP address,
that's dynamically allocated to you.
Right, when you connect to wifi, that in a wifi network,
someone is, there is a process
by which you are going to get an IP address.
Without an IP address, you cannot communicate.
[ Silence ]
Right now with IPv6, you have 128 bits. That's the length of the address.
Then you have a connection. The connection happens between two processes.
Now, on one machine, you can have multiple processes.
One machine, you can identify it remotely by its IP address or a MAC address.
But how you are going to identify when you send a message that you want to send to a particular process out of many that are running on the same machine?
That is done using a port number. A port number is a 16-bit identifier.
It has a local scope to an operating system on which the process is running.
Local scope to the machine.
So therefore, a connection is identified by two endpoints.
Each endpoint is identified by an IP address and a port number.
And this is how two processes communicate. This is how your application communicates.
OK.
So you have MAC addresses, which comes with each card.
These are assigned and they cannot be changed.
They are assigned by the vendor, card vendor. You have IP addresses, which in general are assigned dynamically.
And then you have four numbers which are assigned by the operating system to the process.
So now, in order to identify, to send a package to one process, you need to specify both the IP address of the node on which the process runs and the port number of the process.
The port numbers are again used to differentiate between different processes on the same machine.
So what is the main network functionality? The main network functionality is delivery of a packet from between two hosts.
Across the globe. That's a problem.
You know, that's a service it implements.
What do you need to look for?
What are some properties of such service functionality?
Well, you certainly may want to be reliable.
The packet may be lost, may be lost for different reasons.
Can you think about actually some reasons why packets can be lost in the network?
If it's on Wi-Fi, yes. Radio interference and disturbance. Yeah, very good.
Someone turned on the microwave. That definitely can happen.
Cord was not plugged. Yes, I mean.
And we'll see in the packet, even in the wired networks, they can be still lost.
If, for instance, there are too many packets arriving at the routers, more than the router can handle.
So therefore, the buffer the router has is full. Then you have to drop packets.
So that's one. And now this is what we are talking about. Another thing is a flow control.
The flow control is avoid overflowing the receiver buffer.
So say you have a cell phone or whatever, which is all cell phone, which you can get data only at one, say, one megabit per second.
And I am a big server. I can send you packets. I can blast you to 100 megabits per second.
100 times faster than you can receive.
What you are going to do? There is no way you can get at that rate. Many packets will be lost.
So therefore, what you have to do, you need to push back on the sender and tell the sender, don't send that fast.
Just send, say, at one megabit per second.
OK, so this is what you need to do. This is flow control. The receiver pushing back to the server to not send too fast.
Then is a congestion control. The congestion control is avoid overflowing the buffer in the routers.
And we discussed that if the buffer in a router overflows, you lose packets. The packets are dropped.
OK.
So congestion control is making sure that the sender doesn't send too much data so that the router is overwhelmed and these buffers are overflowing.
So packets are lost.
So flow control is slowing down because of the receiver.
Congestion control is slowing down because the routers are in the network. There's a difference.
Now, we have to have right now, today, we have different nodes communicating between themselves.
Each of them executing the protocol. It has a syntax. The syntax will describe what is the packet format.
The types. Right. Right. And the syntax will specify, OK, I get this packet, what I'm going to do with it.
What action I should take.
This means that the two parties have to speak the same language, have to understand and execute the same protocol.
So we need to standardize.
If you want to communicate with someone, they have to run the same protocol.
Right.
If you want to speak with someone else, that person should speak English.
Or maybe another language, both of you know.
OK. So how does this standardization happen?
There are multiple ways. One is there is a standard out there and every software developers follow the standard when it drives the application.
Of course, the other one is basically have only one person, only one company, but I think the entire software, of course, is not desirable and is not realistic.
So that's why in general, you have the standard bodies for the Internet.
The standard bodies is IETF, Internet Engineering Task Force.
And typically the standardization happens for a new protocol, you know, someone's right, a document, we specify the protocol syntax and semantics and send to the other members of this task force requesting for comments.
It's called request for comments.
And after multiple rounds, that can become us can be approved to become a standard.
Become a standard in IETF, you don't need consensus.
Right. It's not like to PC, to face comment.
The majority has to agree. But one thing that always required in IETF is to have running code to demonstrate, which demonstrate that the protocol is feasible.
And typically you are asked for two implementation, different implementation of the same protocol.
OK.
There are also other ways to have de facto standards when some software becomes so popular, it becomes de facto standard.
And others will follow after it, like Linux.
There is no standard body for Linux, but it's a de facto standard.
So everyone follows that standard of writing the application.
OK.
So one thing about and this is a title of this networking section we are doing, we are learning during this class, during this lecture is layering.
So what about layering? What is a problem?
So the layering is a problem here is that think about you write, you know, you want to send a message from your application, from one process to another.
And that is what you know, you write some instructions, high level language, maybe send, receive.
That will be compiled down in machine code and will be executed by the processor.
And now you send it, but then you send it.
Eventually, that information you send, it needs to go all the way to the wire
or all the way to be transformed in a physical signal.
So there are many kind of steps from a send to all the way to that information to be sent on a wire, on radio,
and then to be received, the signal to be received on the other side and to make its way back to the receiving process,
which invokes probably a receive command and ultimately get the data.
And the problem here also is like we discussed, that is there is not only one way to send a signal.
There are many ways you can send the signals. You can use Bluetooth, radio signals, Wi-Fi.
You can use optical networks, optical signals. You can use electrical signals like in wire networks.
So you have many of these things. So you need to organize all of these.
Carrier pigeon. Yes, yes, yes. That's a very good one. You can do that as well.
You can send the information. Right. So this is a problem. Just thinking about application and transmission media.
So how are we going to do it? Like one way to do it.
It's basically for your application, you write your application so that it's able your converters or adapters to send to use every communication media.
Wire fiber optic, Wi-Fi, Bluetooth name it. That's one way to do it. What is the problem with this?
Kind of a lot of work. That's correct, Arison. Right.
Because you have a new application, now you need to implement this application over all this communication media.
And if you if you are the new transmission media, it's even worse. Every application now, if you want to support it,
you need to update the application to work on this over this communication radio radio over this new communication.
Over this new transmission media.
OK. So, yes, a lot of work. So what is the solution?
Encapsulations almost, but encapsulation assume something else. You encapsulate in what?
Layer protocols. Yes, you are talking about layers. That's absolutely correct.
So here is a solution. You add an intermediate layer.
There is a quote, a famous quote, basically saying that any problem in computer science can be solved by adding another level of indirection.
So this is indirection at work. You have an intermediate layer and then intermediate layer provides only one interface to the application.
And all of these applications are going to be written against the same API, the same interface.
And then if I am going to add so basically this is easy, right? I'm going to a new application.
I need to only be worried about only one interface.
To work with. And if you are going to add to add another transmission media, you just need to provide the same interface of the intermediate layer.
And then everything will work.
If a new application is going to if a new application is developed, no need to touch the transmission media part.
If a new transmission media is added, no need to touch existing applications.
Pretty cool, right?
And this has to do with software system modularity.
Right? And the modularity, whatever is going to provide the abstractions, differentiate between the interface and the implementation.
How is the implementation details? That's why when you develop the code, you are going to write functions.
The function provides a signature that's the interface of the function.
Typically the implementation shouldn't matter. You write a function to do sort.
The sorting, the interface looks the same. You provide a list.
And you get out the list order ascending or descending order.
How the implementation, how that is done doesn't matter.
Bubble sort, quick sort, heap sort, whatever.
So this kind of modularity and also it's related with encapsulation, encapsulate the functionality.
It's widely used as a method in computer science. Right? To simplify complex things.
Modularized. Right?
Now, fundamentally, you there is a there is one disadvantage of modularity is great.
Because, again, I can sense I can change the implementation can be a lot of lines of code without anything else in the application to be changed.
However.
This interface is also hide information.
Some information can be very useful.
And without this information, the performance can be impaired.
Let me give you a classic example.
I send a packet to the network.
And the packet doesn't make it is not acknowledge. I expect an acknowledge.
I don't get acknowledge.
What I should do.
Resend it again. Right?
But how aggressively I'm going to resend it and after how long it will depend on how the packet was lost.
It was because the interference like we discussed. I want to resend it immediately.
If it is because the congestion is a network.
Then I want to slow down.
Because if I send the same right, you know, probably the packet was lost because I was sending too fast.
So if I'm just resending and resending and resending.
That more packets are going to be lost.
So in that case, I want to slow down.
So if the interface doesn't allow me to expose this information and today doesn't.
I don't know exactly what to do. So the performance will suffer.
So network is like system modularity, but network modularity is like system modularity.
But it's simplified.
And it's simplified because they have layers. Modules can be connected in any ways.
Layering is connected in only one way. It's basically one layer on top of the other.
One layer can use only the functionality of the layer beneath, which is beneath it.
Right?
So only the two nearby layers are going to interact with each other.
Now you have a bunch of layers. The next question is about, okay, you have a bunch of functionality you need to implement.
Reliability, flow control, congestion control. We discuss about that.
Which layer is going to implement them?
And we are going to learn next time about end-to-end principles, which provide a guiding principle of where to implement certain functionalities.
And then there's a question about where the state is stopped.
So when you have a failure, right, then you can lose a piece of state.
Then you need to recover it. So this kind of stuff, you know, how you are going to think about the state.
state, shared state, in the distributed system.
And we are going to address all of those.
So we have 10 more minutes.
So let's dive in now in other things.
So I said the layering, it's this partition of the system
where a layer relies only on the services from the layer
below it and provides services only to the layers above it.
And the interfaces between layers
abstract away the implementation of a layer which
provides that interface from the layer using that interface.
So a layer can be changed in isolation
without in a transparent manner to the layers above it.
So there are several concepts which
are associated with each layer and we care to answer.
Service, what a layer does, what functionality it provides.
Service interface, how to access a service,
how do you access a service, what is the API,
what is the interface.
And then is a protocol.
The protocol like we discussed in the past
is how the peers, two peers, communicate with each other.
What is the packet format, syntax, what do I do
when I receive a packet.
When I don't receive a packet, when I have a timeout,
there's a semantics.
So it's service, service interface, and protocol.
So this is a network layering.
Initially, it was a standard body, open system
interconnection.
And that declares that there should
be seven layers, physical, data link, network, transport,
session, presentation, and application.
However, the internet protocol, this standard,
it was unsuccessful in the end.
It was overtaken by internet protocol, which was initially
grew as a de facto standard.
And only later, it was an idea, it was created later.
I think nine, 10 years later after IP was designed.
IP and TCP/IP protocol, remember, it was a software,
it was a protocol which was implemented in Unix BSD,
Verical Assistant Distribution.
So you should be very proud about that.
OK?
And with this layer, with the internet protocol,
you have only five layers.
The presentation and session layers
are included in the application layer.
So this you are going to learn about what each layer is doing.
So let's start.
Bottom up, physical layer.
Service moves the information between two systems connected
by a physical link.
The physical link can be wired, optical, or through the air.
The interface specifies how to send and receive bits.
What are the level of voltages?
How you encode one, the ones?
How do you encode zeros?
And the protocol represents actually the coding scheme.
So it's like the interface is basically here,
I am saying about a bit what is a bit.
It's like transition from low to high voltage,
or transition from low to high voltage,
from high to low voltage.
What is the duration of a bit?
How long is sent?
And these are the examples, coaxial cable, optical fiber
link, and so forth.
The next is data link layer.
So by the way, the physical layer
is between two machines which are directly connected.
The data link layer, it's the same,
but here there are multiple machines
which are connected to the same communication media.
Typically, like for instance, the same local area network,
what is called.
All the machines on a Wi-Fi network, right?
If you are connected with the Wi-Fi
to the same base stations, you are on the same network.
And in this case, you need to arbitrate the access
because you have multiple machines sending
on the same communication media.
They can send at the same time, so they can have collisions.
So you need to think about that.
But this is a service data link layer provides.
It can also provide reliable transmission and flow control.
Remember, flow control is what?
Not overflowing the receiver, slowing down
to not overflow the receiver.
The interface is sent frames.
So here are the packets.
Initially, with physical layer, you send bits.
Here you aggregate the bits into frames.
And you send frames.
Each frame has a header.
And the header will have this MAC address, as you'll see.
Finally, you have the protocols.
It is media access protocol to arbitrate access.
And there are many implementations.
We are going to briefly talk about that.
So here is what you have.
You have a frame.
We have a frame header.
The frame header has a MAC destination and source address.
And then they are converted as a lower level
in bits, which are sent on the wire.
You see?
OK.
So you see that you have the counterpoint.
You have the instantiation of the layers at both peers,
at both endpoints.
OK.
So now, you can actually-- you can look about your--
on your machines.
And if you are curious about this physical address
or the MAC address, you can easily find those.
And as well as the IP addresses.
But this is what-- if you do if config in Linux or IP config
in your Windows machine, then you
are going to get these physical addresses or Ethernet adapter
and so forth.
These are the MAC addresses.
OK?
So like I mentioned, a group of machines
which are on the same communication media,
they are called form a LAN, Local Area Network.
And these are the examples.
Computers in your home, Starbucks, wireless Starbucks,
and Starbucks and so forth.
But the most important thing here
is that when you send a frame on a LAN,
that can reach any other machine on the same LAN.
So it's a-- generally, it's a broadcast media.
It's like we are in a room or on this webinar.
I'm saying something.
Everyone else will hear me.
OK?
Now, how do you know?
How does it know?
Because everyone will get the same frame.
How does it know the recipient, the intended recipient
of the frame to get the frame and others not get the frame?
It's because of MAC address.
When the sender sends a frame, it's a frame header.
It puts the MAC address of the recipient.
In this case, it's B. So now, yes, the frame
is going to be forwarded to everyone.
But only B is going to look at the header
and is going to see that it's addressed to itself
and is going to pass the frame to the next layer.
The second, the C, if a computer looks at the frame
and it doesn't recognize its MAC address, it drops it.
OK?
Now, things are more complicated.
Even for a LAN, there are switches and so forth.
And this is what we are going to continue
to discuss next lecture.
And with that, stopping here, please,
if you have any other questions, let me know on Piazza
or send an email.
And I'll see you all on next Tuesday.
Good luck with the homework.
Bye.