Hello everyone. So today we have quite a bit to cover. And in particular, we are going
to finish layering and networking what we started last time. Then we are going to talk
about end-to-end argument and we are going to then start the discussion on flow control.
So layering. So if you remember, just a recap from the last time, there are a few layers
in the network. The networking stack has a few layers and in the internet you have five
layers. The first layer at the bottom is physical layer and the role of the physical layer is
to send the signal between two machines which are connected to the same transmission medium.
And so the service is to move the information from one machine to another and the interface
is about how to send and receive bits. And the protocol is about how these bits are encoded.
It's like based on the voltage, duration of each bit, frequency. It's again, depending
whether we are using the coaxial cable, optical fiber, the Wi-Fi and so forth.
Okay. So the second layer is data link layer. Also, we discussed a little bit about it last
time. And the data link layer enables the hosts which are connected to the same physical
network to exchange messages or atomic messages. So basically the physical layer sends bits,
zero and ones. Here we send packets, we send messages. Also they are called frames. And
so what are the services here? It's one it's about because you can have here multiple machines
which are connected maybe on the same physical line or the same wireless link, there are
multiple machines which can send data at the same time. So somehow you need to arbitrate
to make sure that multiple centers do not call you. This is very much like in a room
in which everyone can talk with everyone. So there has to be some kind of protocol so
that not everyone's talk at the same time so people can understand each other's. The
interface is about how to send the frames to either from one machine to one host or
another host. And they also includes each frame includes an address because this is
how I'm going to indicate that I'm going to send a particular frame to a particular host.
It's by destination address. And these addresses are the MAC addresses, media access or so-called
addresses or data link addresses. And these are the ones if you remember from last time,
there are 48 bits and they are chosen by the network card vendor. So in the network card
you create a network card or you also associate address to it. And the protocol it's about
like we discussed about how you are going to arbitrate the access like this shared communication
media. Okay. So each frame contains a source and a destination address. Each of them again
is 48 bits. And obviously these bits, these addresses are unique. Okay. Every network
card has a unique address. You can also see these addresses like we discussed last time.
If you do ipconfig in Windows or ifconfig in Linux, here you can see these physical
addresses is called and this has 48 bits. You see one, two, three, four, five, six,
and each of these groups has it's in hexa. So you have two digits and you have four bits
for each digit. So you have in total, you have 48 bits. Remember that the machine can
have multiple network cards. So in this case, that's why you are going to see two physical
addresses in this case, one for the ethernet, for the wire network and one for the wireless
network. Any questions? Okay. So when I said that these hosts are connected with the same
communication media, typically as a data link layer, this kind of network, the shared network
with the host are connected and communicate with each other is called LAN, local area
network. And it's again, examples are in a wireless network, it's all laptops in a Starbucks
affair, all for instance, devices in your home or in your office. But this is a key.
On all the devices connected with the same LAN can communicate with each other. So you
can think about this as a broadcast channel, a shared channel. This also means that when
you send a packet or a frame, that frame is going to be delivered to everyone. It's again,
like in a room, when you say something loud enough, everyone can hear. Okay. But now the
obvious question is that if I want to send a frame to one particular host, then how do
I do it? And obviously the answer here is that by indicating the destination address
of the recipient in the frame. So in this example, if I'm going to send, I want to send
to B, A wants to send a frame to B, he's going to put the address or to B in the frame as
a destination address. Now, because this is a broadcast, the LAN is a broadcast channel,
this packet will be delivered to every host in the network. However, each host can check
whether the data frames are intended to itself by checking its own MAC address against the
destination address in the frame. And if they are the same, then it accepts the packet,
otherwise it drops the packet. Any questions? It's like in our examples, if you are going
to speak loudly and everyone can hear, if you want to say address to your friend, John,
you basically say, "Hey, John," and then you are going to say whatever you have to say.
And by that, this means that John will pay attention and maybe the other people will
not pay attention because that message is not in the data. Now, the LAN can be larger,
can include multiple hundreds of machines and when you include hundreds of machines
or a larger number of machines, they typically they also are connected by switches. Switches
are a little more intelligent and so basically switches are doing some pruning of the messages.
So if a switch gets a message and the host is not behind one of its connections, it's
not going to send that frame on that connection. So in this particular case, for instance,
when B arrives at the switch, the switch will directly send to B. It's not going to deliver
to B and C. So it's more efficient.
Right? And that's why the switches are in general
when you have a lot of war machines,
where it is very inefficient for that frame to be sent
to reach everyone.
Okay. Questions.
How can we ensure MAC addresses are unique?
This is excellent question.
So typically every network vendor,
it's assigned a block of MAC addresses.
And that vendor can only associate the MAC addresses
in his block to all the network cards he produces.
That's sense.
Ha, no news.
So another great question.
Is this where security concerns come in?
Can a host who has a packet is not addressed
to still read the message?
Yes, it's no big.
That's why you are told that when you are going to be
in a Starbucks cafe, what you are going to be,
you are told, right?
You need to use encryption.
Why do you want to use encryption?
Because you don't want just someone to snoop on your packets
and read everything what you send or receive.
Great questions.
Ah, Michael here.
It's another great question.
How does a switch know that MAC address of the,
does a device declare its address
upon connecting to a new media?
Yes, there is a special protocol by which the devices,
you know, the devices connect
and then they advertise their address to the switch.
Excellent questions.
Please keep them coming.
So now one of our problem is again,
now let's think about again, this broadcast media,
because even with a switch, with a switch here,
we are simplifying it,
but behind each of this output of the switch,
there are many, many hosts.
It's not only one host sitting there.
So you still have, almost by definition,
in a LAN, you have multiple hosts being able to send
and receive packets at the same time.
And when you have multiple people,
sorry, multiple hosts sending,
being able to send packets at the same time,
you need to somehow make sure they don't collide, right?
And there are three solutions,
a channel partition, taking turns and random access.
So channel partition is basically,
think about you have different frequencies.
This is one, one typical example.
And what you do is frequency division multiplexing.
You have a band of frequency
and you are going to split that band
in different kinds of frequencies.
And then you allocate one of these frequency
to a different host.
And each host can only send on that frequency.
And you can listen for multiple frequencies
so you can get the packets from,
on any frequency, right?
Now, what are the advantage of this?
Is that it's simple and it's pretty clear.
It provides also some isolation
because you have your own frequency,
you don't care about the other people.
You can send on your own frequency.
You don't care about other hosts.
So, and it's a pretty efficient one, it's very high load.
But when the load is small, then it's very inefficient
because from, if for instance,
you have only one host sending to another host, right?
Out of 100 hosts out there,
then you can use only one percent
of the entire frequency range.
The ones that frequency which is allocated
to that particular host is sending.
While the other one are not used.
So ideally, what you would like is that
of only two machine, two hosts communicating with each other,
you should have none of the other send data.
These two hosts should be able to use
the entire frequency range, right?
The other one is pretty similar,
but this is, this source,
but instead of dividing the frequencies, it divides the time.
So basically here, you have,
imagine that you have a token.
A token is a special packet.
And this token is going, and you can think about
that hosts are organized in a logical ring, for instance.
Okay?
So, and then this token goes from host to host.
Host to host around the ring.
And now you can send data only when you have the token.
If you have data to send, but you don't have the token,
you need to wait to receive the token.
So again, because it's only one host has a token
at a given time, you are ensuring that there is no collision
because only one host can send at a given time.
Again, you have the same kind of little bit issues
when everyone has things to send,
is working great because you get a token,
you already have, you send data, you have to send data.
If only two hosts, one host has to send data to another host,
then it's more problematic because you need to wait
for every other host around the ring to get
and send out the token before you can send the next packet.
So it's kind of an overhead just waiting for the token
to go around, just for each host to pass it,
who doesn't have anything to send,
just to pass it to another to the next host.
So just pure overhead, which, you know,
reduces the efficiency of this protocol.
And finally, it's random access.
It's also, it's a carrier sense,
collision detection is called CSMA.
And this is ethernet, if you heard.
This is probably the most popular
data link layer technology, right?
And a form of this is also you have for wireless.
But here it is, this is exactly, you know,
to better understand it, imagine again,
there is a room full of people
and they are talking, right?
And now imagine that again, everyone hears everyone.
So the room is small enough.
So what do you do, right?
So first of all, you know, before you speak,
you listen a little bit, right?
This is carrier sense.
You listen that it's a pause.
No one else is talking, right?
You also don't interrupt, right?
Someone.
Someone else is talking, you wait for that person to finish
before you start, this is polite.
This is carrier sense, right?
Someone, you know, the media it's busy
because there are some packets being sent out.
Then you wait for a pause for the media to be idle
before you send.
Now, this is not enough to avoid the collisions
because many people may have like in our analogy
with the room analogy, multiple people may wait
for the current speaker to finish, to say something.
And as you know, sometimes happens that people can start,
two people can start talking at the same time.
Now that's a collision, the same here.
If one of the media inside or two hosts
are going to send back at the same time,
the second is like, where's the collide?
Why do you do that?
It's again, assuming that you are polite.
Most people who, you know, like start talking
at the same time, when they stop, right?
They stop for a while and then try again, right?
And sometimes it's again, it's like,
as you probably, you know, I'm sure you witness that,
two people start at the same time, stop,
and then again, start at the same time.
So you want to avoid that.
And here is a design of this protocol
and how do you design it?
Each of the parties, each of the hosts,
if there is a collision,
waits for a random amount of time.
And if you waste for a random amount of time,
it's a probability of collision again,
colliding again, is lower.
So this is pretty much it, right?
And it's very simple, it is decentralized
and it works pretty well in practice.
It's beautiful protocol.
Any questions?
So it's again, the token, you can assume this is again,
like this protocol, the CSMA/CD is like,
think about always like the protocol people will use,
polite people will use in a room
or speaking with each other.
This token protocol we discussed in the previous slide,
terms, you can imagine it's like only people who have the mic are going to talk, right? You know,
when you ask questions like a conference and so forth, when you ask questions there is a mic and
if there is only one mic, only the, you know, someone is going to hand the mic to the person who
has who can talk or who wants to ask a question, but only the person who has a mic can ask a
question. So there are no collisions. Okay, so let's see. Why would I want, Allison has this
question, why would I want my computer to play fair? Can I configure my computer to just shoot
over everyone so then it will be faster? I think, you know, that's a good point. The problem though
is that if everyone is doing the same or even other people don't do exactly the same, you are
going to have collisions and if you have collisions you have garbage, you cannot be hurt.
That's a problem, right? You cannot, in some sense, you cannot increase the intensity of your
signal. So probably, you know, in this case you don't have the ability to increase that kind of
intensity. Like in practice, maybe you are going to yell, you know, your voice will be stronger
than anyone else. But here everyone is on the level playing field, the same, you can send only
beats, the same beats as a beat, the same voltage, the same intensity. So if two people, if two hosts
send at the same time, this is going to be interference and your message is not going to be
that it works as a destination. Oh, Simon, how does random access guarantee a node ever get a chance
to speak? What if in the random someone is always speaking when I try to speak? Could that cause a
starvation? That's a great question and it's probabilistic, right? It's like you always,
you know, there is a the probability that you are going to be able to speak is non-zero. Now, it
turns out that these random access protocols, they work very well. You remember this other
token protocol and the one with frequency division multiplexing, they are working very well
when the system is very utilized, it's highly utilized when everyone talks to everyone.
But it doesn't have such a high efficiency when the system is not utilized because
if they, you know, say if you have only two hosts talking with each other, they cannot use the entire
frequency range or they have to wait for the token to get around only for all the other hosts not
doing anything with the token. This is a reverse. It's working extremely well when the network is
lightly utilized because there are no collisions. But when it's heavily utilized, there are many
collisions, then the efficiency is going down. So there is a problem with that.
But again, so this is probably the intuition behind your question,
Simon. But in theory, you are going to get, you know, you are going to get your top. It's like,
think about the one, you know, it's like here is another analogy. You are coming from a secondary
road and you are in the main road and you don't have a priority and you want to take right or left.
Right. Like you go from, you know, Safeway or other where you exit. Right. So you need to wait for a gap
to get to enter the traffic. And in theory, you know, you may never get that bad, that gap.
But in practice, you know, you don't need to wait too much.
So probabilistically, it is not salvation.
OK. The next is a network layer.
So, yeah, I don't know. I need to update this figure on the right hand side. We are talking
about the network layer. The network layer is actually the most important in some sense.
When you talk about Internet, Internet is a main layer in the Internet, is the Internet protocol
or IP. You heard about the IP, right? IP is the Internet protocol, is a network layer.
So the network layer has its own address. They are called IP addresses.
And every host has a unique IP address.
And this is global. It's at the level of the entire planet.
So network layer is basically going to be able, is going to ensure the main service is going to ensure
its connectivity. You can deliver a packet specifying the network address or the IP address
across the globe from New York to Tokyo, from a network in New York, from a host in San Francisco
to a host in Tokyo. And this will be across multiple data link layer networks.
Because you cannot have just a data link layer network over the entire globe.
Okay. There are possible other services like scheduling priorities, so some packets are more
important than the others. You can think about video packets are going to have higher priorities
than data packets, things like that. And you need also to handle the buffer management. The packets
along the way are going to be buffered. The interface is very simple. You send a packet
to a specified network address destination and you receive that packet, which is intended to you.
The protocol includes defining these network addresses, which are globally unique
and also constructed the router, what are called forwarding tables. So a router, which connects
a router, connects different local area networks. It receives a packet. It looks at the destination
address and decides where to send it out. Okay. So this is the network layer and you see the network
layer packet. It has a payload and the header. They are encapsulated in a data frame. So
encapsulation means that you take a packet from the network layer and you add the header
of the frame. This becomes a frame, right?
And the header contains the IP destination address and the IP source address.
And as I mentioned to you, these are routed by routers. The routers
connect different data link, data layer networks. And all this aggregation of
local area network is called the wide area network. Okay.
So now what is the difference between the switch and the router?
So it's simple. The router, it's only, it recognizes and routes based on the IP addresses.
A switch is only in a local area network and only recognize MAC addresses.
Okay. So router function, like I mentioned, is to get the packets, look at their
headers and decide on which output link to send them. Okay. So this is how the router works.
You have a bunch of incoming links, you get packets on and outgoing links. It's like a
huge intersection, right? And basically what router implements a mechanism which is called
store and forward. Store and forward means the packets are received first, are stored.
And after a store, the router inspects the header and based on the destination IP address decides
where the forwards are. Right. And they are stored because you don't want to drop the packets if the
router cannot process them fast enough. That's the reason. And again, the forwarding table is
a mapping between IP addresses and the output link. Right. So here is an example about the
packet going from host A to host B. Each router will decide to watch output to forward the packet
based on this IP address and based on the information in the forwarding table.
So now this slide is very important. Okay. Because obvious question now,
hey, I have MAC addresses and you told me that they are unique. And now you tell me also about
IP addresses, which are also unique.
Why do I need two kinds of addresses?
Why not using a single type of address?
In particular, why shouldn't I use just a MAC address for routing?
I already have those. Why do I need another address?
The answer is that remember how the MAC addresses are allocated.
Okay.
I am a network card vendor.
I get a block of MAC addresses.
And I'm going to use these addresses in the block to assign to my network cards.
And then these network cards are in computers which are all over the globe.
So there is no aggregation. It's very much like social security number.
Now I am asking you, I'm giving you a social security number.
And let's say they are not private.
They are not confidential.
And I'm telling you, hey, deliver this letter, this message to the social security number.
You know, one, two, three, four, five, six, whatever.
You know, how easy is that or how hard is it?
It's pretty hard because there is now the random across the globe.
Now to compare that, if I am going to give you a message or a letter to deliver,
and I'm telling you what is a home address of the recipient.
It's much easier because the address are structured.
And the only thing, for instance, say I'm going to send the address to this, you know,
10 7th Street, Northwest Washington, D.C. and so forth.
If I'm sending it from California, the only single first thing I need to know is that it's going to Washington, D.C.
So I put it on a plane to go to Washington, D.C.
That's the only thing. It's very easy.
Right. So the amount of state I can use in San Francisco to say what I'm going to send the packet, the letter, is very small.
Only the cities or the states or the country, if I'm sending international letter.
And once the letter is coming, going to Washington, D.C., it remains in the Washington, D.C. area and then it's going to,
I know I'm going to look at the street and I'm looking and then I'm looking at the address of the street.
So you can have this hierarchical structure and routing of the letter from the sender to the recipient.
This is what the IP address gives you. It gives you the structure which will make it much easier.
Right. And then if I'm sending from that one to someone from California, from Berkeley, it's again, just look at the Berkeley,
first look, send to Berkeley to, or someone close to Berkeley, San Francisco, Oakland, on a plane to Oakland,
and from there it's going to be delivered to you.
OK.
OK, any question?
So fundamentally, it's again.
The IP addresses have structure, geographic structure, topological structure, and therefore they can be aggregatable.
Therefore, the forwarding tables in the routers can be much smaller.
While for MAC addresses, there is no aggregation, you need to keep a forwarding table which is equal to the number of MAC addresses, existing MAC addresses, which is huge.
Case in point, assume that you want to send
a packet from New York to a particular IP address, to a particular host in UC Berkeley.
Then the UC Berkeley, actually all IP addresses are starting with this, you know, the first
two bytes are all common, A9, E5.
Right.
So the router in New York, it needs to keep only one entry for all hosts which are associated with UC Berkeley.
If you don't have that and you use MAC addresses, then the new router has to keep an entry for every host,
which is much harder and much harder to update, maintain and things like that.
Does it make sense?
Any questions?
So to summarize here, a MAC address is like SSN and an IP address is like an address, although it's not readable.
Right. And so therefore, it's much easier to build a system like a mail system, in our case, to deliver the letter to a particular address which has structure,
then to some identifier which has no structure.
Any questions?
Okay.
So like I mentioned, this is the Internet Protocol, the Internet's network layer.
And so the Internet Protocol is the Internet's network layer.
The service it provides is connectivity and packet delivery, but it's best effort.
Best effort means that you are not guaranteed that your packet is going to make it to the destination.
It may be dropped, it may be corrupted.
And also, it doesn't guarantee you that the packet, if you send two packets, one after another, they are going to arrive at the same time, in the same order.
Because they may follow different routes. It's like you cannot guarantee that two cars which started San Francisco and arrived to, you know, are driving to LA,
they are going to get at LA at the same order.
So it's very simple.
Now, on top of the network layer, you have transport layer. And the transport layer provides its one level up.
The network layer delivers a packet from one host to another.
But the host does not consume the packet. Application consumes the packets.
And the application is a process. And on a machine, you have multiple processes.
So you need to specify to which packet, to which process on a particular machine, the packet needs to be delivered.
So the IP address of the recipient is not enough.
We need another thing to differentiate between multiple processes running on the same machine, on the same host.
And this is a port number, I could see.
So the transport layer multiplex and multiplex packets, which arrive on the same host.
There are other services can provide, reliability, rate adaptation like we discussed last time, flow control, congestion control.
And timing properties, maybe they are going to, you know, give guarantees that the packet will be delivered within 100 milliseconds.
It's important, say for voice communication.
The interface is the same message to a specific process at a given destination.
OK.
And the local process receives the messages sent to it.
The protocol includes the port numbers.
These are used to differentiate between different processes.
It may implement reliability, flow control and packetization because you may send bigger depending on the interface.
You may send streams. Like if you remember, we have this kind of interface to the network.
We have blocked and streamed interface. For the streaming interface, somehow you need to chop these streams into packets and send these packets.
OK, so this is at the higher level.
You have the transport layer, you have a transport header, the transport header is the protocol number, the port numbers.
And you have also,
Like for instance, 80 identifies for the port is pre-allocated
that port for HTTP server.
There are two important transport protocols
in the internet.
Using UDP, user datagram protocol.
And this provides only multiplexing
and multiplexing among processes.
This is the best effort.
Packets can be lost, can get out of order.
There is no flow control, nothing.
So the application is to take care of.
Then it's TCP, which is a transport control protocol.
And this obviously still provides
multiplexing and multiplexing among processes.
But in addition, has a notion of connection.
You set up the connection, you tear down the connection.
If there are packets which are corrupted or corrupted,
you discard them.
There is a checksum, you check.
And if the checksum is violated, you discard the packet.
It re-transmits the lost packet, so provides reliability
to the application.
And it also provides flow control and congestion control.
Remember, flow control is about not overwhelming the receiver.
The congestion control is not overwhelming the network.
The services which are not typically available,
any bandwidth or delay guarantees in internet,
you cannot specify that.
You cannot say, I want 10 megabits per second.
You cannot say, I want these packets.
Need to be delivered in 100 milliseconds.
What I mentioned to you, I mentioned earlier
that in general, the transport protocol, the transport layer
can provide that.
What I'm telling you now is that the transport
protocols in the internet do not provide this kind of delay
or bandwidth guarantees.
Also, if a session, if you try to migrate an application
from one node to another, they're using VM migration
or something like that, the connection is not preserved.
OK, we have another question.
So the question, so are ports used
to differentiate which packet to send to different processes
on the host?
Yes, exactly for that.
Different processes will have different ports numbers
when they open a connection.
Then is the application layer.
So here, any service provided to the end users,
this application is like--
and the interface depends on the application.
Protocol depends on the application.
In the OSI architecture, there are also
the transport or the session and the presentation layer.
They are not existent in the internet protocol.
So be happy.
We only need to learn about five, really four layers
instead of seven.
And their functionality is absorbed by the application
layer in the internet.
OK?
So this is the entire stack.
So you see kind of the waterfall.
A packet at one level becomes a payload at the next level
as you go down the stack.
And when you are going to go up the stack,
you are going to strip headers after header after header
until you get to the right.
The first layers, physical layer, data link layer,
network layer, are implemented by the host
and by the routers.
The switch is not shown here, but the switch
implements the physical layer and the data link layer.
The host implements transport and application layer,
but the router does not implement that.
Right?
And the protocol is between two peers at the same layer.
OK?
Some announcements.
Discussion will be recorded because of the Thanksgiving.
The office hours for Wednesday, Thursday, Friday
are going to be canceled again because of the Thanksgiving.
The midterm three review session is coming next Monday.
The time is to be determined.
So please stay focused.
We are going to announce it on Piazza.
The midterm three is next Wednesday between 7 and 9 PM.
And homework is released and it has been released
and is due on Friday, December 3.
Are layers five and six used explicitly in other systems
or are they obsolete everywhere?
They were used by other network stacks.
In the past, there are many of them, but all of them
are obsolete.
Eventually, the internet protocol took over
and everyone now provides the internet protocol.
So the answer to your question today are obsolete.
Will previous recording letter be uploaded?
Yeah, it should be.
We'll make sure that it's uploaded.
Sorry about that.
OK, now let's switch gears.
And this is a very interesting aspect of the internet.
It's called end-to-end argument.
So if you look about, this is another way
to look at the internet protocol stack.
Its shape is what is called hourglass.
What this means is that the internet protocol is
a waste of the hourglass.
And that's why internet protocol is so important in the main--
sorry, internet IP layer is so important in the internet
network stack.
Because it's kind of unique.
So everyone has to implement the internet protocol interface.
But under the internet protocol layer and above it,
there is a large variety of different protocols
at different layers.
So you can under the internet protocol,
you can have different data link layers.
You can have different physical layers.
Above, you can have different transport protocols, TCP and DDP.
Above, you have different application protocols.
And this is beautiful.
The reason it's beautiful is because it
decouples the evolution of the layers underneath
and of the layer above.
Remember, we want to discuss the level of indirection last time.
This is it.
Remember, you decouple the evolution above
from the evolution of the layers below.
So therefore, if I'm going to add a new data link layer,
as long as I'm providing on top of it the IP interface,
then all the other application, all of the other layers
above IP should work without any change.
The same, if I'm going to invent a new transport protocol
or a new application protocol, I can do that.
And as long as I'm going to write against the IP interface,
none of the layers below the IP should
care that now there is a new application
protocol or a new transport protocol.
So this is why the IP layer is so fundamental.
OK, so this is what we discussed.
So a single internet layer allows arbitrary networks
to interoperate, allows application
to functions on all networks.
And therefore, because of layers below and the layers above
can evolve separately, this is how we also
evolve the innovation and enable the innovation.
However, changing IP itself is very hard
because it's only one layer.
And at a proof point, the transition from IPv4 to IPv6
was very painful, probably because like 20 years.
Now, the layers, it's a very nice construct, very logical,
very clear.
I provide a lot of isolation because one layer can only
use a service of the layer below it.
At the same time, there are some drawbacks.
Um.
We'll see you again soon.
Because the layer may need some same functionality
like false tolerance or no reliability.
Some layers are going to replicate this functionality.
The layering can also hurt the performance
because one layer can hide information from the above layer.
Like I mentioned to you, it's one classic example
is that the data link layer hides why a packet was lost.
And because the IP layer hides why the packet was lost.
So the transport layer, which provides for instance,
TCP, which is provided reliability
and it needs to do retransmission of the packets.
It cannot make the right, you know, the best decision
because it doesn't know whether the packet for instance,
was lost because it was dropped in the network
because of congestion.
So therefore I need to slow down when I send a new packet
or I retransmit the lost packet.
Or the packet may have been lost because of interference,
case in which I don't need to slow down.
But without having this information,
I need to make a decision,
the decision today to slow down,
which is not optimal for instance, for wireless networks.
Some of the layers are not always cleanly separate.
And the other thing is that you had us, you remember,
like for each layer, I added some header.
So you have a lot of headers and that overhead
because it's not really data you want to send.
So in some cases, the header is much larger
than the actual data you want to send.
So now again, you have all these layers
and you want to implement some functionality.
The one question is at what layer
you are implementing that functionality.
And the end-to-end arguments is a principle
which tries to answer that question.
Some people say it's a sacred text of the internet.
And like any sacred text, there are endless disputes
about what exactly it is.
And everyone cites it as supporting their position.
It's a little bit like a Bible, like the Bible.
But still it's very important.
But let's consider, for instance,
some functionality like reliability or security.
It's obviously, where do you implement it?
Data link layer, IP layer, network layer,
transfer layer, where and why?
So, and our application can implement that.
And the main point here is that,
like we'll see in the next example,
is that because a network, even if they want,
if they want at a lower level of the network,
cannot implement an end-to-end function correctly,
the application may anyway have to implement it.
So let's take a follow-up example.
Right?
So, right?
So here is an example.
So say you want to transfer reliably a file
from one host to another.
So how this will look like,
if you want to build an application.
We read the data from the file,
then you send it over the network from host I to host B.
The host Bs and the application from host B
is going to write it on the disk of host B.
Right?
This is how you copy a file.
Now, if I want to have reliable transfer,
what you are going to do?
There are two solutions.
I make each of these steps reliable.
And now I concatenate them.
I have here five reliable steps,
end-to-end step must be reliable.
The second one,
I don't do any of those things,
but after I get all what I am told is a file,
I'm going to come with a checksum,
and I'm going to send, you know,
to match against the checksum sent by the host,
by the sender.
So basically host A,
when it sends a file, it computes also a checksum.
It sends out the file to host B.
The host B takes the file, saves the file,
and also after it saves the file,
it's the entire file,
it computes a checksum,
and now computes a checksum of the saved file
with the checksum sent by host A.
If they are the same, success.
If they are not the same, send the file again.
Which of the solution you are going to pick?
If it weren't for you.
And why?
Okay.
I'll just say solution one,
because solution three is bad for large files.
True, solution three is bad for large files.
Simon, I like solution two.
Anyone else?
Simon, why do you like solution two?
Because I don't know whether between each step
this might break.
That's correct.
Great answer.
So you see the point is that here,
if I concatenate five reliable steps,
it doesn't mean that end-to-end everything is reliable.
Right? This is, the green is the solution two.
Okay?
It's checking the checksum.
So the solution two is incomplete.
Because what happens, for instance,
when I copy the data from the disk
to the application memory,
and the memory is corrupted.
Right?
So, so fundamentally,
because I cannot guarantee that the solution one is,
is correct.
I need anyway to do a checksum and verify it.
So the main point here is the application anyway
has to implement the functionality to verify the checksum.
Even if you solution one.
So therefore the full functionality of reliability
can be implemented as the application level.
The network doesn't need to do anything.
Now, for correctness reasons,
for correctness reasons, right?
It's a game.
It's enough to implement the application.
The network doesn't do anything.
Still, we are just talking that the network
also implement reliability, not the network.
The transfer may come into reliability.
So why would still the network implement reliability,
a reliable protocol?
It's not necessary for correctness.
We just compute that.
But still, you may want the network to implement reliability.
Why is that?
Yes, to avoid very expensive correction.
Yes, Arisam.
See, if you think about, right?
It's in the second solution,
if you have 10 gigabytes size file,
if one byte, one bit, not one byte, one bit is corrupted,
you need to resend the entire 10 gigabytes part.
However, if you have, the network is reliable.
So ends up.
That's perfect.
(silence)
Okay.
So the question is that,
should I implement this function in the lower layers or not?
Okay.
And the question, the answer here,
it depends.
Right?
Because in, and the answer, you know,
and the reason this is a question is that
if you implement the function, it does a lower layer,
this functionality, this,
it doesn't reduce the application complexity
because you anyway, implement there
and increase another complexity.
But,
worse yet, it can increase,
it can add overhead to application
which do not read that functionality.
Like for instance, if you have voice over IP,
telephony over the internet.
In that particular case, reliability is not helpful
because you need to satisfy, you know,
you need to, the latency is more important
than getting every packet correct.
Right?
If the sound is a little bit distorted,
it's probably it's okay.
But if we need to wait for a second
to return the packet, that's probably not okay.
Yeah. Okay.
(laughs)
Yeah, it was glitchy.
So I don't know what will happen also with recording
because on my side,
it said a little bit recording is in progress.
So I hope that it's just a glitch.
So it didn't, that didn't mean anything for the recording.
Yeah, that was a great timing
while we are discussing about end-to-end reliability.
So, so anyway.
So basically you implement,
you can implement a net, a functionality
at the lower layer of stack,
if we can improve performance.
Okay?
Now there are different interpretation
of the end-to-end argument.
And one extreme implementation, it says,
even if you can improve efficiency, don't bother.
If you cannot simplify the application or the host software,
don't bother to implement at the network level.
This is very conservative.
And you have the moderate interpretation.
So the moderate interpretation, it's kind of,
it's basically says,
well, you can implement the functionality as a network,
but be careful about that.
Think twice.
So in particular,
you can implement the functionality at a lower layer
if and only if doesn't impose a burden on applications
that do not require that functionality,
and it provides a significant improving performance.
So the benefits are out-weighting
the complexity of the implementation.
And by the way, you shouldn't be a burden
for the applications who do not need that functionality.
So if the application doesn't need fault reliability,
it shouldn't suffer.
For instance, it shouldn't experience
heavy latency and latency.
And this is the interpretation we are using.
Any questions?
(silence)
So again, you have a functionality like reliability,
which you must, to be absolute, to be correct,
to ensure correctness,
you have to implement at the application level
at the end hosts.
The question, should you also implement reliability
at the lower layers?
Is it at the lower layers?
The answer here, according to the moderate interpretation
of the end-to-end argument, yes.
But the bar for that is pretty high.
You can implement the reliability in networking
only if you get significant improvement in the performance,
and you are not going to hurt the application
which will not need that functionality.
(silence)
Okay.
Any questions?
Okay, so now we are going to start the last,
one of the last topics of the course.
This is flow control.
So the flow control, remember,
ensures that the fast sender
does not overwhelm a slow receiver.
And we already seen some mechanism,
like producer consumers with bounded buffers.
So you remember in this case,
you cannot overpower the consumer, overwhelm the consumer,
because if the buffer is full,
the producer can no longer put packets in the buffer.
Right?
So the buffer is naturally pushing back on the producer.
When it's full, accepts no new items.
So therefore, if the consumer is slower,
the producer is going to adapt to the consumer speed
because of the bounded buffer.
So that's the idea.
(silence)
Of course, in the case of the TCP,
and this is a talk about TCP flow control,
things are more complicated
because we are not on the same machine.
We are on different machines
and with an unreliable network in between.
TCP is using what is called a sliding window protocol
as a byte and not packet level.
And there are two types,
go back end is TCP Tahoe, Reno, New Reno
and selective repeat TCP SAC.
This Tahoe, Reno, New Reno and SAC
are different types of PCPs.
We are going to talk about more about them
a little next lecture.
Go back end meaning here is the difference.
And let me explain you the packet level
because it's easier.
I sent 10 packets
and the fifth packet was lost.
So the receiver gets the first four packets
and then the last five packets.
So one, two, three, four and six, seven, eight, nine, ten.
With go back end,
you are going to go back and send from packet five.
So I'm going to send five and six, seven, eight, nine, ten.
Despite the fact that six, seven, nine, eight, ten
were already received by the receiver.
So you miss something,
you restart from that missing packet all the way.
Selective repeat like the name implies,
if you lose a packet in our previous example,
you lose a packet five, you send only packet five.
We send only packet five.
Why doesn't everyone implement selective repeat
which seems much easier, much more efficient
is because it's more complex.
Go back end is much simpler to implement,
although less efficient.
Now with the DCP flow control,
the receiver tells the sender how many more bytes
it can receive without overflowing this buffer.
So I'm going to tell you, I can receive one kilobyte.
And in some way, this tells you
that you can send me one kilobyte of data
before you hear from me whether I receive anything.
Because you know, based on what I told you
that I can get one kilobyte,
but you cannot send me more.
Before you hear from me that I can send more.
This is advertising.
Now, like I mentioned, for the DCP,
The protocol is not at the packet level, it's at byte level.
The acknowledgement as a recipient, I'm telling you,
an acknowledgement contain the sequence number of a byte
of the next byte the receiver expects.
Okay.
So this means that I'm telling you
the acknowledgement contains the number,
the signal number 100.
This means that I received,
I'm telling you implicitly
that I received all the bytes up to 99.
There is no gap, all of them up to 99.
And the sequence number is start to count,
you know, it's like, it's from the first byte,
or the first byte which was sent up
as the connection of the byte.
Right?
Okay.
So this is a very simple diagram
showing the sending process, the receiving process,
and the buffer of the receiver.
The TCP/IP is implemented in the kernel.
Remember, where you discussed is about BSD,
Unix BSD.
We said that the TCP/IP
is part of the first implementing in the BSD,
I think 4.3 version, and is part of your legacy.
It's one of the biggest achievements
in the open source software,
because that's internet.
Why do you do that also?
Is that, is because you cannot do context switching.
You cannot do it application level, again, performance.
Yeah, at one garbage per second,
typically the packets have the 1500 bytes, the IP packets.
This takes the same, like one garbage per second
is 12 microseconds.
And if it's 100 byte packets,
it's less than one microsecond.
And by the way, one garbage per second is slow.
Today we are talking about 10 garbage per second,
40 garbage per second, and 100 garbage per second connections.
There is no way you can do context switching,
since that's fast to send every packet.
The application will send every packet.
And actually there is not only one buffer,
there are multiple buffers.
There is a buffer which is between the process,
sending process, and the kernel.
Again, you cannot have context switching on every packet.
Then it's between the receiving operating system,
the operating system on the receiving host,
and the receiving process.
And then you have a buffer actually between,
between the two hosts as a TCP/IP level,
the transport level.
So there is a buffer,
that operating system on the recipient host
is maintaining to get the packets from the sending host.
Okay?
So here it's in more details how things are happening.
So you have this buffer here, and you have this buffer here.
The receiving and the end host, and receiving host.
And, right?
So you have these three pairs, the producer, the consumers,
sending process, sending TCP, sending TCP, receiving TCP,
receiving TCP, receiving process.
And let's take up these examples.
So they say the maximum IP packet size is 100 bytes.
And the size of the receiving buffer,
it's a receiving buffer, is 300 bytes.
Recall the acknowledgement indicates
the next expected byte in sequence,
not the last received byte.
And we assume that these are circular buffers.
What is a circular buffer?
Well, a buffer has a size of N,
and you may have an infinite sequence of bytes,
and a byte with sequence number K,
is stored in a location
with the index K mod N plus one in the buffer.
This is a, for a simple example,
this is sequence numbers of hello world.
So say H is a sequence number 27,
and L, the last L is sequence number 36.
And the buffer has only 10 entries, right?
So then this is how you map it.
27 is 27 mod N, it's seven,
because N is 10, and plus one is eight.
It's N plus, oh, sorry, yes.
This was H, we are looking at E,
which is sequence number 28, sequence number 28,
28 mod 10 plus one is nine, right?
So this is how this data, the buffer data,
from E to R, the blue, which is in blue, shown in blue,
is a buffer in the simpler buffer, okay?
So initially, you know, you are going to have,
we are going to have a bunch of variables,
which point to different things in the buffer.
Three on the sending part, three on the receiving part.
You have last byte written,
which is a last byte written by sending process.
Last byte sent is a last byte sent by sender,
it is a receiver.
Last byte act is a last act byte
by the receiver, it is a sender.
Last byte received now is on the receiving side,
is a last byte received by the receiver from sender.
Next byte expected is a last in sequence byte
expected by receiver.
Sorry.
(silence)
And the last byte read is the last byte read
by the receiving process.
Actually for next byte expected,
this should be the next in sequence byte
expected by receiver, not last.
Okay?
And now the advertise window is a number of bytes
that we decide that this receiver can receive.
So what is this one?
So with blue, let's say with blue here is a byte
which are already in the receiving receiver buffer.
So the advertise window is a maximum receive buffer,
it's a maximum buffer size,
minus the last byte received.
This one.
And the difference between the last byte received
and last byte read, right?
So basically this is, you need to subtract
from the maximum receive buffer,
so from the buffer size of the receiver,
how many bytes are still in the buffer,
which are not yet read by the receiving process.
And on the sending process side,
it's similar to this, you have a sender window,
which is a number of bytes that TCP sender can send.
And the sender window is advertise window.
Okay?
So minus last byte send minus last byte act.
So intuitively this means that I can send as a sender,
I can send a number of bytes,
which is by subtracting what you told me
that you can receive and what I already sent,
I haven't heard from you.
So I'm finishing with this example.
Say you told me the advertising window is one kilobyte.
And since you told me that the advertising window
is one kilobyte, I send you 100 bytes.
How many more bytes I can send you without hearing from?
The answer is 900.
Right?
So that's basically why the sender window tries to capture.
So with this, and I'm going to stop here.
And this materials we've done in this lecture,
you'll be part of the midterm.
And again, best of luck with everything.
And happy sending it to everyone.
(silence)
Thank you.
you