Hello everyone. Welcome to the next to last lecture of this semester. And yeah, to the
next to the last week of classes. So today we are going to have a very interesting lecture
and that will be on the DCP flow control and actually congestion control. And remember,
here we are talking about the transport layer. So this is about the networking stack, the internet
stack. And as you can see, the transport layer, if you remember, sits on top of the network layer.
And the transport layer, it's implemented actually is a first layer if you go from bottom up,
which is only implemented by n hosts. It's not implemented by the network.
And one of the key services that the transport layer is providing, if you remember,
it's multiplexing and demultiplexing connections on the same machines,
between the processes on the same machines. So the network layer doesn't differentiate
between processes. The network layer addresses only machines, only n hosts. So network layer
is going to take a packet and send it to another n host whose address is in the packet header as
destination address. But once the packet gets to that n host, it needs to be delivered to a
particular process, to a particular application to be processed. And the way you differentiate
between these different processes is using port numbers. So the transport layer is the one who
uses port numbers to demultiplex a packet when it arrives of an n host and deliver it to the proper
process. And again, if you remember, in the internet as a transport layer, we have two
protocols, UDP and TCP, user datagram protocol and transport control protocol. And the UDP doesn't do
much more besides multiplexing and demultiplexing of packets from n to processes. So we are not
going to talk more about that. Now, the transport control protocol, which is the one we are going to
talk most mostly in this lecture, is providing two additional services, flow control,
and we talk a little bit at the end of the last lecture, but I'm going to start again talking
about it. We have more time during this lecture and it's a very important topic, and congestion
control. And the difference between the two is that the flow control, the goal of the flow
control is to not overflow the receiver, a slower receiver. The congestion control is to not overflow
the network. Overflowing means that the sender sends more data than the receiver or the network
can handle. So during this lecture, we are going to talk about flow control and congestion control.
Any questions?
Okay, so again from the last lecture and from many, many lectures ago,
if you remember this producer consumer is a bounded buffer. Bounded buffer meaning that it
can accept only a finer set of items in the buffer. So this provides, implements a natural
form of flow control because if the consumer cannot consume as fast as the producer sends
the data into the buffer, inserts item into the buffer, the buffer will get filled and when the
buffer is full, the producer can no longer add new items in the buffer.
So the producer has to stop. So it's going to slow down over time to match the speed that
with the consumer can read the data from the buffer. Right? Make sense?
So that's pretty much it now. So obviously the one problem you have with this one and we are
going to discuss more about it is that if producer and consumer as a buffer are not single machine,
things are easy. But here the producer and consumers are on different machines.
So how do you know producer being on one machine, how does it know the buffer
on the consumer side is full? Right? So it needs to somehow ways for some acknowledgement from the
consumer that it's okay to send more data. The simplest version of that is called stop and wait
and it's as simple as you can think of. We are going to use a lot of this kind of diagram.
And you see you have sender and the receiver on both sides. And then the time goes down. Okay?
So the oldest time is at the top, the newest time is at the bottom. So stop and wait is very simple.
You send a packet and you wait for an acknowledgement. And only after you
got the acknowledgement, you send another packet.
Okay? Now there are several important aspects, you know, metrics here. So this is D,
which is a delay or one-way delay, how long it takes a packet to get to the receiver from the
sender. Right? And this is, it takes some time, you know, there are different overheads in the
network. And on top of that, obviously there is the speed of light. Okay? So across the continent,
I think is what, maybe 10, 20 milliseconds in US, something like that.
And now you need to wait for acknowledgement. So acknowledgement, it might take another
same amount of time, assuming that it's symmetric, the path is symmetric. It's not necessary for the
path to be symmetric because the packet from the sender to the receiver can go on a different path
from the sender to the back, from the receiver to the sender. And even if they go to the, on the
same path, there can be different level of congestion in the network. For instance, at a
given time in the day, it's not taking you the same time to go from Auckland to San Jose as to go
from San Jose to Auckland. Right? Different level of congestion. But anyway, for simplicity, assuming,
assume that you have the same one-way latency, as this assume no congestion. So if there are
no congestion, it does take the same amount of time. And now, so, but then you need to wait for
two times D in the best case scenario to get the acknowledgement back. And these two times
these round trip time, it's called round trip time. The round trip time is how long it takes
a packet to travel from sender to receiver and back. Okay? So now, what is the throughput? You
know, how many packets you can send? So let's say, let me give you some numbers.
So say that one-way latency is one millisecond. Okay? Using this protocol,
assuming that everything is symmetric, all the one-way latencies are the same for all packets.
How many packets I can send in one second? So one-way latency is one millisecond.
And I am asking you how many packets I can send in one second.
Okay.
500. That's correct, Simon. Indeed, that's the correct answer. And it's very simple, right? It's
like we can send only one packet per round trip time because we need to wait for the
acknowledgement before you send another packet. So the round trip time is twice the one-way
one-way delay latency is two milliseconds.
So one second over two milliseconds,
it's 1,000 milliseconds over two is 500.
Okay, good.
Sounds good, okay.
So how fast can you send data?
You answer that question.
Again, the little law applies on this case
as a number of packets,
it's B, how many packets you have in the system
times the round-trip time,
and B will be the number of packets you have in the system.
Sorry, the number of packets you have in the system,
it's only one packet, right?
So you have one packet per RTD, right?
Like we discussed, okay?
Now, let's do a little bit more complicated here.
Now you have, in this particular case,
you have what is the throughput
in terms of the number of bytes,
not in the number of packets, like I mentioned,
I asked you a little bit earlier.
So if you have the round-trip time of 100 milliseconds,
so one-way delay latency is 50 milliseconds,
and a packet has 1,500 bytes,
that what is the throughput in terms of bits per second.
So it's very simple, right?
You can send one packet,
means 1,500 times eight bits in 0.1 seconds.
So it's 120 kilobits per second, okay?
So the main point here though, is that, as you can see,
this is very simple protocol,
you can implement it right away.
So the advantage of this protocol, it's simplicity.
On the other hand, it's very inefficient.
You see, it's taking you,
you cannot send more than at 120 kilobits per second,
no matter how fast the network is.
Because in this case,
this throughput is governed only by the one-way latency.
And the one-way latency will not depend, in most cases,
if you think about it's mostly speed of light,
it will not depend if it's a speed of light component
of the latency of how fast is a network,
how fast is a link.
So if you have 100 megabits per second,
or one gigabits per second link,
or 10 gigabits per second link,
you can still only send at 120 kilobits per second.
So how can you send more?
How would you modify this protocol to send more data?
Batch acknowledgements.
So if you batch, it's true.
So, but if you batch the acknowledgement,
this means that you have to send a packet
before you receive the acknowledgement for that packet.
Your intuition is correct, but of course,
as you'll see, and that's a big part of the solution,
but as you'll see, things will not be as easy.
It's exactly Simon and Allison, yeah, it's the same.
You don't need to get block on NAC,
because if you get block on NAC,
then it's no longer, you can send out, send packets, right?
But the problem is the following.
Okay, you don't draw,
your intuition is absolutely correct.
The main problem here is that I need to wait
for an acknowledgement from the previous packet
before I can send the next packet.
And the solution is, okay, don't wait for that, right?
Send more packets.
That's the problem, and if you don't have losses,
that will be great.
But if the packets are lost,
then here the acknowledgement serves two purposes.
One, to slow you down, to slow the sender down, right?
To block the sender.
But the other one is also to say
that the packet has been successfully received.
So let's talk about losses.
So in the internet, you are going to have losses
like we discussed last time, right?
And actually TCP, transfer control protocol,
is going also to provide reliability
besides flow control and congestion control.
But as a network layer, you are going to have losses
because many reasons.
It's like we discussed in the past.
We have, you know, your microwave
can corrupt your wireless link.
Even in optical networks, the bits can be corrupted.
The wire can be bad, not very well connected.
And many reasons.
Or like we all see, the buffers in the routers
are going to overflow and you are going to drop packets.
Okay?
So now, when you, with a packet, you have associated,
basically, as you'll see,
so there are two ways to lose a packet here.
First of all, the packet doesn't get
to the destination at all.
It's lost.
The second one, the packet is corrupted.
So you get the packet, but some bits are flipped.
Okay?
So on the receiver side, you need to know that,
you need to make sure that you get all the packets.
The packets you got are not corrupted.
And by the way, you also want to make sure
that you get each packet exactly once
to deliver to the application.
So this acknowledgement, like we saw earlier on,
they also serve as an acknowledgement
that the packet was delivered to the destination.
Okay?
So basically, if I am the receiver,
I get the packet, I check the packet, whether it's correct.
How do I check the packet that is correct?
They have the correct information.
How do you do it?
Say you are the designer.
Oh yeah, this is, yeah, you do have a checksum.
Like a checksum, like parity bit,
something more sophisticated than that,
but that's the idea.
Right?
So the packet has a data and has a checksum.
So you take the data and you pre-compute the checksum
using the same algorithms.
And you compare that the computed checksum
is the same as the checksum in the packet.
If they are the same, you say this packet,
the data is correct.
Otherwise, you drop the packet.
Right?
Now, if a packet is dropped, like in our previous case,
right, the question is that I'm sending a packet,
the packet is lost, for instance,
or it gets to the destination, is dropped.
What am I going to do?
So what I'm going to do,
because I'm going to wait indefinitely,
because I'm going to wait for a knack,
which will never come.
So what you do here is basically very simple solution.
Basically, you wait for a timeout.
It's like you in real life.
You are waiting for your friend to call.
And he doesn't call at when it was the time you expected.
What do you do?
After a while, you are calling your friend, right?
Or you go to meet someone and that person doesn't show up.
What do you do?
You wait for a while and then you leave, right?
So now, obviously,
it's again, it's very important to notice here,
by the way, that if you don't get the acknowledgement,
it doesn't mean that the receiver,
that he didn't give the original message.
No, right?
Can you give me an example?
You know, the receiver,
I didn't hear about the acknowledgement,
but the receiver got the packet and the packet is correct.
So I send you the packet.
I don't hear from you back.
the acknowledgement is lost.
The acknowledgement is also a packet
that can be lost as well, right?
So basically, you may send the packet,
you may resend the packet
because you don't get the acknowledgement on the timeout.
And now the receiver gets a duplicate of the packet.
So that's why the receiver has to have a way also
to differentiate between a duplicate
and the original packet.
Because if the original packet was already delivered
to the destination, to the process,
you need to drop the duplicate, right?
Okay, so this is an example.
When the arc is lost, you resend the packet
and now the receiver gets two packets, right?
Now, it's one of the challenge here
is how you are going to pick the timeout.
If the timeout is short, you may get lots of duplicates.
So why is that?
Right?
Remember that this, like in our simple examples,
we assume that the one-way latency is constant.
It's like in real life.
It's like on the highway, like we discussed.
So latency is not going to be the same.
So you are too trigger happy with the timeout
and to resend the packet,
I wait just for the timeout, the minimal timeout, right?
As far as the minimum round trip time.
Then if I send, I may send too early
because I didn't give enough time to the packet
to make the destination and the acknowledgement to come back.
Obviously, if I wait, it is too long,
then the performance suffers.
So for instance, the round trip time,
say it's 100 milliseconds and the timeout is one second.
Right?
So this means that if there is a timeout,
I lost the opportunity to send another nine packets, right?
Or 10, depends how you count.
So how do you do with the application?
Basically, you have somehow to put some sequence number
in the packets and the sequence numbers are unique.
And the acknowledgement will be
for a particular sequence number, right?
And the sender, when you send,
you keep the packets which are not acknowledged, right?
So you know about, you still have the packets
if they are lost.
If a packet is acknowledged, the sender can draw,
can remove that packet from his buffer.
And on the receiver side, I also keep a track
of the sequence numbers of the packets I got.
So if I get a duplicate packet
with a duplicate sequence number, I can drop it.
Okay.
Of course, you want to simplify it
by having only one message at a time again,
and you just don't move until the message has been sent,
has been received by the sender, by the receiver.
Okay. And this is exactly what we are talking about
in our example.
The problem obviously is that it's slow and bad performance.
So now let's go back to solve our problem.
And our problem was that how we are going
to improve the throughput over stop and wait, right?
We said that, you know,
in order to improve the throughput is quite easy,
is basically don't wait, send packets
without waiting for the acknowledgements.
And we saw that doing that won't be that easy
because the acknowledgement also acknowledge
whether the packet was received or not,
and if the packets are lost, things get complicated, right?
But this being said, this is a solution, right?
For improving the performance, right?
You send a lot of packets
without waiting for the acknowledgement.
So we pipeline the sending, right?
So that's very simple.
So now if you have this one, you know,
the natural way to implement this protocol
is to have what is called a window.
A window is how many packets or how many bytes
you can send without hearing for an acknowledgement.
So if the window size, let's think about
in terms of packets, and we say,
let me think in terms of bytes.
If a window size is 10 packets,
this means that I can send 10 packets
before I hear, I get back the acknowledgement
from the first packet I sent.
Okay?
So now in a round trip time,
I can send a window worth of packets.
Right?
Because this is how many packets I can send
without hearing for an acknowledgement.
Right?
So therefore, you know,
and in the number of packets which are in flight
are going to be without meaning in flight
from packets which are in flight,
I haven't heard an acknowledgement for these packets yet.
Is a window size over the packet size.
Right?
How long does the sender need to send packets around?
Well, what is your answer?
How many packets does the sender need to keep around?
So if the packets are lost, can still fix the loss.
Yes.
Allison, this is good.
So you need to keep at least a number of packets
which is equal with the window size.
How long does the receiver have to keep the packet data?
Remember, the receiver needs to keep the long packet data
or at least a sequence number
in order to avoid duplicates.
Until the packet in the window time is time out.
Let's think about, forget about the protocol.
When can you remove a packet?
Think about your receiver packet.
When can you remove the information about that packet?
Again, the main reason you are going to keep
that information around is to avoid duplicates.
So I send you a packet.
When do you know that I am not going to send you again
that packet?
(silence)
When I send the next packet, depends on the protocol, right?
It's the next sequence number.
It's a little more complicated, but that I think we are close.
But fundamentally the answer to my question is that
you know that you can remove the packet
when I know that you got the packet.
Once I know that you got the packet,
I'm no longer going to send you the packet again.
And we'll see a little bit of how that is done.
It's not that easy.
But yes, because you see,
if I'm getting user packet with an ex-sequence number,
it's not necessarily the case, right?
Because like here, if you look at this, in this figure,
a packet will be lost.
If a packet, the third packet is lost, right?
And I get the next packet, actually, in some cases,
you cannot remove the packet one or two,
because in some protocols,
the sender is going to start from the beginning
to send all the packets.
Okay, actually in TCP and MOS version of TCP,
this will happen.
What if the sender is sending packets faster
than the receiver can process the data?
In this case, it's quite simple.
You slow down the acknowledgements, right?
If you cannot get more packets, you slow down.
Okay, so now we are going to talk about,
these are some good questions,
and to keep in mind and see how they are solved.
In particular, the last one,
how long does the receiver have to keep the packets data?
What if the sender is sending packets faster
than the receiver can process the data,
which is exactly the flow control.
So now the TCP, again, I mentioned that last time,
but it was very quickly,
has a slide-down window protocol at the byte,
not packet level.
So, so far we talk about packets,
it was easier to visualize.
And it has two ways to recover.
Go back and, is that if I miss some packets, right?
I'm going to go back and I'm going to send the packets
from the one which I missed,
and also the subsequent packets,
whether you receive them or not.
Selective repeat, you only send all the packets,
it's called DCPSAC.
You only send all the packets which are lost,
or the bytes which are lost.
And the main way this TCP implements the flow control
is by the receiver telling the sender
how many more bytes it can receive.
And this is called advertiser.
And the acknowledgement contains the sequence number,
and of the next byte the receiver expects.
So this means that the receiver has received all bytes
in sequence up to and including L minus one.
If there is a gap, I receive the first 100 bytes,
and then there is a gap of 50 bytes,
and then I received the bytes from 150 to 150.
As a receiver, I am still going to send to the sender,
101, which is the next byte in sequence I am expecting.
So next we are going to go through a bunch of definitions
about some variables.
There are six of them.
And then we are going to take an example, a simple example.
So hopefully the examples will clarify things.
Okay?
But, you know, it's, please, you know, bear with me.
So this is a bounding, you know,
if I'm taking this bounding buffer example,
like I showed you earlier in the lecture,
and I try to map it on two hosts, sender and the receiver,
this is one I can show, I can do it.
I can have a buffer on the receiving process,
that's a bounding buffer,
and the sending was going to send it, you know,
and these packets are going to be,
and queued in that buffer,
and then delivered to the receiving process.
However, like I mentioned to you,
like we discussed last time,
this is not going to work well in practice,
because this means that for each packet,
the sender process sends,
you need to have a context switching,
because your operating system is going to be involved
in the act of sending the packet,
because the TCP/IP, the network stack,
is implemented in the operating system.
And if you do a context switching
on sending every packet,
like for instance, in the case of the internet,
the packet size is typically 1500 bytes,
then in order to sustain the throughput
of a one-gabit per second,
one-gabit per second link,
you need to send a packet every 12 microseconds.
And if the packet is smaller,
like 100 bytes in less than one microsecond,
and this is too little for the context switching, right?
So therefore, how you solve the problem?
You have other buffers.
So in general, you have one buffer on the sender side
and one buffer on the receiver side.
This is what operating system maintains.
And the processes themselves,
they can have other buffers, right?
So actually the process of sending
from one process towards another has three steps.
The sending process sends the data
to the operating system or is buffered in the TCP layer.
The operating system is using the IP layer
to send, to chop the data you send
from the sender into packets
and send it to the receiver, operating system.
The receiver operating system will put the data
it receives in a buffer.
And then from this buffer is going to deliver the data
to the receiving process.
Okay?
And by the way, the fact you see,
that I have a buffer allows me for something else.
The sending process can have a stream-oriented protocol
like we learned.
So I can send a stream of bytes, 1000 bytes,
four kilobytes, whatever.
And then the operating system, this buffer,
I put all this data into the buffer
and the operating system can then take the data
and chop it in packets
because that IP layer is not a streaming protocol.
You have to send packets.
I need to put, take some piece of data,
I'm putting the headers, port numbers
for a source and destination,
IP addresses, then at the lower level,
you put the MAC addresses and things like that.
Okay?
So now let's assume that the maximum IP packet size
for this example is 100 bytes.
Again, in general, in practice is 1500 bytes.
In the size of the receiving buffer is 300 bytes.
So the receiver can, this is a buffer, 300 bytes.
Also recalls that the acknowledgement
indicates the next expected byte in sequence,
not the last received bytes.
And like we discussed last time,
we use circular buffers, right?
If you remember.
So basically a circular buffer is like you see here,
is basically goes around and you keep the head
and the tail of the buffer.
Okay?
So now with all of this, let's see how things are working.
Like I mentioned, we are going to decide
to define six variables.
Last byte written.
So this is a sequence of the last byte written
by the sending process into the operating system buffer.
Last byte sent is the last byte sent
by the sender to the receiver.
Last byte act is the last act received
by sender from the receiver.
Last byte received is the last byte received
by receiver from the sender.
And next byte expected is the last in sequence byte
expected by the receiver.
Is it a convention to start a circular buffer at one index?
It depends.
Depends on language you are going to use.
If you see it's probably zero.
Yeah.
Okay.
So now let's take the examples.
And, oh, and sorry.
The last byte read is the last byte read
by the receiving process.
Okay.
So this basically says that you have
in this blue area in the receiving buffer
is how many bytes you have in the buffer,
in the receiving buffer.
You consume from one end, so this is the start.
The last byte read is the start of the buffer,
of the data in the buffer.
Last byte received is the last byte
in this data, of the data in the buffer.
And next byte expected in this case
is the last byte received plus one,
because that's the one you expect.
OK?
So now the advertised window is by definition,
again, how many bytes the receiver, the sender,
can send me without me overflowing.
[AUDIO OUT]
So basically, if I am the receiver
and my buffer size is 300 bytes, and the buffer is empty,
I tell you, you can send me 300 bytes.
If my buffer, I already have 100 bytes source of data
in the buffer, I tell you, well, you can send me only 200 bytes.
So this formula is computing exactly what I told you.
It's a maximum buffer minus how much data
I have in this contiguous region in the buffer, which
is last byte received minus last byte read.
OK?
The same thing, it's on the sending side or similar, right?
Here I have last byte act.
So here, if I get an acknowledgment
in this protocol, if I'm going to get
an acknowledgment for a byte, this
means that the receiving process receives that byte.
So I no longer need to keep it in the buffer as a sender.
So everything before last byte act can be dropped.
And then you have last byte sent.
So what is last byte act?
What is the things between last byte act and last byte sent?
This green area.
This green area represents the data
that the sending process send it without being acknowledged.
That's it.
OK?
So let me see.
It's exactly the same, yeah.
The packets we send that have not received an act.
So they are not acknowledged.
So now, think about send a window.
And again, you have the formula.
You can look at the formula.
But let's take an example.
Now let's think about from the sender perspective.
Say the receiver, you are the sender.
The receiver tells you, my advertised window is 300 bytes.
And since I love this information,
I already send you 100 bytes.
How many more bytes can I send you
before I'm hearing back from you?
So that I am absolutely certain I'm not going to overflow you.
Right?
See this again.
The receiver tells you, you can send me 300 bytes.
Since you heard that, then when you heard that,
you sent 100 bytes.
Still nothing from the receiver.
How many more bytes you can send before you
hear from the receiver?
Yes.
In my example, it was 200, right?
Right?
Receiver told you, you can send me 300 bytes.
You send 100 bytes.
You haven't heard yet.
You can send another 200 bytes.
So then you send in total 300 bytes before you hear back.
You cannot send more.
And this is exactly this next formula.
The sender window is how many more bytes
you can send without overflowing the receiver.
And it's advertised window minus the number of bytes
you send out without being acknowledged in that window.
OK?
It's still true.
It's a very important aspect.
This is still true if you miss the data, these formulas.
Right?
Because if you miss the data here on the receiver side,
the next byte expected, by the way, you see here,
the next byte expected is the one which is in sequence.
Right?
Because you have a gap, the gap doesn't
matter for the next byte expected.
But for the last byte received, it matters.
OK?
So remember that.
So these are the same formulas if you
miss the data in the middle.
OK.
So now let's take a simple example.
So let's say the sending application sends 350 bytes.
We assume the IP only access package
no larger than 100 bytes.
And let's say the MACs receive the advertised window.
MACs receiving buffer is 300 bytes.
And advertised window initially is 300 bytes.
So sender first, send buffer's packet.
How much big is the first packet?
100 bytes.
Because that's the maximum size of the packet.
With green, I showed the packet which
are sent without being acknowledged.
Here on each side, I'm saying 1 to 100
between these square brackets is the bytes
which have been sent.
I am starting from 1.
OK?
So eventually, the last byte sent
when I am doing, when I'm sending initially
the last byte back, it's 0.
No, nothing was hacked.
The last byte sent is 100 because I sent 100 bytes.
And now eventually, this packet is
delivered to the destination.
Last byte receives is 100.
Next byte is expected is 101.
Right?
Everything is good.
Now, the receiver sends back acknowledgment 101,
advertised window noise 200.
Because I had-- it was 300.
I got 100.
Now you can send me only 200.
OK?
Before receiving this acknowledgment,
because the window advertising is 300 bytes
and I sent only 100 bytes, I'm going to send the next packet,
me being the sender.
The bytes are between 101 and 200.
Right?
And again, sorry, here I am saying
all the packets which have been sent,
all the bytes which have been sent.
So now I send from the sender between 1 and 200.
OK?
This packet is going to--
now the last byte sent is 200.
And it's going to get to the receiver.
And the receiver, you have last byte receives 200,
next byte expected 201.
And I'm going to now write 201.
Now, assume that next thing what happened,
the receiving process, there is some data.
Let's say it is 100 bytes, the first 100 bytes.
So now in the receiving window, in the receiving buffer,
I only have 100 bytes, because 100 bytes already
were processed by the receiver.
We're already delivered to the receiver process.
So when I'm going to send back an acknowledgment,
I'm going to include the next sequence, next byte expected,
which is 201.
And then advertising window, it's again 200.
Because in the buffer, I have only 100 bytes,
and the buffer is 300 bytes.
Now, the sender, it's again.
I still have-- I know that I sent only 200 bytes.
The receiver told me initially that I can send 300 bytes.
So I still can send 100 bytes.
So let me send the next packet.
now to make things more interesting that this packet has been lost.
Okay. That's fine. In the meantime, I advance the last by set send on the sender to 300.
And in the meantime, the sending window now is zero. I can no longer send. You see,
the sending window magically now is zero because I sent 300 bytes. I knew that the advertising
noise 300 bytes. I haven't heard anything from the receiver. So therefore I have to stop sending.
Okay. Now, in the meantime, I get the first acknowledgement back.
The fact that acknowledgement back is telling me I have 101, the acknowledgement is 101,
and the advertised window is 200. Right? So the first packet was acknowledged.
Right? So because the first packet was acknowledged, it was acknowledged,
and also indicates the next packet to send. So the receiver no longer meets the first 100 bytes. So
I'm going to remove this from the sender buffer because the receiver told me that it got the first
100 bytes. Okay. So, and I am going to advance last byte act 100. But the sender window is still
zero because I sent 300 bytes. And now the sender told me, okay, I got 100 bytes, but I can receive
only 200 bytes, 200 more bytes. So yes. Okay. I removed the 100 bytes that sender sent told me
that the receiver told me that they receive, but still I have 200 bytes, which are not
acknowledged. And the receiver told me that it can only send, receive 200 bytes without
being acknowledged. So I cannot send anything. But finally, now I get the second acknowledgement
and the second acknowledgement tells me, it tells the receiver that the receiver got the first 200
bytes. So the next expected byte is 201 and the advertiser window is 200. So now when you compute
the advertise window, you get 100 because it's 200 advertised window. And now I have in flight
only 100 bytes. So I can send another 100 bytes. I don't have 100 bytes to send. I only have 50.
Right. Because I had only, I wanted to send 350 bytes. So I'm going to send these 350 bytes,
the last 50 bytes. And then they are going to be received by the receiver. But now I have a gap
and the gap is the third packet which was lost. So you see now next byte expected is 201. Right.
And the last byte received now is 350. So now I send back to the receiver and say, look,
I got the next byte I am expecting is 201, but the advertiser window is 50.
Okay. So if the advertiser window is 50, what is the sending process going to do?
Right.
Yes, you can send in this case, you can send the packet which was lost.
Why you can send this packet which was lost?
We'll do more about this in a while.
It's still in the green region. It's exact.
By the sending window is less, yeah, it's good. By the sending window is less than zero.
It's good. It's very good. Very good observation. But the point here that I can send the packet
because I already sent that packet. It doesn't count. I can always send a packet which I
previously sent. Right. Because in the worst case, it will be the duplicate.
In the worst case, it will be duplicated. In the best case, it's going to repair the loss.
You see, the receiver by this gap already accounted for the loss packet.
That's a key. Right. So you see, it's already accounted. The next expected byte is 350. So
therefore, if I'm going to send a packet, that's not going to change the window on anything.
It's again, either it's going to repair a loss or it's going to be duplicated.
So that's why I can send the packet. And why I'm going to send now? In this particular case,
I'm going to send it because you see, the second time I get
acknowledgement sender, the receiver told me that the acknowledgement, the next sequence number is
expecting is 201. So basically, if you, and we'll see this next, this is a way to detect the failure.
Okay. So I can, a packet loss. So one way to detect the packet loss is that if the receiver
tells me multiple times, I am waiting for the sequence number, next sequence number.
Right. Because this means that it gets the reason if the receiver can, it will tell me that it waits
for the same sequence number over and over again, is that I send him an ex pack, another packet,
but it's a gap. It's not in sequence. Because if it's in sequence, the next sequence number,
the receiver will tell me will advance as well. Okay.
So anyway, so and now if you have, if finally you get the next packet,
the last packet, the receiver gets the last packet, now he has everything, it's got up to 350,
is going that acknowledgement to contain 351, which the next sequence number is going to wait
for. Advertising window is still 50. And now when the receiver, the sender gets acknowledgement 351,
it can remove everything from its buffer because all the data is sent was acknowledged.
So now we are done.
Any questions?
Yeah, so please, you should, you know, you can go through this
example. It's very, it's very revealing, but you need to go a few times to really feel it,
understand it.
So let's have a short discussion before we move.
Yes, almost everything we talked, goes to back end and selective repeat.
The only difference is like it was said, someone said, for instance, the difference here,
this was mostly I shown you about selective acknowledgement. So I'm telling you what is
the difference. So with go back end, the sender is going to send everything up from 2001, including
the last 50 bytes, which are already received by the receiver. Okay. So you already go from the
first sequence number, which was expected by of the missing packet. Okay. In the case of selective
acknowledgement, there is a set.
sender is like in this case is going only to send out
the missing packets, the missing information.
Yes, would last byte read cause a bottleneck
on how is the question from Simon.
Would last byte read cause a bottleneck
on how fast we can clear the buffer.
If we are not spending enough cycles
to copy from buffer to process,
we cannot advance last byte read as fast.
So that limits our advertising.
Absolutely, and that exactly is a purpose,
the goal of having this last byte read.
The goal is basically, yes,
you know, it's here,
the ultimate receiver is a perceiving process.
So the receiving process for some reason cannot consume data
which the sender shouldn't send faster.
Okay.
Okay, so let's move on.
Let's go, so why not have a huge buffer
at the receiver, memory is cheap after all.
(silence)
A huge buffer at the receiver also mean
a huge buffer is a sender, right?
And we'll see that huge buffer actually also
in the network for congestion control
means that the latency is going to increase
significantly because the latency is going to increase
significantly because it's going to take more
to send to clear the buffer.
Yeah, so it's like the transmissions,
the round trip time, the transmission time
is going to grow a lot.
Sending window also depend on a third congestion
is what we're going to go on to do next.
There are a lot of details about if you're interested
about networking, take CS168.
And by the way, we talk about a few buffers,
two buffers here in the operating systems
for the sender and the receiver side.
In practice, there are more buffers.
There are network cards has buffers,
buffer in the network and everything.
So let's announcements.
Meet the three is tomorrow.
What we've done over today in the lecture is not for next,
is not included in the material for the exam
for the last midterm.
On Sunday, we are going this project three party
between 10 and 2 p.m.
The discussions will be converted in office hours
to help you with the projects, last project
and with the exam, it will be after the exam.
So it don't help you as much.
The office hours also will continue into that week,
again, to help you with the projects.
Homework C6 is due Friday, next Friday
and project, no, yeah, this Friday, sorry, not next Friday.
And the project three is due as you know on December 8th.
Okay, so now we have another 15 minutes.
So let me tell you a little bit about the congestion control.
So flow control don't overflow the receiver.
Congestion control don't overflow the network.
The network has routers, has buffers in between.
So now the question is how you are going to detect
the congestion in the network.
And remember the congestion, I'm going to detect
there's a transfer level layer.
There is no transfer layer in the network.
It's only between two end hosts.
So I can only observe the network.
There are a few ways to detect the congestions.
One, a packet is dropped.
You interpret this to be a sign of congestion
because you assume there's a reason
a packet has been dropped is that because a buffer
of the router has overflow, was overflow.
So filled in, the router cannot send packets
as fast as it gets, the buffer fills in packets are dropped.
There is a more refined version,
early congestion notification.
So when the buffer at the router increases
over some threshold, the router set up a bit,
it's called ECN bit in the packet.
And then the receiver sends back to the sender saying,
hey, don't slow down because this router
it's about to be, is congested.
And the other one is delayed packets.
When the buffer grows, the latency grows.
It's like on the highway.
So if I see that the delay has increased,
maybe I need to slow down.
The simplest one, it's drop packets.
And this is what we are going to assume.
It's still most used sign of congestion today.
And like we discussed, there are two ways
what to detect these drop packets.
Again, the question is how do you detect a drop packet?
Right?
Congestion means the router buffer is full.
And then because it's full, the packet is dropped.
But now if I'm the sender,
how I'm going to know that the packet was dropped?
How I'm going to decide the packet was dropped?
One way is like we discussed earlier on, timeout.
I wait for some time,
which is significantly larger than the router time.
I don't get an acknowledgement.
I assume the packet is lost, even if it doesn't.
So I resend it.
And the other one I just alluded to you earlier on,
it's when I received the same acknowledgements,
the same sequence number in the acknowledgement,
the next sequence number,
expecting sequence number over and over again.
Right?
Because again, in this case, I am going to send you,
so in this case, I send you the packet 200.
Right? From 100 to 200.
So you tell me, oh, the next sequence number,
I'm going to, I want, I am expecting from you is 201.
Now I'm sending you the next packet
with the bias 200 to 300.
You lost it.
You don't tell me anything.
Now I'm sending the next packet 300 to 400.
You give me the acknowledgement for that packet,
but if the sequence number,
next sequence expecting sequence number is still to 100,
because you are telling me about the sequence,
next expected in sequence number.
So now you told me two times, 200,
the next sequence in sequence number,
you expect is 201.
I'm sending you another packet now between 400 and 500 bytes.
Again, you tell me the next byte in sequence
I'm expecting is 201.
So again, an acknowledgement, which is duplicate.
This is what we call duplicate acknowledgement
because you tell me repeatedly over and over again,
you told me over and over again,
you on the next sequence number I'm expecting is 201.
So after a few of those, I decide, well,
that packet was lost and I'm going to resend it.
This is duplicate acknowledgement.
Make sense?
Okay.
So congestion control is a key idea is a sender increase,
to increase ascending rate of the network until congestion,
if the network is not congested.
They introduce ascending rate if the network is congested.
How does the sender control ascending rate?
Sender window size, ascending window size,
which is called right now in this context,
congestion window size.
Here is a great question from Alison
about the previous case, what I mentioned to you.
So the question from Alison is the following.
Can you not conclude it was lost,
the packet was lost after the first duplicate hack?
Tell me why you wouldn't do that.
You could do that, but why you wouldn't do it?
(silence)
Maybe out of order.
Yes, it's exactly out of order.
You see, look at this figure and assume that these packets, which is lost, instead of being lost, it travels on a different path in the network.
And arrives actually at the destination after the packet, the first packet, the one which, right after that, after the last packet, right, which was sent by the sender.
So the second packet is lost in this example, but assume is not lost, but it arrives after the first packet.
So if that's the case, the sender will see the same things. It cannot differentiate between the two.
So waiting for more duplicate acknowledgments is a way to make it more sure that the packet was really lost.
And it's not because the packets are reordered. And the packets are reordered because every packet can take a different route in the network.
Which means also is true, that three duplicate acknowledgments, missing three duplicate acknowledgments are not necessary, always guarantee a packet has been lost.
It's correct. It just increases the probability, that assertion, to be correct.
OK. So how does a sender control sending rate? It's using, again, a window. It's called congestion window size.
And congestion window size is going to take the minimum between the sending window size and this congestion window size, which is computed in the network.
And obviously it might be less than the receiver advertising window and increase the size of the windows until congestion and reduce the size of the window if congestion.
Because the window size, it tells me how many packets, how many bytes I can send without being acknowledged.
Right. So bigger window means higher throughput. I can send more data before being acknowledged. Smaller window size, I can send, you know, if it's one packet, it's top end way.
So finally, let me tell you, I'm going to spend a few minutes on this plot. And this is just to give you a taste about how the TCP is working and congestion control is working.
So first of all, I don't know how much, when I'm starting to send data as a sender, I know how much the receiver can handle.
Because the receiver, there is, initially when I established the connection and a three-way handshake protocol, and the receiver tells me about the advertisement.
It's advertisement. So I know that. I know how much to send without overflowing the receiver. But I don't know about how much I can send without overflowing the network.
So then what I'm sending, I'm going to send, start with a congestion window of one. Let's again think about congestion window one packet to simplify the discussion.
So I'm moving from window measuring in bytes into packets. Two packets again.
So I'm sending one packet and I'm waiting for acknowledgement. So I'm sending only one packet.
So it's like stop and wait. But now when I'm getting the first acknowledgement, I send a packet, it went through. Let me be more aggressive now.
So I'm going to increase the congestion window when I get the acknowledgement by one. So now I'm going to send two packets.
And each acknowledgement I get, I mean, add another one to the congestion window.
Now this is called slow start. Slow start is a terrible name because actually, if you think about in the slow start by using, by CWU is a congestion window here.
If you increase the congestion window every time you get a knock by one, you double the congestion window every round trip time. In the first round trip time, I send one packet,
I got one acknowledgement. So now in the second round trip time I send two packets. I get two acknowledgement. For each acknowledgement I get in the second round trip time,
I'm going to increase the window size by one. So from two is going to go to four. Now in the third congestion round trip time, I'm going to send four packets.
For each acknowledgement, I'm going to increase the congestion window by one. So I'm going to have eight.
Right. So this is what you see the congestion window size is on the vertical. So it's going from small, you know, double every time. And at some point, I am going
probably to lose a packet because I sent too much.
This is when the packet is lost. So what I'm going to do when that happened.
You need to be very aggressive, because it turns out that if you just are, you are not very aggressive, and this is, you know, it's a theory property we don't have time to go into it.
But if you don't reduce the sending rate very fast, you cannot really relieve the congestion.
Right. So in this case, okay, you are very dramatic. So you're going to go with the congestion window all the way to one.
Reduce it. And then you go again, slow start, again, exponential increase. But now you go through until to this threshold.
And this threshold is the last is a congestion window.
In the previous slow start, because you're still successful all the packets made it.
So congestion window, it was eight, I sent eight packets, I got eight acknowledgement, then and then when I congestion window increased to 16, I got, I lost packets, I'm going the next time, I'm only going to stop the slow start or aggressive start to eight.
Because I know that kind of a successful last time, and then I'm going to be much more timidly explore, you know how you increase and explore the capacity of the network.
Right. So I'm going to increase now with one, I'm going only to increase.
This is what I was talking about and now I'm going to increase only the congestion window by one, but round trip time. So this means that you now when I'm going to get an acknowledgement I'm going to increase the congestion window by one over n, where n is a current congestion window size.
Right. So if I have the congestion window size is 10, and every acknowledgement I'm going to increase the window size by one over 10. Now, in one round trip time I'm going to increase the congestion from 10 to 11.
So you get this one. So this is additive increase is called additive increase. Right. And then I get a loss here if I lost here maybe I is because three WK acknowledgement. Now I'm going back, if it's through the WK acknowledgement I'm going to get back to the threshold.
Right. And then I go, I grow again and things like that. Okay.
So, so that's basically what it is. So there is an early stage in which you grow very fast to explore the limits of the network.
And then after that you get into this regime, which is at the end, you additively increase.
Then the window size and you get a loss you multiply it decrease. This is called multiplicative decrease basically you're cutting to half in general.
You grow linearly, you cut it to half, you grow linearly, you cut it to half.
So that's pretty much it. It's again it's fascinating.
Algorithm, very very simple but in dynamic the dynamics are fascinating.
So, I'm going to stop here, and, you know, we talked about the network, the networking summary, we talk about this and we talk about networking.
We have a few lectures on that.
Remember, the internet has five layers physical layer data link layer network layer transport layer application layer.
And we talked about end to end argument and to argument is saying that the higher layers can implement functionality correctly.
You should implement the functionality as a lower layer only if it improves the performance significantly for applications that needs that functionality, and it does not impose burden on applications that do not require this functionality.
And we discussed flow control, which is whose goal is not overflows the receiver buffer and congestion control is the main goal is to not overflow the network.
Thank you and next lecture, I'm going to do it's a special topics. I'm going to tell you a little bit about some of the research, which we have been doing the Rice lab and AMLAB.
Okay, see you all.
So I'm going to stop here.
And there is a question I'm going to take.