[Silence]
[沉默]
So, hello everyone. Welcome to the last lecture. And today we are going to go over some special
因此，大家好。欢迎来到最后一堂讲座。今天我们将讨论一些特殊的内容。
topics, this being the last lecture. In particular, I'm going to talk briefly about Apache Spark and
主题，这是最后一堂讲座。具体来说，我将简要谈谈Apache Spark和其他一些相关话题。
Ray, two systems we developed at Berkeley you may have heard of. And I'll try to go quicker,
雷，我们在伯克利开发的两个系统你可能听说过。我会尽量快一点。
although there are a lot of slides, because really I like to give you opportunity to ask any
虽然有很多幻灯片，但我真的很喜欢给你机会提问任何问题。
questions you may have about this lecture, about this class, or in general. So, and of course,
你可能对这个讲座、这门课或者其他方面有一些问题。所以，当然，
as always, at any point, please feel free to ask any questions. So at Berkeley, we have these labs,
一如既往，在任何时候，请随时提问。在伯克利，我们有这些实验室，
and as you may know, each lab is around five years. Each lab has a particular mission
而且你可能知道，每个实验室的周期大约为五年。每个实验室都有特定的任务。
and consists of a bunch of faculty and quite a few graduate students and postdocs.
并且由一群教职员工、相当多的研究生和博士后组成。
And this is what we started, this is one of the more recent one, it was AMLAB 2011-2017.
这是我们开始的项目，这是其中一个比较近期的，它是AMLAB 2011-2017。
It had eight faculties across different disciplines of computer science, algorithms,
它在计算机科学、算法等不同学科领域设有八个学院。
machine learning, and sorry, algorithms, which in what we meant by algorithms is mostly machine
学习机器，还有抱歉，算法，我们所指的算法主要是机器算法。
learning. Machines means systems. And people, we are looking at some projects, which I'm not going
学习。机器意味着系统。而人们，我们正在看一些项目，其中我不参与。
to talk now, it's about crowdsource. That's why, hence the name of the lab, AMP. And these labs,
现在说，是关于众包。这也是为什么实验室的名字叫AMP。而这些实验室，
again, like some of you may know, are in this floor plan in open space. So even the faculty
再次，就像你们中的一些人可能知道的那样，我们在这个楼层的平面图中是开放空间。所以即使是教职员工也是如此。
have open seating, stay in open seating. And as this lab, they have twice a year retreats
有开放式座位，保持在开放式座位。而且这个实验室，他们每年有两次撤退。
with the industry, they are working very closely with the industry,
他们与该行业密切合作。
between, anyway between 120 and 200 people, half from Berkeley, half from industry in general.
大约有120到200人，一半来自伯克利，一半来自整个行业。
And before pandemics, there have been nice places like Tahoe or Monterey, you go there for three
在大流行病之前，有一些很好的地方，比如塔霍湖或蒙特雷，你可以去那里待上三天。
days and then you present the latest results and you get feedback and you network with people from
天数，然后您呈现最新的结果，获得反馈，并与来自各地的人建立联系。
industry. And we also have this kind of AMP camps, which are basically things, once you build some
工业。我们还有这种AMP营地，基本上是一些东西，一旦你建立了一些
systems, some artifacts, these are some events, you know, which you basically train, provide
系统，一些工件，这些是一些事件，你知道的，基本上是你训练、提供的。
tutorials to people in particular from industry to use for this new systems you've built.
你们已经建立了这个新系统，现在需要为特定行业的人提供教程来使用。
Anyway, so let's start. So this is Spark. Spark started at UC Berkeley in 2009, so actually started
无论如何，让我们开始吧。这是Spark。Spark于2009年在加州大学伯克利分校开始，实际上开始于该年。
in the lab before AMP lab, that was called rat lab. But the main development happened during the AMP
在AMP实验室之前，那个实验室被称为老鼠实验室。但主要的发展发生在AMP期间。
lab. It became open source 2010. It becomes an Apache project, 2013, and also data breaches
实验室。它在2010年成为开源项目。它在2013年成为Apache项目，并且也发生了数据泄露事件。
with the company behind the open source project has been started in 2013. And today it's a de facto
自2013年开始，这个开源项目的背后有一家公司。如今，它已成为事实上的
standard for doing big data processing. So how did this happen? So what was, you know,
大数据处理的标准。那么这是怎么发生的呢？你知道的，那是什么呢？
in 2009 when we started to work on this, what was the state of the world? So at that time,
2009年我们开始着手这个项目时，世界的状况如何？所以当时，
the most popular system to process huge amounts of data, large amounts of data was Apache Hadoop.
处理大量数据的最流行系统是Apache Hadoop。
And Apache Hadoop was an open source clone of the MapReduce, which are MapReduce, which are the
Apache Hadoop是MapReduce的开源克隆版本，MapReduce是什么，MapReduce是什么。
system, high profile system developed internally at Google. And this process, huge amount of data,
系统，高调系统在谷歌内部开发。而且这个过程中，涉及大量的数据，
the processing amount of data, but it was more bad. It was quite slow. But it had
数据处理量很大，但效果很差。速度非常慢。但它有
rapid, you know, it had a lot of industry adoption, some of the big high tech companies.
快速，你知道的，它在很多行业得到了广泛采用，包括一些大型高科技公司。
And Cloudera, Horton, are two companies, which are two new startups, which are
而Cloudera和Horton是两家公司，它们是两个新创企业，它们是
promoting Hadoop open source. And at that time, again, this is open source, it was free. So
推广Hadoop开源。而且那个时候，这是开源的，是免费的。
it came at the right time because if you probably remember or heard 2007, 2008 was this big financial
它正好在合适的时候出现，因为如果你可能还记得或听说过2007年、2008年，那是一次大规模的金融危机。
crash. So, sorry, this should be hard to let me guess.
崩溃了。很抱歉，这应该很难让我猜到。
So this is, and let's not simplify. So this is like how Hadoop is working.
这就是，我们不要简化。这就像Hadoop的工作方式一样。
The Hadoop has two stages, map and reduce. And in each stage, each stage is done in parallel,
Hadoop有两个阶段，分别是map和reduce。而且在每个阶段中，每个阶段都是并行进行的。
a bunch of map tasks reads the data from the stories, from the disk. Then they process the
一堆地图任务从磁盘上读取故事中的数据。然后它们进行处理。
data. Then they shuffle the data. And there is a second stage, which is a reduced stage.
数据。然后他们对数据进行洗牌。接下来是第二阶段，也就是一个简化的阶段。
And the reduced stage provides you the final results. The classic example of a
而降低的阶段为您提供最终结果。一个经典的例子是一个
mabri's job is count. You count how many occurrences of each word you have in this
Mabri的工作是计数。你要计算在这个文本中每个单词出现的次数。
10 millions of documents. So this is basically the high level. And I think that many of you
1千万份文件。所以这基本上是高层次的。我认为你们中的许多人
already know about it. You may have even done projects with Hadoop.
已经知道了。你甚至可能已经用Hadoop做过项目了。
Any questions so far? So the tasks are typically collocated with the data, with the input data.
有任何问题吗？所以任务通常与数据一起放置，与输入数据一起。
And like this figure shows, the input data as well as the intermediate data is stored on the disk.
并且正如这个图所示，输入数据和中间数据都存储在磁盘上。
So the question, can I briefly explain what is a map and reduce means? So think about this one.
所以问题是，我能简要解释一下什么是map和reduce吗？想一想这个问题。
And sorry, I don't have an example here right away. But I think that we can,
并且抱歉，我这里暂时没有例子。但是我认为我们可以，
it's hopefully reasonably easy to explain even without an example of something. Say you have 10
这个希望是相当容易解释的，即使没有具体的例子。假设你有10个。
millions documents, you have large number of documents, and you want to count the occurrences
数百万份文件，您拥有大量的文件，并且想要统计出现次数。
of every word, right, English word in these documents.
对，我会将这些文件中的每个英文单词都翻译出来。
So one way to do it is very simple. First, you define, say you have 100 machines.
所以有一种简单的方法。首先，你定义，假设你有100台机器。
So you take these 10 millions documents and you divide them between 100 machines and you give
所以你将这1千万份文件分配给100台机器，并且你给出
to each machine, I think 100,000 documents, right. And each machine takes these pile of documents
对于每台机器，我认为有100,000份文件，对吗？然后每台机器都处理这些一堆文件。
and it counts each word. Like for instance, the word Berkeley. How many times it appears in each
句子 and it counts each word. Like for instance, the word Berkeley. How many times it appears in each 句子
pile of documents? And one machine will say, okay, Berkeley, it appears 200 times, another machine
文件堆？然后一台机器会说，好的，伯克利，它出现了200次，另一台机器...
finds 150 times and so forth. So this first phase in which each machine is doing independently
找到150次，等等。所以这是第一阶段，每台机器都在独立地进行。
this counting on each pile of documents is called map. Now each of the, each after the first stage,
这个对每一堆文件进行计数的过程被称为映射。现在每一堆文件，在第一阶段之后的每一堆文件，
you want to aggregate, right, because in order to know the total number of occurrences of the word
你想要汇总，对吧，因为要知道该词的总出现次数。
Berkeley in all the documents, you need to sum up, right, because one machine in its own.
在所有的文件中，你需要总结一下，对吗？因为一台机器在自己的。
100,000, like again, found that Berkeley occurs 200 times,
10万次，再次发现伯克利出现了200次。
another machine 150 times and so forth.
另一台机器150次，依此类推。
So you need to add them up.
所以你需要把它们加起来。
This is a reduced phase.
这是一个简化的阶段。
So in the reduced phase,
在简化阶段中，
you are going to map each English word
你将要将每个英文单词进行映射。
on one of the machines, say for instance,
在其中一台机器上，比如说，
A on one machine, B on one machine,
一台机器上的A，一台机器上的B。
we were starting with A on one machine,
我们在一台机器上开始使用A。
we were starting with B on the other machines and so forth.
我们在其他机器上开始使用B，等等。
And then each of the mapper will send for all words,
然后每个映射器都会发送所有的单词。
the count for all words, which starts with A to machine one.
所有以A开头的单词到机器一的计数。
So machine one now gets all the accounts
所以机器一现在获得了所有的账户。
for the word starting with A.
对于以A开头的单词。
So they can sum up up and finally give you the result.
所以他们可以总结起来，最终给出结果。
The second machine, which receives all the accounts
第二台机器，负责接收所有的账目。
for all the words starting with B,
对于所有以B开头的单词，
is going also to count the total number of currencies
将会计算货币的总数。
after it receives the information,
在接收到信息之后，
if the partial counts from each of the mappers
如果来自每个mapper的部分计数
for the word Berkeley.
伯克利
Okay, this is a reduced phase.
好的，这是一个简化的阶段。
Make sense?
有意义吗？
The shuffle stage is exactly this, what I described.
洗牌阶段就是我所描述的那样。
This is what it is.
这就是它的样子。
Like each, for instance, if this is the second machines,
就像每个例子一样，比如说，如果这是第二台机器，
the second machine here is storing the count,
第二台机器在这里存储计数。
compute the final count for all the final counts
计算所有最终计数的最终计数。
for all the words starting with B,
对于所有以B开头的单词，
then it has to get the data from every mapper, right?
然后它必须从每个mapper获取数据，对吗？
So therefore the arrows, this is what they show communication.
所以箭头，它们表示的是沟通。
So every map will communicate with every other reduce
所以每个地图都会与其他每个减少通信
to send this partial information about the counts
发送这部分有关计数的信息。
for the words it found in its piles of documents.
对于它在文件堆中找到的单词。
Make sense?
有意义吗？
Okay.
Sure, I will translate your Chinese text into English and any non-Chinese text into Chinese. Please provide me with the content you would like to be translated.
Okay, great.
好的，太棒了。
Thank you.
谢谢你。
So at the same time,
所以同时，
and we are working on, at that time,
我们正在进行中，在那个时候，
we are working on Hadoop quite a bit, right?
我们对Hadoop的工作相当重视，对吗？
So we're improving the scheduling and things like that.
所以我们正在改进日程安排和类似的事情。
And in 2009, Lester was a postdoc with Michael Jordan
在2009年，Lester是迈克尔·乔丹的博士后。
on machine learning.
关于机器学习。
He came to us to people on the system
他来找我们处理系统问题。
because Netflix had this challenge.
因为Netflix面临了这个挑战。
So the challenge it was,
那么这就是挑战了，
they have this challenge for a competition
他们为比赛设立了这个挑战。
with $1 million prize for whoever can develop
谁能够开发出来的人将获得100万美元的奖金。
the best recommendation algorithm, right?
最好的推荐算法，对吗？
So it gives you a set of data.
所以它给你一组数据。
It was supposed to be anonymized.
这本应该是匿名的。
And in the end, it ended up not, you know,
最后，结果并不是那样的，你知道的。
people realizing that it was not as much anonymized
人们意识到它并不像匿名化那样多。
as they thought it is.
正如他们所认为的那样。
But anyway, at that stage, that was a problem.
但无论如何，在那个阶段，那是一个问题。
They give a set of data
他们提供了一组数据。
and these are the preference of the users.
这些是用户的偏好。
And the question is that,
而问题是，
can you predict what movies
你能预测哪些电影
this particular viewer is going to like?
这个特定的观众会喜欢什么？
Right?
对吗？
This is a competition, public competition.
这是一场比赛，公开比赛。
And he came to us because the team in the AMP Lab,
他来找我们是因为AMP实验室的团队，
you know, they wanted to compete, obviously.
你知道，他们显然想要竞争。
And we told them,
我们告诉了他们，
and obviously with this amount of,
而显然，有这么多的...
you need a lot of data because the more data you have,
你需要大量的数据，因为你拥有的数据越多，
the better models you are going to build, right?
你要建造更好的模型，对吗？
This is one example, right?
这是一个例子，对吗？
So for instance, if I want to,
那么举个例子，如果我想要的话，
the question is that given your age,
问题是，考虑到你的年龄，
can I predict what kind of movie you like?
你喜欢什么类型的电影，我能预测吗？
And basically, the way I predict it,
基本上，根据我的预测，
I am going to predict what is the rating
我将要预测评分是多少。
you would give to a particular movie.
你会给予一部特定电影。
So then I'm going to return the movies
那么我就要把电影还回去了。
for which I predict that you are going to
对于这一点，我预测你将会...
provide the highest rank, right?
提供最高级别，对吗？
So you have a few data points
所以你有一些数据点
and then I'm asking you here in the middle,
然后我在这里中间问你，
what is the prediction?
预测是什么？
What, you know, it's, that's a question.
什么，你知道，那是一个问题。
And the intuition is that the more data you are going to have
而直觉是你拥有的数据越多
the better prediction you can make, right?
你能做出更准确的预测，对吗？
So that's why you want ability to process
所以这就是你想要处理能力的原因
a huge amount of data.
大量的数据。
Make sense?
有意义吗？
So this is a problem.
这是一个问题。
So obviously we told them, okay, use Hadoop.
所以显然我们告诉他们，好的，使用Hadoop。
And they use Hadoop because it processes
他们使用Hadoop是因为它能够处理大数据。
a large amount of data, but Hadoop was extremely slow.
大量的数据，但是Hadoop非常慢。
So let me explain why.
所以让我解释一下为什么。
Machine learning and at that, we are talking then,
机器学习，而且我们在谈论的是，
we are talking about collaborative filtering algorithms.
我们正在讨论协同过滤算法。
This is before deep learning, before neural networks.
这是在深度学习之前，神经网络之前。
It's more classic machine learning.
这是更经典的机器学习。
And, but still each machine learning algorithms
而且，但是仍然每个机器学习算法
are typically algorithms, iterative algorithms,
通常是算法，迭代算法，
meaning that you start with some kind of predictions
意思是你从某种预测开始
and then you train the model, right?
然后你训练模型，对吗？
You are getting more and more data
你正在获取越来越多的数据
and they are going to hopefully improve the prediction,
他们希望能够改进预测。
predict better and better.
预测越来越准确。
Right?
对吗？
So now each iteration, if you want to implement with Hadoop,
那么现在每次迭代，如果你想要使用Hadoop来实现，
is going to be a map reduced job, one job.
将是一个MapReduce作业，一个任务。
One Hadoop job.
一个Hadoop作业。
And for each job, you need to read the data
并且对于每个工作，你需要阅读数据。
from the storage and you need to write the data
从存储中读取数据，然后你需要将数据写入。
on the storage.
在存储上。
So each iteration needs to read and write a lot of data
所以每次迭代都需要读写大量的数据
from the storage, from the disk.
从存储器中，从磁盘中。
Can you remember that reading and writing
你能记得阅读和写作吗？
is the disk is slow, right?
磁盘很慢，对吗？
So now if you have a few thousands of iterations,
那么现在如果你有几千次迭代，
this will take forever.
这将花费很长时间。
So that's kind of what's the motivation, one motivation.
这就是某种动机，一个动机。
And at the same time, so this is again,
so this is an example of machine learning application,
but there are many other people,
because once you have data, what you are going to do is,
you want to do some forecast, some prediction,
some optimizations.
You need to process the data.
And in many cases, this means machine learning
or iterative computation.
The other one is that once you have the data,
the other application trend is once you have the data,
you want to start to query the data, right?
You don't want to just run a job,
run up which takes a few hours to produce the results.
So you also want to provide more R-Hope,
like SQL kind of queries you want to ask
and to get answered very quickly.
Okay, so this is what was happening back then, right?
At the same time, we are starting to look around
and we are working with Facebook, Microsoft, Yahoo
at that time, with a big company at that time.
And we are starting to look at their workloads.
And to our surprise, it turns out that despite that,
they had huge amount of data, many working set.
Remember what is a working set?
The working set is how much space would you need
in say in memory so that your application works well.
That means your application will not access a lot of data
which is not in the working set, right?
So looking here, and this is what I remember,
this is the data since back then.
And this basically shows,
basically you have here three columns, four columns.
The last three columns are for different workloads
from these companies, Facebook, Microsoft, and Yahoo.
The first column is a memory of those machines.
So this again, 2010 around, nine, 10 and so forth.
So 32 gigabytes RAM for a server, it was a lot of RAM.
And the numbers represent how many,
what percentage of these jobs can fill their fully,
can fully fit their data in memory.
So it basically says that for instance, if your memory,
if the server memory is 32 gigabytes,
then 96% of the jobs from Facebook workload
can fit their data in memory,
82% from Microsoft and 97, 5% from Yahoo.
And for 64 gigabytes, 97, 98, and 99.5 respectively,
and so forth, right?
So that's kind of the idea.
So what was the solution?
And this is where Spark comes in.
This was a new parallel execution engine
for big data processing.
It was general, provides efficient support
for multiple workloads.
And it was, because it has a powerful API,
it reduces the code you need to write
for the same application, right?
Because each API was doing more.
The original API was in Scala, right?
It's a functional language.
But you also have API in Java and later in Python.
But the one thing what Spark did,
and was very good at was performance,
at least compared with Hadoop.
So it was, for some jobs,
it was 100 times faster than Hadoop,
MR against MapReduce.
Because it was aggressively exploiting the memory.
And for most workloads, like we just seen,
the data was fully fitting in memory.
Again, it was general.
There is a Spark core.
And on top of that, you have a bunch of libraries,
like to provide SQL interface,
provide streaming functionality,
machine learning, graph processing,
and the Spark R provides support for the R language.
Easy to write code.
This is the word count.
This is the application I mentioned to you.
On the left-hand side is how the size of the code
to write that application using Hadoop MapReduce APIs.
And this is for Spark.
So for 50 lines of code to three lines of code.
Okay?
Okay.
So the main key abstraction of the original Spark
was what we call resilient distributed datasets.
So this is a set of data,
which is partitioned across machines.
And it was stored on RAM or on disk.
And resilient because it was resilient to failures.
We'll learn more about that soon.
There are two kinds of operation,
transformation of the data and actions.
The action, the difference is a big difference
is that transformation can be filtered on data,
selecting just a few lines, a few rows,
selecting all lines in a text,
which contains one Berkeley, for instance.
The actions are the one which produce an output,
a visible output.
Like for instance, I want to get the count for Berkeley.
Right?
How many occurrences of Berkeley are in all these documents.
This is Spark.
It's again, I'm going to show you a very similar figure,
like I showed you in the case of PADU.
So you have these RDDs.
And then now instead of only two stages,
map and reduce can have many number of stages.
Map and reduce are only particular form of stages,
but you can have much more general any stages.
We are going to be calling these stages or steps.
And then you have this kind of stage after stage
and between stages, you can reshuffle the data
and create new these RDDs.
Now all tasks in the same stage implement the same operation
like for instance, map or reduce.
And typically they are single-strated
and they have deterministic execution,
meaning that if you execute,
if you re-execute the same task on the same data,
you get the same results.
And this will be important for fault tolerance
that you are going to see next.
But I think that you already can start seeing
these advantages, right?
And by the way, the resilient data assets are also immutable.
Immutable means that once you created them,
you don't change.
If you want to change them, you create a copy of them
and you change the copy.
And the shuffle kind of plays a role of implicit barrier,
meaning that one stage cannot finish
before the previous stage finished,
because the current stage depends on the data
being produced by the previous stage.
So therefore by definition, you cannot finish, right?
Yeah, so it's again, these are examples
I mentioned earlier on about transformations,
map, filter, group by or actions, count and stuff like that.
So now you see, probably you can guess
why now Spark is much better
for our application on machine learning.
Because now each iteration is one or more stages in Spark
of a Spark job.
And if you go from one iteration to another,
you are going to pass the data through RAM, right?
Directly through memory.
You don't need to hit the disk, okay?
So here you are, each iteration,
except for the first one, process the data from the RAM,
output the data from the memory,
output the data from the RAM, output the data into the RAM
for the next iteration.
So it's going to be so much faster
than reading and writing the data
from the disk between the iterations.
So it's again, this is a question about
why do we need to shuffle?
Yes.
So there are two questions here.
Wouldn't the data need to be sent over the network
in the shuffle stage?
Absolutely.
But it's actually, the network is faster than the disk.
That's number one.
And the number two is again,
you don't need to send them and depend on what is stage.
What happens between the stages,
you don't need to send all the data across the network.
Again, to answer again the question,
why does data needs to be shuffled between each step?
It's again, it's like in our example about counting,
word count, in the first stage,
you devise the documents and each machine
counts of occurrences of Berkeley in sets of documents.
So now each machine has a partial count
of Berkeley occurrences.
To get the total count, you need to aggregate those.
So each machine need to send to another machine
is partial count.
Okay.
So that's why you need to communicate.
And now you have every machine in the first phase,
which has a partial count of Berkeley,
is the first stage,
sends is partial count to the machine in the second stage.
And now imagine that you do this for every word.
So you have to have all to all communication.
Simon, great question.
How do you guarantee the Internet
that RDDs in the RAM stay durable
since the RAM is not as persistent as this?
Great question.
We'll answer very quickly soon.
Okay.
So now you may ask what happens, you know,
so basically Lester or is his group D...
team use Spark to compete and their team is the assemblers.
Okay. So, and as you can see, they tied for the passport,
but they were second because they submitted 20 minutes late.
So therefore they didn't win. This is a team which won $1 million.
So it was just 20 minutes. Maybe, you know, if it had started working on Spark 20 minutes earlier.
Okay. But that's the story. Now let me give you an example, another example of mining with Spark,
and then I'm going to address a question about the fault tolerance. So here is log mining.
You load error messages from a log into memories and you interactively search for various patterns.
So Spark has a driver which runs the code, you feed in the code, and workers.
The driver will send some function to the workers to execute the restep, misstage.
So basically this is a Scala code.
Don't worry if you don't know Scala, I think this instruction will be self-explanatory.
So basically you read the lines from the text file.
And this you are creating the RDD. This will be the RDD.
These lines are going to be a big set and then it's going to be partitioned across machines,
across the workers. Then you are going to filter each line which contains, which starts with error.
And this will create another data set. Again, it represents all lines which starts with error.
It's the second transform RDD.
And now I want to read the messages, so I'm going to split by tab,
because error sends the next of the messages separated by tab.
So I'm going to split between the error and the message. These are messages.
And I'm going to cache the messages.
And then I want to count, for instance, all the messages, error messages, that contain MySQL.
So basically how many error messages I have containing MySQL.
And this is the action. Remember, you have transformation and actions. Filter, map, cache, and transformation.
The code starts to, this Spark has what is called lazy evaluation.
Only when you trigger an action, you start to execute the code.
And the cool thing about this is that when you start to execute the code, you see all these lines you need to execute,
then you can optimize. You can do data placement, compute placement, so you can have higher data localities,
so you reduce the amount of data transfers over the network and things like that.
It's like a SQL query. A SQL query, you present the entire SQL query to the optimizer,
and the optimizer sees the entire SQL query and can do smart things about optimizing.
If I give you one instruction at a time, it's not much you can do to optimize.
But anyway, so all this code is run by the driver.
So let's see what happens. So let's say the original data is in this HDFS distributed file system.
So these are different blocks from this file I am reading, and they are across the different workers.
So the driver sends the tasks to the worker. The task is to read from the first line, for instance,
to read from the blocks from HDFS, this partition. They're doing the transformation,
and then eventually you are going to cache it and send the results back.
The results back are these kind of partial counters, because each of these workers is going to count the number of
occurrences of MySQL across this data. So to get the total count, you need to sum them up.
So these results represent these partial counts which are sent to the driver.
OK, and now you send the second. Now I'm doing the same thing, but I want for PHP errors.
Now the key point here is that now with PHP errors, when you count the PHP errors,
you don't need to go all the way to read from the original file, do the filter, do the map.
Now you are going to read the cache message.
And if you do that, obviously the first time is follower, because you need again to read from the disk,
do the map, do the filter, do the map. You were taking in these examples,
60 gigabytes, 20 EC2 machines at that time, 20 seconds for the first to get the number of the count of MySQL errors.
The second time when it's already in the cache, it's only half a second.
So that's the power.
The second, you have language support for Python, Scala and Java. I mentioned to you,
it's far more expressive APIs and you see map and reducer only towards the APIs.
Even back then it has around 100 APIs.
And let's see, we have another question.
Now in Hadoop, you can maybe aggregate.
In Hadoop you have only two stages.
You need to have map and reducer. You have only two tasks, two functions. That's the only thing you can do.
You have two special tasks. Here you have much more general, like you said, filter, maps, count, things like that.
OK, so now we have this great question about what do you do about recovery, fault tolerance. This is a distributed system.
We know the machine fails. We learn about that. We want to make it more fault tolerant.
So how do we do about that? Let's see.
Let me before going there, let me answer this other question, Ashif's question.
For this log mining example, R is the main reason why Spark is faster because it's using RAM instead of disk totally.
And lazy evaluation allowing, yes, allowing for optimization.
Yes, in part of it. S3 transforms and multiple actions following it as opposed to map reduce on repeat.
Yeah, these are all good reasons. Yeah, these are all true. The lazy evaluation does allow the, and we now, Spark has an optimizer called Catalyst doing quite smart optimization.
Like a database optimizer.
You can link multiple options, actions and multiple transformations.
So you don't need different jobs for those.
And yes, the biggest reason actually is because the data between stages is stored in RAM instead of on the disk.
So now this is a question and this is what actually one of the main innovation of Ray is to make this data set reliable.
So how do we make reliability? How do we achieve reliability? One is replication.
We learn about that if you remember the rate.
But you need to drive the data over the network and the memory can be inefficient.
Inefficient use, right? Because now you still remember the memory is expensive.
You don't have as much memory as on the disk. And now to use the memory to store multiple replicas.
So the effective...
memory size will decrease by half or by once,
by three times, if you are going to, you know,
to have three replicas, it's not good.
You can do backup on persistent storage, right?
But still, if you do backup, right, it's slow.
I still mainly mean to go over the network.
So the Spark choice is what is called
lineage-based reconstruction.
So what Spark is doing, it tracks the sequence of operations.
It records the sequence of operations
that creates a partition of a particular RBB.
And if that partition misses,
it re-executes the sequence of operation,
which created that partition in the first place.
And this way it re-creates a partition.
And this is working because the inputs are immutable.
Once the inputs are used by a task,
they don't change after that.
So you can reuse later.
And the tasks are deterministic, right?
So here is an example.
So you have an RBD-A, you have some filter,
creates an RBB-B, then you have a join operations.
You have a shuffle here, then you create an RBD-C,
then you have aggregation after creating an RBD-D.
Here we have two machines, each like A1, A2, B1, B2,
C1, C2 corresponds to two different machines.
And now assume that before the aggregation get a chance
to read the input, C1, that machine fails, right?
So what does it do?
The driver from Spark side is going to notice that
and is going to just replay,
re-execute the task who created C1.
And find another node eventually to run the task for.
So it reconstructs C1 and now the aggregation function
will have both input C1 and input created.
Of course, now here, for instance, maybe B1 is also lost.
It's okay if B1 is lost or not B1.
B2 says, yeah, B1 is lost, it's okay.
You are going to go all the way to A1.
So in the worst case, you go to A1 to all the data,
which is input data which is stored on the disk,
which is persistent with Spark.
But in general, you don't need to go all the way.
So that's the key.
Make sense?
Yeah.
So this is an iterative algorithms
like our machine learning algorithms.
The first iteration basically,
one to three iteration on the Y axis
is how long the iteration takes.
So here, the first iteration takes longer
because you need to read the data from the disk.
And then you are going, then each iteration takes much less.
And at some point you have a failure,
but the only things what happens when you have a failure,
the next iteration will take a little bit longer
because you need to reconstruct the loss state.
That's all, but otherwise it's transparent.
So now I'm going to end with Spark.
Like I mentioned, right now,
Spark is a de facto standard for distributed,
for data processing.
Very successful.
Databricks is a successful company.
So it was pretty much a success scenario here.
Yes, I said that here, sorry.
What I said here, not B1 is back to persistent storage.
I said A1 is back to persistent storage.
The inputs are read from a persistent storage,
which is resilient.
So in the worst case,
you can go all the way back to the input
to reconstruct the lost outputs.
But yes, I assume that A1 and A2 are stored,
the inputs are stored reliably.
Okay.
Announcements, congrats for taking the last midterm.
- Thank you.
- Project three due on,
well, project three is due next Wednesday,
but Sunday there is a party in Wozniak lounge.
You can get help there.
So if you are around,
you can, you know, it should be a fun and very useful.
Four hours you can spend.
Discussion will be office hours,
like you'll be seen probably,
and the office hours will continue into that of that week.
And the homework six is due tomorrow.
Okay, now let's tweak the gears and talk a little about Ray.
So Ray is a system, and I'll give you the history as well.
We also build AfterSpark.
So the trends, and I'm going to go quickly
with we went through these trends earlier on
when we started the class.
AI demands are exploding.
I show you the plot.
This is a plot from OpenAI,
which is the computation requirements
to train the state of the art machine learning models.
And it was growing 35 times every 18 miles
between 2012 and 2019.
And the growth continue after that.
This is 2020 data point for GPT-3 from OpenAI.
It's not only for kind of esoteric workloads,
like playing games or things like that.
It's also for image processing
or natural language processing.
So really very useful applications.
The other thing is a more slow-as-an-d, right, as you know.
It used to have, it used that, you know,
like 20, 30 years ago, every one year and a half,
the performance of the processors doubled.
No longer true.
Now we're just growing by a few percent every year.
So then there is a huge gap between the more slow
and actually, you know, the more slow is no longer,
it's even worse because the more slow has ended,
like we just mentioned.
So it's a huge gap between the demands
of this kind of machine learning application
and capabilities of a single processors.
And this is also true,
even if you are looking at GPUs and DPOs,
of course the gap is a little bit smaller,
but it's a log scale.
Why coordinate it's a log scale?
It's a logarithmic scale.
So all these kind of differences means
that the gap increases exponentially.
So huge gap growing by the way, okay?
So this means that really you cannot,
there is no other way to run this kind of workloads
other than distributing these workloads.
So Spark was more about data, scalable data processing.
This is Ray is more about scalable compute processing,
compute, scalable compute.
This is an example recommendation service
you have here, basically here,
when you are going to open your application on your phone,
you get some recommendation about maybe new products to buy
or services download.
This is from the largest one,
largest one of the largest FinTech companies in the world.
And the application, when you look,
it looks at the high level, it has three stages.
You get the data, you do some featurization,
you try to extract what are the things from the data
which are important, like the user IDs or things like that.
Then you use that data to train the model,
the recommendation, improve the recommendation
and then to serve the model.
So this means that the next users
or you when you are coming again
or you are running on the application,
you are going to now to be served these recommendations
based on a model you just trained.
[ Silence ]
So now one question is about how fast you can update this model, right?
Because presumably if you are going to update with the most recent data,
the model is going to perform better.
Right? I mean, think about if I am going to use a model to recommend whatever
services from last year, probably not going to be that accurate.
Because in the meantime, there are a lot of other products, a lot of other services which are introduced.
That recommendation will not even, the system will not even know about it.
And certainly will not know how my preferences have been evolved.
But now the question obviously, okay, it's obvious that if I train a model today, it's going to do much
better than the one which I trained last year, but what about the one last week, right?
Or yesterday, yesterday's model. So the question is about how much it matters. So
when this company started, they started with this updating the model every one day.
And they wanted to reduce to one hour and they use a state-of-the-art solution at that time.
And they get pretty good results. Click-through rate is one of the main metrics
for this application. And basically it tells you what is the ratio
between the times you click on the offering which was shown to you
over the number of times that offering was shown to you, right? So if an offering was shown to you
100 times and you click five times, then the click-through rate is 5%. So they got them
increasing of this click-through rate by 5% which was massive. And then they want to get lower,
but they couldn't get lower because there's a solution at that time.
So the main point here is that their solution and even today many of the solutions that,
remember each of these stage needs to be distributed. And we have good systems to
distribute each of these stages, so we saw workload. Data ingestion and virtualization,
you can use Spark or something else. For training, you can use TensorFlow serving,
TensorFlow distributed. PyTorch lightning may be horrible. For serving, you can use another system.
But now in order to build all this end-to-end application, you need to stitch together these
stages. And this is hard. Development is hard because each of these stages is different.
Then deployment is hard because now you need to deploy different distributed systems.
And the management is hard because, of course, you need to manage different distributed systems,
different APIs, and things like that. And also it's slow, and that's why they couldn't do it faster
because now this is going to sound-- now you can recognize this pattern.
To move that data between two different systems, how do you move the data between two different
systems? Well, the way you move the data between two different systems is to write in a distributed
storage system and to read from the distributed storage system. So that's, again, was slow.
And of course, this was a very simple application, machine learning application.
In general, it's much more complicated. You don't need only to do training. You also need to
tune the models. And if you are thinking about something like reinforcement learning,
you also need to do simulations and things like that. So it's very complicated.
So the summary here, today, we need to run all this workload distributed because they need to scale.
And for each of these workloads, we have good distributed systems,
right? For training, model serving, simulation, streaming.
But when you want to build an end-to-end applications,
we need to use many of these systems together. And this is very hard, OK?
It's hard to build, hard to deploy. And also, on top of that, it's also slow.
So this is what is Ray. Ray tries to solve this problem. So instead of having this
hodgepodge of libraries of systems, we need to stitch together.
With Ray, you have one system which is very general. It's a universal framework for distributed
computing. And to support these workloads, you build libraries on top of it.
So now, if you want to support the workload, you just run the library, but on top of the same system.
So a short story started in 2016 as a class project. Robert and Philip, they were taking
a class, and their projects I was teaching. And their project was to scale distributed
deep neural networks. Remember, Spark was created before deep neural networks took off.
And wanted reinforcement learning. And they struggled to use existing systems to do so.
And then, for the reason we mentioned, it was very hard. So we started to develop this
Ray system. In 2017, R-11 Ray Tune was released. This R-11 is a reinforcement learning library.
Ray Tune is a high parameter tuning library. And version 1.0 was released last year. And
AnyScale is a company behind Ray. Like Databricks is behind Spark.
Now, Ray Core-- this is the thing I'm talking about, this blue thing, this Ray Core-- has a very
minimalist API. The core API is this one. Ray needs to start with RayPut, RayGet, Ray.Wait, and
some decorators. The backend is C++. The frontend, so you know C++, this is how the backend of Ray
is built. The bindings, the APIs are in Python, the most popular one. But there are also Java
and some experimental API in C++. So this is what Ray in our shell is doing.
So Ray in our shell is very general for the following reasons. Think about-- this is a way
to think about it. What are the abstractions in most programming languages? Think about C++
or Python. Compute abstractions, there are functions and classes.
So Ray can take a function and can transparently run it remotely,
and can take a class and instantiate it as an object. It's going to instantiate it also remotely.
We call them actors. So remote function, we call them tasks, remote class instances,
instances we call them actors. And stateless means that they don't have internal state.
They get the input, process the input,
spit out the results, and they are done. While actors, it's like they have internal state.
You call the methods, and when you define a class, you have internal state,
and you can modify that state. That means stateful. It also has a future abstraction,
meaning that when I am going to run a task remotely, the call is going to return immediately.
I'm going to show you. And also, you have an in-memory distributed object stores.
And it's not a new language. It's an existing--
extension to existing language. So let me give you an example.
So let's say you have this Python code, you return R, and you do some computation.
And now you are just running on your laptop, and then you run F of A. You run this function once,
and it takes one second. You run twice. It takes another second. So basically,
the program takes two seconds. Okay?
So let's see how the same program is going to run in--
right. Let me see.
It's another.
Yeah, so I was talking here about classes.
It's a programming class.
It's like a class in C++ or class in Python.
I'll show you an example.
I was answering your question now.
So, okay, so this program takes two seconds.
Now let's see what happens in Ray.
So with Ray, if you want to run this function,
f remotely to on a different node,
you put, you add this decorator, Ray.remote.
And then when you call f, you add the suffix, f.remote,
and f, right?
And now the things to notice here,
and you'll see that these functions do not
return the result.
What they return, they return a pointer, a future,
this is called a future, a pointer to the result.
Okay?
And why is that useful?
Let's see.
So this was a driver, it's a worker.
So driver and workers are different machines.
So when you are going to execute the first f.remote on a,
now this function, instead of running locally,
is going to run remotely.
Okay?
This is a task.
But it returns immediately the result to this task.
It returns immediately the pointer to the result.
So this is returns even before the function is executed.
And also even before the function maybe even have been
scheduled on a different node.
But now because it returns immediately,
so basically it's non-blocking, if you remember,
about blocking and non-blocking.
I can execute immediately the next call.
So I'm going to create another task,
which takes the argument b.
And this task, it's returned immediately a future,
a pointer to this result.
So the beauty of it right now, I launch both f and f of a
and f of b simultaneously.
So they can run in parallel.
And now with RAID.get, this is a blocking call.
If I pass the RAID.get the futures,
RAID.get will wait until all the results are produced.
Right?
It's a blocking call.
So now f and fa and fab run in parallel
and returns the results.
And now my program from two seconds
to takes only one second.
Of course, here I am ignoring the message overhead
and other overheads.
But that's the key.
Another question.
The question about the class is which class
at Berkeley was the project?
It was 262a, I believe, in fall 2015.
And their project was to do distributed training
for deep neural networks.
I also asked them to do using Spark.
And actually, they developed an extension
of Spark called SparkNet to work with GPUs to do it.
But then that was a little bit painful because, again,
Spark is Java, JVM, and doesn't design
for this kind of workloads and started the work on RAID.
So what are the solutions before RAID
to do this sort of distributed compute?
Yes, they are mainly domain specific.
Another system which is a little more general,
but it's a pain to use and is not fault tolerant.
It's MPI, but it's for high performance.
Message passing interface is called.
It's from high performance computing faults.
There are also some actor frameworks.
But none of them, at least to my best of my knowledge,
is so general.
Good.
And now this is a Python class.
This is a class I misunderstood the question.
So this is a class.
Now it's a counter class.
And you can do the same thing with this one.
You basically do RAID remote.
And when you invoke, when you create the class,
and you invoke the method on a class,
you add the suffix dot remote.
And just like that, this class is
going to be instantiated as actor C.
And actors means that's active.
It's like a mini service.
We sit there and wait for the method
to be able to process the methods which
are invocated on it.
You can specify the number of-- also,
you can specify here the number of GPUs, the number of CPUs.
Which is very useful for when you do deep learning.
Because a lot of tasks, they may have a lot of needs.
OK, so right now, I said the last thing
is distribute object store.
So let's see how this is working.
So again, a simple function I call.
I have a function f and g.
And it's very simple.
f returns future, which is going to get
to be taken as an argument by g, which
is going to return the result.
So what is this distributed memory about?
Distributed object store.
So when you execute f dot remote,
like we've seen before, you are going
to run this task on a different node.
You get immediately back the future.
The results to f.
And again, it's not only x IDs return, not x value.
And now you call again node--
you call g, right?
And you get the future.
At some point, when f finishes, it's
going to create this object, result object.
And it's going to put in this object store.
So now this reference ID of x or future points to x.
And when that is ready, g is going
to wait for the argument to be ready.
So the system is going-- when it's going to be ready,
then it's going to copy x to node 3 where g is.
And now the argument of g is available.
So now g can execute.
So basically, this is what it is.
So the objects are passed by reference.
Now, if you don't have references, what this says,
imagine that you don't have reference.
If you don't have reference, f will create a result.
And the result has to be returned back to node 1.
And now the result is also passed now to g.
So g will be executed on node 3.
So g and including the results from f
are going to be copied to node 3.
So the results from f, it has to be copied to node 1
and then to node 3.
So needlessly, because node 1 doesn't do anything
with the result from node 2.
So that's kind of the point here.
It's like by reference.
When you pass-- even on a single machine,
when you pass arguments by reference,
one of the reasons you are going to pass
is to avoid expensive copies.
This is very similar, but for this to be said.
So what happens with this example
I showed you at the beginning?
Well, they used Ray to implement this pipeline.
So now everything is on different systems,
but there are different libraries.
And they are able to do the model update every five
minutes from one hour.
And they increase the clicks to rate by another 1%.
So Ray Architecture, I'm going to go
very, very quickly because I want two, three minutes
to finish and let some time for more questions.
There is a driver which runs the code, the workers.
And you have here actors on different nodes
to check the code, these tasks or the actors
which are created.
There is a distributed scheduler to decide
where to run the task and where to instantiate actors.
and you also keep the lineage about for the tasks which are created similar to Spark so
you can reconstruct the lost objects.
Okay, so today, Ray is this core and you have a lot of libraries on top of it. These are
native libraries which are built by us, so to speak, by the original team of Ray. RLE
Reinforcement Learning Library, high parameter tuning, Ray's service about serving, AGDs are
AGDs training, now it's called Ray train, but there are also a lot of third party libraries
which run on top of Ray.
Okay, let me see. Okay, let me just answer this question. Ashir Saab asks, what happens
when F relies on data, say on disk? If the data is on the disk, then it's going to read
it from the disk. No difference that if you run it on your machine.
By object store, does it just mean passing the references? Yes, the object store means
that you can pass the references. You can put the results and you can put the data in
the object stores and then you can pass the references to that object. It allows you to
pass the references. Without the object store, you cannot pass the references.
If it's on the disk of the original machine, what you are going to happen, well, you need
to be careful, right? If it's a disk on the original machine, the way you are going to
do it, actually, if you run it, obviously, if it's local disk, it's not going to work,
right? But typically in this system, you have a distributed storage system, which is accessible
from all machines. Even with Spark, you have a distributed file system, use HDFS, hard
to distribute file system, for instance, or you can use a blob store like S3. But all
these systems, they do assume there is a distributed storage system.
OK, so this is GitHub stars and this is comparing Ray and Spark with other popular systems like
Kafka, Qflow, Dask and so forth and Flink. You know, if you look here, Ray and Spark,
they are actually pretty much matching the slope and they are faster than the others.
There are a lot of contributors now, I think they are close to 600.
This is one system, this AND group built on top of Ray and built, really the entire
platform is called Fusion system. So build algorithms and application and services like
for marketing, advertisement, recommendation and things like that. And they deploy it actually,
double 11 and double 12. Double 11, as you may know, is the largest shopping day.
So this is Uber, they build a machine learning platform, they are building on top of
Ray's and new generation of machine learning platform. But this quote is great, right? It's
like you're saying exactly what I said to you, but someone else is telling you, saying that.
Say by leveraging Ray, we can combine the pre-processing, distributed training
and high parameter search always in a single job running a single training script,
right? So a single machine. And this is a fun example. You know, this is America's Cup.
America's Cup is the biggest selling competition, the most prestigious.
They sold it away from 1841 and it's every three or four years, I forgot.
It was a few years ago, it was in San Francisco, Oracle team who own one. This year,
the team who own was New Zealand team. And that New Zealand team, you know, the boat and the
team was trained with tools built by this Quantum Black, which is a McKinsey company.
And those tools and the boat were designed with the help of Aralib. So that was pretty cool.
Okay, so I'm stopping here and I'm going to help you to take any questions for the remaining time
of few minutes. Sorry, I couldn't leave more time, but really good luck with the end of the semester
and with all your classes, all your projects, and obviously happy holidays. And now I'm happy. Let
me take the questions. Thank you. How is this to migrate non-distributed, non-ML application to
Ray? I may be not understanding, but why not just use existing scaling solutions such as
containers plus Kubernetes plus traditional applications? That's a great question. Why
not containers and Kubernetes? Kubernetes and containers are orthogonal.
This Ray is intended for the programmer. You as a programmer, you build distributed applications
by just adding these Ray remotes in the code. And it's supposed ideally to be and
it's easy hopefully to run, to build this. Ray tries to reduce a gap between building
applications, writing Python code, for instance, and running on your machine to developing
the code and running on a cluster. Right? Tries to reduce this gap.
Kubernetes is helping you, it's resource orchestration. So it helps you to manage
a distributed applications. It doesn't help you to write a distributed applications.
If you have distributed applications, it helps you to manage it. Right?
Where to run different parts and things like that. In fact, Ray is running on top of Kubernetes.
And dockers are just, obviously, you know what it is, it's a package. Right?
Package all the dependencies. And also under the hood, Ray can use dockers. But that's the thing,
they are at a different level. So it's a different box and they are at some level complementary.
So Ray, it helps you to write, it's intended for the developers, for someone like you.
Kubernetes is for DevOps in general. It allows you to manage
the distributed applications, not to write it, to deploy it and manage it.
And dockers is fantastic for
packaging the dependencies. For Python, you also can use conda environments. Right?
Yeah. So hopefully I answered your question. Any other last minute questions?
We still have two, three minutes.
OK. If not, it's a good way to end.
So what are some systems related classes you recommend? I think you can see CS262A
when it's offered. The database is 286. You may also get in if you are offered like 294
with graduate special grad seminars, which are focusing on system, distributed systems. There
are a few of them. But these are the few classes to look at. By the way, I just want to still,
I think it's, I'm happy that and I have to apologize to you that almost all classes,
I went over time. I was not over time, but I was not able to finish my material.
So this is an exception and I'm glad to finish on this note. Thanks, everyone. And happy holidays
and all the best. I'm sure we'll see each other many more times in the future. Yes. Bye bye.