Okay.
So hello, everyone. Welcome to the fifth lecture of CS162. Today we are going to continue with
the exciting topic of files. And then we are going to start another topic, which is on
communications between processes, or IPC, interprocess communication techniques and
mechanisms. Okay. As always, if you have any questions, ask on the Q&A. And let's start.
So yesterday, not yesterday, two days ago, we discussed about the streams, which is a
highest level API for the file systems. Today we are going to talk a little bit of a lower
level file IO API, which is centered around file descriptors. And then we are going to
talk about the difference between the high level and low level APIs. Why do we have two
kinds of APIs? And about how a state is managed across processes, especially when you create
another process using fork. What happens with the file descriptors in the parent and the
child? And finally, two or three common pitfalls you may want to avoid in your projects or
homeworks. Or in general, when you are going to write a program using these APIs for file
systems.
So first, remember what we discussed last time, that one unique thing about Unix is
that it uses a file system of generic abstractions, not only to build all the files or on a storage
device like a disk drive, but also to deal with different devices like keyboard, terminals,
printer, and so forth. The second thing is that the abstraction which is provided, it's
byte-oriented. So byte-oriented means that you have what you get and you read and write
to the devices is basically a bunch of bytes. And you can think about like a sequence of
bytes and you can address it by the index of a particular byte. So you can identify
the byte in the sequence by its index in that sequence.
The other things we are going to learn more is that when you are going to do reads and
writes, these reads and writes are not going to come directly to your application. They
are going first to be buffered in the operating system. And as you'll see also with streams
of high-level API we talked last time, there is also a buffer in the application level.
And finally, the pattern is very simple. You open the file, a file, and you have to close
it at the end and in between you read and write from that particular file descriptor.
So this is a low-level file I/O API and it's quite similar from the high-level file I/O
API. One difference though, it's similar in the sense that it has an open, close, and
in between like your series and writes. It's different, it provides a slightly different
semantics and instead of F open, like for the high-level API, you have just open. And
when you open a file, you pass a file name, then a bunch of flags, which basically says
what is the access, what are the access rights, and whether you read, you have the rights
to read from the file, write from the file, or rewrite the file. And then there are also
bit vector with the permission bits, which are also who is going to have the rights to
access that file. And you can have users. The user is a user who actually runs a program,
which invokes this API to open the file. Then it's a group. This is the concept that user
belongs to a group. We learn more about that. And others means everyone else can access
this file. Then you have the close and you have create when you first time when you create
a file. Now the important thing here is that open returns you an integer. The integer is
also called file descriptor. The integers are greater than zero. If it's less than zero,
this means that it's error. And this integer, it used to identify the metadata associated
with a file you open, and this metadata is stored in the operating system. So that's
why you are going to have-- why do you have then an integer to identify this kind of this
metadata, which also, again, is file descriptor. And why do you have a file descriptor specified
as an integer than specifies as a pointer? Can anyone answer that question?
So it's again, open returns an integer. It's a file descriptor, which identifies the metadata
associated with that file in the kernel. So why not just have a pointer? Yes, less dangerous.
Can anyone save memory? Not exactly. Yes, that's correct. Having a pointer to kernel
will allow-- will mean that will allow the process, which is a user process, which opens
a file to have access to the kernel. Actually, but we know that processes have their own
address space, which is different from the kernel. So you cannot have a pointer to the
space of the kernel. So that's why you have an integer, because an integer is going--
when you are going to invoke one of these operation of the file systems, then you are
going to pass a file descriptor. And the file descriptor is going to be an index in a table
of the file descriptors, which are open at that given time. And that index will point
out to the metadata as sort of the state associated with this open file. So it's a portable way
to identify the file state or the metadata associated with the open file.
Now there are several default files, file names. It's like standard in, standard out,
standard file-- sorry, these are the standard file descriptors. OK? Standard in, it's when
you want to read from the keyboard, standard out when you are going to write to the keyboard.
And the other thing is, again, we have high level APIs, low level APIs. The high level
APIs or stream APIs, if you remember from last time, when you do an Fopen, you return
a file, a pointer. And that pointer, it's actually a pointer to data structures in the
user space. And that address in that data structure in the user space also contains
the file descriptors associated with that open. OK? We'll talk more about that.
And therefore, there is a way to go from the file descriptors and the pointer, which is
returned by an Fopen, Fopen system call. Right? So you remember, if you do Fopen, you get
this pointer, file pointer.
and you can from this file pointer return by an fopen,
you can get the associated file descriptor by using file now operation.
And the reverse is also true from
a file descriptor you got when you open a file, you can get the file pointer
to that file by specifying the file descriptors and the open type. And now you can use these file
descriptors to invoke on that file the high level APIs, the stream level APIs.
Okay. Low level APIs you have again read and write, but typically here when you have read and write,
you are going to read a buffer of a certain size. You read it into a buffer of a certain size,
or you write a buffer of a certain size, right? So read will read the elements from the files
up to the size of the buffer, which is max size. Obviously when you read,
you need to allocate space for the buffer. And the write, it's again similar. You provide the
pointer to a buffer, which of this of a given size, and that will result taking this buffer
and writing it to the device. In addition, the other way to look at, in addition,
you have this common, which is L-seq. So remember the abstraction is byte oriented.
If you look at the file, it's a sequence of bytes. Okay. So if you want now to read or to write in a
file at a particular position, you can use L-seq. And you basically are going to say, where do you
want to offset is from the current position. You want to add an offset to get to a particular,
to a new location, or you want to read from or to write to.
Okay. So let me answer some of the questions. Can we put the PowerPoint into presentation mode?
Thank you. Sorry about that. Yes, absolutely. That was an easy one.
What does mode mean on the open code? Does it apply to just the file descriptor? Can I share
a file descriptor with loser permission than the file in the FS? The mode is again referring
to who has the rights to access the open file using that file descriptor. And it does apply
to a file descriptor. It's per file descriptor. Can I share a file descriptor with loser permission
than the file in the... Well, you cannot because if the file,
the access rights are like the name implies are enforced when you access a file.
So if the file, for instance, when you create it, you can only read and again,
when you are going to create a file, you are going to basically say something like with these flags,
all people, for instance, in my group can access a file. So now if you share your file descriptor
to someone in the same group, they are going to have a right to access a file.
But if you share with someone from other, outside your group, that person cannot access a file
because the operating system is going to look who is going to access a file and is like,
"Oh, it's not the same group." Then it's going to procure the access.
Why is a buffer, this next question, is why is a buffer of type void?
It's basically saying this signifies the fact that in that buffer, you can have anything,
right? It's for generality. But if you put car, for instance, then it suggests that these are
kind of the characters probably in us format and things like that. Void is basically saying it can
be also binary representation. So it can be anything. It's a convention more than anything.
Yeah, so this is an example of a simple example. You open a listing file.
And you open an existing file and you write the output. And
here it's read only. And the user is writing access for the user. And then you read it,
you close, and you send the output to standard out file number.
So one question here is about how many bytes this program reads. So you can see when you read,
and this is an important instruction, you read into a buffer of which you allocated 1000 bytes.
Okay. So how many bytes does this program read? Should be easy. Any answers?
Okay. We have some answers here.
Size of buffer, we have some answers. 1000 or less, at most 1000. Okay. That's correct.
With just a little tiny clarification. You read if the size of the file is less than 1000
bytes, you read everything. You read the entire file. If the size of the file is greater than
1000 bytes, you read the first 1000 bytes of the file. Okay. Like I mentioned, the design pattern,
it's open before user file. At the end, you close it. And in between, add read and write from the
file. Okay. With a low level IO API, you basically read and write a bunch of bytes. That's all.
And you can use L-seq to reposition inside a file.
So one important aspect I mentioned early on, you also need to think about the buffers.
When you read something from a file, that thing doesn't go, it's not read directly to
the operating system, to the application. It reads first, the information from a file,
the data from the file is first read and is buffered in the kernel.
The same is a write. When you write, you don't write directly to the device.
You write to a buffer into the kernel and the kernel writes after that to the device.
Okay. Now, can you think about why would you read and write to a buffer
from and to and from a buffer in the kernel rather directly from the device?
To check for malicious input, faster, the devices might not be directly ready. That's good. Yeah,
it's faster and the devices might not be directly ready. And think about this way, right? It's like,
it's also the fact that the devices, when they transfer data, they may have a natural
granularity at which they transfer the data. Okay. So for instance, when you read from the disk,
you read kind of granularities like blocks, a few kilobytes, right? So this is what you get
from a disk drive. You don't get one byte at a time, you get a block at a time. So even if you
ask for one character, you get a block. So you need to put that block somewhere. So you are going
this is how we are going to put in the buffer, the kernel buffer. Otherwise, it means you throw
it away. And then if you read the second character from that block, you need to bring it again.
The other thing is about another situation is that when I write, say, a buffer to the device,
the device may not be ready. Maybe another write is happening on the device. Or simply,
if you have a disk drive, you need to wait for the disk to rotate such that the head of the disk
to be above the region of the disk which is available, so you can write new data.
So in that particular case, instead of blocking the application, then to wait for that event,
then instead you are going to write to this kernel buffer and the kernel is going to take
care of the rest. The same is another. If I'm going to write at once a big chunk of data
and this is larger than what the network can send at once, larger than one packet,
then what will happen is that case that you are going to write all these kind of chunk of data
in the kernel. And then the kernel will take care to chop how much you want to send in smaller
packets and send packets in each packet at a time. So hopefully, this is enough to give you a sense
about why you need to buffer the data, why you need to buffer to have kernel buffers when you
didn't write. Then there is another operation. It's again, there are differences. While everything
is a file, there are different between devices like you mentioned last time. For instance,
from a terminal, you have terminal is only output, a printer is only output, the keyboard is only
input or the mouse is only input. Like for instance, and then also you may want to configure
the other parameters like a printer to configure the line speed or things like that. And what you
are going to do when you have these extra parameters to configure for which are particular
to a given device, then you have this IOCTL as a escape patch. So that allows you to deal with
these specialized particular parameters for different devices. The other one is to duplicate
the file descriptors. And to duplicate, you can open a file, you can get a file descriptors,
and you can, if you want to share that file descriptor to someone else,
maybe another thread in the same application, or maybe another process to operate on the same file,
then one way to do it is to create another file descriptors, which point to the same metadata,
to the same instance of the open file. We'll show examples of that. And the difference between
Doop and Doop is that with Doop 2, you can actually specify the file descriptors you want
to point to the same data structure of open file. With Doop, you get back the next lowest number
available in the file descriptor state, in the file descriptor of the file descriptor numbers.
The lowest available. Pype, it's about, it's like you'll see, it's a way to communicate
between two processes. You can think as a queue. And we are going to talk about
memory mapping files, file locking, and things like that. So now the question,
an obvious question here is that why do we have high level and low level APIs?
How do we have, why do we have streams and why you have file descriptors? Why do we have fopens?
And why do you have open? Right. And first of all, this is how they compare. So
here it's high level operation, which is on streams of bytes. And here it's operation,
which is on a buffer, right? And the files, the stream of APIs are preceded by f with f letter.
And obviously the other low level API, they don't have any of this prefix letter. So the middle is
the same, right? Remember this is, are going to be converted to a system call because this operation
are implemented by the kernel, right? So what happens here, you are going to call, invoke the
functionality in the operating system by using this kind of trap, right? And special drop
instruction. And before you do that, you are going to fill in some registers with the data
for the operating systems, for the kernel to know which files you are referring, right?
And what operation you want to perform on that file. And for that operation, what are the
arguments? Okay. So this is what you put in registers here, just before the trap instruction.
And then after you do the stop, after you execute the trap instructions, the kernel will take over,
will look at the register to initialize, is figuring out the file descriptors you are
referring to, figure out what is the operation you want to perform, figure out the arguments
of the operation, which are in other registers, perform the operation, and then returns back
to the users once the operation is performed. And if the return values, it's also make sure
that puts a return value in a particular register, like EX, right? The only difference is that,
as you see, the fread, and so this is middle part, it's identical. The only difference is that
with fread, with the high level APIs, you do a lot of some work before or after you
invoke the operating system, you invoke the system call as a user level, you do some more work.
And that has to do is the fact that, as you will see, with the high level APIs,
we have a buffer, not only the kernel, but also we have a buffer in the user level. Okay.
And this is exactly to illustrate that point, right? So if there are two examples here,
we try to achieve mostly the same thing, but they have different behavior. Okay. So in the first
case, you are going to, in both cases, with printf. printf is, at the end of the day,
it's a write operation to the terminal, right? You give a string and you print to the terminal,
right? So this is a high level API, right? And here we have the same kind of operation,
but using the low level API, right? To standard out to the output, to the terminal. Okay.
In both cases, what we do, we write a string, the first part of a string, begin offline,
then we sleep for 10 seconds, and then we write the second part of the string, and, you know,
which is ends with carry return, slash n. Okay. So what is the difference between the two? What
is the difference in behavior? The difference in behavior is that the first one, it prints
everything at once. So although you print beginning offline, you don't see anything at the terminal
before you also print the end of the string, which finishes, which ends with carry return,
right? In the second case, again, you're spraying the same thing. You are going to see beginning
offline, printed, then sleep 10, after 10 seconds, you are going to see the end. Okay.
So what happened under the hood and why do you have this behavior? Well, you have the behavior
because in the second case, you have a buffer and that buffer, it is a kernel. So you send to
the kernel, this kind of the first 18 bits beginning offline. And then the kernel is
going to print on the terminal. The second one, and then when you send the last 16 bits,
the kernel, beautifully, will print the end, right, of the sentence. Okay.
In contrast with the stream level interface, you have another buffer,
which is in the application level. So you don't directly write in the kernel buffer,
you write in the application buffer. And the application buffer is written to the kernel
buffer only when you have in this particular case, when you encounter the slash n character, right?
the end of line character. So in this case, you're reprinting beginning of line. This is going into
application buffer. Nothing happens. After 10 seconds, you add end of line in the application
buffer. And then only now, because you have this kind of line fit, so the end of line,
it's the entire application buffer is written in the kernel buffer, and the kernel will
write on the terminal as the entire sentence. Does it make sense?
Okay. So that's what happens. Now, what is the file into the file data structure? Again,
this pointer to a file data structure is returned by the high-level APIs by FO1.
So you have the file descriptors. This is the one which is returned by the low-level API,
which is this integer. And you have the buffer, like I mentioned, this is the buffer we are
talking about you have at the application level. And you also have a lock in case there are multiple
threads using the file concurrently, then you want to lock and you have only one thread accessing the
file at the same time. Remember about the concurrency discussion we had last lecture.
Of course, there are many other things in the file data structures, but this is,
we are not going to discuss those now. So now when you call a F write or any kind of high-level
API, a stream API, what happens to the data you provide is the following. You get to write in the
files buffer, this application buffer. This is exactly what I mentioned to you. And then
this application buffer or file buffer is written in the kernel buffer in a flash. You have a special
instruction to flash it. In the particular case of the printf, it is flashed when you get the line fit.
Okay, so that's basically what it is. So what does this mean? So when you write code, you make the
weakest possible assumption about how data is flushed from the file buffer. You need to make
that assumption. And why is that important? So your application, in your application, you write,
you use F write. And from your point of view, you may think that all this data already made it onto
the disk. But that's not the case. If you have a failure just after an F write, you are not
guaranteed that the data you wrote is making on the disk. In order to do that, you need to make
sure that it's flashed, the data is flashed to the kernel. And actually, and then the kernel is going
to make sure that it's going to be written on the disk. Okay, so you need to be careful about that.
Okay, and this is a reminder for you, how to use a high-level Stream API
in this particular case to write and read. And this is another important aspect
to allow you to understand the subtel bits associated with this high-level interface.
So in this code, what you have, I have a character C, and I am going to write it
in a file, file.txt. Then I'm going to open the file again, and this is another descriptor here,
F2. And I'm going to read from that file. And I'm going to write it in a file. So I'm going to
write it in a file. Okay, so you write a character in the file, and you are going to read the
character from the same file using different files, pointers. Okay, so what happens in this case?
Right, well, there happen, you know, yeah, sorry, you initialize X here to C, and what you write in
the file is B, not C. Sorry, okay, so then the question, what you are going to get? Okay, well,
you are going to get an monotonistic behavior. When you read here, you can have C or you can have B.
So why is that? Can someone say it?
Okay, there are two questions here. So please try to,
yes, that's very good. So to answer this question, there is an answer to my question.
And the answer to my question is that why you can get a monotonistic behavior is because you
don't know when the file's buffer is flashed to disk, right? So what can happen, remember,
when you are going to write B, that B is written in the file buffer, which is associated with F1.
Now you open F2, and now this is going to create another file buffer, which is associated with F2.
So when you read it, if this B didn't make it from the file buffer of F1 to the kernel buffer
and to the disk, you are not going to read it. Okay? If it made it, then you are going to read B.
Okay? So basically here, you write B in a file buffer,
and you are going to read from a different file buffer.
Okay? So if B didn't make it from this file buffer of F1 to the disk, so then it's available when you
are going to open the second, the file, using another file descriptor, you are not going to see B.
So now there are two other questions on this.
On the second point, does it mean that if a file buffer is full, then the buffer is flashed?
Yes. If the file buffer is full, it is flashed. There are other policies you have no control of,
when the file buffer can be flashed periodically, even before it's full,
after you have data stay too much, maybe in the file buffer. Or you can do it explicitly.
There is a flash command, like I mentioned. Why do we have to make the weakest possible assumptions
on when file is flashed? It's again, because you do not know, unless you flash it explicitly,
you do not know when the file buffer is flashed to the kernel.
Okay? And let me see, there are some other questions. Is there a way to atomic,
to do atomic file operations? There is no easy way to do atomic file, atomic operation,
you can do that. And we are going to learn how to do it. But one of the original designs of,
design decision in Unix was to not support transaction semantics when you update the files.
That's why you have database. But you will say you can do it, but you don't have an operation to do
it. On a F write, if the buffer is flashed, does the input data go into the newly cleaned buffer,
or does it get written to file as part of the flash? If it's flashed, the flash is,
you can sync as an atomic operation, you flash it and then you write in the buffer.
Okay. Does file buffer have a default size or does it depend on the size of the file being opened?
That's a great question. I think I'll check, but as far as I know, you have a default size,
which you may be able to configure. But from what I remember, it's a default size.
Okay. Let's move on. We have still a lot of things to cover. So writing the correct code is like I
mentioned to you, is basically you have to flash the data. So now this is the explicit command I
mentioned to you, FF flush. So now you are going to flash to force the file buffer being flushed.
Okay. With the low level API, we don't have this problem because you are going to write in the
buffer or in the kernel and both descriptors, when I'm going to open the descriptor for the same file,
they are going to see the same kernel buffer.
So when you have one write complete, it's going to be visible to subsequent reads.
Now, the key question, which I expected to get, and I didn't, but it's a very natural question.
And the key question, why do you have a buffer as a user level? So why do you have the file buffer
when you already have a kernel buffer? The answer is one of the answers.
Is one of the answers
is performance.
If you write the character at the time,
if you use a stream API,
you are going to write the character in the file buffer.
This is a user level.
It's just a function call.
If you want to write one character using
the low level API,
that's a system call.
It requires context switching to the kernel.
And a system call,
because the context switching to the kernel
is far more expensive than a local function call,
which is 25 times more expensive.
So let me put it this way and you should try it.
If you write, say, 1,000 characters,
or say 10,000 characters,
if you write it character by character
using the high level API,
will be much faster than writing character by character
using the low level API.
Because in the first case,
you are going to have a context switching
only when the file buffer is flashed.
While in the second case,
you have context switching every time you write a character.
Sorry.
So the other thing is that you can implement
more sophisticated things at the user level.
So the second point here about fgetc,
what I told you about writing,
it also apply about writing, about reading, right?
Because when you read, you can have the entire block,
which will be transferring the file buffers.
And then when you do the fgetc on the next character,
then to get the next character,
you are going to be a local call
because the block is already in the file buffer.
If the block is only on the kernel buffer,
then every time you get the next characters
with a low level API,
it's going to be a context switch.
Okay.
So hopefully this is clarify a few things.
Our system call operation,
which is a low level API,
so in general, less capable.
You can have more functionality like formatting, right?
There's a high level.
And why it's important is
because you want the kernel to be as small as possible,
right?
You want, because the kernel is always resilient
in the memory.
And it's not only that, if you have less code,
it's less chances to introduce bugs, right?
Okay.
So that's why this is another reason
for it to have stream API and high level API
and low level system API
is because you can add more functionality
in the file level API
without making the kernel more complex.
Okay.
So process state for file descriptors.
Let's move quickly.
So here we are doing,
so let's see how the state is maintained in the kernel.
Right?
Recall on a successful call to open,
you have a file descriptor,
which you return to the user
and an open file description.
So the state associated with that file descriptor
is created in the kernel, right?
When the feature system calls,
the kernel looks to the open file description
using the file descriptor, right?
Okay.
So here's a very simple code here.
So this is a code we have two buffers,
buffer one and buffer two.
And we are using the system calls,
the low level calls to read from foo.txt.
And we want to read the first 100 bytes in buffer one,
the second 100 bytes in buffer two.
Right?
Okay.
So the important point here,
it's about the current location in the file
is kept by in this file description, right?
So that's why if you have consecutive calls of read,
you are going first to read the first 100 bytes,
the next read the next 100 bytes.
Okay.
So here is just a slide showing about
what is the file description, how it looks like.
And this is LOV,
is a position of the current position in the file.
The structure of inode, we are going to talk later.
It's where the file is located on the disk.
And there are a lot of other information
is not important for our discussion now,
but it's important for our discussion.
It's about, let's see how things are maintained
in the memory.
Okay.
So you have here a process and here we have the kernel,
right?
Above the dash line, you have the process,
the below the dash line, it's a kernel, right?
In the process, you have the address space,
and then you have a thread and you have the thread registers.
Remember the thread is a unit of execution
and every process has at least one thread, right?
So suppose that we execute open food or text
and the result is three.
So the file descriptor, which is returned by open is three.
So you have open file descriptions,
you have the file which is opened and the position.
Start with zero, right?
And this is where the file descriptor points, okay?
That's it.
This is what I want,
the open file description is what I mentioned earlier.
It's like the state of the file
and the metadata associated with the file.
Okay.
So what is now, so now initially you may ask why it's three?
Well, because the standard in, standard out
and standard error are zero, one and two are already taken.
Remember this has the default file descriptors.
Next, suppose that you execute read
from this file descriptors,
the first 100 bytes in this buffer, right?
Remember the previous code, right?
Okay, so you read that.
And once you read it, the position notice
is the open file description is set, updated to 100, okay?
Now, suppose that you execute close three,
and you execute close three, the file descriptor is gone
as well as a file description, okay?
So it's simply enough, right?
But now instead of closing,
after you read the first 100 bytes, let's say we fork.
Now, if you fork, remember,
the entire state and the entire code of the pattern process
is going to be copied in the child process.
So this is going also to have what is going to happen
is the file descriptors are going to be copied.
So now you have to the same open file descriptions,
you have two pointers, three,
both of them are three obviously,
because that's how you index in this open file description.
One from pattern process and one from the child process,
right?
And you are shared the same state,
the shared state in the open file description, right?
So now if you read from buffer 100,
or in from process one, using the file descriptor three,
now the position is advanced to 200.
Now, if you read the process three, the child process,
it is from the same file descriptor, what happens?
The position is updated to 300,
because again, both the child and the pattern
operate on the same open file description, okay?
And now when you close three in the parent,
the file that is closed from the perspective of process one,
but the open file description is not destroyed
because it's still referred by the client,
by the child process.
So only when the child process is going to close,
it's on the file descriptor three,
only then open file description associated
with the file descriptor three is going to go away, okay?
So the cool thing about this,
now you can have remembered one of the potential,
and we are going to learn more about that.
One of the problems when you have processes on one hand,
you have strong isolation because each of them
commits with own other space.
But you still want to communicate in some cases
between the two processes.
Well, this is one way to communicate, right?
You open a file and you fork a child,
then both the child and the parent
have access to the same file system.
So you can use file system to exchange the data, okay?
It's again, this is the same repeating it
that everything or every device,
it's abstraction, it's a file like disks, networking,
and you'll see some other communication primitives.
And this means that they are going to have a high level,
the same high level API, open, read, write, close.
The same thing happen when...
you have for the first default script or 0, 1, and 2, obviously they are going to be shared between
the child and the parent. So if the child and the parent are going to write, they are going to see
interleaved there, whatever they are writing on the terminal, for instance. So it's again,
if one processor closes standard in, this means that it can no longer get an input from the
keyboard, then the processor child is the only one which can receive inputs from the keyboard.
And that's very important because you may want in your program only the child process to get
the input from the keyboard, not both the parent and the child.
So many of the things we talk about and we are going to talk in the remaining of the lecture
are going to be helpful for you in home or too when you have to write a shell.
And the fork will be very useful for networking because you can handle each connection in a
different process. Now there is another way you can share the access to the same file,
and that is using dupe. So what dupe is meaning, you duplicate the file descriptors and the file
descriptor is going to point to the same open file description. So here you have this, like think
about an alias. So if you created and you open a file, you go to the file descriptor 3. Now if you
call dupe on 3, you're going to get a 4. Now both file descriptors 3 and 4 point out to the same
open file description. There is another instruction which is dupe 2, which has a second argument.
And the second argument is actually saying what is a file descriptor you want
to point out to the same open file description, like the first argument in the call in this
case file descriptor 3. So this is useful if, for instance, you have multiple processes of the same
application, you run all of them and you have a constant there, basically say each of them,
they should operate on the file descriptor 162. One process creates a file, opens the files,
then it calls dupe and then everyone can operate on that file descriptor.
Okay, we are running a little bit late.
So here are some, based on what we discussed, there are some challenges or some things you
need to be careful with when you work with the file systems. And this is particularly very
important for your homework and projects. First, don't fork in a process that already has multiple
threads. Okay. Why? Because the threads are not forked, right? You forked the state of the process,
that is copied. And when you copy a process, when you duplicate all the state from the parent
to the child, the threads are not copied because they are execution, they are ephemeral, right?
So in the second, in the child, you have only one process, one thread. Okay. All the other
threads will disappear. Okay. So many remember. Okay. Only the threads that call the fork exist
in the new process. It's, this is, and remember when you call exec, you don't care about it,
whether there are multiple threads because exec is basically replacing the entire space
of the process who called exec with a program which is going to be executed
in that process. Okay.
Be very mindful when you mix a low level and high level file I/Os.
Okay. It's again, the main reason, remember high level I/O has a file pointer and a file buffer.
They have the file buffer. Right? So in this case, for instance, when here is a subtle problem.
In this case, you have, you open a file as a, with a high level API, you get file pointer F,
and then you get from that file pointer, you get the file descriptor. And now you call Fread
on that file and read on that file. And the file, a file read, you get, you say,
I want to read only the first 10 bytes. And then with a read, which is a low level API,
I want to read the next 10 bytes. This is what you'd expect when you look at this code, I say,
okay, Fread will read the file, the first 10 bytes, read will read the next 10 bytes.
Okay. The problem, maybe that might not happen because Fread, yes, it returns to the applications
of first 10 bytes, but from the kernel, you may get an entire block, which is going to be stored
in the file buffer. So you may get the first 4,000 bytes from the file,
which means that in the kernel, in the associated file description,
the position now will be 4,000. So when you call the read, this will go directly to the kernel
and it will read from the current position. So it may read the bytes from 4,000 to 4,000.
Okay. Before continuing, actually, let me answer this question.
On an Fread, if the buffer is flushed, does the input data go into the newly cleaned buffer or
does it get written to the file? Yeah, I answered this question. First you do the flush, then you
are going to write the new data. Okay. Announcements. The group DA assignments have been released.
If you don't know yet, check on Piazza. Project Zero is due today. Good luck with your submission.
And Project One will be released on Friday. Other than that, many of you are still online. Please
start planning on how your group will collaborate in the most effective way.
Virtual coffee hours, regular brainstorming meeting. And again, try to communicate as much as possible.
Okay. Now we switch the gears and we are going to talk about how two processes can communicate
to each other. Okay. One way to communicate is using the networking. This is a very, very general
way to communicate between two processes, because you can do that even when processes
run on different machines. And this can happen when you have your web browser and
if your browser, this is how your browser communicate with the web browser, with the web server.
Okay. And under the hood, use TCP/IP protocol. We are going to learn about it. For now,
it's just suffice to say and to take a look about the API. The API is very similar. When you want to
send data, you instantiate what is called a socket. This is in some sense, think about the
equivalent of the file descriptor and the file description with the socket. And you are going to
write to that socket, like you write for a file descriptor, but otherwise the API is the same.
Write to file descriptors, a buffer of certain length. And then on the receiving side, when you
want to get data, you are going to have a read, again, the same API read from the file descriptor.
This is the socket descriptor in a buffer of a certain size. Okay. Again, we are going to have
an entire lecture about TCP/IP. What is the other way to communicate between processes? Another way
to communicate between processes, like you'll see that are using pipes and using the shared memory.
But again, taking a step back, here we want fundamentally to punch a hole between the
processes. Because otherwise the process cannot communicate with each other. That's the entire
idea about processes, to be isolated from each other. Each of them has its own address space.
They cannot address data from each other, from each other's address space. Okay.
So here is one example. This is about shared memory. But before, let's again, think again,
and recall about how processes are protected.
from each other. You have two processes here on the left and the right hand side, right?
Program one runs in the first process, program two in the second process. And then you have
each process, it is some code, data segment, heap and stack. Now, both processes share
the same physical memory. Okay? So in the middle, you have the physical memory.
The physical memory is divided into regions. And what happens is the operating system or
the kernel map the code, the data and the heap from different processes in different regions.
Right? And these regions are disjointed. Okay? So that's why you cannot address the data from
another process. Right? Because in the physical memory, each process owns a disjointed space
of addresses. Okay? And the way you achieve that is through translation map. Again,
we are going to learn about that. That's where the magic happens. And making sure
that the processes do not step on each other toes. Okay?
So that's what we have. In spite of this, and despite this protection,
enforced by the kernel, we still want to communicate between processes. Right? Like we
mentioned. Okay? Okay. So how do we do that? And we already shown some examples with the sockets.
Another way, you already know, you can use a file system. Right? A file system can write to a file
data and another process, sorry, a process can write data to a file. And the process can read
from the same file, the data written by the first process using the read and write primitives.
Okay? Now, you can do that. However, this is quite expensive. Because the write to a file
is expensive. And reading from a file is slow. And also, in most of the cases,
you don't need a persistent store. It's an overkill. Okay? Like think about, you know,
if you want to go from your client to the web, to your web browser, you don't need to store
every request and every reply. Furthermore, this works only on the same machine. And
otherwise, you need a distributed file system if the processes are not located on the same machine.
So one solution is to have ability to have shared memory. And the operating system provides that
ability. You can actually create a memory, a process can create a memory, and say that memory
can be shared with other processes. Okay? So, and therefore, in this case, both processes, one and
two, they are going to point to the shares, the same share space is a physical memory, which means
that within this space, they can share data. Okay? So there is an API, there is a way by which you
can create shared memory, and share memory regions, and share that region between two different
processes. Okay? See, it's a question. What is the benefit to having memory of the individual
processes be de-joined? The benefit of having the memory of individual processes be de-joined
is to ensure protection. You do not want a malicious process to access the memory of
another process, or worse, to access the memory of the kernel. Hopefully I answered the question.
What about the other things? What about, you know, if we want to, is there anything the kernel
can provide us to facilitate the communication between two processes? Okay? So, by the way,
so the answer is yes, which I already alluded by providing this kind of socket mechanism,
like when I talk about TCP/IP, right? But fundamentally, it's again, the abstraction you want,
which is useful to provide is like a queue, right? And because we do not want at least four processes
which run on the same machine, we want kind of in-memory queue, right? Again, we don't want to
build something on top of the storage, file storage. We said it's too expensive, too slow.
Okay? So, and what is memory queue means is basically the semantic is that a process
just pushes the data to the queue, and the other is the producer and the consumer read from the queue,
right? And typically the queues, it's first in, first out. There are other kind of queues,
like last in, first out, but typically it's first in, first out, what we are going to talk about.
in this lecture. And one abstraction of such queue is a pipe, is a Unix pipe.
Okay? So the Unix pipe, you are going to have, you can open a pipe and you can, again, it's like
a file descriptor and you can use read and write. Okay? When you write, you write at the end
of the pipe. When you read, you read from the front of the pipe.
Okay? So that's exactly the queue semantics. Okay? Now,
this pipe and you have a buffer of a certain size, so it's not infinite. So if the pipe is full,
then the write blocks, you can no longer write to the pipe unless the consumer, a process,
reads from the pipe and makes room for new data to be written in the pipe. The same, if the pipe
is empty and you want to read from the pipe, you block until someone puts some data in the pipe.
Okay? And when you create a pipe, what you get, you get two file descriptors, like you
may imagine, one file descriptor to write to and one file descriptor to read from.
Right? So file, you have the first file descriptor is to read from, file des
zero and file descriptor one is the second file descriptor is to write to.
And it's implemented, like I mentioned, as a fixed size queue.
Okay? Right? So here is how you can use it. You create a file again, you create a pipe and
then you are going to write to the second file descriptor, you are going to read from the second
file, first file descriptors and make sure that when you close, you close both file descriptors.
Okay? So, pipe between two processes. Again, here you create a pipe, you get the first
file descriptor three and four pointing to read and write from that pipe. Now you do a fork,
the file descriptors are copied. And now you also have these file descriptors pointing to the same
instance of the pipe. Right? So if you want to write, to use this pipe to communicate between
the parent and the child, then you need also, and this is in one direction. So in this particular
case, I want the parent, say I want the parent to send data to the child. Right? So I create the pipe
which is not shown here. And then I fork. Remember, if the result of the fork is not zero,
this means that I am the parent. Okay? When I execute the code. Because the result from the
fork is going to be the PID, the process identifier of the child. So then I'm going to write the second
descriptor and I'm going to close the, this is the right descriptor, pipe FD of one, and then to
close the read descriptor. Why? Because again, in this example, I want only
the parent to send data to the child. The same for the child, right? I am going to read from the
first file descriptors and I don't want to write, so I'm going to close the write descriptor.
Okay, this is what happens. Close three and close four, right? So now the pattern I have is that
the parent process is going to send data to the child process through a pipe.
Okay, of course, if you want to the other way around to get the child to communicate
to the parent, you can do the other way around by closing the other file descriptors. Okay.
When do you get end of file on a pipe? After the last write descriptor is closed to a pipe,
if you continue to read, so if you continue to read from a pipe and there is no write descriptor
open for that pipe, you get end of file. Okay. If the read descriptor is closed and you try to
write to a file, you get a sick pipe, which is an interrupt, right? And you can ignore it,
but then the write will fail. Okay. So here, if you close the write descriptor,
and you continue to read from that pipe, you are going to get end of file.
Okay. Now, once you have established a communication, you need a protocol.
And the protocol need about how we are going to communicate between two parties. Okay.
And the protocol will have a syntax, right? Which will specify how you need to specify
the protocol, the format, the message order, or things like that. How do you send and receive
data? And then the semantics is that what communication means, right?
When you call, make a call to send some data, what actually happens? Right? Okay. Is the data
always guaranteed to get to the destination or maybe lost? Right? Is the data guaranteed to be
get the either destination or the receiver guaranteed to get the data in the same order
in which you're sent out? Right? It's also more complicated because if you communicate over network,
different computers make, you have different data formats. So you need to convert between different
formats. Okay. This is also part of the protocol. Okay. And this is things about like, you know,
like you talk to write telephone, right? You pick up, you dial the number, then you talk with your
friend. And then at the end, you end up, right? You hang up, right? But the protocol here,
part of the protocol is, you know, it's about what are the part of the protocols, right? Of course,
like pick up the phone and open it. It's like an open. Closing the phone is, you know,
closing the call. It's like a close. And then the brick, you mean in the middle, you have read and
writes. But what I mean by the protocol here, like for instance, the dial is how you are going
to contact the other part. That's part of the protocol. It's an address. It's a number, right?
You need to figure out. Then it's this kind of, you know, part of the protocol, typically you start
with a hello, right? I mean, I'm here, right? Also, it's used implicitly to recognize because
the other party, if it's your friend, is going to recognize your voice. Or maybe recognize because
of the number you see, he or he sees. And then before hanging up, you don't just hang up, you say
bye, right? You also, that's an implicit protocol here. When you pause, you expect for the other
person to talk, right? So things like that. Okay. Okay. So the web server, this is a very simple
example. You also have a high level protocol. It's the application protocol, which you have a request
and the reply, right? That's how you are going, you know, you see the results from the websites,
from your Facebook account, or when you do a query on Google, this is exactly how things are working.
You send a request and you get a reply, which is going to be rendered and shown to you in our
browser. Okay. So I'm going to stop here. And in the meantime, I'm going to take the last question.
So we are done. So for people who have questions, I'm going to spend a few more minutes to answer
this question. Okay. So this is a question I actually missed recently. What happens if the
new argument in the DAPT2 function is already being used as another file descriptor? Great
question. Yes. It's the old one. It's overwritten by the Duktu. Okay.
Why is file IO slow? The file IO is slow is because every operation like read and write
leads to context switching to the kernel. It has to be implemented by the, is going to be executed
by the kernel. So if you are going to write one character at a time, the low-level file IO,
what will cause that for every character, you have a context switch from the user process
to the kernel for the kernel to write that character. You write 1000 characters,
one by one, then you have 1000 context switches. And the context switch is expensive.
You need to save the state of the process, load the state of the operating system, and then go
back. Like I shown you from this data is to have 20 function call, it's at least to an order of
magnitude faster than a system call to the operating system. So we can pipe between any two
processes. Yes. You can pipe between any two processes on the same machine. It's a question
from Miles. Can a process ever make a malicious system call? Can you assume that relying on the
kernel for IPC secure? Yes, you can assume because the operating system is again, you cannot, the way
you ask the operating system to do something is to put some data, the system call or the file
descriptor, the argument for the system calls in registers. And the operating system is going to
read the context of the registers. This is how it's going to execute the system call. And when
reading is going to validate the data you put in the registers. So you assume that the validation
is done correctly. And therefore by using a system call, you cannot cause any harm to the operating
system. Okay. Let me see whether there are any other questions on the chat. It's a last one.
It looked like the physical memory of a single process was the joint. I was wondering why not
keep the physical memory of each process continuous? That's an excellent question,
Jasper. So the reason is you cannot have contiguous because you do not know as the
beginning of the process of a program, how much memory you need. Why? A simple reason is, for
instance, a stack. You don't know how much stack will grow. Another reason is heap. When you
allocate dynamically memory, the program allocate dynamically memory, how much, how do you know how
much the program is going to allocate? So because of this reason and because the address space,
the virtual address space, everything that the user sees can be much larger than the physical
address space. Then there is no way, well, you cannot allocate a contiguous region.
Thank you. Thanks everyone. Good luck with the first project and I'll see you next week.