Hello, everyone. Welcome to the seven lectures. So today we are going to continue our discussion
about concurrency. And this will happen also over the next couple of lectures. And as well
as we are going to discuss about lock implementation, which is one of the main primitives helping
us always controlling concurrency.
So remember about, again, this picture-- excuse me-- in which basically we are going to have
a program. And here what we are trying to do is how this program is going to yield the
access to the CPU to another program. If you remember, this was the old examples in which--
one of the first examples in which you have two instructions. The first one trying to
print-- to compute pi and print pi, and then the second instruction trying to print the
class list, if I remember correctly. And the point there is that if you try to print pi,
which means also you need to compute all the digits, you'll never end because pi has an
infinite number of decimals.
So then the solution was that while you are computing pi, you are going to give from time
to time access to the CPU to another process to continue. Otherwise, the CPU will be only
hauled by this compute pi program.
Now yield, it's a system call. And the system call is going to result in a trap to the kernel.
And the kernel will then take over, and it will suspend the current program thread and
run a new one. And this is a pseudocode, very simple. So this kind of you see, run your
thread. This is what is a function run by the kernel, which basically picks a new thread
and switch from the current thread, which is in blue here, to the new thread. And it's
doing some housekeeping and some cleanup when it's going to do this-- update some counters
at the time, for instance, a thread run and things like that.
Now the question, obviously, the key is like there are two things we want to understand
is like how to pick a new thread and how you are going to switch from the current thread
to the new thread. And if you remember, obviously, in order to do that, we need to save the state
of the current thread and then to initialize the registers of the processor, the PC counter,
with the values, with the state of the new thread, and then execute that new thread.
And one of these-- one important part of the state of a thread, if you remember, is a stack.
And let's look a little bit more into more details about these four simple examples in
which you are going to have two functions, a and b. a equals b, and b is that execute
a loop. And within that loop, you yield every time you execute the loop.
And suppose that we have two threads, s and b, and running this program. So both of them
run this program. So thread s is called function a here. And this is on the stack. You remember
that the stack grows from the high addresses to the low addresses. And on the stack, you
are going to have the return values, the return address after you execute the function, as
well as when you call a function, you are going to put on the stack the arguments for
that function. Of course, here, there are no arguments. But that happens in general.
So you have a first, which you call, you put on the stack, then b. And this is the one
which executes the while loop, and then is going to execute and run yield. And then,
again, yield is going to call the operating system. And the operating system, it's going
to execute the run new thread, and switch to the new thread. And when you switch, it's
going to run the other thread, c. We said that we have two threads in the system. And
the new thread will basically execute the same thing. And therefore, it's going to execute
a and b and b whenever it's going to execute the while, it's going to yield. So again,
you go to the operating system. And then you ping pong between the two threads. This is
what will happen.
So now, it's again, one thing we need to do when you are going to switch from the current
thread to the new thread, is we need to save the state of the current thread. So what that
means is that registers, you see, R0 to R7, these are registers. And then sb is a stack
pointer. And CPU is a return pointer. So the pointer of the next instruction should be
executed when I am going to resume the execution of this thread.
And now, the next thing we need to now to take care of the new thread. So we are going
to update the register of the processor, the stack pointers, and PC with the new-- sorry,
with the corresponding state of the new thread we want to run. And by the way, you see where
this state is stored? What is stored? It's in TCP, right? It's thread control block.
So I hope this kind of makes sense and it's pretty simple. Now, obviously, you need to
be careful when you implement that. And by the way, if you have any questions, let me
know. I'll be happy to answer as always.
So of course, you need to be very careful. I mean, for instance, if you forget to save
or store a particular register, say, and register32, then what will happen? Well, sometimes, you
have some things that happen. But what happens, it will very much depend about whether the
value in that register is going to be used by the program. If it's not going to be used,
nothing will happen. But if it's going to be used, you are going to see probably random--
is it random results or random failures?
And then, of course, you say, well, why wouldn't you then store-- you test carefully the entire
code. Well, the testing the entire code, especially testing it exhaustively, is very difficult
because there are many, many, many combinations. Why is there many combinations? There are
many combinations because a thread can be interrupted anywhere. So if you have a thread
which is-- you have 1,000 instructions, it can be interrupted after each of these instructions.
And you have another thread which has another 1,000 instructions. Now you have combination
about where you are going to interrupt the first thread, and you are going to resume
the second thread like 1 million. And there are many, many stories about errors, in some
cases which are found after a long time. Like for instance, in this case, it was a very
early kernel, Topaz. You can see based on the size. So it was obviously very well tested.
But it was one thing what happened is that it was one instruction, one correctly saving
the state of a thread depending of whether the kernel size was less than 1 megabyte.
And initially, it was less than 1 megabyte. But over time, like with any software, the
size increased. And people, developers forgot about this limitation. And when it did happen
and the size increased over 1 megabyte, then they started to get spurious errors. And this
kind of like we will discuss, these kind of errors are also very hard to debug because
they are not deterministic. So obviously again, like when you design, be very, very careful.
Design for simplicity, simple code, it's easier to check.
complex code and all, you know.
So now one of the question is about,
we are switching between two threads.
We are also switching, you know, it's context switching.
And you also have, we also refer as context switching,
when we are switching between two processes, okay?
Now, so, and this again, we discussed this in the past,
but let me repeat because it's a very important aspect.
When you do process switching,
you know, switch between two processes,
which means at the end of the day,
because you are switching between two threads
in a different processes,
that switch is much more expensive, okay?
And the reason that switch is much more expensive
is simple because the state associated
with the process is much larger, right?
You need, again, the process is also on another space, right?
It's also on the file descriptors, okay?
So fundamentally it's a lot of more things you need to do
when you switch a context versus a switching a thread, okay?
And these are the numbers, actually,
the context, the switching between processes
can take between, in this case for this numbers,
again, depends on the implementation,
depends on the hardware.
So take these numbers that are grain of salt,
they are only supposed to give you the relative sense
about the relative difference.
So when you switch between processes,
it can be like between three and four microseconds.
When you switch between two threads,
it's only 100 nanoseconds.
So in this particular case,
you can see that your overhead is 30, 40 times higher
when you switch between processes
as compared when you switch just between two threads, okay?
And the frequency of context switching here,
we are talking, is about 10 or 100 milliseconds.
Of course, you don't want to context switch all the time.
You want to context switch still fast enough,
but not as fast so that the amount of computation
is the same order of magnitude
of the amount of overhead it takes to switch, okay?
So we have a question here from Ashit.
Isn't it trivial to change the address space
because you just change the pointer
and for file receiver again,
don't you just change this process track to 0.2?
It's more than that.
You also need to have the buffers,
if you remember the, for instance, file stream IO.
And the other things you need to do is fundamentally,
you need to have the entire page table.
You need to take care of it
because the page table that is a translation
of the address, virtual addresses, the physical addresses,
this is what each process owns.
Yeah, and also when you switch the address space,
then you can, because you are going to have
probably some of the pages, which of the process,
which are going to be evicted from the memory
to make room for new processes.
And they are going to go to disk or whatever SSD.
So therefore you may also have to do some work
to get some pages in when you switch between the processes.
Even cheaper, you can actually use
without the operating system support,
you can use yield in the user level.
So the application actually is,
there are thread libraries, user level thread libraries.
These are libraries which provide you
like a thread interface,
but the operating system doesn't know anything about it.
Okay, and then what happens when you use a thread,
a user level thread, then when you call yield,
you call the library which is running the same process.
Again, it's not a system kernel.
And then that library is going to invoke,
you are going to just make a call,
a function call to another thread in the same process.
So this is very, very lightweight,
it's just a function call.
And this is some of the first systems
that have been implemented at the application level.
And in this case, all fundamentally,
all these user level threads are going to be
basically mapped on say one CPU.
Now, with a kernel, in general,
kernel also uses some threads, right?
And the number of, and these are kernel threads,
and in general, you map the user thread
on the kernel threads.
And the kernel thread typically uses a number,
the number of kernel threads is typically equal
with the number of CPUs or the number of cores, okay?
And again, you have, typically you have few tens of cores
on your CPU, but you can have then thousand
or tens of thousand of user level threads, okay?
And when the kernel has a concept of thread,
then what will happen, you are going to map
the user thread on top on kernel threads.
Okay, let's look, yeah, easy server overhead, okay,
on context, switch between processes purely
if you have to switch out the address space,
that's a big part of it, yes.
Again, there are also file descriptors and things like that,
but the address space is a big part of it, okay?
Okay, so in today's lecture, we are going to talk,
or in the first part of today's lecture,
we are going to talk about this one to one thread model.
And in the one to one thread model, actually,
in this particular case, we are going to have,
for one user thread, we are going to have assumed
there is a kernel thread.
So this means that for one user thread,
we are going to have a CPU to run on, okay?
So this is, again, it's another figure,
another representation for you to better understand
how things are working under the hood, okay?
So here is, again, you have two processes,
this rounded yellow boxes, and each process,
you have fewer threads.
Each thread has its own state,
and then they have some state they share with the process,
like memory and I/O state.
And then this is OS with green,
and you have a CPU scheduler,
which picks on which CPU the thread will run.
And initially, let's assume that we have one CPU, okay?
So now let's look at the switch overhead.
Now, the switch overhead, there are multiple cases here.
The switch overhead of two threads, again,
eventually what you run on the CPU, it's a thread, right?
So the switch overhead between two threads,
if they are on the same process, it's very low, right?
Because only you need to switch your CPUs,
you need to save and resume the thread state, right?
Which is small.
Now, if you need to go from one thread in one process
into a thread in a different process,
now you need also to switch the context of processes.
So then the switch overhead is high.
Now, why do you have threads and processes?
Well, because the processes,
while this context between processes is slow,
they provide something threads do not provide,
and that is protection, right?
So the protection between two threads
running in the same process is very low
is because they are sharing the same memory.
So one thread can read and write
from the memory of the data of another thread, okay?
While if the threads run on different processes,
that's not possible, okay?
Now, sharing overhead, as we know,
and we learned last past lectures,
threads and you may want to share data
because the applications are pretty complex
and they want to communicate with multiple threads,
they want to communicate with each other.
Now, if there are two threads that are in the same process,
it's very easy for them to communicate.
It's also low overhead.
Why?
Because they can't communicate through the shared memory,
the memory they share in the same process, right?
So you just read and write to the memory, super easy.
On the other hand, if these are two processes,
the threads are in two processes, then what do you know?
What you know is overhead is much higher
because how you can communicate between two processes.
Do you remember?
You can use pipe, you can use sockets,
but all, or you can read and write from a file.
But all of these operations...
are far more expensive than reading and writing from the memory.
So what about the parallelism? Well, in the case of parallelism here,
there is no parallelism because you have only one core. You can run only once at a time.
And here it's a more general example in which you have four cores. So you can have
four different kernel threads running at the same time. So now you have parallelism.
And now you need to-- the sharing overhead is a little bit even more complex.
Because if you have the same process, it's low. And different processes is high. But now there
are different processes-- it actually turns out that if you have simultaneous cores,
so they are running-- you can have processes-- OK, so this is more complicated. But you can
have kernel threads running on the same core. And we see next why, how you can have that.
Then the overhead of communication, of sharing, is lower. And this is what I meant.
It's a concept of multithreading or hyperthreading. Actually, it's hyperthreading,
right? Simultaneous multithreading or hyperthreading. This is what we are talking about.
So, so far, in everything I said, I said you can run one thread on one core. OK?
So-- but it turns out that in practice, you can run at the same time multiple--
one multiple thread in general only two threads on the same core.
Right? And this is called hyperthreading. OK? And almost all processors today provide it.
Right? It's actually when you look at Amazon, for those of you, they give-- they say vCPU,
virtual CPU. A virtual CPU is actually a hyperthread. It's not one core necessary.
So what is the idea? So here is a thing-- look at these figures. Do you see my pointer,
my pointer on the screen? Can someone answer if you see my pointer?
Yes, perfect. OK. So here is a time on the vertical. And here are-- if you remember from
61c, the processor have in the arithmetic logical unit and everything, there are different components.
Right? You need to fetch the instruction. Then you need to-- and then you may use different
components like adds or from the arithmetic processor units, logical unit, to perform that
operation. OK? So each of these line, it's an instruction. OK? And vertical, each of the
vertical is one component in the process, in that core. So this color, what is color, this means
that this instruction, right, where is a color is that particular instruction uses that component.
Right? So for instance, from this example, in the first instruction using the first and the
third component. OK? But not using-- it doesn't use the second one. And then for the next,
actually, I was not accurate. Sorry. Each of these lines represent a cycle, instruction cycle.
Right? Many instructions, they run in a single cycle, some of them. But some of them do not.
OK? So it's instruction cycle. So in this cycle, these two, first and the third component are used.
In the next cycle, there is no component being used. And maybe this is because it is tall.
You know, the data is not available, and the instruction cannot proceed or something like that,
and so forth. So the main point here is that not all components are used at the same time.
OK? So then what you can do then is basically to run two streams of instructions
from two different threads. And if a stream doesn't use all the components at the same time,
then the other stream can use them. So that's kind of the intuition. One stream of instructions
doesn't use all the components of the core at all times. So you can take advantage of that
to support the second stream to better use these other components. So that's why you can run two
streams of instruction on virtually the same hardware. So just better utilizing the particular
core. That's what it is. OK? So it basically provides you the illusion that now you can run
multiple-- like you have multiple cores. Of course, the speedup is nonlinear because sometimes you
have conflicts, right? You have the two stream instruction at the given cycle. They want to use
the same components. But this is super useful technique. And it's used by almost every processor.
OK? So now, a file-- remember, a process can relinquish access to the CPU in multiple ways.
Right? One is voluntarily yield. Another one is I/O. Right? So when it's making an I/O,
when it's calling an I/O operation, like in this case, it is from a file.
OK. Then it's another question. Let me try to answer the question.
Are some components not used even if we do pipelining? Yes. Because pipelining means
there are multiple-- you can also have stalls and dependencies in the pipelines, across instruction
in the pipelines. So the answer is yes. Actually, all the processors already do pipeline.
And pipelining, yeah, it helps you to-- each instruction, new instruction to every lock cycle,
you start a new instruction. Yeah. But pipelining helps with utilization, but it doesn't solve it
entirely. Great question. OK. Let's go back. So here, again, we are going to show the stack.
And you have copy file called read. And when call read, read it again. It's a system call.
You call the kernel, kernel read. And what is the kernel doing? Well, it's going to start the read
operation. But before you get the answer to the read operation, the CPU is free. So therefore,
it's going to switch to suspend you, you being the copy file program, and give the CPU to another
thread. The same thing happens. And the same-- it is similar when you have signals and joins or
operations on a node. OK? And finally, one question we also asked in the past,
what happens if there is no-- the program doesn't voluntarily yield the CPU, there is no IO,
and general never waits. Right? So in that case, you still need to multiply the CPU
between different threads. And the way you do it using external events, external events like
interrupts, in particular, timer interrupts. Right? So you program the timer to give an interrupt
every 100 milliseconds. When you get this interrupt, the kernel is going to switch from
the current thread to a different thread. OK? So that's what it is.
So let's see another question. It seems like hyperthreading benefits concurrency. What about
parallelism? It definitely also benefits parallelism because you are going to have now,
if you have-- you are going to double the number of threads you are going to run at the same time.
OK? So this is a picture which basically shows you here the CPU. And then it shows you how you
are going to interface with different devices. Right? And again, the way you interface actually
the operating system with the--
the different devices is through these interrupts.
When an event which requires the attention of the kernel happens,
that device has to go in to generate this kind of event,
which is interrupt.
So and you can also have software interrupts.
Like SQL is a software interrupt.
It doesn't come from a device.
It comes from another process or it comes from the kernel.
And this is a timer, which is a special kind of interrupt
like we discussed.
And for interrupt, you can mask interrupts and we'll see.
And the interrupts, they have some priority.
And the higher priority interrupts, for instance,
can interrupt the lower priority interrupt.
But this is what you have.
You have basically, this is actually
this hardware, this kind of different lines,
hardware lines in an interrupt list.
And then the kernel will always look at the highest interrupt
and will treat the highest interrupt.
And if a higher interrupt than the one you are currently
treating occurs, then you are going
to switch to treat the higher interrupt.
And then you come back to finish treating the lower interrupt.
The software interrupts can be cleared by softwares.
And CPU can disable all interrupts with some internal
flags.
So I don't want to be interrupted because what
I'm doing is very important.
And there is also some non-maskable interrupts,
which you don't have anything to do.
Like for instance, reset.
It's a non-maskable interrupt.
Right?
So you have to just kill and reset
everything on the computer and restart.
That's one example.
So now, this is an example about how the network interrupt
occurs.
So say you execute these instructions.
And now you get an external interrupt
because a packet arrives.
So the kernel needs to copy the data into the kernel buffer.
So what do you do?
So first of all, you flush the pipeline,
the pipeline of the processor from the state
of the current instructions.
You save the program counter.
So to know when you are going to resume,
where you are going to come back,
what is the program counter, you have
to come back to, and disable all the interrupts.
Because now you need to do some work
and you don't want to be interrupted.
And basically, what you do here, you raise the priority
and you mask all the lower level interrupts
because I don't want to be interrupted
by lower level interrupts when you do that.
And you save the registers for this current thread.
And you dispatch to the handler of the interrupt
because you need to treat the interrupt.
In this particular case, read the data from the network.
Transfer the network packets from Harvard
to the kernel buffers.
Once you are done with that, you restore the registers.
And you clear current interrupt because you are done with it.
You disable all interrupts again to do your work.
You don't want to be interrupted by the kernel.
And you restore the priority.
You then clear the masks, the mask which are clear here.
The mask which you set here to not be interrupted,
now you clear it.
Basically saying, now I can be interrupted by anything.
And now I return from the interrupt.
So that's it.
So it's very simple.
And it's again, an interrupt, though,
to think about it's a hardware-involved context
switch, right?
There is no separate stack.
There is no decision of what to run next.
It's very clear.
I am going to run the handler to treat the interrupt.
And I am going to go back to the program I just interrupted.
OK?
So like we mentioned, one way to interrupt a program now
and give control to another program
is simply by using the timer interrupt, right?
As the timer interrupt, when the interrupt happens,
timer interrupt happens, you are going to--
kernel is going to execute this timer interrupt handle.
And the timer interrupt handle or team,
it's doing some housekeeping.
It's again, update some counters and things like that.
And then run new thread.
Right?
And you know that your new threads, what it's doing,
saves the state of the current thread.
OK?
Initialize the state into registers of the new thread
and start the new thread.
And in between, you need to decide which new thread
you are going to run.
OK?
So this is what we are talking about, right?
You initialize the registers field of the PCB,
your stack pointer with PC return address,
and also in this case, is a functions and the function
arguments.
You pointer to this function and the pointer
to the function to the list of function arguments, which
you put into registers, in this case, a0 and a1.
OK?
And then what about the stack?
So again, the stack is in the memory.
The memory is sold by the processor.
You don't need to do anything other than pointing
to the correct location of the stack, which
is a stack pointer.
OK?
So again, let's see what happens here.
In this particular case, this is the old one,
in which basically we went through this one.
So here, use yield, which is voluntarily relinquish the CPU
to be used by another thread.
And when this happened, you set up the new thread.
You are going to initialize the pointers and registers
of the processors with the values from the PCB
from the thread control block.
Right?
OK?
So and then you are going to run the new thread.
So this thread root, this is a root
for all the thread routines.
So when you have to switch it from one thread
to another thread, this is what you are going to execute.
OK?
And the thread root, what it takes,
it takes this address to the function of the thread
you want to execute.
Right?
Remember, a thread is just a function
you have to execute at the end of the day.
Right?
So you need to provide to this thread root
the function of the new thread to execute and the arguments.
Right?
Again, you do some housekeeping.
You do the user mode switch.
So now you are in the kernel.
So you need to go to the user mode,
because the application runs in the user mode,
and then simply invoke the function, the thread function,
with the arguments.
And you are done.
OK?
And like I mentioned, the housekeeping
includes things like recording the start time of the thread,
how long the thread is run on the CPU,
and other statistics, number of context switchings,
and things like that.
Obviously, the stack will grow and shrink
with execution of a thread.
And when you return from this function,
this is you call the thread field.
What is a thread finish?
Okay.
Is you need to execute another thread, right?
So you need to find and wake up a sleeping thread.
So now you're really going to concurrence.
And it's again,
once you have multiple threads running at the same time
and have the kernel non-deterministically decide
at what point to interrupt a thread,
to suspend it and resume another thread.
Now you need to be very careful.
And you need to be careful
because these threads can share the same data.
If there is no shared state, it's fine, no problems.
But if the state is shared, then you can run it,
we can run into problems.
So here, or you want to be very careful on the design
and you should try to what we call correctness by design,
meaning that you need to convince yourself.
Maybe in some case you can even prove
that the design of, despite the fact
that multiple concurrent threads can access the same data.
The design is correct, nothing bad happened, right?
Recall again, different executions
and the execution we really care about is B and C
where threads are interleaved
or they are running at the same time.
So they can touch the data at the same time.
And this is extremely, extremely important, right?
And here is an example.
To drive home the point
that handling the concurrency is important.
So think about ATM, you have an ATM
and you have obviously with ATM,
you want to either deposit or withdraw money, right?
And the state assumes that it's in a database.
So you need to be very careful here, okay?
So you're supposed to implement this functionality, right?
So then you have,
you need to process fundamentally,
you have to have an infinite loop
where you wait for requests from the users
and then you process the requests, right?
As a request is basically specifying operation,
withdrawal or deposit,
account ID and the amount, right?
This is you receive the request
and then you process the request, right?
The process request is simple, right?
If it's a deposit, you deposit the amount in account ID,
if it's withdrawal,
you get the, you subtract the amount from the deposit.
Okay?
And the deposit functions, what is a deposit function?
How does it look like?
You get account ID, you get the account,
the account data structure from the account ID
and you add the amount to the balance
and then you store the account,
read account, modify the account, store the account, okay?
So if you do this thing, right?
At one given time, you are only to serve a single request.
Okay?
So what is the problem with that?
The problem is can be very slow.
And why slow?
Because, not because of computation,
adding numbers is super fast, right?
What is slow is to access a database,
to get the account information from the database
and to store the account information to the database.
That is what is slow.
And during this time, the program is blocked,
just waiting for the database operation to complete.
And the opportunity here is to overlap communication
with a, you know, database IO, with a computation.
So while you wait for an account to be read
from the database or written to the database,
you can very well serve other users.
And by the way, the users actually in this case,
they can operate on different accounts,
on their own accounts.
So how do you do that?
So one way to do it, and this is typical,
is called event-driven.
And with the event-driven approach,
you basically split the requests, right?
In multiple pieces.
One piece, for instance, you start on request
is basically, for instance, this piece can only start the IO.
It can only make the request to the database.
And then you switch, you end up.
And you wait for an event to come from the database,
basically saying, and from, you know,
then the operating system saying,
this request has been set, has been, you know, completed.
Now there is a data.
Now you can go to continue the request to read the data.
Okay?
So this is kind of the things you're doing, right?
By hand, you are going to basically say that
in the programming by hand,
I think that you're interested in the program.
You make sure that there is no part of the program
that's wait for, is blocked for the IO request to complete.
Okay?
But now this way to write programs is pretty,
it's pretty hard.
What if you miss the blocking IO?
Well, then you are going to block.
The performer is going to suffer, right?
What if you, what do you have your,
your function has hundreds of IOs.
Well, you need to split it into hundreds of pieces.
Very hard to reason and debug.
Okay. However, this is super fast.
It's even faster than threads, right?
There is not even context switching between threads.
Okay. Super fast.
So this is used when you really, really need performance,
like graphical programming.
So now the obvious question is that,
and this is what we brought in this example,
then you may say, well, but what about threads?
We just said that threads can handle a concurrency.
It's a unit of concurrency.
Indeed. And using threads, you can do this much easier.
Right?
So let's see how this is done.
You basically, you run each of these operation
in different threads.
Right? You can do another thread.
Each operation can be another thread.
Of course you have a thread,
you can have a thread pool to make sure that you have,
you don't have a huge number of threads.
So the system is going to crash
like we learned in the last lecture.
But otherwise the only thing you need to do,
each operation is a different thread.
Because if you remember from what we learned,
when a thread is going to wait for an IO operation,
it's going to be suspended.
And the kernel will let another thread to run.
Okay?
The problems are here is that, okay,
now it's the two threads can access the same data.
And here is a very simple example.
Okay?
And, you know, we have maybe here two threads,
two threads which are depositing in the same account.
Right?
And look what happened here, right?
The thread one is reading the balance.
After that, the thread two reads the balance.
And then add the amount to the balance,
which is in R1,
and then save the balance.
But now I am going to resume to thread one.
And thread one, the first thing it's doing,
it's at its own amount with a balance,
and then store the balance.
So what did I do?
What is this code accomplishing?
What is not accomplishing?
What happens here?
What is the end behavior?
I have a balance, you know, thread one say,
I want to add to the balance $100,
thread two, I want to add to the balance $200.
$200.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So I should have added to the balance $300.
But if I execute the code, what happens?
Amount is lost.
Very good Simon.
So basically in our example,
only $100 are going to be added to the balance
and the 200 will be lost.
Okay.
And we have, there are many, many examples.
Like in this example, thread one, it's X,
say X one and thread B, Y is two.
This case is simple, right?
They are separate threads, separate data structure.
They don't interfere.
Everything is fine.
However, in this case,
they have operate on a common variable, Y.
What are the possible values of X here?
Why don't you take a little bit of time
and answer this question?
So if I run thread one and thread A and thread B,
the initial value of Y is 12.
What results I can get here?
Okay.
One answer, please.
More answers.
Okay.
Excellent.
Right?
So you need to take all, you know, Y is 12, right?
So remember, so in say thread A is running to completion.
Right?
Then what you get is 13, right?
Now say thread B runs before thread A.
What happens?
Well, Y is two, it operates to L.
Then you multiply by two, so Y is four.
And then here you are going to have five.
Right?
Or you can only run the first instruction of B
before you run A.
So again, you initialize Y with two over I 12 initial value,
and the result will be three.
Okay?
So you see, pretty complicated, but also fun
for to do these exercises.
Oops.
But this is even simple examples.
X is equal one and X equal two.
What is the result?
Non-deterministic, you get one or two.
And for fun, if the instruction to store data
is non-deterministic, you can even get something in between.
Right?
Sorry.
If the instruction to store the data in memory
is not atomic, I said, no, not deterministic, which is wrong.
It's non-atomic.
Right?
We learn more about atomic instructions.
So it's a mess.
Okay?
So to understand the concurrent program,
like in this past example you've seen,
we need to know what is the indivisible operation?
What is atomic operation?
An atomic operation, what is an atomic operation?
It's indivisible.
You can interrupt in the in between, in the middle.
Either run or doesn't run at all.
That's all.
Right?
You cannot just have observed the output
of running half of atomic operation.
Now, your output, it's observed output is either
as if the entire operation runs
or none of the operation does a run at all.
And this is a fundamental building block.
On most machines, load and stores are atomic.
Okay?
The wired examples in the previous slide
cannot happen in this case.
But many instructions,
and here we are talking about processor instructions,
are not atomic.
Double precisions have not atomic,
so you can interrupt in the middle.
And there are instructions on the old computers
which copy a whole array.
They are not atomic.
Right?
If bad things happen,
you can see the results only of a partially run instruction.
Now, of course, if we run,
if we know only what are the atomic instruction,
this is helpful, but it's still not enough
because we want, you know, you can see that atomicity,
it's a very convenient way to control the access.
To a shared variable.
Because atomicity, if I can say all these bunch
of instructions is not going to be interrupted.
I don't need to be worried that someone will read or write
or I am executing these operations.
You remember how these are called?
It's critical section, right?
And the way to do it, in general, you do is a lock.
You have one lock and you acquire the lock
and you execute some code.
And while you have the lock,
no one else can acquire the lock.
So no one else may be able to execute these instructions.
And then you release a lock when you are done.
Okay?
And the threads libraries,
they do have the lock primitive.
Okay?
How do we fix it?
The previous example,
remember when multiple threads can run at the same time,
they can run at the same time
and then can access data at the same time.
Well, simply, simple, right?
You acquire the lock before you execute all the instruction
on an account, and then you release a clock, right?
So this is what in the middle of acquiring
and releasing the lock is called critical section.
So if multiple threads want to execute the same code,
only one will execute at a given time.
Right? Very simple.
So one thread and then thread B and thread C.
Okay?
So, but you need all this value of the same lock
or the same lock should be shared by all the threads
who want to access the same critical section.
Okay?
So remember, okay?
These two, three notions, synchronization,
using atomic operation to ensure cooperation between threads
and for now only slow than stores we assume are atomic.
Mutual exclusion, we ensure that only one thread
has a particular thing at a given time.
Right?
This means that one thread exclude another thread
from running the same code.
And critical section is other side
of the mutual exclusion coin
and critical section basically define
which is a sequence of instruction or the code,
which is can be executed by a single thread at a given time.
Here is another example.
Thread A and thread B.
Thread A starts with I, it initialized to zero
and then arts one has a loop, arts one.
And when you get to 10 exits and say prints A wins.
Thread B is doing similar things, but decrementing.
Start with I zero decrements it.
And if you reach to minus 10, B wins.
Both of them, they share these variables.
Why?
So what is the result here?
Who wins A or B?
(silence)
Okay, let's,
only 20 minutes remaining.
So let's get a little bit of energy.
Yeah.
Could be either, right?
You cannot know, right?
Let me ask you another question.
Are you guaranteed that at least one will win?
Now, excellent.
I listen and action.
Now, because in the worst case,
you see these three instruction.
I is equal to I plus one, I is equal to I minus one.
What happens if you have context switching
and between thread A and thread B and this.
thread only executes this instruction.
Right?
You get stuck with the same value.
You never finish.
None of those threads finishes.
OK?
Excellent.
Thank you.
So it's again, this is an inner loop.
And this is-- we see what is happening under the hood.
And all those are facts that what
you see is that in the program, it's
actually even more subtle.
Because when you see the program in the previous slide,
let me just--
we should have said, when you see this i is i plus 1
or i is i minus 1, actually maybe you
think that this is also atomic.
That means executes to completion.
Cannot be interrupted.
But it's not true.
Remember, only loads and stores are atomic.
So actually, things are even more complicated.
Because i and i plus 1 and i is i minus 1
can be interrupted in the middle.
And this is one example.
Right?
Where you execute-- you interleave the instruction
from thread A and thread B. And the result here is what?
Nothing changes.
Right?
OK.
Because in the middle, you read the same values.
You write the same at the same location.
And in the middle, you add to the value 1 and subtract 1.
So nothing changes.
OK?
So it's-- and typically, this is called race conditions
when you have two threads attempting to access same data
at the same time with one of them performing a write.
OK?
So how do you fix it?
Well, we know now.
You put a lock.
Does this fix it?
Not really, because we discussed, right?
You can execute this block of instruction, y plus 1,
and then execute the second block of instruction.
And it's true that you are going to see the changes.
But before you execute the next while,
the value was updated to the same value.
Right?
And the main point here-- and I need probably
to go a little bit faster--
concurrency is hard.
Like, look, these simple examples,
there are a bunch of instructions,
just a few instructions.
What?
Three instructions, four instructions?
Even that is hard.
Now imagine that you have thousands, tens of thousands
of instructions.
And there are many, many such issues.
And these are just some examples.
This was TeraK-25, a radiation therapy machine.
As a result of this kind of race condition concurrency,
of not being careful, accessing the same variable
from different threads, resulted in an overdose,
which caused even death.
OK?
It was improper synchronization between the input thread
and the positioning software where to apply the radiation.
Mark Pathfinder priority inversion.
Priority inversion here means that basically what happens,
you have a high priority job.
We'll learn more about that.
A high priority thread waiting for something
from a low priority thread.
But the high priority thread contains a lock,
maintains a lock, which is required by the low priority
thread to update that value or to do something
for its high priority thread weights.
But it cannot do it because a critical section is owned
by high priority thread.
So you get hacked.
This is another thing.
Toyota uncontrolled acceleration.
This was 256,000 lines of C code and whatever,
11,000 global variables.
So here it was inconsistent mutual exclusion.
So acceleration was uncontrollable.
You just doesn't respond.
You click a little bit and the car takes off
like you would floor the acceleration pedal.
OK, so next let's look about a little bit more
sophisticated things.
And let's look at about a Q. Producer consumer
with a bandit buffer.
Why this is important?
Remember about pipes last time.
We learned about pipes.
Pipes is a buffer.
It's a Q. You put at one end of the Q
and get the data from the other end of the Q.
When you do a pipe, this is also when
you do the piping between different--
when you chain different shell commands,
the same thing happened.
And we'll have another example of Kog machine later.
And there are many examples.
But this is what you want.
Ideally, you put at one end of the buffer
and you read from a different end of the buffer.
And typically, there is circular buffers.
They're easiest to handle.
And you have immediately to deal with several problems.
How to tell if full?
How to tell if the buffer is empty?
What to do if the buffer is full?
What to do if the buffer is empty?
What needs to be atomic?
OK?
So let's take a simple example.
Let's think about what is a simple implementation.
The producer, what do you need to do?
While the buffer is full, don't do anything.
You cannot put another item because you don't
have where to put it.
If the buffer is not full, you can use the item.
And because you need to do this operation,
you want to be atomic, you are going to guard it with a lock.
OK?
Can anyone tell me why you need to do this?
What can happen?
What can happen if I don't lock?
Yes, you may have buffer overflow.
Excellent.
Right, because you can have two producers, two threads.
OK?
And one execute-- both execute while buffer.
And both are happy.
The buffer has just one place for only one item.
Right?
So both are going to pass of the while.
But now one is interrupted, obviously, right?
And the other one is going to execute the item.
So now the buffer is full.
But for the first producer which was interrupted
or was suspended, resumes, he doesn't know.
He's going to try to add another item.
And now you have the overflow.
OK?
And now is the dequeue.
The same you do lock for this critical section.
And you wait now.
If the buffer is empty, you don't do anything.
If the buffer is not empty, you are going to dequeue it.
Right?
Now, let's assume now for this code,
if we do this, would we ever come out of the way?
This is a question.
So say that nothing is above them.
All right.
Then that's fine, right?
You are going to fill the buffer.
But let me ask you this question.
OK, maybe we're not unanswered.
Let's see.
Now you can block on the consumer.
Exactly.
So, let's say that the queue is empty and the consumer executes.
It acquires the lock and then it executes a while and it's stuck because there is nothing
in the buffer.
And the only one who can put something in the buffer is the producer.
But in order for the producer to put something in the buffer, he still acquires the lock.
But it cannot acquire the lock because it's owned by the consumer.
So your hand.
OK.
So it don't work.
So how can you do it?
One solution is to release a lock, OK, if the buffer is full.
We need to release a lock if the buffer is full to give a chance to the consumer to consume
from the buffer.
Right.
OK.
And then acquire the buffer.
You see what we've done here.
You acquire before you check again whether the buffer is full.
You release this to give a chance to the consumer to execute.
You acquire the buffer back to check back whether the buffer is full for the lock.
OK.
What happens when one is waiting for the other?
Like I said in this thing, it could work.
OK.
And for multiple clockwise, we'll discuss this a little bit later.
Let me just-- and then there are other things we can do here.
And this write abstraction of synchronizing threads that share memory.
Locks is one abstraction.
And-- but it's not the only abstraction.
OK.
And let me just see the question here.
Let me go back and it's important to understand that.
So the question here, it's what happens when one is waiting for the-- why do we need to
acquire the lock?
We need to acquire the lock because here what happens in the while loop?
In the while loop, it's an empty instruction.
You need to repeat the-- you repeat the-- what is this while?
You repeat the check whether the buffer is full.
And in between the checks, you release and acquire the buffer.
We need to be in critical section to check the buffer because you don't want to be--
the buffer to be modified while you are checking about-- checking whether it's full.
So that has to be critical section.
But between multiple checks, you want to release the lock so the consumer can consume.
That's all.
Right?
OK.
So another way to do it is a more general way using semaphores.
And we did the semaphores.
We learned slightly a little bit about them.
This is just recalling what we learned.
There are two semaphores, two primitives-- sorry, two primitives on the same semaphore.
Sp is an atomic operation which waits for the semaphore to become positive, then decrements
by one.
If zero, it just-- its waits is blocked.
And b, we just increment the semaphore and wake up any other thread which waits for the
semaphore.
Right?
So semaphores are like integers in the sense that you can increment and decrement them
except there are no negative values.
And the only way you can increment them is to use the p and v functions.
And these operations, these operations are atomic.
P and v are atomic.
So this is a railroad analogy.
You can implement like, for instance, in this case, you have two lines, two railroad lines,
two rails.
So you increment-- you put the value of the semaphore to two.
So you can have an engine parked on one line and then an engine parked on second line.
You notice that every time I have accepted an engine, I decrement the value.
Now its value is zero.
So you have another engine.
It stopped.
It cannot get in because the value is zero.
Now when one leaves, it's going to increment the semaphore and the third engine can enter.
Right?
And so forth.
So you can use semaphores to implement mutual exclusion.
And this is equivalent to having a semaphore with a binary value, zero or one.
Right?
So how do you do that?
You do a P on the semaphore, you initialize the semaphore to one and use a P. So the first
thread which calls p is going to enter the critical section because you can decrement
value to zero.
The second one is going to call p while the first thread in the critical section cannot
enter in the critical section because semaphore is zero.
When the first semaphore leaves the critical section, it's going to increment the semaphore.
So the second one comes.
Right?
We also say in this case that the semaphore implements scheduling constraints.
And also this is about, sorry, a second use case, which you'll also learn last time, it
was about waiting, a thread waiting for another thread to finish.
You need the code.
And this was implementing join operation.
Right?
Remember this code.
You have a thread join and you are going to wait for the thread to finish the other join.
You run a thread and you wait for it to finish.
And how you do that?
You are going to have a semaphore which is initialized to zero.
And when you start the thread, when you finish a thread, you increment the semaphore to one.
And then, okay, let me take it back.
You initialize the thread to zero.
Okay?
When you start the thread, nothing happens.
And the main thread is going to wait to execute thread join.
And it's going to be blocked because the semaphore is zero.
When the thread finishes for which I am waiting, then the thread is going to increment the
semaphore.
And now the P in the thread join can decrement the semaphore and can finish.
Okay?
And this is when we say we implement scheduling constraints.
So, this we are a little bit slow.
Let me just go over announcements.
Let me find the announcement and we are going to be done.
So announcements, very quick announcements today.
Please sign up for design reviews.
The design documents also, don't forget, are due Friday.
Next week, you are going to get the feedback on your design documents from your TA.
So you need to sign to schedule that meeting.
And the homework one is due today.
So good luck with that.
So good luck again with the homework.
Good luck with the design documents and see you all next week.
Thank you.
[ Silence ]