Hello, everyone.
So welcome to the eighth lecture.
And this is really an important lecture.
We are going to learn a lot and continue to learn about synchronization and how we are
going to solve the problems and ensure critical provides a critical section abstraction and
synchronization primitives.
So let's recall a few things from the last time in particular semaphores.
And if you remember, semaphores are like generalized logs and they are defined many times, many
years ago, like 60 years ago almost.
And it was a main synchronization primitive used in original Unix.
And when we are talking here about synchronization, we are talking about in the context of implementing
a critical section.
If you remember, a critical section, it's a sequence of code in which only one thread
can be active at a given time.
So therefore, if one thread is active in a critical section, the other threads which
want to enter the critical section, basically the code, they need to wait.
So we need a mechanism to synchronize this kind of entrance to the critical section.
And then when a thread exits the critical section, another thread from the waiting ones
is going to enter the critical section.
And there are two primitives, p and v. p, if the semaphore is zero, p is waiting.
If the semaphore is greater than zero, it decrements it.
And the other one, v, it's basically just increment the semaphore by one.
And if the semaphore is zero and if it's incremented to one, then it's going to wake up one of
the threads which was waiting on a semaphore, if any.
And these are two years of the semaphores we went over last time.
One is mutual exclusion.
So it's, again, this is about implementing critical sections.
And here, it's very simple.
You are going to initialize the semaphore to one.
And then you put before and after critical section, a p and a v.
So the first thread, which is going to execute the instruction p, the semaphore, it's one,
it's going to decrement it, it's going to enter the critical section.
If another thread comes and tries to execute the code, the semaphore now is zero.
So it has to wait.
When the first semaphore x is the critical section, it's calling v and v is incrementing
the semaphore.
And therefore, as a result, we signal the thread who is waiting to enter the critical
section.
And it's also the scheduling constraints.
And this is basically, we want to signal, to wait for a thread or signal a thread to
do something.
And here, the initial value is zero.
And the classic example is a join implementation for the thread.
You remember that with a join, the pattern, the thread which executes the join waits for
another thread to finish.
And so basically, the thread which waits to finish, the join, they use to implement this
to use the same semaphore.
So the thread, we initialize the semaphore to zero.
And the thread who waits for another thread to join to finish, then it's just calling
p.
Right?
And if the other thread, when it finishes, is calling v. OK, so if the thread hasn't
finished, the semaphore is zero.
So the join operation will just wait.
And it will wait until when?
Until the thread it's waiting for, it's executing this thread finish, which calls v, it's incrementing
the semaphore to one, which means that and signals the waiting thread.
And the waiting thread now is the semaphore is one and going to start executing and decrementing
it to zero and finish the code, finish the join operation.
OK.
Any questions?
OK, please ask any questions, you know, if you have any.
So and then we want to do this bounded buffer.
So remember the bounded buffer, we have a bunch of producers, a bunch of consumers,
the producer put elements in the buffer, the consumers get elements around the buffer.
And you hear, if you look at the constraints, what we are talking about here is that for
the consumer must wait for the producer to fill the buffer.
If the buffer is empty, then the consumer have to wait.
On the other hand, the producers must wait for the consumer to empty the buffer.
If the buffer is full, then the producer has to wait because there are no place in the
buffer to put new elements.
And there is obviously there is the buffer itself manipulating the buffer or the queue.
It's basically it's a critical section and only one thread is going to manipulate the
queue.
Right.
So it's one consumer or one producer.
OK.
So, how we are going to implement this?
One implement, we are going for each of these constraints, we are going to use a semaphore.
So we are going to use a semaphore for full buffers.
This is consumer constraint and empty buffers.
OK.
And basically, each of the semaphore at a given time will show how many elements are
in the buffer, full buffers, and how many elements you can still put in the buffer.
So basically, if you add that to these two semaphores, you should get the total number
of elements at buffer size.
And then a mutex, a semaphore mutex for the mutual exclusion to make sure that you have
only one thread manipulating the queue, that is whether inserting a new element or removing
an element from the queue.
OK.
So let's start.
So full slots is basically zero because initially there is nothing in the queue.
Empty slots is a buffer size.
So remember, if you add here full slots with empty slots, you get the size of the buffer.
And mutex is one.
Right.
So no one is using the-- no one is in the critical section.
And the producer then is very simple.
Right.
It's like basically you are waiting for slots to be available.
And then you use a mutex to protect the critical section.
And then once you are done, you are incrementing the number of slots or full slots.
Right.
Because you added one element.
And the consumer is very similar.
You are waiting for two full slots to be greater than zero.
This means that there is at least one element in the buffer.
So if you have more than one element in the buffer, you can dequeue that element.
Again, the dequeue operation is protected by the mutex.
And then once you are done, you are going to increment the empty slots because now it's
one more available slots in the queue.
OK.
So you return the item.
So that's basically here.
And you use a mutex to protect the critical section.
So therefore, now two threads at the same time operate on the queue to remove, to manipulate
the pointers, to remove the elements or to add the element to the queue.
And then the other one are scheduling constraints of full slots.
It's incremented by the producer and then it's decremented by the consumer.
And similarly, the empty space is incremented by the consumer and decremented by the producer.
OK.
Any questions?
So a discussion about solution.
So you can see there is asymmetry, right?
The producer is doing-- is calling P and then V on empty buffers and full buffers.
And the consumer does the reserve, reverse.
Is calling P on the full buffers and V on the empty buffers, right?
So there is this asymmetry.
OK.
And it's exactly what we expect, right?
Because the producer has to decrease the number of empty slots and increase the number of
occupy slots.
And the consumer-- sorry, the producer has to wait for-- the producer, yeah, it has to
wait for empty slots to be available.
But then once you put the element, you decrease the number of empty slots and you increase
the numbers of occupy slots.
consumer is the other way around when there is at least one element in the buffer, you
decrease the number of occupied slots because you take one element and then also this increase
the number of empty slots.
So now this is a question for you.
And if there is there, you remember in the original code, let me just move this, we call
first, producer calls first, semaphore p on the empty slots and then the mutex.
Now is that order important?
Okay, that's a question for the class.
So looking forward to your replies, to your answers.
Yes, it is.
If you do this, it can be we can deadlock.
Can someone explain how you can get the deadlock here?
It's very simple.
Yes.
Thank you Aaron and Akshay.
So basically it's very simple, right?
For instance, you imagine that you're the producer and the empty slots, there are no
empty slots.
So empty slots is zero.
So what happens?
You acquire the mutex for the critical section and then you are going to start waiting because
empty slots is zero.
There is no place in the queue to insert a new element, but a new element.
But now you are going to wait in the critical section.
And the only way the empty slots can be incremented is by the consumer.
But in order to do that, the consumer has to dequeue an operation, but for that you
need to acquire mutex, but you own the mutex, the producer owns the mutex, so you cannot
acquire the mutex because you can have only one thread in the critical section.
So therefore consumer cannot dequeue any element and therefore the producer will continue to
wait for the empty slots to be incremented, which will never happen.
Very good.
Is the order of V important?
Well, I have the answer here is that, yeah, now because you just do the increment.
What if you have two producer and two consumers?
Is this, do you need any changes to this code?
I mean to the previous code which is working, not to this one.
So assuming that somehow P and mutex and empty slots are not reordered.
So do you want to, do you need to make any changes to this code?
If we have two producers and two consumers.
Yes, Anali, you are correct.
Now you don't need to do it to make any change.
It's going just to work, when the reason is going to work, it's again because no matter
how many consumer and producers you are going to have, it's only one of those can be in
the critical section.
Yes, exactly.
Thank you.
Good.
So, it's again, so you can see that P and V are synchronization primitives.
Now what we are going to do in the rest of these lectures, we are going to try to figure
out how to implement the synchronization primitives.
Synchronization primitive P and V are at the higher level, but as a low level, you have
what you have when you are talking about the processor.
What you can do, you can execute instructions like load and stores and you can disable interacts.
And then we'll see there are a few other specialized instructions like test and set and compare
and swap, which it make it much easier to implement higher level synchronization primitives.
Because like you'll see using just load and store and disable interrupts, they are not
ideal solutions.
Then as a higher level, we have locks.
We discussed last time, we are going to discuss more this lecture.
Semaphores and then monitors and send receipt operation.
But monitor, we are going to discuss locks, semaphores, their implementation and hopefully
we are going to also get monitors during this lecture.
And then programs, there are higher abstraction at the program level and we are not going
to talk about them at least this week.
And here is a motivating example.
And if you haven't paid too much attention until now, please from now on for this example
pay attention because it will learn you a lot.
And remember that next Wednesday we have the first meter.
And this and the next lecture are going to be part of the topics covered by the meter.
So here is a problem.
And basically the problem is that there are two roommates and both of them like milk.
And the question, the problem is that if there is no milk in the fridge, then whoever discovers
that they are going to go and get milk.
And the goal here is to not get too much milk.
And how can you get too much milk?
Well, think about the same sequence of events.
At three o'clock, first roommate, let's call her person A, look in the fridge, there is
no milk.
So leaves to go to the store and while arriving at the store, it's a closed store, the second
roommate call her person B, look at the fridge and it's out of milk.
So she's going to do the same thing, leave for store and arrive at store.
And during this time, the person A left the store, arrive at her home, put the milk in
the fridge while the person B is at the store buying milk.
And then we are going to get at the end of the day, we are going to have two bottle of
milks in the fridge.
So this solution certainly doesn't do what we wanted and what we wanted to not buy too
much milk.
So how do we do that?
Well, obviously, the problem here is that in some sense, both person A and B execute
the same instructions and so to speak, take the same actions without any coordination.
They execute that kind of code, each of them at the same time.
And so what do you want?
You want only one person of the two to go to the store to buy milk.
So basically, you can see now the concept of critical section.
If you think about the program as going to the fridge, going to the store to buy milk,
we want only one person to do it.
And one way to prevent that, like we learned and we saw last time, is to have locks.
So you lock before entering the critical section and you unlock after leaving the critical
section.
Now, the one important thing which will come over and over again and what makes the implementation
of locks challenging is that any lock implementation or synchronization, primitive implementation,
involve waiting.
And why is that?
It should be obvious, right?
Because if many threads wants to enter the same critical section and only one at a time
can do it, this means that
One will go in a critical section and the other ones, what they can do, they have to
wait.
There is no way around it.
So remember the boat.
So of course, one way to do it is to lock all the way also the fridge.
And basically, before you go to the store, you lock the fridge.
And if the other person sees, comes to the fridge, it's locked.
It's going to wait for you to unlock the fridge.
And then this guarantees that it's only one person, you buying the meal.
But of course, this is not ideal because what if the other person wants something else than
milk from the fridge.
So this is kind of very coarse grain solution.
Okay.
So let's see how we are going to solve this problem.
And before doing that, it's again, it's like this is a tricky problem and these problems
when concurrency problems are tricky.
And they are tricky fundamentally because there are many entities doing the same things
at the same time.
And it just, as a human, we are more used to thinking linearly than thinking about many
things happening at the same time.
We are not very good at that.
So that's one of the reasons.
And you can very well miss different edge cages.
So what you want when you have to deal with this kind of problem, actually, you want to
do that when you deal with any kind of problem, programming problem.
But in particular with this kind of problems, you need to be very careful and think quite
a bit about what you want to achieve and how to develop a solution to meet the requirements
you want to achieve.
So don't start to code first.
Just think first.
And again, the way to think about it is to write down what you want to happen.
So what do you want to happen here or what are the correctness properties?
So you want no more than one person buys some milk at a time.
If two person buys milk at a time, you end up with two bottle of milk.
At the same time, if there is no milk, there must be someone buying the milk.
Otherwise, you don't get the milk.
And let's think about if you restrict yourself to just load and store.
So load and store meaning that you are going to modify some variable in the memory, which
can be read by any program.
So here is one example.
And the way we are going to emulate this load and stores in this problem is through notes.
You put a note on the fridge with a message.
This is basically, it's equivalent to storing.
And you read the note, obviously, and it's equivalent to load.
So let's say what we have here, we have two notes, two kind of notes, one note.
And then what is a code?
One possible code can be one possible solution.
It's like if there is no milk, right?
And there is no note.
We assume here that a note indicates that someone else is going to buy the milk.
Then you leave note and you yourself go to buy the milk.
And when you come back, you remove the note.
Simply enough.
So what can happen here?
Do you think it's a good solution?
Okay, let's see now answer here.
It's not a good solution, right?
Oh, okay.
We have an answer.
Not atomic, that could cause problems.
Yeah, there are problems here.
And the way to look at, again, is people just can work, but if this is done by machines,
the machines are myopic.
They only see these instructions, they only nothing else.
So let's see what can happen.
And always in these concurrency problems, the bad things can happen if somehow the instruction
are interleaved in an unfortunate way.
So let's see here what can happen.
So let's say we have thread A and thread B.
Now thread A is looking and check for the milk.
And then once thread A checks for the milk, it's context switched, it's suspended by the
operating system, by the scheduler.
And thread B starts to execute.
And thread B is again check for no milk.
And in both cases, the answer is A is true, there is no milk.
And then thread B is check for the note.
And there is no note.
But after checks for the note, again, we context switch to thread A. Thread A check again for
the note, since there is no note, and leaves a note.
Buy milk, remove note, and thread B is going to do the same thing.
Because from the point of view, there is thread B, there is no milk, there is no note.
And from the point of view of thread A, the same is true.
When you check, it was no milk, and when it's checked, there was no note.
So you have now both thread A and thread B buying milk.
Any questions here?
So it's too much milk.
This happens occasionally.
If you don't have this unfortunate order of execution, actually this code will work.
And the problem is this will happen occasionally is that, you may say it's good news.
It's like it only happens from time to time.
But the problem that when this happens is very hard to debug because it's not happened
all the time.
And that's what also makes these problems, all these programs frustrating because they
are very hard to debug.
Another reason to think very well before starting to code.
Okay, so how do you solve this problem?
So clearly this note is not exclusive enough.
And one solution you may be saying is because it's not, why don't we place a note first?
What if we do this code?
Instead of checking for the note, leaving the note before buying the milk, let's leave
the note even before we check for the milk.
What about this code?
Any problem with this code?
Yes, this is a very, actually this is a pretty stupid code.
Because if you leave the note here, then if no note will be always true.
If no note will be always false and no one will buy milk.
If you leave the note, if you leave yourself the note, and then you check for the note,
there is a note, so you don't buy milk.
That's why I was saying this is stupid.
So it won't work even for one user.
So let's go to solution two.
So this kind of didn't work.
Maybe we need to be more sophisticated.
Maybe we need to have two kinds, two notes, one for each person.
So let's rewrite the previous code.
So thread A, leave note A. Thread B, leave note B. And thread A checks whether thread
B left the note, and thread B checks whether thread A left the note.
Seems more sophisticated, may work maybe.
What do you think?
Is this going to work?
You
Okay, why don't you guess? Okay, you don't need to tell me whether, you know, why is
going to work or not. Just take a guess. Yes, now, good answer. I hope that this answer
is not given because you'll look to the next slide. But anyway, so now it doesn't work.
And here is the reason, you know, an example. It's again, it's about how these instructions
are interleaved from thread A and thread B. You leave node A, you leave node B, thread
A leaves node A, then we context switch to thread B, thread B leaves node B, it checks
for if there is no node A and basically there is a node A, so this is false and this is
not going to execute it. And at the same time, thread A is looking whether there is a node
B and there is a node B, so this is really false. So it's not going to execute the if,
what is under the if condition. And at the end, both of them remove their own nodes,
but no one bought the milk. Okay. Make sense? Any questions here? Okay. So it's again possible
for neither of the threads to buy milk. And it's again, this is really, really hard to
debug because it happens rarely.
So now let me tell you, you know, I told you something about initially about any synchronization
primitive should involve something. And actually, even without reading the code, you can see
you could have answered the question whether the code is correct or not. Can you tell me
why and how you could have answered this question immediately? Whether the code is correct or
not? Actually, the question is more clearly, you could have immediately see that the code
is not correct.
Yes, Nicholas, that's true. There is no wait. I told you that fundamentally any of the synchronization
primitives has to involve a wait. Because if someone is in the critical section, the
other one thread has to wait. If it wants to go into the critical section, there is
no way around it. It's fundamental. But so far, none of these codes has a wait instruction
or something equivalent. So that's why you can immediately say this code is not going
to work.
So finally, okay, so let's go. If no one gets the milk and this continues, and obviously
this is called starvation, we're going to learn more about starvation in a few lectures.
So now finally, here is solution three. There are two nodes, but not yesterday. It has a
while. A while, this is a waiting instruction basically. Because you wait for the node B.
If there is a node B, then you wait until the node B is removed. Okay. So in other words,
thread A will not execute, will not buy the milk, will not even look at whether there
is a milk in the fridge. If thread B is checked and already went to buy milk.
Yeah, testing set, it's a synchronization. So the question is from Michael, instead of
waiting can we skip the critical section, do we consider test and set as having a critical
section? The test and set, they are going to be used to implement things like locks.
That's it. And you need to have a while in order to wait on a test and set. Okay. So
our answer is correct. Right? So you need test and set alone. You need to also have
a while around it. We'll see that. Is this going to work? Yes. And how are you to convince
yourself? You see these are these two points, X and Y in each of these thread programs.
And what you say here is that at X, if there is no node B, there is say for A to buy. Right?
Okay. Say for A to buy, sorry. Yeah. Right? Because if there is no node B, the thread
B will for sure is outside this section of code. So for sure thread B doesn't buy milk.
So it's safe for A to buy if there is no milk. Now, if I am at Y, if there is no node A,
it's safe for B to buy. Why? Because if there is no node A, this means that thread A is
not in exactly in this code. So it cannot buy milk. Here is another way to look at it.
There are these two actions, leave node A and no node A when it's checked. So if leave
node A happens before no node A is checked by the second thread, right? Then it's obvious
that thread B will not buy milk because there is a node A. And it's also obvious, at least
for now, that thread A will wait because there is a node B. Right? Now at this point, now
the thread B is again, there is a node A, so it keeps buying milk and then go all the
way and buy and remove the node B without doing anything, without buying milk. But notice
now what happens with thread A. Once thread B removes node B, thread A exits the while
loop. It checks whether there is no milk and there is no milk and buys the milks. Okay?
So in this particular case, thread A bought milk. Now let's assume that if node A happens
after thread B checks whether there is no node A. What happens in this case? Right?
So thread B found no node A, there is no milk, so it's going to buy the milk. And then it's
removing the node B. In parallel, node A is going to execute while node B and is going
to wait for A to remove node B. When that happens and thread B removes node B only after
it bought the milk. So now when B removes node B, this means that thread A will exit
the while loop and now check for the milk. But now there is milk in the fridge because
B put the milk in the fridge, it bought the milk. So therefore A will not buy milk. Okay?
So yeah.
done. So you see in this case, in both cases, only one thread and exactly one thread bought milk.
Okay, so the solution it originally protects a single critical section piece of code,
and this is a critical section. If no milk, you buy milk.
So it's just three words, but it's not very satisfactory. It's pretty complex,
right? Even in this simple example. And like you see, we got like what, five, six instructions,
and it still took us like whatever, 10, 15 minutes to convince ourselves that it's working.
And also, eighth code is different from this code. What if you have not two threads, but three threads
or 10 threads? And finally, yes, we have a wait here, but it is busy waiting, right? This thread
A consumes the CPU resources while waiting. We don't want that in general. So let's look for
better ways. So think about lock interface you are considering. You want to acquire the lock,
and release the lock. These are the instructions. If the lock is taken, you are waiting in the acquire
until someone releases the lock. Okay? And then your milk problem is very simple. You acquire the
lock. If there is no milk, you buy the milk, and then you release the lock. This is like our very
first solution with a lock, right? The physical lock to the fridge. But now imagine that you can
put the lock only on something in the fridge where contains only milk, right? On a container in the
fridge or contains milk. That's equivalent, right? So now the question is how to implement lock?
This is what we are going to discuss. Remember, all synchronization primitive involves waiting.
But you don't want to do the waiting, busy waiting. Just, you know, spending the CPU resources
while waiting. Instead, you want to sleep when you wait, and you want to be woken up when
you can acquire the lock and enter the physical section.
Solution three from the milk, our milk-3 solution, was basically equivalent to using atomic load and
stores. Again, pretty complex and a lot of problems. So now the question is about how we do
this, implement the locks, because I saw that if we implement the locks, the solution is much easier.
So one way to think about is to implement it in hardware. However, if you implement it in hardware,
a lock, it turns out that it's pretty complicated. And there are some processors doing it,
but it's again, the complexity is high and it's also slow. And because the chip is more complex,
it's actually slowed down many other instructions. So one simple solution to implement it with what
you've learned so far, it's about using the interrupts. Remember that we have these interrupts,
external interrupts, internal interrupts, but fundamentally the interrupts,
when you execute an interrupt, you are going to run some code. And what we are talking about here
is that think about lock acquire, disable all interrupts. So this means also there is no
context switching because in order to have also the context switching, you're going to have the
timer interrupt, or the interrupt, another interrupt, external interrupts to do it.
And the lock release, you enable interrupts. So this is, so that is a problem with this approach,
it's not going to work. Before we acquire an interrupt, if you do acquire a lock and you
disable all the interrupts, and then you do something like a while through, you hang,
the computer hangs. It's again, it cannot be interrupted. You need to do something like yield
to voluntarily provide, give access to the scheduler in order to the kernel to schedule
another thread. But this code will lock the entire computer. So it's very, very risky.
And you don't want to do that. And there are many other reasons, like for real-time systems,
there is no guarantee of timing because the physical section can be arbitrarily long.
And obviously what happens when there are very important IO events.
So let's think about a better implementation of the locks by disabling interrupts. So here is one.
So basically you maintain, as a way to think about, you use a lock to implement a lock.
And what you want is that when the segment, you want to minimize the code
between disable interrupt and enable interrupts. That's what you want to do.
Okay? Because in the previous case, the problem is that you disable interrupts and you enter the
critical section, then the critical section can be arbitrarily long. Depends on the application.
But in this case, we are going to implement the lock with a disable interrupt and enable
interrupts, and then expose acquire lock and release lock to the application.
Implement it under the hood by the disable interrupts. But notice here,
the disable interrupts and enable interrupts, you have a very small piece of code here.
So it's going to run very, very quickly. Okay? So ideally what you do for the acquire, so say
the value is a lock value and it's either free or busy.
So to acquire it, if you disable the interrupt to manipulate this value,
if the value is busy, what did we say? We want to sleep. So push thread on the wait list and
go to sleep. And somehow you want to enable interrupts. Okay? So other thread can execute.
Right? Else, you acquire the lock value is busy and you enable interrupts. Okay?
And for release, you disable interrupts. You look if there is only anyone on the wait queue,
waiting for the lock. If it is, you give the lock to one of the thread from the wait queue,
and you place that thread on the ready queue. So that thread can execute the critical section.
If there is no one on the wait queue, the value is free and you enable the interrupts.
Okay? So you see here, the wait happens because you put the thread waiting on the waiting queue,
and you take that thread from the waiting queue when
another thread released the lock. Any questions here?
So now it's again, it's what I was saying. You increment the lock by another lock, right?
And the reason for that, because the second lock you are going to use, you can use the disable
and enable interrupts by making sure that the critical section protected by disabling and
enable interrupts is very short. And this can be implemented by the operating system.
So you have control about the length of the critical section protected by the interrupt
disabling and enabling. Okay. So that's the main difference from using disable interrupts
and enable interrupts directly. Okay. With this design, the users can take as long as they want
in their critical section, right? Because their critical section is not protected by
disable interrupt or enable interrupt. Now, what is a big problem? Here is a big problem.
We need to enable interrupts
when we put the thread on the wait queue, because we need to allow
other threads to execute, in particular the thread which is in the critical section.
But the question is where do you need to install to enable the interrupts?
There are three possibilities. One is here before putting the thread on the wait queue.
It is correct.
It's not because the release can check the queue and not
wake up the thread.
So you put the enabling traps here.
Before the thread is put on the wait queue,
you do context switch.
You can do context switch to the thread, another thread, which
is executing the release.
And the release is going to look if there
is any thread on the wait queue.
And there is none because acquire didn't have a chance
to place a thread on the wait queue.
So the thread will not be open.
What if you put the enable interrupts before go to sleep?
Is that correct?
Does if-- so here is a question from Michael.
Does if have to be replaced with while?
No, I'll let you know why because--
OK.
Let me go through this slide, and I'll tell you why after that.
Now, because this is not correct either because the release
puts the thread on the ready queue,
but the thread still thinking it needs to go to sleep.
OK?
So you put the thread on the waiting queue.
You enable interrupts.
Now, assume that the release from the other thread
is executed.
And here, the release is looking on the wait queue,
and you have a thread on the wait queue.
And take that thread to execute it.
But then, when the thread is executed, it goes to sleep.
So it don't execute.
Now, to the question.
I said that it's a busy-- that we need to have some waiting
for any synchronization primitive.
We need to have waitings.
So why we don't have a while here?
The reason we don't have a while here is very simple.
Like I mentioned, but probably I was not very clear.
It's because waiting here happens implicitly
by acquire.
If the value, if the lock is busy,
you put the thread on the waiting queue.
Putting the thread of the waiting queue, that act,
means waiting.
Right?
It doesn't happen in the program.
It happens in the kernel.
Right?
You put the thread on the waiting queue,
and the thread will wait until the release
is going to be executed.
And the lock is released.
OK?
Anyway, so in order to solve the problem,
you need to put to release a lock after going to sleep.
But how you do it?
Because the thread is sleeping, so how
can execute an instruction to enable the interrupts?
Any suggestions?
So the problem is very simple.
OK?
It's like I want, logically, to enable the interrupts
after I go to sleep.
But how can I do that because I am sleeping?
Modify sleep function, Aaron.
That's good.
But I need to--
how you modify that?
That's not easy.
You can try it, but you'll see that it's not easy.
Because you still have a bunch of instructions,
and you'll see the same problem like you have here.
Have the kernel do it for now.
Yes, you can have the kernel do it for now.
But how do you do it?
You do it whenever you do the sleep.
That's not good.
Right?
Because you can call a sleep in different other--
for many other cases.
So actually, the solution is quite brilliant, in my opinion.
If the thread, which go to sleep,
cannot enable the interrupts--
the solution is that another thread, which wakes up,
is going to enable the interrupts.
So you do it on context switching.
And in some sense, you can argue this is done by the kernel.
You can do that in the kernel.
But this is a solution here.
Right?
So and the nice thing about the solution,
it's again, is like if the thread which goes to sleep
cannot enable the interrupt because already you
went to sleep, the solution is for the next thread, which
when you return from the sleep, to enable the interrupts.
Right?
So you have another thread enables the interrupts.
OK?
So this is pretty nice.
So when you wake up, you're enabling interrupts.
OK.
Some announcements.
Design review schedule as soon as possibly
you haven't done already.
The review is your TA.
Needs to be done by the Thursday.
So you have two days.
And show up on time listed.
There is no break-like time.
We have now 10 minutes after.
Meter, it will be between 7 and 9 PM, eight days from now.
We are going-- it's going to cover everything up to
and including the next lecture.
There will be a midterm review on Monday between 7 and 9.
And for logistics on profiting policies and so forth,
cheat sheet, look out for the posts.
Let me see.
Sorry, it's 29 what I'm saying here.
Wednesday, 9, 29.
Thanks for catching.
So question here was, how do you can context switch?
Because here, everything disabled--
the interrupts are disabled.
So here, we are not talking about context switching
based on the time or event.
We are talking about here.
This is here.
Let me just see all the code.
So this is a code.
Right?
You see this part where if anyone on the waiting queue--
so when you do this, you go to sleep.
By the go to sleep means you yield the control
to the kernel.
OK?
And the kernel, the interrupts are--
you are going to execute this instruction
and take the threat of the wait queue.
And when you do this, you enable the interrupts.
OK?
So this enable interrupts from here--
I hope that you are seeing what I'm highlighting--
is going to happen here.
You take the threat of the wait queue,
and you are going to--
you return from the--
this means you return from the sleep,
and you are going to enable the interrupts just
before place on the ready queue.
OK.
Hopefully, it answers the question.
So let's see how here--
and we have another 20 minutes.
So here, this give you a sense about how this is working,
doing kind of a simulation.
So here is lock acquire.
We have a release.
This is a code.
And we have two threads executing the code,
thread A and thread B. Each of them is doing lock acquire.
Go to the critical section, lock release.
And let's say thread A acquired it.
It is able to the interrupt.
Sorry.
The value--
In this particular case, no one has a critical section.
This is the first thread A, which look, execute, acquire.
There is no one using the critical section, so the value is zero.
Increments the value to one, which means that it acquires a lock and it enables the interrupts.
And now you are in critical section.
This is what happened.
At the same time, let's assume that while you are in a critical section, thread B is
starting to be executed.
Again, while you are in a critical section, the interrupts are enabled.
So thread B is going to start running.
Thread A in the meantime, it's in the ready queue.
This is just context switching, traditional context switching.
You do the lock acquire, execute lock acquire.
But now you look and what you can see is the value is one because the lock is acquired
by thread A. You cannot acquire the lock.
A bead cannot acquire the lock as well.
So you go to sleep.
So you are going straight, it's going to be waiting.
It's going to be on the wait queue.
And now you are going to start executing thread A because it's ready to execute and this thread
B went to sleep and thread B is going to sleep, is going to voluntarily release the CPU.
So the kernel is going to start executing thread A, resuming the execution of thread
A in the critical section.
Critical section ends and then is releasing the lock.
And now if anyone waits on the waiting queue, is anyone waiting on the waiting queue?
Yes, it's thread B. So thread B is placed on the ready queue, from the waiting queue
on the ready queue.
And now you enable the interrupts.
You are done.
So thread B is ready to execute.
And then next time you are going to execute thread B. And thread B executes, acquires
the locks, and continue and enter the critical section.
So please go and try to go carefully through this example.
Any questions?
OK.
So what is the problem?
So is this working?
Yes, it's working.
But there are several issues.
You cannot give lock implementation to users.
They are going to make mistakes.
And now, OK, you can solve that by saying the kernel can do it.
And that's a very valid answer.
But the other problem, especially with the interrupts, is that it doesn't work well on
multiprocessors.
You have multiple cores which execute in parallel.
And all cores can access the memory.
So therefore, the value of the lock.
So what you need when you need to disable the interrupts, you need to disable interrupts
on all the cores.
You need to send messages between cores to disable interrupts or enable interrupts, which
is very expensive.
The alternative to this is to have atomic instructions.
And typically what they do is they read a value and write a value atomically.
So instead, load and stores, only reading a value is atomic and writing a value is atomic.
But this adds another element.
The read, you can have a read and write, which is all atomic, like one operation.
And these are great.
They are working both on a processor and multiprocessors.
And yeah, they are quite simple.
And here are a few of them.
The first one is test and set.
So what is it doing?
Test and set read a value on the particular memory, the value at a particular address,
and returns it, and also at the same time, set it to one.
So reading the value, setting it to one, and returning the previous value, the value before
I set one, original value, is atomic.
That's it.
That's atomic instruction.
So you see there are multiple operation in this which are in this atomic instruction.
And it's a swap.
And a swap is basically what is doing.
Right?
You give, you get a value.
You put a value in a register.
And that value put in the register is going to be swapped with the value at a particular
address.
OK?
This is what it is.
So you give a value in a register which is going to be swapped with a value at a particular
address.
And finally, it's compare and swap.
This is a little bit more complicated.
You give two registers here.
And if the memory address is still equal with register one, you put the memory address in
the memory value in register two.
Otherwise, you don't change the memory.
And these are-- x86, obviously, it's Intel.
6800 was a very popular chip, Motorola chip, which was the chip used by Apple, early Apple,
and Macintosh computers.
And testing said it's actually in most architectures today.
OK?
So here is an example about how to use compare and swap.
And this is about how you are going to use to insert atomically a new element as a head
of a cube.
OK?
This is what you want to do.
This is n-cube operation.
So insert a new element as the head of the cube.
So here, what you do it.
First of all, you have a while.
Do you see?
Do until.
Right?
It's a loop.
OK?
And in the condition to exit from this loop, you compare and swap R1 and object.
Right?
Object is the object identifier.
R1, you can see, is a root address.
OK?
So it's the original root.
Right?
So what happens here is basically you are going to wait until-- so what you do here,
you set the root to the new object.
OK?
And then you are waiting until the root is pointing-- sorry.
What you do is the following thing.
You set the next object to point to the first element in the cube, this one.
OK?
This is what you do.
Right?
So this is you get the pointer from the root, which is a pointer to the first element in
the cube.
Then you set the next-- the object to point to the-- the new object to point to the old
first object in the cube.
And then you are going to use a compare and swap to move the pointer of the root to the
new object.
And you wait until that is done.
OK?
So that's what happens here.
Now how we implement log-switch test and test, test and set, is very easy.
Acquire, you just-- you set up the value to 0 here.
And acquire, it's-- you just wait for test and set to be 1.
Right?
time.
and then release value, release, you just set value to zero.
Okay?
So what happens here?
Remember what does test_nset is doing?
The test_nset is going to read,
to return the value
and set it to one in one instruction.
If the value is zero,
you return the value to while,
so while is going to exit,
and set value to one.
So it's great.
So lock is not busy, you acquire the lock.
If the lock is busy, so value will be one,
you are going to set the value to one,
it's already one, so nothing will happen,
but you return one.
So you are going to be stuck in the while loop
until the release is going to be executed
and the value is set to zero.
Right?
So it's quite elegant, right?
Obviously the problem here,
you have the while, you do the while in the program, right?
So very inefficient.
Right?
So you don't want to do that.
But this is a correct implementation,
very simple implementation.
So you see how test_nset allows us
a very simple implementation of locks.
Right?
And again, the test_nset, very easy to remember.
You do two things, return the value and set is to one.
That's all.
Okay, so the problem is busy waiting.
Of course, busy waiting, again,
it's a correct implementation.
The machine can still receive interrupts,
the user code can still use a lock,
work on multiprocessors, all positives,
but of course you don't want this busy waiting.
It's inefficient,
also can result in what we call priority inversion.
Right?
If the busy waiting thread has a higher priority
than the thread holding the lock.
Right?
So this is another way to think about it.
Okay.
Oops.
Another way to think about it is like,
you have two threads and one has higher priorities
than the other one.
Higher priority is going to be always executed
before the other one, the one with the low priority.
And now the thread with the low priority
is going to have the lock.
If the thread with the lower priority has a lock,
the thread with the higher priority will be stuck
because it's going to be stuck in the while loop.
And the thread with the lower priority cannot execute
because the thread with the higher priority,
but because the thread with the lower priority
cannot execute, it cannot exit the critical section,
it cannot release a lock.
So this is priority inversion.
And this has happened in many cases.
So that's a problem, right?
And so we really want,
because we don't want us to, you know,
this busy waiting, we need to find another solution.
And in general, when you have the homework problem
or exam solution, unless otherwise specified,
you should avoid busy waiting.
Okay?
So now let's see for the next couple of minutes,
think about maybe better locks using test and set.
So the question, can we use test and set
to implement locks without busy waiting?
And this answer here, we cannot,
but we can minimize the busy waiting section.
And again, the solution here is like with,
if you remember with interrupts,
we use a lock to implement a lock in some sense.
So the lock we want to implement is value,
is called value, okay?
And then what we do, we protect the critical section
of the acquire and release,
the critical section being the one which modifies a lock,
which is value, by a test and set.
Okay?
So use a test and set to implement
and protect those critical sections,
you know, acquire and release.
So the solution is very simple.
We have defined another variable, which is called guard.
This ensures a mutual exclusion
for these critical sections,
which are in the acquire and release, okay?
And while we initialize to zero, so while guard,
if guard is zero, then you are going to,
you acquire the lock, so while will exit, right?
Because remember, testing set returns a current value
of guard that is zero and set is one.
So you exit the while loop and then you set up the value.
Right? What do you know?
And the release is the same.
You, again, you protect the critical section
by test and set.
And then here you have the same problem,
like with release interrupts.
When you go to sleep, you also need to set your guard to zero
then when you need to set up it up, right?
But this will be much easier.
Okay?
So, and when sleep has to be set up,
sleep has to be sure to reset the guard variable, right?
So, and we are going to end up here, this lecture.
On this note, we are going to continue next time.
And you should think a little bit about this code.
And there is a question here.
Why, oops, let me see.
(silence)
Okay, I'm going to stop here because for some reason
I lost my pointer.
So I cannot see my pointer on the screen.
So there is a question at the end of the previous slide.
Please think about it until the next time
without looking at the next slides.
And there is, yeah, there is a question here.
If while test and set, so we are, the lecture it's done.
I am going to try to ask the last question,
which was on the chat and we'll meet next time.
So for people who want to hear the answer can stick around.
And the question here is that from Michael
it's while test and set while you yield critical section
and then while is zero, and then you set up all to zero.
(silence)
Yeah.
I think that
that should work.
So, yeah.
If you, that should work.
That should work.
The problem here is all that if you yield
then you are still going, you yield the processor.
You are still going to be woken up
before the lock it's available.
Okay. So for instance, you again, it's like you go,
you yield, you yield the processor for another thread.
That thread can execute.
It may not be necessary.
The thread who has a lock, when that thread finishes
when a time quanta finishes,
you are going to be all kind of game and so forth.
So it's still not as efficient.
It's better than just doing busy wait,
but it's not as good as putting the thread on the wait queue
and being woken up only when the lock was released.
In this case, you are going to be woken up multiple times.
Okay. So with that, I'll see you next time.
Thanks everyone.
(silence)
Thank you.
.