Hello everyone. So welcome to the nice lecture. So this lecture, it's the content of this
lecture, it's included in your first midterm. And so that's quite important. And it's also
a very important lecture for your future homeworks and projects.
So, and we are going to continue our discussion about abstraction to implement critical sections
and synchronization between processes. And if you remember, last time we discussed that one of the
main abstraction which would make it easier to implement critical sections exclusion from
critical sections. So only one thread should be active in a critical section at a given time,
or LOBS. And we discussed the implementation of LOBS using interrupts. And then we said there
are some disadvantages of using interrupts and some dangers. And then we discuss about then using
atomic operation, which are more sophisticated than load and store to implement these LOBS.
And one of them, it will be like test and set. If you remember the test and set,
it takes a value and maintains a local variable. Think about test and set, maintains a local
variable. And the atomic operation is that taking a value, updating the local variable is a new
value, and then returning the previous value of the local variable. That's pretty much it.
And this is an implementation, again, we discussed last time of a lock acquire and lock release,
and using test and set. And basically, you test and set here also to implement
mutual exclusion of operating of the value, the value of the lock. So the value of the lock,
whether it is busy or free, determine whether you can enter or not in the critical section
of the program of the user. And now we have a second, we use test and set for a second smaller
critical section, which is only concerned of updating the lock value to be zero free.
And if you remember, all this synchronization primitives involves weight. And the reason for
that is because it's fundamental, because if you have two threads which wants to enter in the same
critical section, you can only allow one thread to enter in the critical section. And therefore,
the other thread has nothing else to do but wait for the first thread to finish.
So that's why waiting is fundamental. And the other thing to remember, if you wait,
one way to wait and it's easy to implement is to do busy waiting. You constantly check whether the
critical section is free, whether you can acquire the lock. But of course, this consumes the CPU
cycles without doing any useful work. So therefore, waiting what you want to, the best way
to implement waiting and the preferred way is to go to sleep. So to put the thread on the waiting queue
and then to be woken up when the previous thread exceeds the critical section.
Okay. So this is what you see here. If the value is busy, so if someone acquired the lock
and has acquired the lock, it's in the critical section, you put the thread on the wait queue,
and then you go to sleep, and then you reset this guard, which is again, this guard, it's about,
basically, you freeze a lock for the critical section, which is concerned with updating the busy
value. Okay. And whilst the value is busy, you set the value to be this,
you acquire the lock, and then you again set guard to zero. So therefore, you are
going to allow another thread to look and to read the lock value and modify it.
Okay. Any questions here?
Okay. So not again that we have the same discussion, we had the same discussion like
in the case of when using interrupt to implement acquire and release, and that is when we are going
to set the guard to zero. That is when you are going to disable the interrupts. And this needs
to be done. You cannot do before sleep, you cannot do before the thread on wait queue. Just remember,
why is that? You can look at the last lecture. So you need to do in some sense after, but then after
the thread itself, which call acquire cannot do it because it's sleeping. Okay. So that has to be
done either by the operating system or by the next thread, which is going to be scheduled to reset
the guard. Okay. So, and here it's a simple example. Oh, gosh. Ah, this is a great question.
So one question here is whether the guard and value will be on the heap. Yes, they're going
to be on, they're going to be a global variables. So yeah. So everyone can access them.
Okay. So now we've seen two implementations actually of acquire and release logs. And
one is using interrupts and the other one using test and set. And this basically shows is to show
you that actually the logic is very, very similar. And you can think about while test and set,
it's similarly disabled interrupts and enabling and resetting guard to zero is like enabling
interrupts. Okay. And this is again, the code for, we went over last lecture about implementing
acquire and release by disabling and enabling the interrupts. Okay. And if you remember also what we
did last time, when I talk about locks, we did in two stages. First of all, we said, we gave this
very trivial implementation of the locks. Acquire, you disable the interrupts. Why disable the
interrupts? Because you don't want new threads to interrupt you, right? While you are in
the critical section, right? And then the release is enabling the interrupts. But of course,
this was very dangerous because if you call at the user level, acquire and disable interrupts,
and you have a very long critical section or you make a mistake and you have an infinite
while loop in the critical section, then your computer will hack. Okay. You can do anything
about it. The only thing probably is power off, power on. Right? So therefore, the more
sophisticated implementation was to use disable and enable interrupts only for updating the value
of the lock. So now you have a value of the lock, which set to zero and use disable and enable
interrupts to update that value, right? Or to read that value. Okay. So now, yes, you still use
disable and enable interrupts, but now it's very short. The critical section is very short and is
going to finish very fast. Right? So, and if you look again, if you look now at the same example,
but now implementing acquire and release using test and set, we went again through two iterations.
The first iteration was very simple that while test and set value, so you are going, the value
is a lock value. So while the value, this is why the value is one, right? Again, the test and set
here, if value is one, it's going to return the previous value of the internal variable of test
and set, and then set that variable to the new value. Right? So if it's the previous one was zero,
return zero means there's a lock it's acquired, but now you set one. So next time when someone
tries the value is one, the internal variable is one. So the internal variables will not change and
this test and set returns one.
once you are going to be stuck in the while loop.
But it's again, the problem with this one,
and the release is simple, you set the value to zero.
But, and the problem with this one,
remember that this while loop,
it's again, it's like, it's busy waiting,
which we discussed that we want to wait.
We want to, sorry, it's busy waiting,
which you remember we want to avoid.
So again, in this case, we went to the second iteration,
which we just also presented again,
earlier in the lecture, today's lecture,
and you use the test and set
only to protect the critical sections,
which are concerned with updating the value of the lock.
And now again, this is much shorter critical section.
So the test and set will be,
we'll wait only for very short time.
And now instead of like in this case, you're waiting,
you are waiting as a previous case,
you are waiting as long as someone is in the critical
section to busy waiting.
So once you have the CPU cycles, in this case,
in the more refined iteration,
you are going to put the thread,
which is waiting on the wait queue, right?
So there is no busy waiting.
Okay.
Any questions here?
So, so where we are going again, we synchronization.
So let's see what we've done.
We look at the, on the hardware support,
low stores, disable interrupts,
test and set and compare and swap.
These are similar for test and set and compare and swap.
They are much more useful than load and store.
And we saw how you can use these to implement locks.
And also we discussed abstraction about semaphores.
And yeah, and then next also later,
we are going to talk about monitors.
And it's again, the higher level,
the abstraction is easier will be for the programs,
for the application to implement mutual exclusion
and critical sections.
And so next we are going to go
and talk more about the abstraction.
Let's talk again about semaphores, right?
And if you remember, just to remind you,
the semaphores you have,
they are a little bit more sophisticated than locks.
A lock can have only two values, zero or one or busy and free.
With semaphores is like a counter, right?
The special counter, right?
It's like you have a primitive,
which increments the semaphore
and a primitive which decrements the semaphore.
And if semaphore is zero, then you are going to wait, right?
You are very much, you are waiting for a lock,
which is busy, okay?
So if you remember, so that's provides you a little bit more,
more, more,
a little bit more power.
And therefore it also gives you more,
if it gives you more functionality,
you can implement with the semaphore,
both critical sections,
but you also implement a mutual exclusion,
but you also implement scheduling constraints,
basically telling, signaling one process
from another process or a thread from another thread.
And if you remember the example we gave last time
about this was about, if you remember,
it was about implementing the thread join,
waiting the thread who launches,
create another thread waiting for the new create,
for the creative thread to finish, okay?
It's okay.
So now we are going to move from locks and semaphores
to a new abstraction, which is called monitors.
And monitors are better, are simply more powerful.
And the main idea is to split between
and supporting explicitly these two functionality
about mutual exclusion and scheduling constraints.
And you use locks for mutual exclusion
and what are called condition variable
for scheduling constraints, right?
So a monitor, it's a lock
and a zero or more conditional variable
for managing concurrent access to share data, okay?
And we'll talk more about that.
Some languages provide this natively
and most of the others,
you can use lock and conditionals variables
as a distinct abstractions.
So I'm going again, if you have any questions, let me know.
This is again, so these lectures,
the past lecture and these lectures
are not very easy to follow
because they are about concurrency,
are about programs which execute concurrently.
And like we discussed last time,
we as humans are not very used about handling many things
which happen at the same time.
We are much better in sequentializing things.
So it's perfectly fine,
if you feel this is a little bit more challenging,
but at the same time, this also means
that you should spend a little bit more time
to try to understand deeply what's happening here, okay?
So again, some languages provide monitors
and let's see what is a conditional variables.
So conditional variables, what is a conditional variable?
It's a queue of threads waiting for something
inside a critical section to happen, okay?
So, and the nice thing about the critical section,
send the conditional, sorry,
nice thing about the monitors and condition variables,
is conditional variables allow sleeping
inside the critical section,
by atomically releasing the lock at a time we go to sleep.
Okay, so what I mean by that, here is what I mean.
Okay, remember about this slide,
I'll go soon, you know, in again in presentation mode.
Here, it's again, if you try to acquire the lock
and the lock is busy, so the value is one,
you have to go to sleep.
And what we want, we want this to,
how we want this to happen is to put the thread
in the waiting queue.
But when you put the set of the waiting queue,
you need also to resell the guard, right?
To let other threads enter the critical section
to look at the value and maybe to modify the value, right?
So now the sleep and the guard
have to happen at the same time, okay?
So they need to be atomic.
And well, monitors provide,
and conditional variables for monitors,
provide you this atomicity between the threads going to sleep
and giving up, releasing the lock,
because guard is equal to zero,
release a lock associated with a guard atomically.
You don't need to worry about that.
That's what conditional variables in monitors
are going to do for you.
And that's why they are very useful.
Okay?
And here are the operations.
The operation, you wait for the lock, okay?
Which you can,
you can atomically, this is going to,
the operation is going to atomically release a lock
and go to sleep.
And you can require the lock later.
We'll have a few examples to make it more understandable.
And then you have signals.
You remember that one of the use of the semaphore
was to signal when a thread won an event,
right between two threads, right?
So now you have a very primitive, which is called,
you know, makes a lot of sense, a name is signal.
And you have also something which is called broadcast.
So the signal is waking a thread,
which is waiting for some particular event to happen.
Broadcast is waking multiple waiters,
all the waiters which wait for that event.
Signal, if there are multiple waiters,
it's going to wake only one.
And that's non-deterministic.
You know, you don't know which one is going to be waken up.
And in many cases, you don't care.
Broadcast wakes all of them, okay?
Okay, now, when you do operation
on the condition variables,
of course you need to own the lock, right?
Because this is in critical section.
This is one way to represent it.
The monitors, so X and Y are conditional variables.
Each of them is associated a Q.
And you have a lock which provides a mutual exclusion
with the shared data in this monitor.
The conditional variables are shared data.
But it's again, one of the main advantage,
you are allowed to wait in the critical section.
And this is not allowed for semaphores,
which makes the semaphores very much harder to use.
So now it's again, let's see,
and we are going to have a lot of examples.
So we give you a better sense about how these monitors,
how you use the monitors.
And also we are going to talk about how they are implemented.
So hopefully by the end of this lectures,
you are going to have a pretty good feeling about monitors.
So here is an infinite queue, synchronized queue.
You have producer, consumer.
It's infinite in the sense that the producer
can put any numbers of items in the queue, right?
The queue is infinite, right?
So how do you do it?
The producer is like you acquire the lock,
and release the lock.
You have a buffer lock.
And the consumer also acquires the lock
and release the lock, right?
And this is in order to protect the critical sections,
which are operating on the queue, right?
You don't want a producer and the consumer
to operate on the queue at the same time,
because inserting, adding a new element to the queue,
and removing an element from the queue
are not atomic operations.
And therefore bad things can happen
while you both of them are manipulating the pointers, right?
To insert or remove an element from the queue, okay?
And now you can use these condition variables,
like buff, you know, CV, in order to signal.
The producer, that's basically what it says.
The buff CV is a way for the producer
to signal the consumer that there are elements in the buffer,
in the queue, right?
So this is what it is.
You signal it.
And then what do you do from, in the consumer?
While it's empty, so look for the queue whether it's empty.
Right, it's in the critical section.
So it's fair to look at the queue,
because no one else will modify the queue
while you are in the critical section to operate on the queue.
And then you call this condition, wait.
So you're waiting for the signal for buff CV.
And you also, you see, this is the first argument
of condition wait.
And the second argument is buff lock.
Why is that?
Because if the queue is empty, right, this is true.
So this in condition wait, and what you are going to do
is basically you are going to put the thread to sleep
and you need to release a lock, right?
This basically tells the condition wait to release the lock
once the thread is put to sleep.
Remember, we want here to have atomic operation,
sleep the sleep and releasing the buffer
should be an atomic operation.
Aaron has a question here.
If you use a broadcast, it will create a race condition.
Not necessary, not necessary.
We'll see that in an example, right?
Because still, you can wake up all the waiters,
but only if all the waiters want to go
to the same critical section,
still only one will succeed, okay?
And the other one will go back to wait.
So you're still going to be okay, okay?
So, oh, sorry, okay.
Okay, so this is basically what happened here.
So now, and I think this was a question last time.
I don't remember who asked that question.
It was great question about what you remember
if you go to, I think was in the context of test on set,
why do you use while and not if?
It's a similar thing here and we'll explain why
and what is the difference.
And the problem here is that, you know,
if you look at this piece of code,
will you just the consumer wait for the queue
to be non-empty to have elements in order to be queue,
a new element from the queue, it has a while, right?
And the natural question you can ask, look, why, why?
Because the thread is going to sleep, right?
So why do you do that?
And it's true that it's a good question.
Let me start with that, right?
Okay, you see that why should I do the while?
Because it's again, it's like the thread is going to sleep
and it's going to be woken up
if another thread exceeds the critical section, right?
So I should test again.
And the answer here is that
it depends on the implementation, okay?
You can actually, depending on the implementation,
you can replace while with if, and that will be correct.
Okay?
So, and there are two implementations.
One in which you need to put while,
you have to have while, and the other one,
you need to have, you can use if.
The first one which requires you to have while
is called Mesa style, right?
And because it was implemented
in Xerox Spark Mesa operating system.
And this is what most operating system are using.
The one in which you can use if
is Hoare style implementation.
This is a British logician, Tony Hoare.
And in this case, you can use if, okay?
So let's see how Hoare monitors.
So this is a one you can use if, how they are implemented.
So here is how it's implemented.
You have acquire on both sides,
and let's say the first, you know,
sorry, so in both cases,
you obviously you protect the critical sections
by a buff lock, and the code on the left hand side
is going to send a signal.
And as a result of the signal,
the thread which are waiting on this conditional variable,
buff CV is going to wake up, right?
So the sled on the left is going to send a signal,
and the code on the right is going to be of a sled,
which is going to be open up by this signal, okay?
So let's see what happens.
So it's Hoare, what happens when you execute this signal,
you automatically release a lock, the buff lock here,
and the CPU, and you schedule immediately the sled,
which is waiting for the buff CV conditional variable.
You are going to execute it,
and then at the end, you are going to release the lock,
and then you go back and continue to execute
the first thread, which signal the second one, right?
And that's what it is, right?
So this is the implementation.
Now, so this seems like good, right?
It's basically in the signal.
When I signal someone, I stop,
I give the lock to the thread which is waiting,
and the operating system will schedule that thread
to execute, exit the critical section,
and after that, I get the control back, okay?
This is correct.
What is the problem?
The problem here is it's a little bit harder to implement
and may lead to a lot of context switches.
Furthermore, as you'll see
from the next Mesa-style implementation,
it's not really necessary.
And here it's about Mesa implementation.
With a Mesa implementation, after you signal,
you do not give the control.
To the thread waiting for a condition variable.
Instead, what you do, you just take that thread,
waiting on the conditional variable,
and you put it, move it from the waiting queue
to the ready queue.
It's ready to execute.
And then you continue, okay?
And eventually later when you are done,
you are going to schedule the operating system,
is going to schedule the thread,
which is now in the ready queue.
Okay?
Sometimes later.
But you see now, so what is,
but we see now that now you need to check
this condition again, this empty queue.
Why?
Because in the meantime, there can be another between,
in the meantime, you can.
have a race condition and another thread comes and wants to acquire the lock because it's free,
and now you are going to have two threads on the ready queue which want to enter the
same critical section. So that is not good. So that's kind of the problem.
But by doing so, you are going to have less context switches. In this case, you have
the first thread finishes exiting the critical section, then you are going to,
after that you are going to execute the second thread. So it's one context switch. In the
previous case, you have one context switch going from the signaling thread to the thread which is
waiting and back. So at least you have two. Okay, any questions?
So let's look now at our buffer queue example and use
a more, and now we are using two condition variables for producer and the consumer. Let
me give you the code. And we are also looking now is bounded buffer. So in previous case,
we use only one condition variable and it was unbounded buffer, infinite buffer size.
Here is bounded. Okay, so how do you have two variables? You can check whether the buffer is
full or empty. And then if the buffer is full, while the buffer is full, obviously, the producer
waits. Otherwise, you enqueue an item in the buffer and you signal the consumer because now
the buffer is no longer empty and the consumer can drain, can take that element from the buffer.
Okay, and the consumer is the same. If the buffer was, if the buffer is empty,
you can do anything. There is no item you can take from the buffer.
Okay, if the buffer is not empty, you dequeue it and you signal a producer
that there is at least one free slot in the buffer, you can insert a new item.
So this is how this is work. Okay.
Any questions?
So you see that fundamentally what you do is condition variable here is like we mentioned
earlier is to signal between threads when an event occurs. In this particular case,
the producer signal to consumer when it's inserted an element in the buffer
and the consumer signals to the producer when it removed an element from the buffer.
So now the producer knows that for sure it can add a new element to the buffer.
Also, again, I want to reiterate that the thread when it's waiting, it doesn't do busy waiting,
it's sleeping. The condition variable, the semantics there or conduit is to take that thread,
put it on the wait queue and release the lock to the critical section, buff lock.
Okay, can you construct monitors from semaphores?
The locking aspect, it's easy, remember? You can use a semaphore which has only two values
and the wait is basically decrementing the semaphore. If it's one, you initialize
semaphore to one. If it's one, you acquire the lock and it's zero. If someone else thread comes
and want to decrement it, then it cannot and it has to wait because you need to wait for
the someone else to increment the semaphore back to one. This will be the signal.
But the biggest problem here is that the wait, if you do that while you are in a critical section
and you have to do that to be in the critical section, then you are going to wait and you are
not going to release a lock. So that's the key. The monitors on the condition variable, condition
weight, that function is releasing the lock atomically when you go to sleep.
Are this working? What about this one? You release a lock immediately, you're after wait.
This will not work. And one of the reasons the condition variables have no history in the sense
that I always signal, if I signal you five times, you are going to be woken only once.
But semaphores have history. Let me see.
Yes, so this is exactly what I was saying. It's a great question, Thayu. So the question is,
it is half full. If the buffer is half full, will the condition variable still going to signal
in the either case? Absolutely. That's exactly what we mean here. The condition variable has no
history. Yes, you are going to be signaled. And in that case, a signal doesn't mean anything because
you may not, you know, if you signal and there is no thread on waiting, then nothing will happen.
Very good question.
And, and yes, this is exactly what I said, if the thread signals and no one is waiting,
there is no operation, there is no op. If a sled later waits, then it's a problem right now here,
because it's again, if that happens, then it's going to,
you wait with a lock and the other thread cannot increment the semaphore, which correspond to the
lock. So you are going to be, to be stuck. Okay, anyway, so there are a bunch of questions here,
and I invite you to answer the questions. And I just want to, as an exercise for you,
and you may be very well get some problem like this one and asking you these questions.
But instead, instead, because we are, you know, running a little bit out of time,
I want to go to the next part of the lecture, which is extremely important part of the lecture.
And this is about reader and writer problem. Okay, let me just see.
Okay, let me just, I think I don't have the announcement before going there.
Let me do verbally and I'm going to add the slide about the announcement to the lecture right after,
the lecture slide right after the lecture. So basically, the most important thing
is that obviously next week, you are going to, we are going to be doing a lot of work
and we are going to have the first meetup, and it will be between seven and nine on Wednesday.
Okay. And we are going to have also a session for between seven and nine p.m. on Monday
for the meetup. So you can come and ask any questions you have.
And, you know, this is pretty much it. We are going to provide more
information as we go close to the meetup. But if you have now any questions, let me know.
Okay. So now this is a more complex problem, and this will illustrate very clearly the use of
monitors. Okay, so here is a problem. The problem is about accessing a database,
which is shared by multiple people. So you have a bunch, can have a bunch of people who want to
write and a bunch of people who want to read to the database. And these writes and read operations
happen concurrently.
and they modify the same data.
So how you are going to implement it?
One thing is to use a lock for the entire database.
You read or write, acquire the lock,
you do your job and release the lock.
So is that sufficient?
(silence)
That's a question for you.
Yes, it is sufficient, meaning that it's correct,
but it can be very slow, right?
I mean, if you think about fundamentally,
give me two examples why this is inefficient.
It's exactly, Aaron.
Aaron gave a great answer.
So basically, for instance,
if people only read from the database,
there is no need to lock it because nothing will change.
Okay?
Also, there are other reasons we are going to discuss later,
but even if you have writes,
then the writes can be different records.
They don't need to wait after each other.
We are not going to solve this problem here.
We are going to solve the first problem on multiple readers.
We should allow them to read the database
if there are no writers.
Read writers, yeah.
Okay?
Very good.
So let's see what you want from the solution.
Readers can access database when there are no writers.
It's exactly like we said.
If there are no writers, no value will change.
So therefore, any number of readers can read concurrently.
Writers can access database.
A writer can access a database
when there is no reader reading
and no other writer modifying the database.
And finally, we have some state variables
and we want only one thread to modify them at a given time.
Right?
This is, so this is the basic solution.
It's a structure.
For the reader, you wait until there are no writers,
access a database, check out,
and wake up waiting writers.
And the writer wait until there are no active readers
or writers, access database,
and then you check out and you wake up
other waiting readers or writers.
Right?
So let me ask you this question.
You see here, there is some asymmetry
and some asymmetry is derived from our constraints.
Right?
If a reader, it doesn't need to wait
until there are no other readers
because it doesn't conflict with other readers.
It can only conflict with writers.
So that's why you wait until no writers.
The writers is going to conflict both with the readers
and writers because if a reader is going to read the data
while the writer changing the data,
it can read, the reader can read garbage.
But then there is another asymmetry.
When a writer is done,
is going to wake up readers and writers,
while when the reader is done,
it's only try to wake up writers.
Why this asymmetry?
Why do you think?
Why do you think the reader
is not just waiting as the readers,
waking up as the readers?
(silence)
Very good.
The readers are all concurrent
so that it should be no as any other reader wake up.
Very good. Okay.
So let's move on.
So how do we implement this with our monitor?
It's a beautiful abstraction we just learned about.
All right.
So you see, wake up a waiting writer
and wake up waiting readers or writers.
These are, what are these?
You can implement them condition variables.
It's like signals and waiting
on that condition variable.
Okay.
So you have two condition variables.
Okay to read, okay to write.
And then what are the state variables?
Well, the number of active readers,
number of active writers.
How many active writers can have at a given time?
One, right?
Remember, we cannot have two writers at the same time.
Then you have the number of waiting readers.
Are there readers which are waiting to read?
And the number of waiting writers.
When do you have readers waiting?
Yes. When there is one active writer.
Very good.
So let's write the code for the reader.
So here it now look like.
Acquire lock, release lock.
Because within this code
manipulates the state variables.
Okay.
It's a reader.
So I am looking if there are no active writers
or waiting writers.
Right?
So if there are, is there active writers
and waiting writers, then you wait.
You implement the number of waiting readers
because now is myself.
I'm going to wait.
And then I'm going to wait on the condition variables.
Okay to read.
And I need to wait until it's okay for me to read.
And release a lock.
Now, why I'm doing here, I am waiting for both.
Active writers is normal, right?
I cannot read on someone who is writing.
But why I'm waiting also for waiting writers?
Because this means that I'm going to wait for other writers
to write before me, before I can read.
Why is that?
Why do you think it's that?
So a few people say we don't read garbage
or we don't read what are our results.
But why is that?
Because why would we do that?
Because in that case, you can have,
so here is what can happen.
You have a bunch of readers, no writers in the system.
And now I have a writer who wants to write.
And that writer has to wait
for the current readers to complete.
And in the meantime, I have another reader
which wants to read.
And I'm not going to let this reader read the database
together with the other readers before the writer
is scheduled to write and update the database.
Okay.
So it won't result in wrong results, right?
What the reason you do this, right?
So, but it is fundamentally what this gives.
It gives priority to the waiting writers, right?
That what happens, right?
And why do we do give priority to the waiting writers?
Is the reason was, you know, the answer is correct
is from Akshay is that you want to read the most up to date.
to read the most up-to-date.
information. Otherwise, you can starve writers. If you always have readers coming in, you
will never update the database. Before a reader terminates, finishes, you have another reader.
You are going to schedule that reader and so forth. So the writer will not be able to
be scheduled. OK, sounds good. So anyway, so after if there is no active writers or
waiting writers, then you are going to increment the number of active readers, because now
you are becoming you are allowed to read. So you are active reader and you release a
lock. You access the database, it's read only, right? And then after you are done, you acquire
the lock and to manipulate the state variables and you decrement the active readers because
I'm done. And now what do I need to do? Well, what I need to do is to wait, wake up threads
which may wait. For instance, to write to the database. So here, if active readers is
zero. And there are waiting writers. Then I'm going to send a signal OK to write. OK.
Simon has a great question here. What if new writers are coming all the time? When do you
get to read if you keep waiting for all writers to finish? That's correct. OK. So in this
particular case, you know, yeah, if writers come up all the time, you are not going to
get a chance to read. In practice, you need to be a little bit more sophisticated. But
that's a good point.
So this is one question here is why do you want why you release locks there? Why don't
you release a lock all the way to the end? Why is not access database part of the critical
section here? Yes, so any readers can get the lock. Right. You don't change the state
variables. The locks are for changing the state variables. And in this particular case,
you also want all the readers. If they are only active readers in the system. If they
are only that's in the system, you want them to read concurrently. Right. Very good answers.
Now let's see the code for the writer. It's very similar. Right. You acquire the lock
and now you check whether you can write. And what is that is there? There should be no
active readers. You cannot write while you have readers reading the data, manipulating
the state variables. And obviously you cannot have writers, active writers. You don't if
you have any of those, you go to wait and you wait on the conditional variable. OK,
to write because you are a writer. If not, you are going to increment active writers
because now you are an active writer. Release a lock. You access a database read write.
And then once you are done, you acquire the lock again to manipulate the state variables
to decrement the number of active writers, because now you are no longer writing. And
then you check if the number of if there are still waiting writers, you are going to wake
up. One of those by sending signal. And now, if that's not the case and the number of waiting
writers is zero. But there are waiting readers. Then you send a broadcast. OK, to read. So
now you can you see that use of the broadcast. You are going to wake up all the readers.
Because all the readers can read at the same time. Concurrent. OK. OK, let me ask this
answer this question. Does the question is, does there exist some situations that the
reader is waiting to read some intermediate state while some writer joins the wait? Yes,
definitely. Yeah, but the writer is not going to be able to modify that state. So we are
going to be fine.
Oh, sorry. So basically, you say if I read. Yes. So the reader is already waiting. And
now, yes, a new writer joins the wait. Yes, so that's valid. And in that particular case,
the writer will be prioritized over the reader. But it's again, at a given time, only one reader
and only one writer can manipulate the state variables. So it should be fine. OK, we discussed
why giving the priority to writers earlier on. OK, so now. Let's do the following we
are going to in order to. You know, get. Hopefully, you better understand what's happening here.
Let's go through a simulation. OK. So. Let's see, let's assume the following sequence of
operators operations. We have three writers and one writer, a series of three readers
are one or two and three and one writer. OK, so first to get the first reader, the second,
the second reader, then the writer and then the third reader. Initially, all the state
variables are set to zero. So let's see what happens. R1 comes along. There are no waiting
states, there are no other states in the system. So let's see what happens. It acquires a lock.
Check whether there is an active writer or a waiting writer. Both of these variables
are zero. None of them, none of such state in the system. So you exit the while loop.
And R1 can start reading. You increment the active reader variable. You read the lock.
OK, we know that why. You access the database. And let's say that while you are accessing
the database. R2 comes along. OK. Remember, now the number of active readers, it's one
because R1 is still accessing the database. So what is R1, R2 doing? Obviously, it's going
to execute the same code. It's acquiring the lock. Now it's checking whether it's an active
writer or a waiting writer. None of this, none such thread is in the system. So again,
you skip the while loop and increment the number of active writers. Release the lock
and you access the database. So now both R1 and R2 are accessing the database. The number
of active writers is two. All the other state variables are zero. OK. So now it's again,
Assume that it does take a while to access database.
And assume that during this time, now when W, the writer,
the writer comes along, W1.
So what is that?
The writer is going to execute the writer code.
So it acquires a lock.
And now it looks at active writers and active readers
in the system.
There are two active readers, now active writers.
Still, because there are two active readers,
the writer cannot proceed.
So what do you do?
You increment the number of waiting writers,
because now you have to wait.
And you wait on OK to write condition variable,
and you release a lock.
So W1 cannot start because of readers.
Finally, R3 comes along.
Acquires a lock.
And now it checks whether there are active writers or waiting
writers.
There are no active writers, but there is one waiting writers,
W1.
So therefore, the new reader, R3, has to wait.
So increment waiting readers now by one.
And you are going to wait for the condition variable OK to read.
And you release a lock.
Any questions here?
Is that clear so far?
[AUDIO OUT]
OK, so let's go with our simulation.
So status rate is time.
R1 and R2 are still reading.
W and R3 are waiting.
OK?
So let's say R2 finishes.
R1, still accessing database, W1 and R3 are still waiting.
So R2 is going to acquire the lock
to update the state variables.
In particular, to update the number of active readers now
is less to decrement it, because R2 finishes.
And now it's looking whether the active--
whether it can wake up any threat.
And he's looking whether there are active readers,
if there are no active readers, and there are waiting writers.
OK?
So he's looking for that.
And then the condition is false, because there are still
active readers.
This is R1.
So then you release the lock.
And R1 now is done.
OK?
Now let's say R1 finishes--
sorry, R2 is done.
Right?
Now say R1 finishes.
He's doing the same thing.
Acquires the lock, decrements the number of active readers.
Now both R1 and R2 are going to be done.
And now active readers become 0.
And are there waiting writers?
Yes, there is W1.
So now this condition is true.
And now you are going to signal to the writer
that it's OK to write.
OK?
So all right readers are done.
You can signal to writer that W1.
So now the writer, which was waiting
on the condition variable OK to write, receives a signal.
It's moved to the ready queue.
And now we can start executing it, executing this thread.
It acquires a lock back, because remember, we are still
in the critical section.
Decrements number of waiting writers.
I am no longer waiting now.
Increments the number of active writers.
I am active now.
But it is a lock and access a database.
And again, although I am writing now,
it's still OK to access a database outside the locks,
because this database is going to be accessed.
You can show only if the number of active writers is 1.
You are guaranteed that it will not be greater than 1.
Then say you are done.
You acquire the lock.
You decrement the number of active writers.
And now you look to signal.
Again, you give priority to the waiting writers,
because you want prioritized writings of readings.
So if there are waiting writers, you'll call OK to write.
But in this case, there are no longer waiting writers.
So therefore, you are going to look
where there are waiting readers.
And yes, there is one.
It's R3.
So then you are going to signal to R3
that it's OK to continue to read.
And now I start executing the code for R3,
who is resuming the execution, acquires a lock back,
decrements the waiting readers, access the database,
acquires a lock, decrements the number of active readers,
reads a lock.
So we are done.
So now all the readers are done.
All the writers are done.
So here is a question from Haoyuan.
If we want to signal the writer with a fixed order,
how should we modify our code?
Any suggestion here?
So the question, the way I understand it,
if we want to signal the writers in a particular order,
how do we signal them?
[SILENCE]
Any suggestion here from the class?
Yes, that's great.
Yeah, there are two ways to do it.
One is the way.
You can use a different condition variable
for each writer.
Very good.
The other one is to have more condition variables
than to have a queue of writers to maintain it,
and only wake up the one from the head of the queue.
But it's pretty complicated.
But anyway, it's a possibility.
Very good.
OK.
So we are all done.
So here are some questions.
Let's see.
Let's check your understanding.
So let's say-- sorry.
Can readers starve?
Yeah.
You-- we answered this question.
Readers can starve if you have continuous stream of writers.
Here's the second question.
What if we erase a condition check in reader exit?
This one.
So basically, we say, whatever a reader finishes,
say it's OK to write.
What will happen?
Is this a good idea?
Is this work going to work?
Any drawbacks?
[BLANK_AUDIO]
OK.
One answer here is writers can start writing
when readers are reading,
other set can be reading.
Okay, let's look.
Let's look at this one.
In order to answer that question,
let's look at the code.
Okay to write.
So this is a writer code.
Here.
Okay.
So what will happen here guys?
You see, you get okay to write.
You go out here,
it's waiting write to your decrement waiting writers.
But then what do you do next?
You go back to the while loop.
And in the while loop,
if there are still active writers or active readers,
you still cannot write.
You go to sleep again.
You see?
Because this while,
because you check again this state variables,
you are going to be fine.
What this will happen is that it just wakes a writer
just for the writer to go immediately back to sleep.
So you just graduate to context switching.
So it's a efficiency problem.
It's not a correctness problem.
Okay?
Good.
Let's go to the next one.
Let's go.
Okay.
Further, what if we turn the signal into broadcast?
Okay, instead of having a condition broadcast okay to write,
you broadcast okay to write to everyone
instead of the signal.
What will happen in this case?
Is it correct?
First question.
(mouse clicking)
Okay, let's try to give an answer.
Anyone?
(mouse clicking)
Yes.
It's actually, it's correct Sonali.
Yeah.
Yes.
And it's absolutely correct.
It's for the same reasons.
You see the fundamental observation here,
let me just, it's again.
The fundamental observation here,
it's again for the writer, I'm going here to the code.
You are still in the while loop.
So no matter, even if you are going to be
open up by mistake, no matter who is waking you up,
you are still going to check
whether there are active writers and active readers.
And if they are, you go back to sleep.
So it's inefficiency problem again.
It doesn't matter how many times you are waking up,
open up, you are not going to do stupid things.
Okay.
And the last one, finally,
if we use only one condition variable,
call it okay continue instead of two separate ones,
both readers and writers are going to wake up.
Is that going to be correct?
(silence)
Yes, it's going to be correct for the same reason.
Neither writer nor the right reader
are going to continue if the test for the while loop
is still true.
Okay.
So here is what happens.
Right, and this is what I'm going to end up with this one.
Okay.
So you can use one.
Right.
Okay.
Although there is in theory,
there is one thing here, right?
And this is subtle things.
This is correct with one condition, okay, to continue.
Right.
It's actually, if I, okay, continue,
is going to wake up one single thread
and that single thread is an incorrect one and go to sleep.
So here is the thing.
If I wake up, if I do,
if I have only one okay, okay,
continue conditional variable,
both the writers and the readers are going to wake up on that
and now assume that by mistake, not by mistake,
it just happens.
I wake up the reader.
The reader is going to check and there are waiting writers
and it's going to go immediately to sleep.
But now the signals were spent out.
Okay.
And the writer cannot continue.
It's already, it's asleep.
The reader is asleep.
And if there is no other thread coming in,
we are deadlocked.
In order for this to work,
it will also change this signal
from the writer reader to broadcast.
Okay.
Okay. So you need to broadcast.
And you also need to broadcast.
So you need to do some changes.
So the summary here,
and we are going to end up with this,
is that these while loops are extremely powerful, right?
Because they are going to guard against doing stupid things
or incorrect things.
If you are woken up by mistake.
So we are safe.
So what we need to be careful about
is that because there is no history
with this condition variables,
I am protected to waking up the wrong thread.
But then if I am waking up the wrong thread,
that signal was wasted.
And the correct thread will not be woken up.
So you can have deadlocks.
So that's why here you need to be careful.
What do you need to be careful about?
That's why you have to be liberal with the broadcast.
So we are going to end up with this one.
And I think that it's a good place.
We are done with this example.
Please take a look at these examples carefully
and for the exam.
And I'll stop here and the lecture is done.
I am going, there is one last question
I'm going to try to answer.
And thank you.
And I'll see you on Monday, on Tuesday and Monday.
So two questions.
One question, the while loop give us good protection,
but doesn't that cost a lot of CPU cycles
since we are constantly pulling?
Absolutely.
It's inefficiency.
It's you are absolutely correct.
It's inefficient.
It's correct, but inefficient.
And from chat,
wouldn't this possibly make a finished writers broadcast
hit a waiting reader first before a waiting reader
if there are voice boss waiting readers and writer,
which mean observed ordering priority of writers
before readers.
Yes, this will no longer guarantee the priority order
between writers and readers.
If you have only one condition variables,
you are no longer going to be guaranteed this one necessary.
And yeah, although it is still,
you are not guaranteed the readers when you wake up,
but still if you want to proceed,
you are, the while loop will take care of that.
So being from the point of view of accessing the database,
the while loop is going to enforce the priority
because a reader it's going to look
whether there are active writers or waiting writers.
And if there are waiting writers,
it's not going to proceed, right?
So as long as there are waiting writers,
this while conditions will ensure
that the reader cannot proceed.
So actually the priority is still enforced.
Okay, so the priority is enforced
by the while of conditions.
But the priority is not enforced in the sense
that you can wake up a reader
while you shouldn't have woken up.
And this can lead again to deadlocks
without changing the code and be more liberal
in broadcasting the okay continue.
Okay, thank you.
And I'll see you on Tuesday and Monday.
Bye bye.
(silence)
Thank you.
[ Silence ]