Okay, awesome question.
Thanks for the pointing this out.
Sorry about that, everyone.
We have.
Now, what are the rules for this year?
Still, mostly,
this class will be remote.
All lecture will be remote.
This is where the department decided,
actually early on,
even before delta variant,
all exams will be remote,
will have three midterms.
There is no final.
We have 17 discussion sections on thursday and fridays for on thursday,
13 on friday.
Out of those four will be in person.
There will be on friday,
and 30 will be remote.
Now, please make sure because of that you have a working camera,
because you are going to have zoom procuring of exams and require
a section design reviews,
working with your colleagues for the group projects,
all requires to see each other and also screen shots.
Goals of today lectures.
It's an introductory lecture, obviously,
is to try to figure out a little bit what is an operating system.
And in particular, also, what is not.
And also,
i'm going to say a few words about what makes operating systems so exciting.
It's a while and is actually probably one of the excite most exciting times
to study and work on operating systems.
And then we are going to talk a little bit more at the end about how does
the class operate.
Please,
interactivity is important.
Now I know that it's harder,
especially with a weapon are i'm going to stop from time to time
and look and take questions.
Please ask questions and notes,
because even while I am talking,
other people could answer them some of our t as
what is fundamentally an operating system.
One way to think about the operating system is that software layer,
which runs on top of hardware of the hardware and provide support to the application.
Right?
Why does it mean providing support to applications?
Means that it makes it easier to develop applications on and take advantage
of the hardware capabilities.
It also protects application from each others.
It provides security and authentication,
so only the applications which should a use a hardware and have access
to the data,
and also provide support for cooperation.
There are applications which cooperate with each other.
Obviously, this is more and more expected today.
We are in the age of the internet.
Right?
Why do we care to provide support for applications?
Because most of the things you do online,
you do through applications.
That's it, right?
It's the most a is a way people interact with computers is that people
are going to interact with the virtual world.
So you have physical world, virtual world,
ritual or means application.
And also to drive home,
the.here are some numbers about how is a global mobile market size.
You can see it is huge.
And actually,
even year over year,
the growth is significant about 20% or more.
Right?
It's, again, an application provides the abstraction,
manages the resources,
harder resources.
It's achieving that through using a bunch of algorithms for scheduling
application or processes.
Providing access to resources from different concurrent applications
running at the same time
and security and many more.
Right now,
let's look again a little bit.
There is a question here.
What is now what is now an exciting,
why is now an exciting time for starting working hours?
We are going to answer that later,
because the impact of the os and the challenges are bigger than ever.
That's a short answer.
Here, again, it's not a problem during this lecture.
If you don't understand everything, this is pro.
We are aim here to provide some kind of end to end feeling about what
the operating system is doing.
But the rest of the class you are going to dive in.
We are going to look at all these aspects.
I'm going to touch during this lecture in more detail.
Basically, again, it's an application.
You want to run an application, run a program.
You run to one, you have to run it on top of the harbor.
Now,
what is a harder consisting from of?
You have a processor needs to execute the instructions to run your applications,
and you clearly have a memory.
Right?
We store the data and store the program.
You store the application code.
The processors read the instructions and read the data,
and executes those instructions on the data.
And this is how your application is running.
In addition to just memory, you have a cache,
keep the most recent data or the most access data around closer to the processor.
This for, obviously, for improving the performance,
you have aa base table and tlb translation aside buffer this.
Again, it's are the mechanisms for improving the performance.
Besides that,
you have aa storage where you need to store the data as a program at rest.
The process and memory are storing the data and run the program
only when they are powered on.
Obviously, you have a lot of peripherals,
you have displays,
you have mouse,
you have network,
you are connected to the internet and many more.
So this is quite complex.
Right?
Now, the key here,
and they are connected, right?
All of these species are connected.
The key here is basically how you are going to make easy and secure
for the application to run on this hardware and also take advantage
of the hardware capabilities.
And many of these things you learn like there's a machine structure
in cx 61 c it's,
again,
one of the main functionality of the operating system is to abstract away
this hardware to the application.
Let me, do I do this next set of few slides?
And then i'll stop for questions.
So one way to think about operating system is this like you lose honest.
Right?
Why is that?
Because again,
it's provides this kind of abstraction of the physical resources.
The abstractions are much easier to use and the applications
than the application using directly the harbor.
One of the way it makes it easier to use the operating system makes
easier for the application to use is removing limitations.
Right?
For instance, it provides you the illusion to the eu being the application,
the illusion that you are the only one,
the application is the only one using that machine.
It provides the illusion that the memory is like infinite.
There are no limits, right?
It provides the illusion, you have files,
and data stored in files.
You have users, you have messages.
So like,
it's a much higher level of abstraction than operating just on beats.
And the main way the operating system provides abstracts.
This resources,
harder resources to the application is through the process.
The process is execution environment in which the applications run.
And the process consists of threads.
This is basically the concept,
the unit of execution.
It's our address space.
This is a unit kind of allocates allocation, right?
Allocate resources.
And you allocate addresses memory,
and you have access to files and sockets to communicate over network.
The process encapsulate and provides all this abstraction to the application.
The application only need to understand about how to operate on threads,
another space, how to rewrite files,
how to communicate our sockets,
so to communicate our network.
So that's it much easier.
How does application take advantage?
You write the code and you compile the code.
Your code is not only the code you are writing,
but it's are going to use also libraries and a bunch of system libraries,
which are coming with any operating system.
Again, to summarize,
the application view of machine is that of the process.
Each application program runs in its own process.
This process provides this much, higher level,
much nicer interfaces, then they are harder.
Okay?
It's again here you can see.
It's like I mentioned,
you have the program,
the code you write,
which is going to use some calls to the system libraries,
which are going basically to implement this api for this abstraction
of our api its application programming interfaces,
to manipulate these abstractions.
And then you take care of this, you compile it,
you get the executable code and that you run it on your machine.
Let me stop here.
And let's see,
there is a question.
What else do you like the best?
I think that's a good question.
I think, look,
it's like you.
I'm not going to surprise you here.
I think there are two systems which are quite good.
It's and i'm using them.
It's linux and macros.
Mac west.
We are going to talk about that.
It's actually build also of the unique bsd which originated from berkeley.
So,
okay,
so please ask questions and sorry,
again,
i've never used a minor.
We are using it because it's more scalable,
but is less interactive.
So,
but we promise to improve on using these tools.
So excellent.
Again, just to summarize,
and i'm going to repeat a lot of things,
a lot of over and over again.
So hopefully i'm not going to borrow you,
but there are actually not a lot of big concepts you are going to love
in this class,
but the concepts are quite difficult and intricate it.
And also because they are going to interpret and interact with each other.
But just to summarize,
a process consists of an address space,
one or more thread.
And this is the control,
the execution in that other space,
a bunch of other resources, like files,
sockets, and things like that.
This is activity monitor.
If you have a mac, if you go on here,
you can look and you can see all these processes.
You can see, actually, the processes that tells you also,
I think the column probably i'm not sure you see my mouse,
but there is a column here called threats,
right?
This is unit of execution.
Basically, for chrome, here,
you have 22 threads,
22 activities which are running concurrently in the same process.
Okay, so that's fine.
Again,
we obstructing away harder resources to the applications.
It's one of the main main things
that the application is that the operating system is doing the main capabilities.
Now, less,
we are going to look for other car.
We are going to go over the other capabilities as the operating system provides,
and to illustrate the need for the next one.
Now assume that you are going to have not only one program,
but two programs to applications running on your machine.
And that every actually today,
almost every computer,
your laptop,
your phone,
allows you to run multiple applications,
which means multiple processes at the same time.
Right?
This now,
the point is that it's, again,
it's like one of the abstractions.
Remember that I mentioned that the operations operating system provides
to the application is that
provides the illusion of a dedicated machine.
Right?
But now how you are going to do it when you are going to have
multiple applications running at the same time,
because they are going to run on the same hardware.
Here is where it comes this kind of the other way you can look
at the operating system as a fairy,
because the only way you can provide the illusion of two applications,
and each of them,
they have their own virtual machine.
So to speak is to protect one of each other,
to isolate one of each other.
Right?
That's the only way here.
It's just,
let's go in a little bit more details to illustrate the need for that.
Now,
let's start with a processor.
So you have only one processor,
and you have two applications,
and you have to run on the same processor.
At a given time, you can run on the processor,
only one application to give the illusion that both of them are going to run.
They have their own machines.
So to speak,
the way you do it is that you are going to divide the processor time
in slots or slices.
Each slice, you have a different application running.
The slices are a few million seconds.
1 millisecond, 10 millisecond things like is something like that.
Right?
In this particular example,
you have the brown application running.
If you can see here,
the processor access is a memory,
which is in the process allocated to the brown process one.
It read it reads a code and executes that code.
Is there for running program on?
Right?
But now,
next,
you will also have program two, support.
Program two in memory,
also have some piece of,
you also have some piece of memory which is allocated to process,
right?
At some point,  Right?
You run at some..
Now.
I said after a little bit of time,
you allocate to program one to run.
Now you are going to switch the program, too.
You are going to run.
And by doing so and switching at a very high frequency,
you give the evening is an illusion to each of these applications that it's
using the computer allowed.
Right?
Now, the problem here, if you can see, for instance,
if you look at the memory,
you're having the same memory,
physical memory.
You have the data from multiple applications,
and they have to to read and write the data.
Right?
And certainly,
you do not want,
say, in this case,
a program to our process to read or even more to write the data in process on.
Right?
You also don't run the any process store for that matter.
Of fact, any process to write to modify the operating system memory.
Right?
Because then the operating system may crash.
If you write up an application,
modify the operating system in memory.
And also you need to be careful with the storage.
Right?
You shouldn't allow one program,
two of one user to modify the data of another users,
especially if that data is private or read it.
Okay?
So this is what we mean.
Now you need to you protect protection,
so you need to protect one application,
one process from another.
You need to protect one process from the operating system,
and protect the operating system from the process.
Right?
When an application on a program tries to execute some of these actions,
which are precluded like accessing the data of the memory,
which belongs to another process,
or accessing the memory belongs to the operating system.
The operating system,
one way is going to deal with this offending application,
is crashing the processing segmentation fault.
But it's, again,
the main point here is that in order to create this illusion of to
a process that they are using the machine alone,
you need to isolate and to protect processes from each other.
Also,
in order to make sure that the operating system itself is not crashes a as
a result,
processes modifying operating system data,
then we need also to isolate the operating system itself from the processes.
Right?
Let's see.
I was looking at the question,
why is a good time for learning oils right now?
It's again, we are going stick around until for the next half an hour or.
So so now,
the last way we can look at the operating system is like a glue.
Right?
Why is that?
Again,
it's very logic, right?
Illogical.
First,
you need to abstract those harder to make it
much easier for the application developers to write applications.
Second,
you need to provide protection, isolations,
because typically, you are going to have multiple applications,
multiple processes,
sharing the same part.
And the final part is that these applications or some applications
are communicating with each other.
So you need to provide some kind of glue between them to provide
some common services.
This is coming the form of networking or storage.
You can application can communicate through files,
one application write in a files,
another application read from a file.
Obviously, this also comes with authorization and things like that.
But this is where you can think about the operating system as a glue.
Right?
They need to provide the communications,
enable you the ability to share the resources.
And again,
the common the operating system is doing that by providing these common services,
file systems, networking,
so forth.
I'm going to stop here.
Are there any questions?
One question is,
what are the methods that allow different processes to talk with each other?
I know your socket communication.
It's a valid method.
So there are a few of them,
and we are going to learn about them.
One is me soccer communication,
so it's like networking.
Right?
You can communicate with each other to processes whether they are
on the same machine or different machines,
through sockets, through a network interface.
The processes which are on the same machine,
they can also communicate through share memory.
You can also have the ability to communicate with share memory.
And also, like I mentioned earlier,
you can communicate through storage.
An application can write a piece of data on the store on the local file system,
or even for a global file system.
And others application can read.
Okay?
Is a processor just what we call a cpu?
For most cases, these are interchangeable,
although we are also going to call processor like specialized, harder,
specialized processors,
several.
So it's a little bit broader,
but unless has a right specified the equivalence.
Ha ha ha.
Will adam replace x 86 in consumer space?
Ii it's clear that autumn has a lot of momentum right now.
One example,
obviously, it's m one from apple.
You see that become more and more proud, powerful,
but there are also arm starts to be deployed in data centers.
Actually, there is one new instance which from amazon called graviton.
This is around armed processor.
And it's quite fast.
It's actually his very good performance and is cheaper.
Now, we'll see, right?
Because what intel is going to do,
clearly, they announce a bunch of initiatives,
but adam,
it's has a lot of momentum at this..
Let me go here.
There is something about visualization.
There is something about there are a few more questions here.
Let me ask answer them.
It's one question on the chap.
By the way, please try to ask question for on q and a so I have one source.
I can read them from.
So there's a lot of there are some comments about vmy about visualization.
We are going to talk about visualization even a little bit during this lecture.
But visualization is a way to provide the illusion to every process
to every application that they are using.
They're using alone the machine.
There is another question about risk five.
This obviously was done at berkeley.
I think these five it's has a great future.
And for those of you don't know,
at least five is an open instruction set architecture,
which means that you don't need to pay any license to use it,
to build process to build processors around it.
In contrast, arm for arm,
you need to pay life license in order to use and to provide the art
of instruction set.
But risk five.
Now it's targeting internet of things or mobile devices, very low power.
This is how they started,
but this is the way they are started.
So you'll see maybe a risk.
There is a chance that are going to follow the trajectory of arm.
And it can become for arm what arm is for into.
But again, it's obvious this is in the future,
but obviously,
it has a lot of promise.
I'm going to go back now to the lecture slides.
Again,
this is give examples about some of the services which are provided
by the operating system.
We didn't discuss so far.
And some of the management services and does the operating system provides,
and maybe you do not think right away to them.
It's like power management,
correct?
Or especially for mobile devices,
you need to manage the power.
And across the application,
if you have an application which user is proportionate amount of battery,
maybe you want to isolate to protect other applications from that.
You need to manage a network.
You need to manage almost every shared resource,
right?
When I I referred shared by multiple applications.
So in summary,
it's, again,
repeating.
There are three things.
An operating system is doing.
One is providing a clean easy to use abstractions of the physical resources
to the application,
make it much easier for application developers to develop this application.
And this means like you can think about this,
like is like you lose your list,
then which follows from providing clean abstractions.
You can think about operating system as a referee.
And in this case,
the operating system provides protection and isolation of shared resources across
for multiple applications.
Right?
We share those resources.
And the final is that it's a glue that operating system provides common
services in particularly also enables this application to communicate
to each other.
So now,
let's talk a little bit more about cs one city to,
in general,
and then talk a little bit about why now and why it's exciting and challenging.
Why take cs on ct two?
It's again,
because some of you will actually design and build operating system
or components of them like file systems,
right?
You go to google,
you may work on android.
For instance, you go like apple,
you may or microsoft,
you may work on their operating systems,
or if you are to any company which depend running its software on linux,
you might work on linux to provide new capabilities for the applications
that are important for your company.
But many of you are going to build software which run on top
of the operating systems.
And to build better software,
you need to understand how the operating system was working.
You need to understand to the concepts.
That's what it is.
So next,
i'm going to talk about what makes operating system exciting and challenging.
Let me check again for the questions.
How can application interact with these common services
through the api application programming interfaces?
I mentioned a little bit in passing earlier on.
These are exposed by system libraries.
Right?
For instance, if you want to access a file,
you are going to have an api to access that file, read, write,
seek the same for sending our communication,
sending and receiving data.
You are going to have another api and this is exposed
by these system libraries and implement it.
Why does searching for files from windows?
File explorer for this feels super slow?
Unfortunately, I don't know.
Ii have no answer to that question,
but if you get the answer,
i'll be interested in the answer.
In short, what makes the system,
the operating system?
Now,
extremely exciting is because there are many things happen.
In the next few slides,
i'm going to tell you what happens.
And these things actually makes operating systems,
addressing the operating system problems more difficult,
and hopefully more rewarding once you solve the problems.
So as you probably know,
i'm sure everyone heard that many times for the more than 50 years,
all our industry,
hardware industry, software industry,
and large part was really driven by the morsel.
Machines are harder,
becoming more and more powerful, very fast.
So according to gordon moore,
who was a co founder of intel,
in 65,
he predicted that the transistor density of semiconductor chips will double
roughly every 2 years.
There's a morse law, right?
And you have this plus here.
You see a line,
but you have see a line on the x axis is a time on the y axis.
It's the performance or the number of transistors.
And you have a line y because the y axis is in log scale.
Now,
morris law says the transistor density doubles roughly every 2 years.
So on the same area,
you can cram twice as many transistors.
This leads to the performance of the processor doubling roughly every 18 months.
Why discrepancy?
The discrepancy is?
Because since the transistors are becoming closer to each other,
the latency between transistors to communicate between transistors decreases.
And therefore, you have double reasons you have that are these compounds
to increasing the transistor density.
And therefore,
the performance increases a little bit faster,
or used to increase a little bit faster.
The challenge is that the modest law ended.
Okay?
This again,
it shows here is a performance versus time the performance
of a single court for processor.
And between 1995 and2002 or 2003,
this was what you see here is green.
This is the golden age,
so to speak,
because in this period,
but 4 months increased,
doubled every 18 months,
or increase 52% of the year.
And the problem right now is that this performance will call increasing
just a few percent every year.
So this is a big problem.
Why it is a big problem,
because at that time,
when the capabilities of a single core basically are no longer increasing,
the demands of the new applications are increasing faster than ever.
Here,
it's a plot open.
I plot.
Many of you may have seen it.
And it shows Compute cup requirements to train the state of the art models.
This is plot was going back to 2012 was published in 2019.
Again, it's a lot of scale.
If you look here,
this growth is absolutely astounding.
The requirements,
computer requirements grew 35 times every 18 months.
I added here another data point for 2020.
A new model was released.
If you remember a little more than 1 year ago,
gpt three from open ai made a lot of waves.
It has 175,
55 million parameters.
And again, it fits a curve.
This, again, is not only as aesthetic models.
You have models like with the gpt three is actually language model,
video model,
pattern recognition,
and things like that.
And now here is a morse law.
Actually, it's a morse law.
Even forget that it ended,
even if it were intended,
a we would be in a big trouble.
But it ended.
And this is actually how the morse law looked like.
You see, is a gap.
This is huge, and this is explanation.
It's, again, the law a you have a log scale here.
And the gap increases exponentially every year or every day if you want.
So now what do you do about it?
Right?
You heard about specialized processors.
You have gp us like and media,
gpsa 100 is the latest on dp us from ten several processor units from google,
sarah brass.
This is a company building huge chips,
very powerful.
And any of everyone else builds their own version of gpu intel alchemist,
your announcement,
md radium, and so forth.
The main idea here,
obviously,
we specialize harder is that you are going to narrow the workloads you
want to support,
because of that,
more about that workload.
So you can do more optimization,
and you can be smarter in the way you design the chip.
You increase the parallelism and things like that.
So you can make it much faster for that workload than a general purpose processor,
right?
But now you need to program these things as well.
You may need to share these things as well.
Right?
And they are going to be quite different from the cp us.
And who has to deal with that.
As big as stand,
your operating system has to be with it.
Now, the problem is that even with this specialized hardware,
they help,
obviously, there are more powerful than a single call,
but still,
they don't close the gap.
Here,
it's the performance of the gp os and of the tp os on the same on the same block.
And there is a start here, basically same.
We are assuming in order to make sense and to normalize.
Typically, aspect,
in particular, based on open ai data,
the utilization of the hardware by this,
the state of the art training algorithms is like 33%.
When I show the performance of the gp us and dp us here,
I am factoring it for that utilization.
So that's huge problem, right?
Even with the cp us and gp us,
and is a memory demands are growing as fast, even faster.
Here,
it's a log scale is a number of parameters of these models.
This is from 2016.
And now the last.is,
this is from china.
And this is1.70 55 trillion parameters.
So it's 10 times larger than gpt three.
I'm sure you are going to hear about other announcement,
even bigger models.
If you plot and if you look at this data, it's again itself, again,
lock scale.
Although it may not look like,
since 2016,
the size of this model increased 40 times,
every 18 months.
And if you look at the last 3 years,
300, 40 times.
Right?
This is phenomenal.
During this time,
the gpu memory,
1.7 x every 18 months.
It used to be not a few years back.
Right?
In 2017, eighteen,
you can feed the largest models on a single gpu now,
you need more than 1,000 gp us to just to store the parameters
of the largest models.
So let's see,
what are the other trends?
Now let's move to storage capacity.
Storage capacity is still growing exponentially.
The one thing here,
it used to be dominating the storage by harvest drives no longer.
Now you have more and more solid state devices.
You can see here, the capacity of a solid,
a a solid state drive started to exceed in 2015, 16.
That of the so the biggest ssd drive exceeded the capacity of the biggest
harvest drive around to fifteen to 6 to 16.
And today, if you are looking the largest ssd3.5 inch drive,
it's 100 terabytes.
The largest ssd is 18 terabytes.
Now,
you are going to pay dearly for this 100 terabyte ssd drive.
It costs 40 k is 400 per terabytes.
While to get 18 terabytes, they say,
sorry, this is hardest drive.
I'm going to just correct this one.
For that, you pay only $600,
a 33 dull pet terabytes.
Now,
you can have more economical or economical choices when you look at the ss ds,
like, for instance,
if you under four terabytes ssd it costs $95 better up.
Terabyte still more expensive than the harvest stripes.
Despite of this,
the ss ds are winning the war.
There is little question about that.
Why?
Because the hardest drive are cheaper,
but they are much slower.
Sometimes between ten x and 100 x consumes much more power,
very important for data center and mobile devices or laptops.
And they are less reliable.
These are some projections to make to drive home that point
on the left hand side.
It's about, you can see different technologies is projected up to 2030.
You can have here with dark blue is ss ds with light blue.
It's a flash.
So this is usb the storage in your camera and things like that.
And then the yellow is actually our tapes.
So all the technology,
probably many of you have never seen a tape,
but they are very cheap.
That's why.
And then o is dark orange or with orange is actually harvest lives.
Also, the same study anticipate that in 2026, actually,
the ss ds will be cheaper per terabytes and hardest drives.
And that's why probably you are going to see on the left hand side,
a point in around 2025 after which the market share of and
not only of the harvest drive is going to decrease.
Networking still going very fast.
Today you can have 100 garbage connections to your machines in aws next
will be probably 400 garbage per second.
There are other factors, right?
It's like,
for instance,
another important aspect is the fact that it used to be early on.
You have very, few huge computer computers.
They are extremely expensive,
tens of millions of dollars.
In that case, you have a lot of people using the same machine.
Right?
Actually, in 60s, if I remember correct or 50s,
when ibm started the to to build computers,
watson,
who was the founder of the ibm and the ceo was saying that he
doesn't believe that there is a need,
then for more than five or six computers in the entire united states.
Of course, over time,
the computers have proliferated becomes smaller and smaller.
It used to be probably in 2000s.
At the end of the previous century,
you have one user, one computer.
And now you have a user.
One user is many computers, right?
If you're in your car alone,
you have ten and send ten of cp us.
Right?
So this change,
and as you can imagine,
this also is going to impact the way you are going to design the operating system.
There is another aspect here.
There is an extreme range of time scales.
This is from jeff dean of google,
very influential computer scientist,
build many of the distributed systems there.
If you look about from an application and the operating system,
you have to deal with a latency as low as lower than normal.
No, second, this is l one cash, this is a cash,
which is the first level cash which is on chip.
All the way.
If you are going to send a packet to communicate with someone in california
to netherlands,
what?
It's 150 million seconds.
So you need to handle a scale,
a difference in scale,
in the range of what?
Eight order of magnitude more.
Basically,
let me actually stop here and see what are the questions.
Why does industry intel,
apple say the onslaught is not over?
So the morse law from that very definition of the morse law,
it is pretty much over.
It's physical,
right?
What they say is that what this company say,
it's fundamentally look,
if the morse law,
if you say that the morse law is over and i'm building chips,
why would you build?
Why would you buy chips from me?
Because this means that the new chips will be the same like the old chips.
No more power, right?
So there is a little bit also of,
they said,
I cannot say that the morse law is,
it's over,
because the morse law is what the public associated with the performance.
Right?
So it's a little bit of also marketing.
The more slow is over,
but the more slow it has a very precise definition.
And these companies they talk to the public.
And the public doesn't know the precise definition.
Now, a small, slow means it means fast.
Things become faster and faster.
Now, in truth, they use a lot of other techniques.
And we are going to talk about those in order to improve the performance.
Right?
And this is very visible in your iphone or in your android phone.
We'll talk a little bit about how they do it,
but that is not by improving necessary.
The performance of a single core is by adding gp us,
neural engines,
adding more course,
things like that.
We'll talk more about it.
But good question.
There are programs like spark and made videos that allow us to use
networks or computers to process a parallel workload.
But would it be feasible to create some type of operating system
of software that could string together resources of multiple
computers for personal consumer use?
I think
the question is it's a distributed operating system.
I think that there is not a coherent operating system,
but the elements of a operating system dispute operating system
are already there.
Because one thing can you probably know about cuba net is cabernet is
provides resource orchestration,
resource management over multiple machines, over a cluster.
That's one.
The now that then you have distributed file systems,
right?
Like hdfs or you have these blob stores like,
i'm as I double ss three.
We'll talk more to towards the end of the class.
It's a good question.
Probably you should expect that at some point,
you are going to see this kind of pieces coming
together in a more coherent way in what you could call
a distributed operating system.
So fundamentally,
it's again.
So why things are exciting?
Because they are challenging.
Why are things challenging?
Because they are complex.
And this complexity,
it's growing fast.
Why is complexity growing?
Because you have the demands of the new application
are growing faster than ever.
Capabilities of us of the harder are no longer growing like they used to be.
So then you need to add to innovate on the architecture.
You have different specialized chips.
You need to distribute these applications.
You need to parallelize the programs and many more.
And i'll talk a little more about it.
And then the applications themselves are more complicated.
The application goes to have a variety of software modules.
And we'll talk more about that.
But remember,
if you have almost every application you are using today is not running
on only on your machine,
it has a back and use facebook.
A lot of things happen in the back and use google
or any other google applications and80% is into the backup.
Do it at everything almost right net flicks name it.
Right?
And then it has to run a different heart of architectures.
And because of the more slow has ended,
you are going to have or to see a proliferation.
You are already seeing a proliferation of hardware architectures.
Just to give you an example here,
and it's a personal example when he started spark and he started in 2009.
So what 12 years ago,
we are focusing only for processing data,
which is in the memory efficiently,
and we are focusing only on cp us.
Right?
It's like we assume that the processing is done by the general purpose,
proposed processors that I end up when he started ray,
which was that was happening like in 2016.
So it's after only67 years,
we already have to take into account and to design it
for heterogeneous harder to handle gp us at that time.
Now, to handle gp us and so forth, this is real.
Obviously, this comes with additional complexity.
It's once you are over the network,
you are also exposed to attacks.
And this means that because heterogeneity is increasing dramatically,
that the operating system becomes even more important,
because it's much harder to extract them away.
Right?
Because if you don't ask like the way,
it's very hard to write applications,
and the operating system is one of the key roles, like we discussed,
is to make that writing developing application very easy.
Right?
That's why it's operating.
Some are more challenging,
are more needed than ever.
Now, we discussed and they only discussed about specialized hardware.
I mentioned that it's not only specialized hardware.
How people try to go around the more slow or kind of so to speak extend
in terms of performance.
In other ways,
are having more and more courts,
even for general proposed processors,
like intelligent five that has a processor is 64 course.
I am the epic, the same 64 course,
although there are rumors that the new version will have 128 course.
If you look at these processors,
actually they are them complicated.
Right?
This is how it looks like.
You have a bunch,
you have cash,
you have some other components to manage memory.
You have other components here down to can also
control the io input output,
getting the data in and out of the processor.
And reading from the memory,
which is not on the cheap, it's off the cheap.
You have also in many systems,
you have processor,
you have some integrated graphics.
Right?
This is a trend which come and sorry,
if you look under the hood,
they are connected.
It's like mini system in miniature.
Right?
In this case, you are going to have this is a corpus or car.
Now you are connected to different airports,
memory and many other things.
And this complexity just increasing.
So here down is like it's what we are seeing.
Here is another trend.
It's system on a chip,
right?
And when going back to that question and apple say, maybe say is more slow,
is not done.
This is what they do.
And how they sustain the increasing performance again,
which is not necessarily later is a morse law,
is putting more and more intelligence,
more and more functionality on the same chip.
Right?
Here, I will show you have not only cp us,
and the cpu have multiple cores.
I'd be sent or eight between six and ten,
but you have gps right?
Integrated on the same chip.
You have a core gp us,
right?
A core cp us.
And in addition to that,
you have no oral engine,
which is really focused on neural to supporting machine learning workloads,
the newer land or water blocks.
Right?
This is the things which are like your fingerprint sensor,
or recognizing as your face using your face to unlock the phone.
Right?
Face recognition.
That's how you are going to get more performance.
The code is also very complicated,
is growing in complexity.
And I don't have the numbers more recent numbers,
but here is a vista.
This one15 years ago called it was what?
50 millions code lines of code is huge complexity.
Just to give you a sense of nasa space shuttle,
you remember, it was a space shuttle,
is no longer in service.
It has what?
I don't know, one of the millions lines of code is crazy.
And then it's, again, like I mentioned several times,
you have to scale everyone to,
because you can no longer do these workloads on a single noun,
on a single machine.
Like I show you the data for machine learning workloads,
the same thing is for big data analytics,
scientific computing.
You have so we have several computers which are parallel computers
or indispensable computer since 80s to support this kind of work.
And then on top of that,
everything is connected.
This is the internet.
Probably the most and the most impressive artifact.
The humans have created.
Right?
It links the entire world,
right?
And is what you have 4.5 billions people connected to the internet.
This is what this plot shelves.
Right?
And this is what is it happens only25 years.
It's quite amazing.
And then the smartphone shipments exceeded the pc shipments,
what I think in200011.
And today,
right today actually turns out that you have close to 4
billion smartphones and 5 point something billions mobile phones.
Right?
This data is a little bit old.
And all of those all the phones are connected.
So you have 4 billion,
this kind of very powerful devices at the end of the day which are connected.
You have everything,
you have a huge range, right?
You have everything from data centered with hundreds of thousands
of computers to sends on others,
right?
Which you may not be even able to see these chips,
And everything in between,
right?
And different or close.
And just to drive home the.and i'll here.
So just like I mentioned earlier,
many of the applications you are using today,
they are distributed,
right?
Facebook, twitter, and so forth.
And this is what happens under the hood.
Right?
And let's say you do a simple search,
right?
From your android phone or iphone.
Right?
What do you do?
So first of all,
you need to figure out were back and were servers you need to connect,
to get to send the request,
your search request, to get the answer.
In order to do that,
you need to do this.
Dns request, domain, name,
salaries.
Right?
And it's like you need to resolve use this link, right?
It's google dot com to a particular server.
You have an entire domain,
dns infrastructure,
which consisting of many servers,
they will cooperate to give you an answer,
to tell you who you need to connect to,
who you need to send the pakistan.
Now, when you get that address,
which is an ip address,
you are going to send it over the internet, right?
Over the internet,
these packets are going to be rooted by switches, routers, and so forth.
And it's going to go based on the ip address,
probably in a data center,
they are going to learn to a load balancer.
The loud balancer, you get the packets you send to a server,
the web server,
probably the web server is going to look at the request.
And based on the request is going to send
request an entire other disciplinary systems
to resolve that request.
Right?
To give you the answers.
If you have a google inquiry,
obviously, you may also have to get some ads in the result in the process.
You have another infrastructure doing only that,
figuring out what as the shelf.
And then you need to put together the entire page and send it
back and to be displayed on your computer.
This is just to give you a sense how complicated things are.
And all of these interactions are handled by the operating system.
Right?
At the lower level.
Let me just,
we have only 5 minutes.
So what i'm going to do,
i'm going to do the following thing,
and we are going to continue next time.
Let me first try to answer some of the question,
and then i'm going to go straight to some logistics.
How low level does this class get?
Do it talk about things like pipelining?
We want to talk much about like pipelining.
If you are referring as the cpu process in the cpu pipelining,
like instruction pipelining,
we are going to talk a little bit about hyper threading.
We are going to talk about that.
We'll answer.
This is about hyper threading.
We are going to talk more about being short.
It's a way in which you can share the core,
one core between two threads,
which can be come from different applications.
So it's multiplexing one core.
So let me just skip,
and obviously,
we'll do that as next time and talk a little bit here,
more about the class syllabus.
And it's online.
You have the class.
So we are going to, obviously,
to learn the operating system concepts and how a system programmer
is going to use these concepts.
What are the interfaces?
Ap is?
Then we are going to learn about how the operating system implements a lot
some of this functionality.
Like how is going to manage concurrency,
multiple applications,
accessing share resources at the same time,
address space,
how you are going to provide isolation between different applications.
So that each one application or process will not step over the memory
of another application or process.
File systems,
how you are going to access and store the data and retrieve the data,
send the data and receive the data over the network.
We are going to talk a little bit about disability systems
and the protocols which are and the mechanics which are implemented
by the distributed systems to make them easier to use and to be more
efficient.
And we are going to talk about reliability and security for tolerance,
protection, and so forth.
Finally,
we are going to talk about a little bit about cloud infrastructure,
which is very relevant, because right now,
cloud is the effect of standard.
You are going to.
Many companies are building,
especially startups are building their application.
This class is hands on.
You are going to learn by doing.
You have a bunch of homeworks and projects are extremely important.
And with the projects you are going to implement,
actually also in the homework,
some mechanism, some functionality that operating system,
though I like your strength and scheduling file systems,
and so forth, memory allocation.
This will be very exciting.
Now, what are the demands?
The project will require you to be
very comfortable with programming and debugging c so remember,
recall pointers,
memory management,
use gdp for debugging.
So just go over 61 c again,
you need to know how to use git for version control.
There is ac programming reference here if you need.
So please consult that.
I think the first section are dedicated to programming and debugging reviews.
So please attend these sections.
You can attend it to section, I believe,
for the first 2 weeks after that,
you need to choose one session a section.
The other thing I want to say and to be quite quick here,
but also I want to emphasize that projects are very important,
and projects are not only about doing a piece of software and building
a piece of software,
but project about teaching you how to collaborate,
how to work in a team.
This will be extremely important for you.
If you go and to join to be a software engineer,
this is a key skill you need to learn.
You are going to learn to do to work in a team.
You need to make the team successful,
because that's that's how you are going to become successful.
You are not going to work alone.
We require the project to have four members,
never five.
The exception will be very rare.
Please, this is pandemic.
Still, pandemic is very hard, more active.
Most of the activities will be online.
If you do online,
turn the camera on,
try to emulate the physical presence as much as possible.
But also now you can also the campus is open.
Right?
If you feel comfortable,
you can go and meet in paris.
Right?
But collaborate,
right?
And also not only between yours,
your man, you and your members of team,
but also your da right?
Over communication is how you make this project successful.
Then you need to devise the work among the members of the team,
right?
To require both decision and additional collaboration,
because every you are going to depend on the work of other people in your team.
This is a grading.
36% is for 3 meters.
We have only meters.
Now, final,
36% projects,
80% homeworks,
10% participation, section, lectures, and so forth.
You'll hear more about the project.
You have a design document.
Design document will be due.
You are going to get feedback from the t as and so forth.
Books and infrastructures,
you should be able to find all the Information as a class web page.
There is a piazza.
You find the link to the piazza as well.
There the lectures will be recorded.
Sorry, about today,
about the beginning of the lecture.
The textbook is the operating system principles and practice
from Tom Anderson and Tom Anderson and Mike darling.
There are a few other books, very good,
and you are encouraged to consult and to,
you can refer to.
And we are going to have a few supplemental materials,
a few research papers, and so forth.
We are going to let.
Finally,
Lee's is like,
this is not no joke.
Personal integrity.
You sign there used to be academic honor code.
So please leave by it.
You can explain the concept of other people in the group.
You can discuss the concept with other people on the group.
You can even help your friend to debug your code, the code,
or you can search online for generic codes.
This is no good,
but you cannot share the code with other groups.
You cannot copy or read another group's code or best cases.
You cannot call to copy or reading online code or test cases from prior years.
And we are going that we compare all projects submission against priority
of emissions and online solutions
and will take actions right against your friend.
So please don't do that.
Is not going to help you to with learning.
That's probably the most important reason you shouldn't do it.
Let's try hard to make this class in to keep this class interactive.
I'm going to stop here.
I'm going to take it about the talker.
Obviously,
a little bit more about the operating system general overview next time.
Now let me answer the questions which are still here.
How there are two other questions.
There is actually one last question.
Would it be good to review material of the later half of six times c
like absolutely components of the CPU how much of this?
Absolutely?
This would be very useful?
We are going to talk about cashing.
We are going to talk and reviewing that.
It will be so useful.
How does a participation grading work?
This will be mostly because it will be a more smaller groups from interacting
with your t as office hours and discussions,
discussion sections.
I am at the size of this class.
I don't think I will have the opportunity to interact with many of you,
especially since we are remote.
But obviously, if you have any problem, anything,
please do not hesitate to drop me an EMAIL.
And you can look for me,
i'll be in a soda hall,
at least now and then.
Thank you so much, everyone.
And i'll see you next Tuesday.
If you have any other questions,
please ask the questions.
If you also have any other suggestions about how to make the class better?
More interactive, please don't know how to hesitate to let us know.
It's again, II the first time I'm using is a seminar,
a it's hard to just talk at the screen and see the slide,
not see any of your faces.
But let's try to do our best and any idea.
You see, you have to improve interactivity to improve the class.
In general, let us know.
Thank you.