Hello, everyone.
Welcome to the tennis lecture.
Today we are going to finish synchronization, primitives,
and then the rest of the lecture,
we are going to focus on scheduling,
main key concepts.
And we are going to learn some of the basic policies.
Recall that last time we learned about monitors and condition variables,
just to,
if you remember a monitor,
it's a lock,
and which owns one or more conditioned variables,
these condition variables are used for managing the access to share data.
Okay?
The way this is happening is our conditional variable.
You can imagine it as a queue of thread,
waiting for something to happen inside a critical section, a section.
And they are waiting for a signal from this condition variable.
The key here is that because you are waiting for something to happen
in the critical section,
the critical section has a lock.
You need to look at critical section to implement mutual exclusion.
But because you are waiting in a critical section before,
when you're being the thread,
you are put to sleep on the waiting queue.
You need to release a lock.
And the monitors does the art for you.
You don't need as a programmer to do anything.
Basically, from the programming perspective,
you can wait in the critical section for the event to happen.
But under the hood,
the lock is released.
Once you are put on the radio.
Okay?
Besides awake wake,
we take the argument as a lock of the critical section.
You are going to wait in order to trigger events,
to wake up the threads which are waiting for these events to happen.
There are two primitives, signal,
and broadcast.
A signal wakes up only one waiter.
Aa broadcast can wake up all the waiters,
which are waiting for that particular event to happen.
Okay?
When you do condition variable operations,
then you are going to have to, obviously,
to keep the lock.
One question here from actually,
that why it is nice to be able to wait in the critical section.
So if you remember,
if not, if the program doesn't allow you to wait,
if the program constructs api doesn't allow you to wait,
then you need somehow programmatic to give the
lock while you are going to sleep.
Because if you are going to sleep while you keep the lock that no one
else can acquire the lock.
So basically, the entire system.
So no one even can wake you up.
So the entire system is deadlock.
It's fundamental that as you are going to go to sleep,
you have to be the lock.
But doing that in a program is to separate instructions going to sleep and reading,
the lock is very difficult.
It cannot the instruction has to be atomic.
These two actions should be atomic in the same instruction.
That's what monitors provide to you.
Good question.
Now,
aa key question is that the monitor is clearly a a much more advanced api
for synchronization.
And one of the natural question, actually, it's about,
can you use lower level synchronization primitives like some of us to go
to implement monitors?
Right?
Again, we got out of two to constructs,
you need to implement one.
It's about,
you need to,
you have a critical section,
you need to implement.
So you need to lock the lock primitive.
The other one is signaling, right?
To signal in the events or condition variables.
The condition variables, basically,
you can think you can do it,
because you can one possibility would be to wait to use a semaphore.
You wait for a similar for,
and the way you do it,
you the seven p p operation and so forth.
If you remember the p operations decrement the similar for it,
it has a value greater than one.
If it has a value later than the issue is,
the film sum of our value is zero, then you wait.
And then signaling its use as an operation which is v which is
just increment the cinema for right?
If you are waiting on a similar for because the value zero and I
am implementing the similar for the value to one,
i'm going to basically wake you up,
but i'm going to signal it.
So does this work?
One think,
one reason this may not work,
because if you call weight in during in the critical section,
then it doesn't release a lock.
And if you have the problem,
I just mentioned earlier that you are going to sleep with while you hold
the lock.
So no one else can enter the critical section.
In order to avoid this problem,
you can think to have something like this, right?
It's like,
when you wait,
this is the implementation of the weight function.
Right?
You release a lock,
then you do some r for p and again,
you try to decrement,
you acquire the lock.
Right?
So basically, so in this sense,
is that if you are going to slap sleep across the center for zero,
your lock was at least the signal is the same.
It does this work.
Right?
It doesn't work a for a series of reason,
but one of the things which is, again, we discussed last time.
But I want to emphasize is that the condition variables,
when you send a signal,
there is no history.
If there is, if no one is waiting on a condition variable,
some are someone will send a signal for that condition variable.
That signal was lost.
That is,
if you send a signal upon a conditioned variable on which no one is listening,
is writing.
Now,
someone else comes after you send the signal waiting on the condition
variable that someone else is going to be stuck,
is going to wait.
This is different from singapore.
The singapore have history because you are increment in the singapore.
So take the same scenario.
No one is waiting.
But now the semaphore,
you called a signal and use a semaphore implementation.
What will happen then?
What will happen?
Then?
You are going to increment the summer now the summer for each one.
So the next,
if someone else waits on the summer for price to wait,
is no longer wait, because it's not for one,
is going to decrement to zero.
And it's going to go ahead.
Right?
This is one of the key difference.
This is exactly what I mentioned.
Okay?
This is a key difference investment.
The other the main problem here is that another way to say it is
that p and v are committed if it doesn't matter in which order happen,
the value of the semaphore will be the same.
Right?
On the other hand,
the condition variable or not,
because like we explain, if you send a condition,
if you send a signal on a condition variable,
and no one is waiting on that condition variable,
that signal was lost.
Okay.
Here is another try.
Let's try to fix a problem.
And how do we try to fix the problem here?
You are going only to increment the semaphore.
If there is no one waiting on the npk or is aq is empty for that condition variable.
The condition variable associated with us an offer.
Is that?
So it doesn't talk either because, for instance, there is,
you cannot look at the center for,
you cannot look at contents on some of the cube that there is no primitive.
There is no api for that.
Right?
That's one of the reason it doesn't work.
And also there is a race condition,
the signal that can just signal after the lock release and before the way
to execute some authority,
hear what the rest condition can happen.
Anyway,
it turns out that it's actually possible to implement this correct reason for,
but it's a very complex solution.
The take away here is that the monitor is a very useful abstraction.
One way to see that it's useful abstraction.
It's by the fact that it's very hard to implemented using
more primitive or more basic abstractions like some of us.
Okay?
In conclusion,
monitors they synchronize the present the synchronization of the logic,
then capsule the synchronization logic of the program.
And this means that to wait for some event to happen and the ability
to signal that event.
And the typical monitor based program.
It looks something like that, right?
You look the critical section,
you acquire the lock on the critical section where you
are going to manipulate state variables.
If you remember,
in the previous lecture,
we have to acquire the lock.
While we are manipulating,
we are updating where we are testing,
that active writer is or waiting writer is activity that is waiting readers.
You are going to wait if necessary for some condition to happen.
Right?
In another,
typically, another critical section,
you are going to signal.
That condition becomes true.
You are going to signal.
Now you are going to wait,
wake the threads,
one or more threads,
which are waiting for that condition variable to happen.
If you send a signal,
only one threading member is going to wake up that if you send broadcast,
if then all the strategies are waiting on their condition,
variable are going to wake up.
Now, question is about,
what about these languages?
What is the support in today's languages?
There is every language has some level of support for synchronization primitives,
some better than others.
Like, for instance, for the sea language,
they do have support.
You do have support for the locks,
right now,
with this support, for locks.
So you need to be careful if you are going to return, right?
Because if you acquire the lock at the beginning of your function,
naturally, you are going to release the look at the end of the function.
But you need also to release a look at every time you return from that function.
So you need to be very careful,
because if you forget to do that,
you can happen.
Aa deadlock can happen.
Now, the other problem is that in sea,
it's actually or unfortunate.
You can also jump.
And if you are going to jump into the program again,
you can create the deadlock.
But even when you have more rocks,
things are just becoming even more complex, right?
Because you need to keep track in the program as a developer
when to release every each lock.
And it's the program is not even going to look uniform in the same function.
Right?
Still, depending on where you allocate the locks and so forth.
And for somebody tells you have to at least two locks in this example,
for some of them, only one lock.
You can imagine that it's very easy to make mistakes.
And again, once you make mistakes,
you run into the danger to create that looks.
Okay.
That another problem I just mentioned why is harbin see to to get locks
because in ceo can also jump around.
You have a goal to stay.
Right.
Now you can think about they can use go to statement to provide
some syntactic sugar to make it easier,
right?
Instead of having to instruction release and return,
you are going to have,
you are going to jump to another.
So you are going to release the lock and basically return.
Right?
You can write only one instruction to release and release and return a lock.
Now, the big obvious problem is that if you need to release two locks,
you need to write another kind of instruction to release boss locks and so forth,
right?
Or to organize a code so that when you jump to one and address,
you release both locks and you jump on another address,
release only one look is, again, very complicated.
C plus,
ac plus, again,
in her support for rocks.
Now, we see plus, actually,
things are even a little bit even more complicated during your head locks.
Why?
Because you have, if you remember,
in c plus, you have exceptions.
If you get an exception during the critical section,
you jump to treat the exception,
but you still hold the lock.
So you don't need a lock.
So in order to release a lock,
you need to catch every exception and release a lock explicitly.
Okay?
Because if you don't do that again,
you are going to go and attribute the exception And with while you
still have the law,
so you don't need the law.
Okay.
Now, fortunately,
c plus is a new version of locks,
which is called lock guards.
You can think about this looks like a variable.
And the cool thing about that is that you acquire the lock when you declare
the variable.
And whenever the variables is going to go out of scope,
the lock is automatically released.
So you basically don't have an explicit instruction to release a lock.
You just declare the lock as a variable.
And in that function,
everything gets under that lock in that function.
And whenever eu or the method,
because it's c plus,
whenever you are going to go out of scope returning,
whether that's basically throw an exception or just turn,
then the lockets automatically list.
Okay?
With python,
you have this other construct, which is pretty cool.
Again, you can declare lock like almost like a variable.
And then you can use a statement with lock to basically declare a critical section.
So everything under the swiss lock,
it's going to be locked.
It's a critical section protected by the lock.
And again,
when you are going to leave the block,
the release of the lock happens out an article.
A little bit similar is bad locks.
We java goes one step further and also provides you
what they call synchronized methods.
Right?
So basically, you can have synchronized methods,
a in a class.
Basically,
the synchronized methods are think about that they protect all the variables,
a in the class, in the object,
by a lock, by an implicit lock.
So you can think about,
when you say public synchronized,
then this method automatically acquires a lock,
and it leaves as a lock for everything what is happening
in this particular method.
So pretty cool.
And java also support monitors.
You can wait.
You can also have the notify and notify all for us to to notify
when an event happens.
Any questions here?
So announcements tomorrow we have the meantime between
5:00 and 7:00 pm is will david a proctor of a zone?
Please read the proctor in policies very carefully.
You can have a one handwritten cheat sheet.
And in addition to that,
upcoming deadlines at homework two is due on monday,
next monday, and the project to first project with you next monday.
Great.
So now let's switch the gears.
And next we are going to start talking about scheduling.
Okay.
Before talking about scheduling,
remember about why do we need scheduling?
And remember about the user kernel thread models.
And for a very good question here,
I79 it's 79.
Thanks for,
okay.
Thank you.
In general, unless other.
So you have user level threads,
right?
Which are to be fine, say,
with ap thread library.
And then you have the kernel thread.
And typically, unless,
as though I specified,
we assume that one user level thread is going to be mapped in a kernel thread,
the kennel, this,
and they cannot only see kennel sets.
Okay.
And the kernel responsibility is to share the resources,
the cpu resources across threads.
There are a few others way to that you can also have
many user threads mapping on the same kernel thread,
or many user threads mapping on many canon threads.
But in this particular case, and again,
for unless otherwise specified,
we are assuming that it's unusual thread map to our calendar thread.
And for this thread,
if you remember,
in a a process has at least one thread,
the kernel maintains a thread control block,
pcb what you have in the thread you have is a state of the thread when he suspended.
And that's the state,
which is enough to resume the thread execution from the.where it was suspended.
And this means the content of the registers,
the program counter, and the stack..
In addition,
some kernels are only belongs to the some threads only belongs to the kernel.
This is for the kernel to do some work.
In the background.
You can do some, maybe can do compaction of the file of things like that.
Let's again look at this layout.
We have two processes here and one kernel.
A process, each process here has a thread.
Remember, a process has at least one thread.
The thread is a unit of execution and concurrency.
And a process owns before the stack.
It it's defines an address space,
which contains the before besides the stack,
it contains a code global variables and the hip.
And if you look at what happens in the kernel,
when what is what the kernel maintained for these processes?
It's going to maintain the pcb is a process control block.
And the kernel,
the stack for the kernel stack for the process.
When you are going to execute,
you are going to run a say, for instance,
things like cisco on behalf of that process in the canon.
Obviously, the kernel has its own code and global variables and the heap.
Now, as you know,
like, with a process can have more than one threads.
And here is a process one.
Now have two threads thread,
the thread b as you can see,
the only thing which you are going to replicate is a stack.
In this figure,
the thread had its own stack,
but all threads in the same process,
they share all the rest of the address space,
which means a code,
global variables and the ship.
Remember, in our example,
in which in our model,
we have one user thread per kernel thread.
Basically, in the kernel,
we are going to have now two threads.
Once for each a user threads,
for processor ok and in addition like I mentioned,
the terminal itself can have as some threads on its own to do
some activities in the background.
Okay?
So these are using totally by the kernel.
They don't corresponds to any users such.
Okay.
Now, this is any question here.
The kernel thread,
the question is kernel thread an actual thread,
or just a block of data in the kernel that store the stake.
Fundamentally, every strategy is just a block of data.
When it's not active,
a bunch of pointers.
It's a data structure.
A thread is a data structure they send,
and they have some data associated with it.
Right?
You have, in this particular case,
you have that in this particular case, again,
you have thread control block.
And that's what you have in the stack.
When you run the threads, though,
okay, then when you run the thread, you activate the thread.
And now you have some active part of the thread,
which is running,
executing the instructions on behalf of the thread,
pointed by the program counter.
So that's what why do we need us?
Another question.
It's a very good question.
Why do we need multiple kernel threads?
What is the benefit of having my money over having one?
It's, again,
remember, i'm the kernel does not see user threads, right?
The kernel only seek kernel threats.
If you cannot has only one,
there is only one kernel thread.
The kennel only will schedule that thread.
Now, if the user wants to have multiple user threads,
the threads,
the only way for these threads to have threads running in turn,
while there is only 1 kind of thread is for the threat
to voluntarily release acpu basically,
say, yield,
then the yield will let another thread from the same processor.
In this particular case,
the application itself is responsible for allocating that time across threads.
If you map a user thread on a current thread and the operating system
automatically make sure that allocates times superior times.
To each set, the application doesn't need to do anything.
Where are the pc bs?
And pc bs started in kernel,
in the kernel datas,
in the kernel data segments?
Typically,
they are going on hip,
because they are allocated at new and new processes and new threats are created.
Let me see.
So now remember about the stack segment.
So you want to this and this actually has yelled.
And you remember that you have this kind of to procedures.
One procedure calls b and b is calling while.
And from time to time yield,
what happens in this case when you call yield?
Then you relieves you.
And again, when I say, yell,
there are three implementation of yield,
one implementation of yield,
which is gives a control.
This is a yield here.
It's a cities call.
It's an operating system called kernel call.
But there has also yelled when you have only one single camera like we
discussed in the past,
which is only at the application level.
It's a library in the application.
And when you do the yield,
you just jump to another function,
in the application level,
to another function,
in the same to another thread in the same process.
In this case, I yield is basically operate.
It's a kernel.
It's accessible.
And when you call yelled,
you basically tell to the kernel to run another thread.
As I said,
in this case,
it's going to be b and sorry,
in the other side will continue to will run the same code.
This is that code will, again,
run call a and a call bb starters to execute while.
And then it calls yield.
And then it relinquish the cpu then the caramel is going now
to go and back to s right?
Okay.
Basically,
the important things to do to see here that when a yield happens,
you ask the kernel,
the red things start executed by the kernel.
The blue things are executed by the application,
but run your thread.
You basically ask the kernel to find a new thread and run it.
If you don't have yield,
then if you remember,
how do we make sure that we still share the cpu between different threads?
You have a timer and the timer after you devise a time in time slices.
And every at the end of every time slices,
you have this timer interrupt.
And this is stated by the operating system.
And as a result,
it's, again, is looking is suspend the current thread which is executing.
And then it selects another thread to switch to a species to another thread.
So you run a new thread.
The same things happens when you are now call a sis aa system call,
say, for instance, to copy a file and io operation.
And that is a cisco.
And if it's a waiting operation,
then the current thread is suspended and gain around a new thread
is selected to run.
So taking a step back,
you've seen here a few years cases in which the thread voluntarily yield
to the cpu another one,
when you have the time mark the the system timer,
forcing the suspension of the current thread.
Here, in the last case,
you have a cisco which is awaiting cisco,
which leads to the we do the celebrity involves are called waiting,
so being suspended.
So in all these cases,
you need to look for a new thread to run.
Okay?
And this is what the scheduling is about,
right?
Which thread you are going to pick if there are multiple threats which
are going to be able to run,
are ready to run,
which one you are going to pick?
That's it.
Okay.
Threats.
Scheduling is complicated.
And this is aaa comment from dennis rich chain.
One of the inventors of unique sense, see.
And it's a comment which is for a scheduling,
some scheduling functionality.
The main.here, you are not expected to understand it,
because it's too complicate.
Scheduling is complicated.
And the reason it's complicated because it has a time they mentioned.
Right?
You need to be careful about the time.
That's part of you need to integrating the scheduling,
but a new thread.
And it's about,
you look at the threads which are ready.
You select the next round to schedule and run the next lap around this.
Next they select this thread.
So that's it.
The rest of the lecture,
we are only going to focus on scheduling.
Again,
the scheduling is selecting which thread to schedule out of all currently threads,
which are ready to run.
Now,
this is basically a diagram About the flow in the scheduler,
flow diagram of the scheduler.
This is acpu we are running to the side of the cpu and it's a radical.
The scheduler is going to pick one thread from the radical graph.
While the thread is running,
the thread can go into have io request and it can wait for the io request
to complete.
It can wait for the time slice to expire.
This is going for the timer to kick in,
say, after 10 million seconds,
you can wait, for instance,
if you for a chilled child,
you wait for that child to finish,
to execute or to execute.
And you can also be interrupted by an interrupt.
And then,
once you are waiting, it's over.
You are going to be put back in the video.
Again, scheduling is about deciding we spread from the radio to schedule.
And when you say automatically,
you say to the scheduling,
it's about which task to run.
If I have more than one task,
then I automatically have a queue.
So queues are integrate our fundamental part of the scheduling.
You are waiting in a queue to be scheduled.
Cpo scheduling has been a big area of research since what?
50 years for 50 years.
And there are many implicit assumption and many kind of scheduling problems.
Like you can have one program per users.
You can have one separate program or multiple threat programs.
Programs are independent.
Right?
And so in many, and this,
you make these assumptions to simplify the problem,
to make it more productive,
right?
And therefore, to solve it.
But this problem is much more complicated.
That's why there are so much research in the 70s,
because there are different concepts.
So when you decide to run a new thread to pick a new threat to that,
when you decide that,
we said you are going to pick according to what the one is ahead of the cure.
Is that fair?
What does the fairness mean?
Right.
I if you and for different programs,
it's like for different user may be fairly that I get the same amount
of cpu like you get.
Okay.
But what about the applications?
Because the applications that are application which are io heavy, right?
Like an elite,
spend very little cpu right?
Mostly, it's waiting for you to type in new characters.
Or you can have like compilers.
If you do a run a computer compilation job,
computers, and that's very cpu bounded.
Right?
So what does mean for to be fair between these 2 kinds of jobs?
No.
Matter what is your answer there?
At the end of the day,
you need to allocate the cpu if you have one cpu,
but we have fewer cp us.
And so that's we need to allow to slice the cpo and allocate
different time slices,
two different threads.
Now,
there is another implicit assumption which is done by today's,
but many of the today's schedulers operating system schedulers.
That assumption is that many of the applications are reversed the applications.
This means that they use a cpu for a little bit,
and then wait,
the news against the cpo for a little bit then, right?
And like application,
like user facing applications,
like editors, like anything you interact with your computer.
Web browsers.
Any other thing like that?
Fit in this category?
Right?
Because most of the time that program waits for your input.
And while it's wise, it doesn't need to use acpu again,
this program satellite between cpo and io like we discussed.
And this means that you want to prioritize, for short, worse, right?
Because you want to be responsive the program.
This is one way to think about the scheduling.
If you think about scheduling discipline,
I want to prioritize a short burst,
right?
Because the studies are facing,
they are going to be interactive.
I provide good experience to the user.
And if something is longer burst,
it takes for a while.
Like like a compilation job,
it can be lower product.
Right?
So keep in mind that one.
Now,
we move on what are the other possible policies?
What are the properties young for a scheduler?
There are many of these properties.
Again, that's the reason or the many of these policies.
And there's a reason for it.
You have a a lot of research in scheduling for decades.
So on.
It's obviously minimize response time.
Right?
You want to finish the task,
the job as fast as possible.
Fair enough.
Another one is maximize the soup,
right?
The soup with it's about the number of queries per second,
Number of transactions per second.
Here, this is more complicated because there are two parts.
It's aio part and the cpo part.
It's also, if you, in general,
and it's also one way.
Typically, you maximize the throughput is batching,
which her two is a elapse time.
For instance, let me give you an example.
If I want to optimize each the response times the latency of each rip
to the disk,
it's one power problem.
If I want to maximize the number of reads to the disk is another problem.
In the first case, for each read,
i'm going to execute separately and trying to execute as fast as possible.
In the second case, instead of executing one read, at a time,
I am going to batch the reads and send them to the disk and the risk,
we can do a better job of serving these sleeves in a more intelligent way.
So it's going to increase a throughput to serve more risk per second.
But as the expense of the latency,
because now I need to wait for the batch to complete in order to get
the result for my reach.
So typically, this is one,
one trade off between the latency and the support.
The other thing it's about,
let me give you another example,
just thought about it.
If you want you go to grocery,
I know that many of you you are now you are the buying online,
but think about when you go to grocery.
If I need something right now,
I need milk in order to reduce the latency by how when i'm going to get
the milk.
Okay?
I'm going to go right away and get milk,
but typically don't do that.
Right?
And I I get the milk saying half an hour.
But typically we don't do that.
What we do is basically we batch.
And when we go to grocery,
we buy many things.
Right?
So like ambassador, instead of buying me today,
i'm going to talk tomorrow.
I'm going to go to grocery.
I am going to wait until tomorrow because I have a lot of other things to do.
And then I get them by tomorrow.
So it's lower latency.
But in terms of the throughput,
i'm going to get a a lot of more things.
At the same time,
the circuit will be higher,
but the latency will be lower.
And another thing it's about policy could be failed,
like we discuss in the past is fairness.
You want to share the cpu in some equity equitable way.
Okay.
Good.
So now next we are going to go through some first to go
through some scheduling policies.
And we are going to start from simple to more complex.
For each of them,
we are going to look at what properties they have and one or what we
are going to,
again,
compare them based on some metric.
And typically, the metric we are going to compare them.
It's a response time, how long it takes to finish things.
Right?
This is what we are going to do now.
One of the first and the simplest scheduling discipline is first curved,
first come, first served,
or first in, first out.
Right?
And a this is like,
you go to grocery everywhere.
This is exactly what it is, right?
People are served in the order in which they arrived to the queue.
And now,
let's assume that now we have three processes.
Let's assume that we first come first serve.
Each process runs to completion is a reminding idea of this lecture.
I am a use processes and jobs interchangeable,
but it should be clear from context.
So now p one,
say it takes 24 time units.
Let's say 24 seconds.
B two takes 3 seconds,
and basically takes 3 seconds.
Now.
Suppose the processes the expression is arriving in the queue in the order
of p one,
p two, p three.
With the first come for self scheduling discipline,
we are going to serve to run the processing the same order for asp one,
then p two, then p three.
Now let's see when each of these processes finishes.
Right?
What is the waiting time?
The waiting time is how long you wait before being scheduled.
So, and when you complete,
so the first process doesn't play it any time.
So starts immediately.
The p two was 24 seconds for the p one to finish,
and p three ways for 27 seconds for p one and peter to finish.
Right?
And the average waiting time is 0+24+27/370.
Now, if you look at completion down,
so the finishing time p one takes 24 seconds to finish b two.
27 seconds from the time was submitted and p three thirty seconds.
Again, in this particular case,
we assume that all processes arrive basically the same time,
but that in certain in the queue,
in the order p one, p two, and p three,
let's say,
cash, it's actually a very good question.
Is there any way for the kernel to estimate,
know the first time of for a job without actually running it?
That's excellent question.
I think,
in general, now,
and you'll see this is one of the problem which is scheduling discipline,
one of the many and the but you can, in some cases,
you can know it, for instance,
for its from historical data.
In some cases, it is possible.
But in this case, again,
this killer doesn't even care about the running time of a job,
a of a process.
It doesn't care, right?
It just executes them in the order.
That means they arrive with lecture.
But we are going to touch to go back and touch this very question
later in the lecture.
Good.
Now, if you look at this one,
i'm just curious,
can you think about a better way to schedule
these processes to have lower completion time?
Yeah, run p one after peter and after the p three to still a very good.
That's very good.
Okay.
You see, this is a problem.
It's exactly the problem with this kind of scheduler is very simple,
very simple.
Right?
But the problem is that if you have some short processes,
they end, they can get stuck behind a long process.
This is called convoy yet effort.
Right?
Think about you go to the grocery,
and you are going to be stuck behind someone which has100 items is a couch.
Right?
You don't want that, right?
You have only three or four items to do to buy.
How do they solve the grocery this problem?
How they try to alleviate this problem?
Express lines.
Yes, in the express line,
there is a cap on the size of the job of the size of the process, right?
Because the capital like,
you can only have 15 items, right?
No more than 15 items, okay?
To cap basically how long it takes the process.
Indeed,
a it should be a much better answer.
Now, the average waiting time is three.
Instead of I seen 24 and 13, I believe,
instead of 27, let me.
So it's 3 and 10 instead of 17 and 2013 instead of 27.
Okay.
Good.
We learned that we know.
Now here is another one.
It's implemented by many schedulers,
this policy around robin.
Right?
So around robin,
for come first serve, depends on this.
When the order is submitted.
The round, robin uses this preemption,
which exactly we discussed as many times so far.
So basically, here, you do not wait for a process to finish execution.
Instead of preempted.
After you, let it run, say,
for until it blocks,
because wait for something or until it runs for, say,
10 millisecond and then preempted.
You suspend it.
And you run another process, right?
So this is a round robin.
Right?
And the reason is called round robin is because You take it 1 by 1,
you have ten processes.
Now iii run for ten ten10 millisecond one process.
Ii run process two for 10 millisecond process three for 20 seconds and so forth.
After 100 millisecond,
I am back to running processor.
In this case,
each process get one over if there are n processes.
Each process gets n one over n of the cpu time.
And if a time quanta is q then each time gets for q time contract.
And each process has to write how long n minus one over q if you have ten processes,
and each process takes the time quantize ten,
nearly 10 million seconds,
it takes for an entire round is take 100 million seconds.
But for one processor for it transferred in the second and history
for another 90 million seconds.
To for his turns come,
it's n minus one.
In that case, n minus one nine times ten is nineteen eighty second.
Here,
it's very interesting to look at and considering like what happens
when the queue is very large.
Right?
If the queue is larger than the largest running time of a process,
then it's provides identical results,
like first come first serve.
If q is very small,
you have a lot of interleaving between the processes.
Okay?
Now, there is a trade off here.
Ideally, you want to be as small as possible.
However, remember about contact switching,
there is an overhead of the complex switching.
If the quanta is too small or time slice is too small,
then you can spend more time in switching between the context
than actually running the process.
Okay?
Sounds good.
So is that question here whether we can make the chat default instead of having the
using the q and a i'm going to try to answer and I decided trying the past
to answer both from q and a and the
chat.
But if people prefer to use chat,
I am finding that here is an example time quanta,
24 hour example.
Right?
So what will happen?
You first run p one,
remember now and look at here.
We take another example.
I you have four processes,
p one, p two, p three,
before which takes 50 38, 68,
and 24 seconds, respectively.
Now save the time quantize trend.
This is the order they arrive at the queue,
b one, b two, b three, before.
Let's see what happens.
First, we start with the first process, b one.
It runs for 20 seconds, 20 seconds.
And then after 20 seconds, we interrupted,
we preempt it.
We start running p two.
P two is only 8 seconds,
so it's less than the time quanta soft 8 seconds finishes.
We are done.
And now we are moving to the next energy speech.
Three.
B three has 60, it takes 68 seconds.
Therefore,
it transferred 20 seconds after which is preempted after iran
before for 20 seconds,
after which is preempted.
Now you come back for p one and p one.
You're the only one take 20 seconds out of p one.
So you have another 73 seats,
33 seconds to run.
So you run 20 seconds for 20 seconds.
And you preempt.
Now b two is done.
No need to run it.
And you are b to b three.
From p three, we already run it.
We already run p three for 20 seconds.
Now we have another 20 seconds.
We take another 20 seconds for to run for peace three after each pre preempted.
And then things continue like this.
You can easily follow up on it.
Okay?
The one interesting case is that at the end,
you have only pc remaining to run,
so you are going to run.
You have only one processing the queue.
You are going to run the process over and over again.
What is the waiting time here?
It's more complicated to look at the waiting time,
because for ap one,
you have what is the waiting time?
You run p 13 times here at time zero,
at time 68?
At a time 1:12,
the waiting time initially is zero.
The second time on your run at time 68,
the waiting time or twelve sixty eight-20,
because it finishes previously, p one finished,
finishes a cushion at time 20.
And for a pew on,
when the last time when pew on the grounds,
it started at 1:25,
but the previously finished at time 88.
So it's 125 minus, sorry, 112.
Sorry, i'm sorry.
P one starts at 112,
and previously finishes at time 88.
So it's 112-88.
The total waiting time is 72, right?
P two at the time 20.
So it says there is only one time is 20 and so forth for the other processes.
What is the average right waiting time?
You are all the waiting times of all processes,
and you divide by four.
It's 66.25.
The same completion by, right?
The p Sorry,
p one completes at time 1:25.
Sorry.
P two, this is 125 here, p two complicit.
I'm 28, p three complicit time on 53 before complete the time on 12th.
The average weighting completion time,
it's 104 and1/2.
So around robin,
what are the pros and cons better for short jobs?
If you are assured jobs,
your turn will come faster,
especially if you are at the end of the queue.
But now it adds contact.
Switching is more contact switching overhead.
It's again, if you have the the response time, right?
Is like, is the can decrease.
Here is an example to illustrate how you around robin decrease
the response time and assume the duration of a task.
Now is then and of the other one, it's one,
p two is one.
We are using the task and processes interchangeable.
And here, if you want,
runs first and you do next,
the average response time is 10.5.
Okay?
However, if you use a tanguette,
that was a time quanta ten,
where is larger than any burst,
if you lose a time quanta of ten of five,
t one will run only for 5 seconds.
Then you run t two after you run t one.
They are very response time in this case,
will be 8.5,
because t two finishes at time six.
What do you want finishes at time 11?
And so now think about,
if you have two tasks,
but they are one time unit.
And you average the quantize,
then it's obviously the average response time.
It's 1.5.
If it's time quantitative,
one is the same.
The point here is that if the average,
if the time quanta is larger than the birds,
like there is a time,
it takes a task for a process to complete,
then it doesn't matter.
There is no difference in the average response time.
Now, if the quanta girl is smaller than the time it
takes to complete or for a task or a process,
then this is an interesting case.
Here is 0.5.
So basically, you run t 140.5,
then t 240.5,
then t 140.5,
and t 240.5.
If you look as they are very response time,
it's 175.
So it's larger guess.
So that's kind of interesting, right?
So we, at some point,
at least in this scenario,
we reduce the time quanta.
Instead of the response time to decrease.
It's actually increase.
It's very easy to see why this happens.
And this happens when,
in particular, when all task or processes take the same amount of time.
Right?
Because everyone takes the same amount of time.
If you see one first come first set up,
it's your first time you finish the first process and the second process
and sub process and so forth.
Clearly, the first process finishes earlier than the last process.
But now, if you have very small time quanta and you do round robin to exam,
you do a little bit of each of them, yourself,
a little bit of each of them,
then all of them are going to finish almost at the same time,
meaning that all of them are going to finish more or less when the last one
finishes.
That's why is the intuition why this the round robin
actually can also lead in some
cases to increasing the response time,
not only decreasing it.
How do we implement around?
Robin?
Is the kernel.
It's using the time I interrupt.
Every time a quant expires,
you trigger a time interrupt.
This is what the pure project two is going to be about.
In summary,
you've done robin.
If the time slice or quanta is too big,
the response time will suffer.
If it's infinite,
it's basically first come first or five.
If the time slice is too small, the throughput my suffer.
And in some cases,
also the response time I suffer.
So it's the actual choice of time slice.
It has to be large enough.
So it amortizes, the context switch overhead.
So stinky has to be a few times,
maybe one order to order a magnitude larger than the context switch.
That's basically what it is.
Right?
Basically, you want,
if the typical the context switches 1 millisecond,
you want the time commander to be, say,
100 million seconds toward the romantic language.
That's a rule of town.
This is an example again to drive back home like assume that you were in ignore,
ignore the context switching overhead is round robin
always better than first cast herself.
Like we discussed the answer is now this drives home the point by having
another example,
each we have ten jobs and each job or ten takes 100 seconds.
Right?
The round will be in caterpillar at the time quantize 1 second.
Okay?
If this happens in the round robin in the five for kids or first come
for self case,
the first job finishes after 1 second 100 seconds,
the second after 200 seconds,
the last one after 1,000 seconds.
While in the round robin case,
the further job finishes after 991 seconds,
the second bar and after 992 seconds and so forth,
right?
Both round 3 time and first come first serve in each at the same time.
But the average response time is much worse for country time.
Around 3 time that i'm sorry not around the time.
Around robin,
it's bad when all jobs have the same length.
Remember.
And there are other reasons for each round robin may suffer.
With round robin, you can switch between processes.
If you see between processes,
the casual suffer,
right?
Because each process can be a different program and is going to need
a different code.
It's accessing different data is going to not benefit from the caching.
From the previous process,
you need to gain between everything into the cache.
In the case of the first come for the set of then one program run
or one process run until finishes,
it's going to maximum to maximize the benefit of cash.
This is another example here in our we have this one
of the previous examples and have three,
four processes, which takes eight, 24, 53,
and 68 seconds,
respectively.
He had the best first come, first serve.
What is the best order?
P one,
b two, b three, and b four.
And what is the way down?
Right?
Is the best order,
the best for comfort person, right?
You start with p two, then before, then p one, then p three.
So what is the wait time?
For a week time for the p one is 32.
For p two is zero,
for p four is eight,
and p three is 85.
You have 71.
And a quarter worse,
first come first serve.
It's when does this happen?
When you run firstly three,
then p one,
then before so reverse order.
And in that case, the worst case is 83 and 1/2.
The corresponding completion times for the best first come for a service,
69.5 for the worst one.
It's one,
20:00 1 and 3/4.
In the meantime,
in between here,
you have four different bank want us.
For this is the result for the time qanta, one, time qantas, eight,
and one,
and five and ten.
So please, as an exercise,
take a sheet of paper,
you can check the results for different time quanta.
Great exercise to better understand about how round robin scheduling is working.
And as you can see here,
the average waiting time for the round robin,
it's between,
as you might have expected,
is between the first come first serve and the best first come, first serve,
and the worst was first come, first serve,
and the same for the completion time.
Let me see is that a few questions here.
Since we cannot estimate the run time of each burst,
how can we schedule the order in each first count?
Scheduling is the best.
That's a very good question.
It's again, you can use historical data if available.
But one reason we study the best first come first serve,
which is also called like you'll see shortage of first,
for obvious reasons,
is that this is like a baseline.
You can actually, as you'll see,
you can prove that running shortage of first,
using shortage of first leads to the lowest wait time or completion time.
Another question is, the best first come,
first serve order is shortest or longest.
The best first come for self is a shortest,
is when you start with the shortest job first,
the world's first come for self is the longest.
And you start with the longest job for us.
Okay?
You can see here about like p two.
And we are PP two is we are all over.
The place is very sensitive,
right?
Depending of where,
depending when is scheduled,
right?
You go from 0 to 145, right?
Which is pretty bad.
While for p three,
which is the largest,
hits more stable.
Right?
And it's natural, right?
Because the longer the bigger you are,
the more you are going to dominate,
the wait time,
and also the completion time.
This is p three, and this is p two.
There are many other scheduling disciplines,
another scheduling discipline here.
We are going to talk a little bit about this priority.
You can have different jobs here,
and different jobs have different priorities, like, for instance,
jobs which are associated with interactive user interaction.
They can have higher priority than jobs who are doing compilation,
where our jobs which are going to process data you receive on the network
from the network that can have higher probability.
With this scheduler,
you assign a job of priority,
then you always execute the highest priority job first.
In this particular example,
you are going to execute job one, job two, and job three.
Before you execute job four,
you execute your four, before you execute your five, jobs six,
and jobs seven.
So one of the biggest problem is this one is starvation.
What is starvation here?
Assume that you always have new jobs arriving with the highest priority.
So as long as you have jobs with the highest priority arriving,
you cannot process jobs in lower products.
You can also have this one is called propriety and version.
We talk a little bit about that in a different lecture.
But here is what assume that say job five owns a lock
after each job one waits.
So job five.
Okay?
It is a critical section.
It was preempted by a higher priority job.
And then job one comes and wants to enter to critical section,
but it cannot because the job five still owns a lock.
It cannot be scared before you go on.
So that's how you have a deadlock.
There are many ways to fix a problem.
We are not going to talk about as much about this,
but there are every single and dynamic priorities.
If like,
you'll see if a job is too much at a high priorities and you
are going to push it down to a lower priority.
There are many other holistics, but it's important.
You to know about this problem.
The strict priority can lead to salvation and can lead to deadlock.
Now, what about scheduling?
Fairness?
Oops, sorry.
So strict priority.
What do you now solve?
What will the state priority clearly is not fair, right?
Because by definition,
priority is not fair, right?
You give priority to process is the highest priority.
The fairness is at all,
so is a privatization,
right?
And around Robin, on the other hand, is fair,
Because there is no difference between the jobs you give to each
of the jobs that I'm quanta until it finishes.
And you go round Robin across the jobs.
But you'll see that the tradeoff is like fairness,
which is round rock win.
One of the policies around Robin can hurt the average response.
And how do you implement the fairness?
Again, you can do around Robin.
There are other ways to get some price,
even if you have priority scheduling.
There is an article version in which if you wait,
if you wait for too long on a lower priority queue,
your priority is bump up.
You do eventually get to the higher product you,
and then you can get up now.
Let's go to answer the,
let me answer this question before.
And then I'm going to stop because you have done the best first conference,
orderly,
shortest to longest.
Sorry, it's yes,
the best first come, first serve.
Order is shortest, the longest.
That's correct.
And we are over time.
We are going to stop here.
We are going to continue Thursday to talk about scheduling.
If there are any other questions,
i'll be happy to answer until then good luck at midterm.