Hello, everybody.
Welcome to the 11th lecture.
So hopefully you hear me.
Today we are going to continue our discussion about scheduling.
We are going to learn a bit about fairness, real time,
and making further progress,
avoiding starvation,
and do one or two case studies.
So one thing just to start with is us a question I got from some people
also before the midterm.
It's about what is the operating system,
scheduling processes or threads?
The answer, obviously, is threats.
A process has at least one threat.
When a process has exactly one thread,
then you can think about its interchangeable.
The scared the kernel will scared either a process or astray, you can say.
But obviously,
when a thread,
aaa process has multiple threads,
kernel threads,
then the operating system will schedule independently each thread of the process.
Okay?
Now the one thing to keep in mind is that when you switch between the context,
switching between two threads,
if you remember which belong to the same process,
that's much quicker because they are living in the same address space,
you do not need to switch the address space.
However,
when you switch between two threads which are indifferent processes,
then you need also to switch the address space.
And that's much more expensive.
Think about one order of magnitude more expensive to switch to context,
switch between two stress in different processes,
then switching between two strides in the same process.
And also remember here that actually,
there is this multithreading or hyper simultaneous multithreading or hyperthreading,
that's kind of the harder level which allows you to run multiple threads
on the same call.
But from the operating system and from the application,
the only difference is that is hyper threading.
You can run more threads,
kernel thread at the same time.
There's the only difference,
nothing more.
Now, we discussed last time,
we did come first set of we ended up with this kind of discipline,
which is when we look at the best first compass, if you remember,
we are starting with the smallest job first,
and then to minimize the waiting time and to minimize the completion time.
Okay.
Obviously, the question here is that for that,
we need to know the future.
And if the future,
can we meet all the best?
First come first serve?
The answer is, obviously we all be said,
what is a discipline?
And that is to run the first job at first.
Right?
So whatever job takes,
the least run.
It has priority over other jobs.
And there are two versions of that.
One, it's a preemp.
It's non preemptive version and gone.
And the other one is preemptive version.
As and I implies for the non preemptive version,
you run each job all the way to completion.
In the preemptive version,
you are going to comprehend the existing jobs.
For instance, if any existing jobs,
there's still 10 seconds to run.
And now a new job arrives,
which is only 1 second to run.
The new job is going to preempt the existing job because it has
only 1 second to finish while the preview while
the existing joke still has 10 seconds to finish.
Okay.
This is about shortest remaining time.
First,
this is a preemptive version of shortage of us.
So remember about that?
So this is optimal.
And you can show that is optimal from the point of view of reduction,
reducing or minimizing the completion time.
So keeping keep in mind,
this is an optimal scheduling discipline.
Now,
so it's,
so one question here is that when you have shortest remaining time, first,
if you want to compare with his first come first set up,
the one question is,
what if all jobs have the same length?
Because it's all jobs at the same length?
What you are going to do all of them are going to take the same time.
In this case, there is no difference between them, right?
Because it doesn't matter in which order you are going to run,
because you need to break the ties,
because they all have the same length in some arbitrary fashion.
And first come first service one of these ways to break the ties.
And you are going to get the same results.
Obviously, if the jobs are varying length,
then with the shortest stop short,
the remaining time first is going to prioritize, obviously, the short jobs.
And they are not going to go to to start to be stuck behind the long ones.
Remember that the first come, first set, they didn't have,
you might not have a good average response time when you have a big job,
and then as a small jobs are just stuck behind the big job,
because all the small jobs are going to inherit the completion time,
the running time of the big job,
because I have to wait after it.
Here is a simple example to illustrate the benefit of the shortest
remaining time.
First.
The shortest reminding time,
remaining time first.
It's a preemptive version of shorter job first.
And here you have two jobs,
a and b they are cpu bound,
meaning that they use only the cpu say,
run for a week or for a long time.
And then you have another job see,
which is io bound.
This means that you do an eye operation in one will take so many seconds
to do eye operation,
like, say,
you read or write to the list,
but then I you wait for 9 million seconds for the operation to complete.
Okay?
If you run one of the jobs at a time,
then job a or b will use 100% of the cpu and 0% of the io of the disk.
If you run c at the time,
c will use10% of the cpu and 90% of the risk.
So what will happen with first time for a setup?
With first fargo?
First come, first serve.
Once a our big is scheduled,
then it's going to run the story.
Going to hold the cpu for2 weeks together.
They are going to get in because even if she starts to love me,
as starts to learn,
starts to run.
After 1 mini seconds is going to give up the cpu because it has to wait
for to get
the eye operation complete.
Now, what about a round robin or short as remaining time?
First in this particular case?
Let's see what happens.
This is round robin and assume the round robin.
The time slice is 100 million seconds, okay?
So you execute in round robin every job.
So let's start with c it's again and say the time slice is
100 million seconds again.
So you start to see c runs for 1 millisecond and then gives up yell the cpu
because it needs to wait for the eye operation to complete.
Then you have to run a and then b and c again.
Now a and b because our cpu bounded,
they are going to take their entire time quanta.
That is 100 reset.
Right?
In this case, a discretization,
if you look about,
is like from around,
when you schedule caabc then it takes to all of them to complete takes 200,
1 million seconds,
100 for a 100 for b and one for c and out of this time,
because you have the only one eye operation,
because the schedule c only once the eye operation kept takes 9 millisecond.
The discretization is 9 over 201,
which is.5 years ago,
4.5%.
Very little bit.
Now let's say you do that.
Our robin of 1 millisecond.
If you do round robin of about 1 millisecond, what do you go?
What happens?
Your schedule?
C first, it takes 1 millisecond.
Then c will have to wait for 9.
Millisecond is going to be in the waiting queue to wait for the operations
to conflict.
Right?
During these 9 million seconds,
you are going to ultimate between a and b each of them for 1 million seconds,
because they are ready to always run,
because they are only cpu bounded, right?
What you get here,
the discretization is 90%, right?
Because see, it's already once an io completes see,
it's ready to launch the next time.
Right?
The problem here is, if you see it,
this is great maximize the discretization,
but in this particular case,
you have a loss of context switches, right?
Because between a and b you have a lot of contact switches.
And at every one, the second.
Now what happens is the shortest time first,
the shortest time first,
remaining time first.
So shortest remaining time first.
Let's see what happens.
First, exactly see.
Like in the previous two cases,
it takes 1 millisecond,
and then is going to wait for9 million seconds for the eye of the complete.
Right?
See, it's on the way to you.
So now you need to schedule between a and b let's say you schedule a you
are going to schedule a until c becomes,
again, ready for execute to execute.
And he will become ready to execute when his io has completed.
So after 9 million seconds,
in the first 90 seconds,
you run a and now c is ready to execute,
and c takes only 1 millisecond.
The remaining time to finish first for seats,
1 millisecond while for a it's 1 week minus9 millisecond.
So we are going to schedule c see it again,
takes 1 millisecond to go to sleep,
because it's just like for waiting for the eye operation to complete.
And now you have a and ba remaining time.
It's 1 week-90 seconds,
the remaining time for b we didn't run at all b it's 1 week.
A is 1 week-90 seconds, b is 1 week.
A will take shorter to complete to terminate.
Therefore, you are going to schedule a gaming,
so you started to do it.
You do cacaca until a finishes this utilization 90%,
and much fewer context edges.
Right?
Any questions?
Please ask?
Let's make it, again.
More interactive.
It's pretty hard to just stare at the screen.
Anyway, now,
what is the problem with shortest time?
First?
As short as yours are remaining?
The time?
First is starvation, what does it mean?
Starvation?
Can someone tell me what starvation means and why we are going to have starvation?
In this case?
Never getting to run b never is scheduled in the previous example.
Actually.
After you finish a you are going to eventually run.
So we will wait a long time,
but starvation means that it may never be,
you may never run as a joke.
Any other answer?
So it's against starvation means that the job industry remains a system
without ever being run executive.
When can this happen?
That's great.
So allison,
so if you have a stream of short jobs,
you always get new, short jobs,
then the long job may never be scheduled.
That's exactly what happens.
The other problem with this shortest remaining time first is that you
need to predict the future.
You need to know how long a job is going to take.
There was a question or two last lectures about this.
There are some ways none of them is perfect.
One way is to rely on the users and as the users,
how long will take the job or the job will take.
But with this has certain problems.
First of all,
you assume the user now,
which is not always true,
or which is rarely true.
And also you open yourself to an attack in the sense that a user,
because if the user now that the system using the shortest remaining time first,
will declare a very short time,
even if the job will take long.
Because in this way,
she can ensure that the job will be scattered.
The other thing which is not here is basically to keep the history.
If you run a job repeatedly,
you look at the history.
If you see how long you basically assume that the past running time is
a good predictor for the future running time for the same job.
And we are going to use that prediction.
But anyway, so this is hard.
However, shortest running time first is still a very important discipline.
For one reason,
it represents a yardstick.
It's a baseline for measuring other policies.
When it comes to minimize the average response line,
it's optimal.
You cannot do it better.
If you are looking, if you are designing a new scheduler, one of them,
at least the average response time,
you are going to compare the average response time
of that new discipline or scheduling discipline through your design,
Against the shortest,
a remaining time first.
The closer you are, the better you are,
in summary, for shortest remaining time.
First.
It's optimal with respect to a very response time,
but it can be hard to predict.
It brings the future.
You need to bring the future.
And this is hard.
And can be unfair.
Here means also starvation.
The long jobs not may never be scheduled.
This is what I said in the earliest.
This is one way to implement what I said.
In the previous slide,
that one way is to predict is based on the past behavior.
Right?
So you look at is that how long a particular job or process the first time
is the previous first time?
And you use that as aa prediction for the future times and for the future.
And one way is to do this exponentially averaging in which you
are going to put away against the
duration of the last time the job runs,
and then discount to one minus alpha
for the existing prediction.
You have an existing prediction.
You can multiply that pre existing prediction with a way.
Then you add to one minus weight,
the last running time of the job.
At one extreme,
if you wait with zero,
the previous prediction,
this means that you don't care about the past execution,
but the last one because the weight will be one for the last execution.
And if you have a small weight for the last execution,
this means that you are going to put a lot of weight
on the previous equations before the last one.
What about the fairness?
And this is a very important aspect they are going to talk about.
We discuss about first come first serve,
not really fair.
We discuss about shortage of first not really necessary fair.
We discuss about robin actually that's kind of fair.
And now,
keep in mind that this kind of fairness is another very important metric.
We are going to use to characterize the schedule.
And fundamentally,
there is a strict,
it's a hard trade off between the average response time and the fairness.
Right?
If you remember,
we had last lecture,
we had this example and between the round robin, which is fair,
because during one round,
you schedule every process or every job.
First come, first serve.
If you remember, you are looking at equal a length of jobs.
And because if you really want to be fair,
everyone will finish at the same time.
So everyone will be like,
right?
Heard the average response time while if you are not fair,
if you run everyone at comfortable at every job to completion,
then the one that you get first are going to finish
much earlier than the last one.
Right?
So you're going to get better response to keep in mind.
The fairness may in general hurt the response to how do you and basically also
have other scheduling discipline like we are going to learn about fixed priority.
The fixed priority is also fundamental fair.
With a priority, basically assign different jobs,
different priorities,
because you deem that some jobs are more important than the others.
And by the way,
whenever you say something is more important than the other,
basically, you give up on the fairness.
It's at some level.
So how do you implement fairness?
One is around robin.
But and but the fundamental thing is that to implement fairness, you need,
in some sense,
to divide to visualize the cpu you need to divine devise acpu and give
each job a fraction of the cpu
and now,
let's talk a little bit about units.
In unix,
it's using an original unit is using priority scheduling.
So you have a bunch of priorities,
as if you remember from last time,
and the jobs and with the highest priority are going to run first.
And jobs is a lower priority can run.
Only if there are no other jobs is higher priority which are ready to run.
So this is a call.
But now how do you are going to get some fairness?
Right?
There are I many proposals,
one way to implement.
It's not very scheduled.
Okay?
So this one,
and it's a very nice analogy.
It's basically the lottery scheduling.
You give each job some number of lottery tickets.
And each time,
each time slice, you randomly pick a winning ticket.
Right?
On average,
the cpu time is proportionally allocated to the number of tickets given
to a job.
Now, how you can assign the dockets, right?
How you are going to.
And it turns out that the nice thing about this lottery scheduling,
you can approximate some of these other disciplines.
If you want,
or you can use to implement,
like, if you want to implement shortest running time first,
you can give those are small jobs,
a much larger number of tickets.
Right?
The long jobs get fewer tickets.
Now,
the nice thing it's also can avoid starvation.
If I give to each job,
at least one picket,
right?
At least one picket,
then that job is not going to be stuck forever,
because it will be at some. that is the cat will be selected.
And therefore, it will be scattered.
This is one advantage of our state priorities, right?
Again, you restate priorities.
If a job,
a if you are aaa job cannot run unless there is no other job ready to execute,
which has high approach.
With this one, we say the jobs in the heart already have more tickets,
but the job is a low priority.
Have at least on weekend.
Now I will be stuck.
Here.
It's an example,
lottery scheduling.
So assume that you have short jobs and long jobs,
and you have a job,
get ten tickets,
and long job get one ticket.
Right?
If a short job gets ten tickets and a long job gets one ticket,
then the cpu get given to the short jobs is 91%, right?
The other one is 9%.
Because in total,
you have 11 tickets in the system,
then for the short jobs,
one for the long jobs.
If you if you are going to give you have two long jobs,
and you zero short jobs,
you are going to divide,
because each long job gets on tickets,
you have only two tickets in the system.
Each of the long jobs will get 50%.
If you have two short jobs,
you have 50%, each of short jobs.
You don't have any long jobs.
You have ten, short, long,
short jobs and long, long jobs.
You have now101 tickets in the system because each short job will have ten tickets.
Therefore, the short jobs get,
they should each issue jobs,
each issue job get 9.9%,
all short jobs will get 99%.
The a as a long job will get on% and so forth.
Let me see if there is a question.
Since the scheduling is probabilistic,
isn't there still the possibility that the long job gets started
for quite a while?
That's correct.
The long job can still wait for a while,
but eventually is going to be selected while in,
say, for instance,
with shorter job first or with for a strict priority scheduling,
a job might never ever be scheduled.
If there are always enough lower priority jobs in the system,
very good question.
Okay.
What if too many short jobs are in the system to give reason
of the response time?
You can take a long time.
So it can be hard to make progress, right?
Because there are too many jobs.
So it takes too long to get your thought.
11answer here is that kick some users out of the system.
Now,
let's take a step back and let's say,
what are the kind of jobs you are expecting to run on to your computer?
And typically, there is a mix of jobs.
One of them will have the short burst time,
and some of them longer burst times.
Let's see, think about what are this kind of job?
What are the possible?
Some jobs are interactive jobs,
right?
These are,
it's editors,
your chat application.
You're interacting with the browser.
And it's not a short burst, right?
It's interactive like the short burst.
They have to respond quickly into the user interaction.
Then there are other ones which are io it's also io not necessarily the users,
but they are waiting for networking to get the data from the network
or for an eye or to complete.
Right?
There are others which are long run.
Like, for instance,
one example,
would be a compiler,
or one example.
You do training,
machine learning.
And you'd expect here that if something is interactive,
it has to get the higher priority,
because he needs to provide the user good user experience and the one which
are not in long running jobs.
It's okay that they are not interactive because they are running in the background.
Right?
It doesn't matter if a training neural network model is going to take
5 hours or 5 hours and 5 minutes.
These are not will not realize.
Okay.
So again, in general,
it's hard to characterize all the application.
But,
again, you can classify broadly in interactive applications.
They have typically have short bars and long running applications,
which have obviously long reversed.
So in recognizing that this is how early implement the scheduler,
this is multilevel feedback schedule.
The mind never scheduling is like it has a bunch of cures,
and each queue has a different priority,
the different time quant, let me guess.
So the cure at the top has a highest priority,
and there were a task.
It's the process is in cue first.
And the same time quanta says 8 million seconds.
And if a job spends
too much time on at some level,
is demoted to the next level.
In this case, there's an execute,
which is quantum of 16 millisecond.
If you spend too much at this level,
you are demoted to the next cure,
which is first conference set.
So the first two,
can each of these levels can use a different schedule and be separate?
The first two, in this case,
can use round robin.
The last time first come, first set.
Basically,
what does this mean is that if you have an interactive job which are small bursts,
that will be first endured.
At the first level,
as a highest priority,
it will be scheduled quickly.
If it's a small burst,
then it relinquishes a cpu, goes to sleep.
So it will always remain at the first level.
Now consider a long job.
Come like training a neural level.
It starts at the first level.
And after a while,
say, after several seconds,
is still running.
Right?
It's going to be in the mounted to the second level.
And the second level, if he stays and continuously running for,
say, i'm just making up like for another 1 hour,
then it's pushed to the lower level.
So you can see that in this way,
the jobs takes a long time.
They are going to fall through this kind of different levels to the bottom level.
And you'll have lower products.
These are very nice mechanics,
but adaptive mechanisms,
but in which that jobs with short bursts remains the high priority,
high levels.
And the one is lower,
which takes a long time they are going to be demoted
naturally to the levels with a lot of birds.
Okay?
The results really here,
you can think you approximate the shortest remaining time.
First.
Again, if the job is small enough,
you always got executed with the highest product.
Again, between the queues,
you have fixed priorities.
And then you can have different time quanta,
like we saw in these examples between different cures.
Here is a question.
This was probably about lottery scheduling, sorry,
for not saying it bit short job.
These are short job and long job run simultaneous.
In that case, we assume they don't run to completion.
We assume a lottery scheduling,
assume a preemptive scheduling.
This is a preemptive scheduling discipline.
So you're basically each time qanta is, again,
you run a lottery and your work.
Cpu to the winning ticket,
to the process with the winning ticket.
So from that perspective,
they are interviewed That the short jobs and long run,
long jobs are intended.
Now, obviously,
if the scheduler,
you can actually fool the scheduler.
For instance,
if I want,
what can I do for my job to remain as a high priority?
Well, i'm going to insert some io operations from time to time,
because io operations put the process of the job to split to sleep.
And there are 40 to remain at the high in the double level tears.
And that I actually run games in which it is all the law.
It's an old head program game.
You try to play against computer.
The key is to do computation at a higher priority than the company competitor.
So I see,
again, the way you do it,
the way you are doing it,
some of these game developers just put a bunch of print depths,
because the print depths, again,
you have io the thread is put us to sleep.
When you come back, it's going to go with a high priority queue.
While if you don't have to go to sleep,
you are going to fall through the levels to the bottom level,
and you are going to be with a lot.
Right?
So it's fine.
Multicore scheduling.
You have multiple core.
Now, all the processors have multiple cores.
Your mac has multiple cores,
your pc has multiple cores,
your phones have multiple cores.
Algorithm.
Italy is not a huge difference now,
but implementation way,
why is there are some things you need to keep in mind.
And one thing to keep in mind is a cash coherence.
Every court has its own cash.
Therefore, you want to have this affinity scheduling.
You want to schedule a thread on the same cpu when it doesn't come.
Speak.
Why?
Because if you do so,
that thread,
you can leverage the date of the set,
which is still in the local cache of the same superior.
If you schedule the thread on a different cpu then that cash will not have
any date out.
That's right.
Speed, lock and multiprocessor.
Let me guess.
It turns out that the one way,
actually to,
especially for multiprocessors,
there are two reasons or you use as spin locks.
The spin lock is just waiting for some condition to become true,
and you can do the test and set on a particular value, right?
It's like think about acquiring the law, right?
There are two cages to use a spin lock, one.
It's typically when you have multiple strides to execute at the same time,
like, for instance,
you have two strategies communicate between each other,
you have to run them at the same time.
So you want,
then the threats to wait for each other to be scheduled at the same time.
If I said it's scheduled.
First, the second thread,
it has to wait for the second set to be scheduled, in order to say,
for instance,
to start the communication.
You use, typically for that test and set.
Now, the problem is this test and set.
If this test and set is done on,
you have different threads on different course.
The piston said you are going to involve aaa right?
If you remember the test and set,
it takes a value from the other is savage.
And then set that value to one,
irrespective of what was the value before and write it back in the memory,
and then return the original value.
This is what is less than said, if you remember.
But if I am going to write and another test and set is going to read
from a different processor,
then you are going to the value has to go through the main memory
and then go back between.
It is going to go to me to go to the other process.
You can understand that any of these investments,
if two sides of the good test and set and they run on different cp us,
then you are going to ping pong,
the value between each other without doing anything.
And another way to do it,
if you need to do that is to do this test and set.
Basically, instead of doing having in the wildest and set,
in the while you have the value,
just look at the value.
You look for the value, for the inquiry,
look for the value to become zero.
Then this is going to just do a read.
So you read local value always.
Then you are going to do again a while at best and said,
if the value is zero.
And the reason it is a second test and set is because the race condition,
because you don't want,
because you want to acquire the lock in this case,
or which means to set the value to one.
You don't know the race condition is that two threads executing
test and set at the same time,
they receive the value zero,
and then they both of them,
they are going to settle one.
In order to avoid that,
you do a test and set again to the value.
You have only one will succeed because test and said is going to be atom.
But again, the main.here is that you avoid a right,
because you avoid the right,
you are going to go through the main memory,
and you are going to go to avoid a lot of context,
which is this.
That's a great question.
Is this an issue of correctness of all efficient?
This is a progression from outside.
It's about it.
This is about efficiency.
It's not about correctness.
Both codes are correct.
Both using both test and set and test and set are core.
It's only about the patients.
Good.
This is exactly why when these are used this spin locks and spin waiting.
When multiple threads, again,
like ii just mentioned,
work together on a multiple floor,
try to schedule them together.
This is also called gang gang scheduling.
There are other ways to do it instead of using spin lock.
Another way is basically to tell the os to tell the application.
Iiii could schedule only three of your threads, and you take care,
you should that you have three slides with running parallel.
So you can figure the way you run the program,
knowing that you have only three slides which are running in power.
Right?
By the way,
there is another reason.
There is another example in which you do this been a spin locks.
And the reason is that if you expect that you have an eye operation,
which we expect to finish very quickly,
so this is to avoid the context switch.
So say a context switch, it takes 1 millisecond,
but you are a program,
and you do an operation which takes 0.1 millisecond.
So you do not want to be just suspending a delinquent acpu and also is
not very effective for the system,
because it takes 1 million seconds to which is wasted time
to contact switching to another strike.
Instead, you just do us.
You are waiting, busy,
waiting for the for the eye operation to complete.
And then you write only for 0.1 millisecond and then continue.
Right?
No contact switching.
You spend wasted 10.10 millisecond,
but it's shorter than 1 millisecond.
It's a contact switching.
You are going to get much better response time because you
are continue to run instead of waiting to be scheduled again.
Announcements, congrats for finishing with them on.
We started to grade it will take a little bit of time.
We'll let you know for sure that is the ada to give your grading on monday,
hopefully will be very close to monday after monday.
Homework two is due on monday.
And project one code and final reporting member is due on wednesday next week.
Now.
Ii understand that things are difficult, right?
It's like we are still in this kind of remote instruction.
It's you still have a tough time,
maybe home and so forth,
and make making things work.
You are stressed.
So make sure that your da understand any issue that you may be having
because of that,
or and also is a group.
And if you,
if you want to escalate,
i'll be happy to meet with a group,
just send emails,
an email,
and i'll be happy to meet with you and provide some best practices
and some advice.
So next, let's talk about real time scheduling.
Real time scheduling,
think about you,
your the programs which runs on your car,
like abs anti blocking,
whatever for breaks.
You have in your car, you have probably of processors,
tens hundreds of programs run.
Okay?
Or think about self driving.
You really want their predictable performance.
You run sinks to finish by a certain time,
like our steering or it's out in a self driving car.
You need to steer in time, right?
If it doesn't steer in time, you have an accident.
So therefore,
these are the core the power plant.
Think about landing and taking off for airplanes,
which is done automatically.
For all of these use cases,
you need to have programs.
For sure,
you don't get starvation,
right?
And you can predict these are predictable.
Now, the real time is, again,
is predictable predictability about things happening by a certain time.
It's not about being fast.
And there are multiple classes about real time.
In real time, it's again, a big area.
There are conferences only dedicated real time.
It's about meetings, the deadlines, right?
You have some deadlines by some task is to finish.
And in these areas,
there are different categories.
There are soft real deadlines,
hard real time deadlines.
You need to meet all the deadlines.
Several times, best effort.
Try to be your best to meet.
Most of them.
Depends on the application that you expect.
There are a lot of algorithms,
and the algorithms scaling algorithms are quite different.
And we are going to look at only one, which is very simple,
which is early deadline first.
By the way, another,
for an example of a soft real time,
is for multimedia,
for your playing back video or the voice over when you chat over your over phone.
Right?
It's great to have hard deadlines.
Your message,
what you are saying to arrive to the other and say
within 15 minutes seconds never later.
But if it's alive,
it's a little bit longer.
It's okay.
The humans are going to adapt.
And here we are,
and we are going to talk about only ones are scheduling, this discipline,
which is a leader line first.
But here is a model.
The model is that the task have deadlines.
This they declare about the computation time is now.
So here we are talking about sinks,
getting repeatedly being done.
You have pretty good idea about each when each task,
how long each task is going to take.
It's different from general case in which it's hard to predict the future.
Here, you have to predict the future,
because how can you set up a deadline without knowing how much
a conversation will take?
It's impossible.
So it's part of the game here that you are going to know how long a task
is going to take.
Okay.
Now the question is,
you have multiple tasks.
Each of them, they have certain computation time and certain deadlines.
The computer, the thing is that can all the task meets at that place.
That's a good question.
Right?
Here is one of the example of scheduling.
Again, it's preemptive.
You still have time quanta between these tasks.
And it turns out this other deadlines,
the up arrows.
The answer is apparatus is when the task,
even which triggers the computation arrives.
And the down arrows are the deadlines.
And here is an example in which this scheduling,
particular scheduling of these tasks is going to violate the deadlines for desktop.
Now,
I like I mentioned,
we are going to learn about one
such a scheduling discipline and leader line first.
Difficult.
They assume that the task I is periodic is period pi meaning
that and computation ci meaning
that in each period,
you have to perform a computation for that task,
like, for instance,
every 100 millisecond,
the task needs to perform a computation of 10 millisecond.
Example.
Think about,
It's again, something like a self driving car or anything in the car.
You have sensors which are like video cameras and so forth,
which periodically take take a measurements,
maybe the state of the brake or the speed,
or obviously a video frame.
Right?
And these are periodic.
And they need to be processed.
Before the next measurement mistaken,
we need to process the previous measure.
But that's kind of my motivation.
And the early deadline first is very simple,
is basically saying,
like the name implies,
you always schedule the task whose deadline is the earliest.
That's it.
Let's take an example.
Okay.
So let's have three tasks.
And for each task,
the two numbers in parentages represent the period,
the first number, and how long it needs to come?
It should take to compute in this period.
So for one,
means that every 4 time, you need say,
for every set 4 seconds,
t one is requires 1 second of computation.
The two during 5 seconds requires 2 seconds of computation.
These three average 7 seconds requires 2 seconds of competition.
Right?
And these are the first deadlines, right?
Because you need to finish to process in the current period
before the next period starts.
41, the first deadline is Time for, sorry,
42 is five, 4037.
So there are four.
First,
you are going to schedule and say that i'm going to hear each one.
So first, you are going to schedule.
You are.
Right?
Why?
Because the deadline the earliest.
Right?
You see,
is that for the other deadlines are at five and seven,
once you are done of that,
you are going to schedule p two.
And let's assume that we don't preempt here, for simplicity,
because the two has earlier deadlines and these 35 versus seven to schedule
that.
And finally,
you schedule pc now,
what are the next deadlines?
He said the next deadlines of t one is at time of eight.
The next line of the two is time ten,
and the next line of history is time14.
We are going to spend the first step,
which is the next deadline.
Again, duan is earlier strong.
Then again, d two and against this.
Again.
But again,
before going to this three,
let's look at the next at last.
The next deadline of t one is now 12.
The next deadline of t two is now 15.
The next deadline of these three, actually,
the second deadline,
it's 14,
which is the earliest deadlines we need to consider now.
Right?
You are the next one.
It's 12.
They do 50 and 340.
Obviously still on.
They are going to schedule pr so now you see that you schedule
for the first three periods of yuan,
while for these three,
you scattered for only one.
But now after a schedule 41,
you are going to consider pc because it's deadline.
It's earlier than people.
And then you continue.
Now, an interesting question here.
It's,
let me just say it's how do you know that you can satisfy the algorithms
can satisfy all the task deadlines?
As you can see, from the previous example, is not easy.
The order that it changes as your progress.
Okay?
It's actually quite complicated.
Now, it turns out that is early deadline.
First, there is a simple condition.
You can use to check whether you can satisfy early deadline first,
satisfy the deadlines of all tasks,
and that you sum up the computation of a period for all tasks.
And if that is the lesson one,
you the edf is feasible.
It's working.
In our case, it's 1 over 4 plus 2 over 5 plus 2 over 7 is less than one.
It's feasible.
We've seen, at least from our simulation for the first,
whatever 30 seconds.
This is very cool, because you see,
this is also optimal from the point of view optimization,
because c over b for a task is how much is going to utilize from the cpu
if I want to utilize,
I have like the first task,
one time unit,
1 second out of 4 seconds,
the utilization that task alone is going to get 1 over 4 of the cpu
25% of the cpu so the sum of
these see over these cannot be greater than one,
right?
Because you cannot use more cp us than you have.
This is a very good.
That's how you are talking about salary, because it's very good.
It's also optimal.
Now, things are more complicated,
and we touch a little bit about starvation.
We are going to talk more during this lecture and the next lecture.
One thing to make sure is that starvation is different from deadlock.
Starvations means that you are a star,
but eventually you are not,
you can still run.
Like we are talking.
In the previous case, you are start and you can be started forever.
If there are prosperity scheduling.
If there are always lower produce tasks or jobs in the system,
but once that they are no longer,
you are scared that look is a different in the sense that you get
to a point that you cannot resolve that.
No matter what happens in the system,
unless you kill the process, so you start the system.
Right?
We'll talk more about the next time,
but we also going to touch a little bit during this lecture.
You have these causes of starvation, scaling police, like we said,
never runs a particular thread on the cpo and so forth.
But we'll explore more about these problems.
One way to avoid survey starvation is not one way.
It's it's obviously one way to alleviate starvation.
Is that if the cpu is always yours,
if there is work to do,
right?
If you have a scheduler which doesn't use the cpu and keep the cpu idol,
obviously, it's much higher chance that you are going to stop some threats.
The schedulers, which are always using cpu.
They don't leave the cpu idle while there is work to do while there are
ready processes in the system.
Already threats they are called work on sale.
They are scheduled which are not considering a schedule which are they
may maintain the cpu idle,
even if there are processes in the system,
which can are ready to execute.
And obvious, like I said,
they can linear triviality to this to celebration.
In this class, you'll assume that the schedulers were concerned.
We don't need to worry about hong kong were conserving,
but just to keep for completeness,
let you know that there are such catalysts.
Here is another thing.
There's another example of schedule as a few example of schedule,
which leads to starvation.
Again, you already knew now about some of them.
Here is a new one,
is life for last in first out.
It's as opposed to first team first out or first come first serve.
This is going to serve the tasks which arrived,
which are inserted,
which arrived the latest first.
Right?
And this can be very unfair and obviously can cause starvation,
because you can have new task always arriving.
You are already all only going to schedule those.
And when arrival rate exceeds the how much the number of task which you get,
it's more than what you can process,
obviously are going to start the whole task.
54doesn't really have that problem.
But anyway, this is just about what about first come, first set,
but it for five or first come first set is the same thing.
They don't have as much of a problem,
because eventually you are going to drain the cure.
Right?
Let me see.
It's a question.
Why would you ever want a non work on serving scheduler?
A that's a good question.
Why we always would like to.
So there are there are schedulers which you want to be very predictable.
There are scheduler.
You want to happen certain things to happen exactly the right at the right time.
You want, for instance,
to produce a result every 100 millisecond.
In that particular case,
even if you can process more and earlier,
you are not going to process because you are going to produce a disaster.
So that's kind of one.
When you want to regularly,
this is also a networking.
You're not talking.
You want to send one packet.
Every say you have one packet,
you are going to send one microsecond.
Now you may ask,
why do you want to do that?
Right?
Why?
And in general,
one reason you may want to do this to keep this kind of pace,
because you don't want to overwhelm the next stage or the next processing stage,
like, for instance, in networking.
If you send burst of packets instead of facing them,
then you have a higher probability.
You are going to go into overflow,
to send more packets and downstream router can handle.
Then I guess it'll be lost.
So that's an example.
It's again, the first come first serve.
The only problem you have is that you are going to have a very long job
with nobody else.
Then you have to start for samoa while.
But it's again, as long as over some time intervals,
the load of purpose,
a system that the system has to process is lower than the capacitor of the system.
Everyone's is going to run is the round robin from the starvation.
If you have any processes and if you have aa time quantum
of then of q then your turn will come every n minus one times
few millisecond.
What are you doing?
So we see you don't have salvation.
Now is priority scheduling from the salvation.
It is we just discuss about that, right?
Again, early scheduling grants every job,
every first it has to finish all the jobs at the high priority level
before going to the next time.
And now as what you say,
what is the word it's like as a preview for the next lecture,
for the deadlock?
Let me give you one example about a deadlock.
We alluded about this deadlock last lecture when we talk about priority inversion.
This is what can happen.
But again, that means you are stuck.
Can do anything.
Even if you have no other job in the system, you are still stuck,
you cannot make progress.
So say a job at priority one,
lower priority acquire a lot.
And now the job one is in critical section.
But now jobs three comes, it's a hybrid,
and jobs three tries to acquire the lock held by job one.
Right?
But you cannot your block on a query.
By the way,
now, job three waits for the job one to finish to release a lock.
And job to one is not executive because jobs three has a higher product.
That's kind of that.
This is priority inversion,
because you are waiting for a job with a lower priority to release a lock.
And we cannot believe a lot because of you.
And this is the definition of working version.
This is another example is a live block.
You have local choirs, local release,
the low priority.
The high priority is, again,
try to achieve live long,
always busy waiting.
So what are the solutions?
One solution is priority donation or inheritance.
In this particular case, if job one,
which is not priority, holds a lock,
and jobs three wants to acquire it.
What happens in this case?
Job three, donate its priority to job one.
So job one while it is a critical section and while holding the lock,
now it's going to be promoted to priority three to the highest priority.
Now it's got times to run and to finish after he believes it goes back,
job one and priority one,
dollar priority on his previous priority and jobs three can acquire the law.
And you're going to have in protective.
Here.
It's an example.
This is not only theoretical.
This is a marathon,
but find a robber.
And I have here for the fun,
which is not necessarily like it with the lecture.
This is in 97 or so many years ago.
But it was a big event because it was the first one of these
satellites.
And actually it has also actually landed on the planet since 76,
so after 21 years, right?
And one thing it was fun.
It was this kind of different delivery mechanics.
Let me just see whether I have this one.
So i'm guessed, okay,
do you see my screen?
You don't see my screen.
Let me just, i'm not sure how much you see it.
For some reason, I cannot let me see if I can do it.
Let's do this for now.
It's a very interesting delivery mechanics.
How is this lander delivered how he planned it on mars?
It has like balloons, like airbags,
all over the place.
And this is how is the house delivered?
Very innovative, very, very cool.
So eventually stopped.
But this is the one we are talking about.
And now the problem is that a few days intermissions into the mission,
multiple systems resets occur,
and it was forced for the software.
And the system appeared to reboot randomly,
losing valuable time and making progress.
What it turned out to be was priority inversion.
It was his priority to high priority,
which was a data distribution task.
They need a lock.
The problem is that the collector, the one,
another task, which was collecting samples, collecting data,
which was lower priority,
was getting the lock.
Now,
the priority,
the collector adds a log.
And the data distribution task couldn't acquire the law.
Now, what happens?
Typically in these systems?
You have a watchdog.
It's a the white dog is a process which looks whether there is forward progress.
If there is no further progress and you have this, in this case, a backlog,
what is going to do is going to reboot the system.
It turns out that the rose actually called for the priority donation
to avoid this problem,
writing version.
But it was turned off because
the developers thought it's still worried about the performance.
In this case, the fix was to upload and feedback the code.
Again, what you are talking here is not only theoretical.
It happens.
Let's talk about others.
It's shortest time first and multilevel feedback you from the starvation.
They are right.
Like we discussed shortest time first.
The long job can be started in the favor of short runs.
If you have always short jobs arriving,
they are going to start the long jobs with multilevel feet queue fit by queue.
It's an approximation assured that remaining time first.
So it suffers from the same problem.
Again, in some sense,
the case, the cause for starvation, it's always a priority,
whether it's a fixed priority,
or whether it's implicit,
explicit fixed priority or implicit priority,
like the length of a job.
So you have this kind of a priority which is encoded in the schedulers,
how schedule make the decision?
It should be a raise a flag that it you may then end up with starvation.
Again, our job, remember,
is the server mix of CPU bound and io bound and interactive jobs effectively.
Here you want to have interactive jobs to be interactive,
be very quick response time,
verify the response time.
We need to give I abound the jobs enough CPU so that they are going to do
their work.
Ideally want them to be our bound, right?
And then the CPU bound ones,
you want to still let them running to eventually finish.
Now,
the scheduling discipline,
it's also we are going to learn and we learned.
It's also a reflection of the changes in the landscape of computers
for big mainframes,
where you have a lot of users using them.
To b C's,
you have one user over and maybe one program earlier on a single machine
to multiple programs on a single machine,
but only one users.
And to even internet of things,
which the things are sitting there just to get some Information from the environment.
Right?
So priority by scheduling is rooted in times sharing.
When you have fewer resources,
lot of things running on the same competing for the resources.
And that's why.
But and then they LED to starvation.
People try to resolve the starvation,
try to develop new scheduling,
which are more fair,
and things like that.
And one question here is that this is
desperate providing some jobs necessarily start those that aren't prioritized.
Not three priorities in certain cases, like we've seen, absolutely.
It turns out that people have a bunch of holistics to reduce that miss,
reduce,
alleviate starvation.
There are a few ways to do it.
Multilevel feedback,
if you remember,
tries to reduce the starvation by having CPU bounded jobs,
falling that the one which keeps along to,
it takes a long time to admit,
to be deprived,
to go to a lower priority in time.
The other things are the mechanics like the mechanics,
which are API exposed to the users to being nice.
Right?
So basically, and if you want it to be nice and is this a unique command,
you can be prioritize your task,
your program.
So other people will work and run their programs.
The nice value ranged from-20 to 19,
negative values are not nice.
The things is that for in this particular,
in this particular case,
you can think about for unique sum systems, like unique.
Suddenly, some version of UNIX,
the lower priorities are the lower properties.
Values are higher priorities.
So far in all our examples,
you assume the higher priority values of priority three has a high priority.
But in UNIX,
at least some version of UNIX is the other around.
The lower priority values of priority zero is the highest priority,
and priority three is the lower price.
Then in this case,
so therefore, if you increase a nice value, you increase,
you basically decrease a priority of your increase a priority value,
but it is a priority of your job.
Okay?
Let me stop here.
And we are almost done with the lecture,
but we are going to continue next time.
It's the last lecture on scheduling.
And we are going to look a little bit about Linux,
how Linux is implemented.
And then we are going to talk a little bit more about fairness with that.
If there are any other questions, I could answer
the deadlock.
There only happens that does deadlock only happens here on spin locks.
In that particular example is yes.
But interlock is a much more general concept like we will see you next time.
No.
Other questions.
Thank you so much, sir.
And I am going to see you on Monday.
Good luck with your homework and the project.
Bye.