Hello, everyone.
So today we are going to finish the discussion on scheduling,
and then we are going to start the discussion on deadlocks.
So last time,
we discussed quite a bit about a few scheduling disciplines.
If you remember one scheduling disciplines which has been
very popular and it's still popular,
it's priority scheduling.
And one of the reason it's popular,
it's very simple.
The pure priority scheduling, if you remember,
you have different levels of priorities,
and you always start from the highest priority.
And then you run the jobs at the highest priority.
Only after you are done with those jobs,
you can go to the lower priority.
One obvious question is desperate,
privatizing some jobs,
necessarily start up those that aren't prioritized.
So do higher priority jobs,
necessarily start of lower priority jobs.
And this is what we are going to talk a little bit about here.
And what kind of clicks you can do to
priority scheduling to avoid starvation,
right?
Because is if you remember,
if you have always high priority jobs,
then you'll never serve the low priority job jobs.
So there, therefore,
you are going to start to starve the low priority jobs.
Let's look through some of these mechanisms.
On mechanics,
it's an api which is provided by early unique systems,
which is called nice.
This,
as the name implies,
it allows you as a user to be nice to others,
the way you are going to be nice to others is by lowering the priority
of your job of your application.
In the case of unix,
lower values of priorities mean high priority.
And is a nice value ranges from my-20 to 19.
Negative value values are not nice.
In order to be nice,
you can increase this value,
which means lower product.
Okay?
So that's very interesting.
Now a few words about linux.
Let's see how linux the basic scheduler is.
It's organized and it's implemented.
So you have 140 priorities.
The first 100 are for the kernel and the real time tasks.
Again, the real time task are the one who are predictable.
You want to be predictable.
And then the last 40 are for the user tasks.
And,
again, lower priority values,
it means higher priority.
And the algorithm is all fun of fun complexity,
meaning that it takes constant time to select the next process to run.
And you also have time slices.
So its preemptive scheduler,
a job or a process doesn't,
and to completion is going to be interrupted when his time slice expires.
There is also a 140 bit bit mask,
which indicates the presence or absence of a job at the given priority level.
So why do you have that bit mask?
Right?
The reason you have that this mask is that think about you want to be
very quick and you select the
next job to our next process to run.
Now assume that you have two processes in the system,
one process that priority is zero plus the priority one thirty nine o k
so once you finish to run the process of priority zero,
you need to run the process as a priority to 139.
But you need to find that process,
that process.
And the simple implementation is to have a list of priorities.
And each head of that of for each item in this priority list,
it's a list of processes that are priority.
Now, you start from zero,
and you are done with the process.
Now you have to go to next one,
which is the next level and the next level and the next level until you get
139 in order to find the next processor.
If you have a bit mask,
then basically the bit mask,
i'm just going to look at the bit mask which is 140 bits.
The bit mass will say that the next automatic will say that only there are
processes active at level,
priority level on 39.
In between there is no process active.
The beats in the bit mascot, not set.
So it's very easy to do.
The other thing which is doing is that you have two
priority queues in terms of for active processes,
the processes that you have to start to.
They are still to run and then expire.
Processes expire means after you are going to run a process,
you are going to put it in the expired.
And then once you are done with all the processes in the active queue,
the active queue is empty.
You just switch,
be expired, so active become expired,
q and expired becomes the active.
You swap them.
This is what an example you go through the active queues.
You have here, all these priorities,
each task with its own priorities.
And once you are done with all the tasks from the active cure,
you are going to put them all in the expire queue.
And then you are just going to swap they expired you with around you.
Any questions?
And then in order to avoid kind of starvation,
like we discussed last time, there are many holistics.
Like you, if a task is aisle bound,
you try to boost this priority to increase its priority.
If a task running for too long,
you are going to lower like its priority.
More precisely, here is a list of holistics.
The user task priority is adjusted in
+-5 increments.
It's, again,
you have the user task priorities between one hundred and one hundred seventy nine.
And basically,
you are going to update it, like, for instance,
if the sleep time and a run time,
if the process lives much longer than it runs, you increase this priority.
This is probably because it's an aisle bound task.
If he's running for a long time,
you are going to decrease disparage.
And if he doesn't sleep at all,
again, if you task it for a long time,
you are going to a cure credit,
you are going to increase a priority.
When he's going to run, you are going to spend this credit.
You're going to decrease this priority if it's running for too long.
And for interactive tasks,
you give them special treatment,
because you want to always have high priority.
Although in general, many of the interactive tasks are the aisle bound,
because they are waiting for the user input.
Many of them.
So then they can go automatically higher priority because they
are going to sleep more than they are.
Let's see that I have two questions here.
That's a very good question.
So the question is,
does this mean getting a new process?
Schedule takes a long time since the existing cure needs to be exhausted
before new things can be added?
Yeah.
And you are right.
It's a strategy in the process is getting scheduled,
not the process itself.
Although we are, again, when you have one process, one thread,
we are going to use interchangeable.
So this very much depends on the scheduler.
But when you are going to run a new process,
typically you put the process as the highest priority.
This means that you are going to start executing that process or thread quickly,
which is the highest priority.
You can start executing that thread as soon as you finish executing
the current thread.
When the time slice of the current slide you are executing is expired.
It's also here you receive a word of histories.
You use the studies is to avoid changing interactive data
from temporary changing changes in behavior.
What is hysteresis?
Do you know,
anyone you can say on the chat?
The we are not going to go into more data into a lot of details here,
but hysteresis means that when you have a process,
a control system, in general,
and you have a threshold.
And when that exceeds a threshold,
you change the output and you decrease the threshold,
you reduce your game, change the output.
If you have a system which is just around the threshold,
the system changes its behavior.
Quite frequently,
you go on to, and even if you has noise,
if you have to imagine that you have noise around the threshold.
So you want to avoid that.
In order to avoid that, you have actually, in general, two thresholds.
You have one thresholds,
low threshold, and high threshold.
And you change the behavior.
When you exceed a high threshold or in its own,
you go under the low threshold.
In that sense, you have a range.
The system behavior doesn't change it.
So if there is a noise,
we are within that range,
the system will become constant.
For instance, in this particular case,
you don't want to change the behavior.
Like, for instance,
imagine that you have an editor with an editor,
not editor,
maybe I don't know whether use laid back or something like that,
or you have an editor.
Let's take an editor.
So you take an editor, and there are two different regimes.
One, you are going entering the text, editing the text.
And another one is, for instance,
you save or love.
Okay?
You don't want save or load or even worse.
The editor doing some rendering and doing some compute heavy, say,
maybe operations.
You don't want that,
just because you do a little bit of computation that to make the editor
less responsible,
you want to be more robust.
And only if it's for a long time,
the editor just doing some a lot of rendering.
Maybe you are going to declarize that what hysteresis means
real time task.
They have lower than 100 priority.
They also pm the non narrative task.
For each queue.
At each level, there are 2 kinds of schemes.
At this priority level, again,
you have multiple each priority levels.
You have a queue,
which contains multiple processes or threads.
And you can use all the 54 without no time slice or round robin,
there is a time slice.
Here is a real time task.
They are not scheduled using the early deadline first,
which we learned last time,
the last lecture,
they are assigned priorities.
There are other scheduling algorithms,
real time scheduling algorithms,
which can use priorities to schedule these tasks and still guarantees you
can meet the deadlines.
Another thing like, if you remember,
we can do and to be more robust and avoid starvation,
is basically using proportional share schedule.
This is regulated with lottery scheduling.
Lottery scheduling is an implementation of of proportional share scheduling.
And basically, here, it's, again,
if you remember,
you allocate these tickets and you have, say,
100 tickets,
maybe you are going to give to one thread.
You are going to give ten tickets and the other 190 tickets.
Okay?
Now you are going to do the lottery.
So every time though you select a winning ticket,
now, obviously, the probability of selecting the second thread,
which has 90 tickets,
it's 9 times higher than probably to select the first ride,
which is one ticket,
which has only ten tickets.
This means that you give to the second thread, nine,
90% of the cpu on the average,
the first thread only 10%.
So you can see that you can use this kind of weights is different.
A number of tickets you are giving to each thread to approximate priorities.
Right?
Because clearly you can see that the task with the thread with a90 tickets
has a higher priority than the task with ten tickets.
The nice think about this kind of scheme is that it avoid starvation,
right?
Even if you give a task,
19 aa thread,
99 tickets and another said only one still out, on the average,
out of 100 time slices or quanta.
The stablish has only one ticket is going to get a chance to run.
So it's no stop.
This is basically tells you a little bit more giving a little more math on that.
Now you may ask,
then why we don't do only this lottery scheduling,
all this proportional sharing?
Right?
The answer is that it's harder to implement.
It's more complex to implement,
is slower.
Then the priority or so, is so on.
All of one super simple to implement.
So that's yes.
Let's again, unix has a lot of schedulers, actually.
The first one was a basic scheduler.
You have this kind of two cures,
active and expired.
It's all fun, very simple,
but it has also a more more sophisticated scheduler.
And one of that, this is completely fair scheduler.
The back the idea here is to track the cpu time per thread
and schedule stress to match up on average rate of execution.
Right?
So basically, you want,
in other words,
You are different threads.
If you don't have different threads,
more than one threads,
you want all of them to make kind of progress at the same rate.
That's a high level.
Okay?
This is if the cpu time like,
this is the cpu time,
and this is one over n you have three threads.
In this case, n is three.
This is each of them.
You get 1/3 of the cpu then you look at how long each of them they run,
starting for a given time.
And in this case, the one run longer than the two.
And these three.
Therefore,
here you are going to give the next time when you are going to schedule,
you are going to sell to select probability, too,
because you want to catch up with to do to catch up with the one and history.
Again,
this is a simple one.
A simple case by so complicated, right?
Because threats do not start at the same time.
Threads.
Excuse me,
threads are the io bounded, right?
Instead of they don't use their entire full quanta.
Okay.
So there are many things,
and that's why these schedulers are much more complicated.
There are a lot of papers,
research papers written about these catalysts.
This is discussion is to give you a sense,
some intuition about what are the problems and how these schedulers are working.
Again, this is a goal here,
is to provide this illusion of conflict of fairness.
Each of the past thread gets the same kind of makes progress is the same,
but I get cpu the same, right?
And it's close related with factory.
How do you implement it?
You can use a heap scheduler,
but it's hard.
A heap schedule is log n right?
Or n is a number of threads.
If you look,
if you look about the number of threads on your mac or on your probably pc,
you'll see that you can have on your machine.
You can have like tens of thousands of cells at a given time,
tens of thousands.
This is can be quite slow.
The log n are to remove threads.
Right?
But this is a very using a heap like scheduling.
It's easy because you can always from a hip,
you are going to get select the task which has allow us cpu time,
which user cpu the list.
Now, we said that these things are more complicated.
You can have a sleeping seat threads.
What do you do if a thread is sleeping?
Because waits for some event to happen or it's like think about the thread
is sleeping,
which as a process.
When forks,
another process is going to sleep and wait for the other process to finish
and to join back.
Basically, one thing to hear you is like when a thread sleeps,
you don't have basis if you types,
if you don't have basic advances,
cpu time,
then when it wakes up,
is going to have low cpu time.
It's going to have priority is going to be scheduled.
Right?
But now, the problem is that you cannot do that unbounded.
Like what happens if I have a thread which is slips from me since yesterday?
Right?
That will have a higher than a lower superior time than anything in the system.
Basically,
it's going to have priority over all of them.
So you need to adjust for that as well.
It's again, we are not going to go into all the details.
But at the high level,
once one trade off with the schedulers,
like we also discussed last lecture,
it's about between being very responsive and between a bit risk
between responsibility and fairness.
Right?
You remember, it's like an algorithm which is fair is round robin.
Each of them you go across around the threads.
And every round you are going to schedule to give a time quanta
through each thread thread.
That's very fair.
However, the memory don't be very responsive,
because you have any threads.
You need to wait for n minus up to n minus one times quanta to get a time contact.
What was right?
Thread particular thread has can wait for n minus one times one.
On the other hand,
the priority is very effective and provide your low response time,
at least for the threads with a high priority.
Right?
If you have,
they say, ten threads and the interactive studies priority,
the highest priority that is going to set up a very, very fast.
But it's not going to be fair, right?
Because the high priority threads are going to get all the cpu
as the expense of low priority sets.
Right?
So that's a fundamental trade off.
And what linux is doing, it has this kind of, perhaps,
could this constraint about target latency?
It's a period of time over each.
Every process gets service right time,
guaranteed that target latency.
So I say it is 100 million seconds.
I'm gonna be that i'm going to get access to the cpo within every 100 millisecond.
This defines a time quanta,
because if you have n number is a number of processes or thread,
then the time quantity is a target latency over m right?
For instance, if you have the target latency,
20 millisecond and you have four processes,
but is a time quantity has to be five, right?
Because it's longer.
You cannot guarantee that this process is going to get access to the cpu is
in 20 millisecond.
Right?
But now if you have20 millisecond,
they have 200 processes.
The time quanta can be 0.1 millisecond,
which is too little, right?
To remember, if it's a time slice of time quantity is too small,
then the overhead of context switching can dominate.
You are doing more context switches between this kind of processes
than really running these processes.
Right?
So this is one thing.
The other thing is about,
obviously want to the reason we want to avoid xa lot
of overheading context switching is to increase to preserve the throughput,
right?
This robot is defined as a useful work done by a system.
Context switching is not useful work.
Therefore, in order to make sure that this report is not going to plummet,
it's not going to be too low.
You are going to,
we are going to say,
what is the minimum length of any time slice?
So it's a minimum ground already constraints.
You have a target latency and meaning granularity, which, in general,
can be at odds,
because they are at odds in sometimes you have to violate one.
Like, for instance,
if you have target latency of 20 million seconds and minimum gratitude
of 1 million seconds,
then in this case,
you can minimum granularity is going to prevail and is going.
You cannot reduce the time slice to less autonomy seconds and the target latency,
you cannot do it.
If you just do our robin.
Right?
Because if you do our robin is going to take100 millisecond to a process to
get it stern.
So you need to wait for 99 million seconds to get your turn.
You are going to violate the target latency here.
It's a question here.
What is granularity?
Yeah.
Okay, so these are very good questions.
What is granularity?
It's how granular you are going to provide.
What is the granularity at which you are going to provide the service?
I this is what we mean.
It's like what we mean is about what is the minimum length of the time slices.
This is what I mean by granularity.
What is the times life size?
Why would we have boss?
It seems like minimum length is the only real powerful constraint.
Yes, you are correct.
And this is, in this example,
we illustrated that minimum priority is a stronger constraint, if you want.
Because if you go too low,
then the system doesn't may not do any work, right?
It's again, spend all the time doing contact switching.
But target latency,
it's also a constraint if you want to support interactive workloads.
Right?
How we are going to,
there has to be,
there are limits in terms of how responsive your editor or your computer
should be.
Different applications should be to provide you a good experience.
Okay?
So you should strive to provide that kind of level of interactivity
and the level of interactivity.
It's obviously related with this,
a target latency.
Right?
Because if you are going,
if the target latency you like,
if you cannot get your turn,
say, in 500 millisecond,
this means that your application,
you may have to wait for half a second for your application to respond
your text application editor water.
So in summary,
as the minimum granularity is a stronger constraint,
but target latency captures the demands of the interactive applications.
It's also important.
The other question here is about priority like this kind of a little bit
for organization.
What if you want to give more cpu to some to some threads or unless to another?
So allowed for a different rate of execution is very similar.
It's awake.
It's like you give you give away, in some sense,
you see that is w so basically you have the equal share is
basically the equal share here.
It's about how much of the cpu you are going to give.
And it started latency over there, right?
Like we discussed earlier on.
Here is a way to sharing.
You are going to give.
Within one of these target shares,
you are going to run one thread more times, multiple times.
This is very, very similar,
but it's using different notation,
but in as the the outcome is basically identical a it's another implementation
to having different number of tickets,
giving different number of tickets to different threads or processes.
That's basically what it is.
Right?
This is basic equal share.
It's one over n if you want weighted share w you'll give
up higher weight one process.
This.
So then you get the fraction you are going to get from the cpu it's your weight
divided by the sum of the ways of all the other sets of processes.
They use a nice value to reflect shares rather than priority.
This is over using api an existing api and this is how you use it.
You have the nice is becoming the exponent.
This is how you are basically think about that when you are going to use nice,
what will happen?
You are going to change the weight as provided by this formula.
And I your way, by default, is 1, 10,
24/1, 25.
It's 10, 24 if you are going to increase your nice.
So you have to basically being nice.
It means that you get less access to the cpu so you let others use acpu
for longer.
Right?
That means to be nice.
And this is reflected in getting a lower weight.
Again,
the particular way you are going to get by using nice is given by this formula,
10,
24/1.25 at power.
Nice.
It's here just to give you a sense.
If it's a nice,
it's implemented of in terms implemented,
if you remember that,
you can implement it,
units of five,
1.25 power five is three.
Right?
So if you increase your 9th×5,
this means that your way to decrease by three,
there is a concept of virtual time.
We are not going to discuss it here.
But if you have questions,
i'll be more than happy to talk about this special time.
I did a lot of research during my phd many years back on this one.
So really,
again, scheduling is a complex problem.
There are many hundreds of scheduling algorithms,
hundreds thousands of research papers that are
probably only about just talking about fair queuing
or proportional sharing is the same name for the kind of the same scalar.
But in different domains,
like cpo networking,
there are probably hundreds of thousands of papers,
only for this particular discipline.
So it's huge.
And why is that?
Is?
Because the scheduler is hard,
because you want to do it extremely fast.
And then there are different competing priorities,
competing demands from the applications.
Right?
You want to be fair.
You want to be interactive.
You want to have high throughput and so forth.
And therefore,
that's why for different Demands or from the applications,
you can come up with different schedulers,
which are best fit to satisfy those demands.
For instance, if you want cpo struggle,
throughput is first come first set up.
Because what you want to minimize,
you have you want to minimize the overhead for the scheduler.
First comfort said, picking up a a new job.
It's super easy.
It's all fun, right?
It's the head of the queue.
And then there is no context switching.
And you are going to continue to run that the job to completion,
minimizing the operation,
to select the overhead,
to select the next job,
minimizes the overhead to the number of context switches.
Average response time is shortest time.
First, right?
This is probable optimal to read to up to minimize the average response time,
and so forth.
Fairness here, you have silly,
no cfs you can let lottery scheduling.
If this is for superior time,
also fairness and fairness,
if you want to be very predictable,
how long to wait until to get the cpu just to go round robin?
This is relatively targeted latency meeting.
The outlines a leader line first.
If you want to have some very few important tasks which they cannot be delayed,
you can use priority.
For our support is yours.
Srdp approximation.
Again, we discuss about that, I think, two lecture ago,
but we have these examples of two tasks which each of them takes1 week.
And then you have this other task,
which is our bound.
It takes runs for 1 million seconds and race for 9 million seconds.
If I remember, correct?
Okay.
Now, how to evaluate these scheduling algorithms?
Right?
You have all of those different properties.
How and you are going to design them,
how you are going to evaluate.
There are several ways.
First of all, deterministic,
you basically, you get a workload.
And given this workload,
you compute the performance of the algorithms in the face of that workload performance,
meaning response times throughput,
latency, whatever metrics you care about for your application.
A deterministic pray, term workout,
you say you are going to have each
processes continue every one process.
You have one process arriving.
1 second, and this process is going to have10 seconds or sort of compute,
right?
Or a thing like that.
Okay?
Queuing models.
This is a mathematical approach for stochastic workload.
In this particular case.
Basically, you are saying that the load is not deterministic,
right?
You give the load in statistical terms.
Is all you say, on the average,
you'll have one process arriving every second.
This process are on the average,
has it takes running time is 10 seconds.
Those numbers are drawn from a particular distribution, like, for instance,
the length of the process is exponentially distributed.
Right?
The average, the mean is 10 minutes, 10 seconds.
The arrival time is like, say,
poisson distribute.
Poisson means that the in the inter arrival between processes is drawn
from an exponential distribution.
This is just an example.
And for that, you are going to get statistic.
You are going to be able to compute statistically,
what are the performance of the scheduler alike?
For instance, again, mean response time or and things like that.
And the other one, you just implement it.
You just takes python.
You implement a simple simulator and run it and see what results you get.
This is general, flexible,
as long as you don't have bugs in your simulator.
So a final order on scheduling,
the scheduling matters when there are not enough resources and many of the
things we learn in this class,
many of the algorithms and many of the problem is solved.
These problems occur because there are not enough resources.
We'll see virtual memory.
Why do we have ritual memory?
That?
Because there is not enough physical memory.
It's one of the reasons not scheduling.
Why do we need to have a scheduling or sophisticated scheduling?
Because there are not enough superiors.
If you have one cpu per thread,
there is no scheduling right problem.
Okay.
Why shouldn't you simply buy a faster computer or highways?
Look,
you can buy it if you can afford it, but remember,
the more slow is ending.
Now, if you buy a new computer,
you could buy your mac or your rpc it's not a lot of more powerful
than the one you have from 3 years back.
Right?
You need to be careful about not.
You don't understand too much money.
The other thing, what you need to understand,
this is a curve on this right hand side.
Maybe we should do a lecture on it,
because it's extremely important.
A it's an extremely important curve.
And this is what I say.
This curve.
Say your system has a certain capacity.
When you are approaching the capacity of the system,
the response time is growing super linear.
It's almost goes to infinity.
A as if you go to that,
if you go to 100%,
okay?
You can.
And again,
we don't have time here to say why,
but intuitively think about the highway and the rush hour.
So it's not like,
it's like the difference where you start to be to approach the capacity
of the highway.
And if you just inject a few cars,
a few more cars,
then the delay is going to shut up.
For instance, if there are on the highway,
now there are 100 cars per hour.
The capacity of the system is 120.
And now you have a speed,
and the latency says 50 miles per hour.
Now, if you add ten more cars,
there is still a lesser capacity.
Instead of going 50 miles per hour,
you are going to go suddenly 20 miles per hour.
And again, things about your experience,
just a few more cars,
everything to a crawl.
Again, let me see what I can have a lecture on that.
Now,
let me see it any half.
What if all the cars are managed by computer and all of them of simultaneously?
In that case, you can achieve the capacity.
But the point is,
that's not the case and the car left leaves gap between them.
And these gaps you cannot recover them.
Say this gap stakes from the capacity of the system that's kind of the invasion.
So announcements,
I know that everyone waits for that mid term on we are planning to release
the grades by next monday.
We are degrading.
You have to meet that.
Project deal is doing this wednesday,
called final reports,
peer evaluation, everything.
If any of them is late,
you are going to encourage sleep days.
Remember that group evaluation coming for project on, right?
Every person, I believe you get 20 points per partner,
which so everyone every person get 20 points.
And you are going to hand out these points to other members in your group,
not to yourself.
So this is a way to media.
What is the contribution of other members in your team?
Office hours?
There are a lot of students,
and we all want to, again,
to answer all your questions,
but you say,
like you see in this lecture,
when the resources are scared,
we need to put some conditions that have some policies in place.
But I to try to be to provide some level of fairness to you guys.
T as will spend, in general,
were bound to spend 15 minutes per student.
It's again to not starve other students from their attention.
You need to have a detailed ticket field out,
and the gdp pulled up, right?
So to be absolutely ready.
So the compact switching is minimum, right?
Between students.
And from these 15 minutes,
you get the full value for these 15 minutes.
You don't wait for 55 minutes to set up your gdp and provide
the ticket detail explaining to the da and thing like that.
Great.
Now we are going to switch gears,
and we are going to talk about deadlocks.
That look is a particular type of starvation.
Thank you for the this is my date is wrong.
The wednesday, it was wednesday.
Thanks.
Deadlock is a deadly type of starvation,
starvation, the threads may wade indefinitely, right?
Allow priorities, right?
Waiting for resources,
because there are many other high project threats,
the deadlock,
it's a circular waiting for resources.
And this is a very simple example.
Say you have two threads and both threads in order to make progress,
require to get access to two resources,
resource one and resource two.
And now one thread gets access to resource one,
and the other thread get access to resources.
And both of them, they hold these resources.
None of them can get the other resource,
so they are deadlocked.
They cannot make progress.
This is what it is.
Deadlock implies starvation,
because starvation,
because you are guaranteed that in a deadlock,
now I will make progress.
Starvation doesn't imply that log because starvation can end.
Eventually, if the high priority task finish,
the low priority task just be executed,
that law cannot finish without some external intervention.
Here is example.
It's a real example,
a a it's a one line bridge,
right?
As you probably know, it,
if you enter your sanity on california and one for 140.
Okay?
The point here is, again,
there are two directions right?
Now, typically you have a traffic light for these ones,
but assume that you don't have a traffic light.
So if you don't have a traffic light, what happens?
Right?
What can happen intuitively?
What is the problem?
The problem is that two cars come from both ends,
because there is no line.
They are stuck their deadlock.
And the way you can model this is basically thinking that you have 2/2
to the entrance,
2/2 of the bridge.
And each car acquire 1/2.
But in order to cross a bridge,
you need to both halves.
It's exactly like the previous example,
right?
Each card has 1/2.
Each card required a boss halves.
They are stuck.
In order that how you say solve is the only way to solve this.
A deadlock is for one car to back up.
And this is a kiva land.
With the other car, we didn't back up to preempt the resource,
which is hauled by the car who backed up.
Because now the car,
which didn't back up,
is going to acquire the second half of the bridge.
Now he has the first half, second half,
and then it going to cross the beach.
Now, the equivalent of starvation here is basically saying,
you have a lot of cars from one side is you have cars after car and
the car which comes from the other direction will not get an opportunity
even to get on the beach that salvage.
Again,
starvation eventually can end when there are no longer cars coming
in this case from the west or from the east.
Now,
let's look about what does it seem from the point of view of our program.
You have to stress here.
And let's go to,
it's like,
it's like locks, right?
These resources are like, locks are resources.
And this figure and the examples,
we can see that so far can be expressed the following way.
Thread a you have two blocks,
x and y acquiesce,
block x and y and then the lease is y and x and b acquires the locks
in a different order and releases them in the different order.
So in this case,
you can get that lock.
Right?
When does this happen?
When this kind of order the interleaving,
you the cpu interleaves,
execution of instruction from different threads.
For instance,
when this happens on thread a acquire x then thread b acquire y now,
thread a is stalled,
because thread b owns y and thread b cannot progress farther, either,
because it wants to acquire x which is our by a so this is that long,
right?
Hard to debug.
Because this happens,
not doesn't happen all the time.
And again, you want to avoid it.
That because it's, again, like, for instance,
if this happens,
you don't have that lock.
Right?
So this is non deterministic.
It shall be a non thermissive bug.
You always need to be afraid of our on their missing bugs,
because you cannot recruit them.
If you can recruit a bug,
it's the result is relatively easy to fix it.
If you cannot reproduce it, how you are going to fix it.
Here is another classic example.
He had four trains.
And in this configuration,
none of them can make progress.
You have a deadlock.
You have here a deadlock,
just basically to illustrate the point.
So far as the examples we had,
you have to,
it is which are in bad luck,
two cars or two threads.
But obviously that law can happen between multiple more than 20 days.
And here is an example for four.
Here, each train wants to turn to write.
This is a real problems which are in in different systems,
encountering different systems.
Yes, it's exactly san francisco traffic a that's a good one.
So how you fix it?
One way to fix it,
it's actually for some ordering.
You'll see this as a recurrent theme.
One way to fix that lock is to have an order.
For instance, in this case, always go east, west, first, and north, south,
then back first, right?
Don't go north, south,
and only east, west, and north, south.
Right?
Okay.
As you'll see, like for our previous example,
this is a lot.
So as you see, in our previous examples,
when you have this kind of deadlock,
we'll say it a few more times,
but it's good to remember that one way you can avoid the deadlock,
in the previous case,
is to enforce that both threads are going to acquire the locks in the same order.
Okay?
Again, if I go back here,
if you enforce that both and b acquire threads in the same order first x
and then y you are going to solve this problem.
Again, we have the deadlock here,
because we do not have enough resources.
Right?
If we have enough resources, it's not a problem.
You wait for a resource that multiple threads compete to,
right?
There are also threats, car blocking,
waiting for other threats,
like pipe or sockets or wait, like, for instance,
I am blocked to wait for a to get a message,
but I am waiting for if I am remembered about bounded cures,
I am awaiting for queue to become to get a free slot.
In order.
If i'm a producer.
Ii can wait.
If the queue is full.
I am waiting until the queue is drained.
So I can put more items in the queue.
It's again that local space is an example like here.
If you don't have enough resources,
you have two threads is threads want to allocate2 megabytes,
but they want to allocate that into different calls.
And now assume that you have 2 megabytes of space.
Right?
He said, allocates to megabytes,
32megabytes.
But he's doing that one megabyte at a time.
Right?
You can get here a deadlock situation, right?
Because if one thread gets one megabyte,
one thread car gets another one megabyte,
they are deadlocked,
because none of the thread can get an extra megabyte in order to finish.
Here is another very famous problem
to illustrate the deadlock.
Dining.
It was called philosopher problem.
This is a little bit of a joke with the lawyers.
But think about this,
you have five people.
And there are only five chopsticks.
Now, in order to eat,
you need two and you need two chopsticks.
So if everyone grabs one,
chopstick is deadlock,
because no one can eat.
Right?
So how do you do that?
In order to break this deadlock?
We need to give someone to chopsticks.
So if everyone has one chopstick,
we need to get one someone to give up her chopsticks to her neighbor.
So I know now my neighbor has the chopsticks.
She can eat,
she can finish.
And now she can give the chopsticks to her neighbors.
Now,
other that her neighbors can finish, right?
Okay?
This was a deadlock solving the deadlock after it occurred.
But ideally,
you even want to prevent that.
You have to have an algorithms.
You want to prevent that a lot.
You don't get in the deadlock situation.
In the first case.
We'll talk about this,
but keep that in mind.
Now it is,
if you remember, when you have this kind of situations,
you have some concurrence.
This is also an example of concurrent access to the resources.
We saw something similar with this.
When we talk about critical section,
we really want to have some to formalize the problem.
If we formalize a problem and say,
what are the conditions a solution should meet?
Then we should focus on.
We can only focus when developing a solution to meeting these conditions.
So what that the requirements,
first of all,
let's think about when does the deadlock occurs?
Because if we know the requirements and under the lock occurs,
then if we basically break one of these requirements,
then we can break the deadlock.
So there are four requirements for a dialogue docker,
mutual exclusion.
Only 1 sat at a time can use a resource hold and wait,
a thread holding, at least on resources,
waiting to acquire additional resources,
held by other threats.
Because if you don't wait, you can proceed.
You can finish it.
You can release a resource.
And now there are more resources in the system.
So maybe as a threat can finish,
which are writing for the resources, your fault,
no preemption.
If a thread hold the resource,
that thread is not going to release,
that is sort of voluntary.
Before it finishes with it,
then it is circular weight.
There exists a set of threads,
says that t one is waiting for a resource that is held by t two.
T two is waiting for a resource that is held by the three and so forth.
This means the last actually
requirement give us away to detect deadlocks.
How is that?
So basically,
you want to detect that cycle.
Let's use the same symbols.
You want to use them, but the threads are circles.
The resources are rectangles,
and you have multiple dots.
So this a resource,
when you each dot represent an instance of a particular resource.
So for instance, you have acpu is, for course,
you are going to have four dots.
Each representing worker.
And the patterns of manipulating a resource is very simple.
You request a resource,
you use a resource,
you release a resource after you are done.
Now, we can have a resource allocation graph,
and we have 2 types of vertices,
threads, and resources,
resource types,
and 2 types of vertices or edges.
Sorry, and 2 types of edges.
These are directed edge.
If a thread, you have an edge from a thread ti to a resource rj if set
ti request the resource j and then you have assignment age,
which is a direct age from rj to thread di
when thread di allocate or has allocated resource
rjok so basically,
here, in this example,
this edge from r one to t two basically says that t two own r one,
the edge from t one to r one,
say that t one requests resource r one.
This is some
examples you see here.
Let's see, which are,
it turns out, and we are going to learn more about that,
but it turns out that these middle examples,
it's in the deadlock.
Why?
Because two reasons, first of all, you have a cycle.
You see here,
t one was for our own,
which our own is owned by t two,
and it always are of our for us.
I'm sorry.
The cycle is this one,
r three, d two, r two, d three.
The two owns are three.
Requests are two,
which is owned by the three.
And finally, these three requests for are three, which is owned by people.
So this is a deadlock,
because you have this cycle.
And there are other conditions, if you remember.
Here, another requirement is hold on weight thread, holding,
at least on resources,
waiting to acquire additional resource, held by other threats.
Every thread here in this example,
it's in this situation, right?
It's waiting for a resource,
handled by another thread.
Here is an example which there is a cycle,
d one, r one, d three, r two.
But this is not deadlock,
because d two and d four owner resource,
but they don't do it for any other resource.
Okay?
The reason this is not a deadlock, again,
we learn more in the remaining of this lecture and the next lecture is that
t two and t four can proceed,
can run to completion.
And once they run to completion,
they free or an instance of r one and r two respect.
I see,
how does that three have two assignment edges?
Assignment?
Good answer.
There are two instances.
Yes, like I said.
So you can look about this r three and r four as type of resources.
And the dots within these rectangles are the number of instances
of that particular type.
And typically,
one thread here with require one instance of a particular resource type.
We do have also a deadlock detection algorithms.
You want an algorithm.
And the vector that on detection algorithms is very simple.
You keep an array of free resources,
then you have an array of requests,
threads of the current request from thread x you have all
sorts of for each thread x you have the current request of that thread.
The current resources are located by the threat.
Okay?
You initialize the available resources to the free resource.
Right?
The free resources are the one which are available.
Then you look at all the notes which are unfinished.
You keep all the notes,
which are all threads.
This represents all threads which are not finished.
And you take one by one.
And you look whether you have enough available resources for that thread
to finish.
In other words,
if the requested resources by that thread
can be satisfied by the existing available resources.
And if you are going to run the threat,
and then now all the resources on the thread are finishes are going to be added to the
availability set,
because they are available now.
So you do that.
And if there are no longer unfinished resources,
and if there are no longer items in or threads in their finished list,
you are done.
That is not a deadlock.
Otherwise,
there is a deadlock,
so not left in unfinished out of that.
Okay.
Let me there is a question here,
but t one and t two,
t three is still in deadlock.
So I can say,
so let me stay here.
So this is a question.
It's a great timing for that question.
There's a question here.
T two and t four finishes,
but t one and t three are still in that lock.
Here is a sink.
If you run this algorithm is what will happen.
You see, t two actually will finish the execution.
And whilst the two finishes execution,
it releases the instance of our one.
Now, there is one available r one instance.
T one can acquire that instance.
Now, t one has both the instance of ours,
two and r one.
So we can run and complete.
That's a trick,
because the t two,
whenever you have a threat,
which can complete think that is going to release the number once it finishes,
the number of three resources available resources going to increase,
which will give an opportunity to as a thread which are blocked until then,
to acquire the newly the new release resources and to finish themselves.
And then they are going to finish even more resources are going to be
available for in the system for the other stress to finish.
So how should we deal with the deadlock?
There are four different approaches,
bedrock prevention.
You write your code in a way that is not that law cannot happen.
Can happen.
Did that law recovery?
You let that all happen and then figure out how to recover from it.
Remember, this was like,
so on the bridge, a car, we come back up.
You can preemptive.
So things like that.
Deadlock avoidance.
With that.
Look of doyle as they can dynamically delay resource request.
So that doesn't happen.
You kind order and impose an order and a time when different threads,
they request resources.
Now, a very simple example from the beginning, if you remember, you just say,
first, you let duty one acquire the resources,
and then t two,
and then there is no deadlock.
The last one,
it's obviously not a solution.
You can deny that the deadlock and see what happens.
Maybe you are lucky.
What is the difference between deadlock avoidance and then lock prevention?
That's a very good question that a lot avoidance is that you can Write
your code,
for instance,
the law prevention meaning that,
you make sure that you never had more stress than the resources that I
do have plenty of resources,
then you prevent either lock.
Deadlock avoidance is that the law can happen.
But you can make sure and you write your your code,
and you are trying to schedule your threads.
And you are trying to order as a resource request.
So that doesn't happen.
Like in our examples of brains.
When you go south, east, west,
and then North,
south, then you don't go first, North, south, and then south,
east,
west.
But they are related.
And okay,
so many operating systems avoid the deadlock.
They don't ignore the deadlock.
When can you ignore that?
The deadlock?
To let me here we are making a little bit of fun that denial in this Oscar covering.
So you pretend the problem is not doesn't happen,
is not happening.
But when actually deadlock denial,
it's okay.
When crashing freezing,
isn't that big of a problem?
Yes.
And when they are very,
very happened very readily,
when it happens very rarely.
Okay.
That's what when it's okay.
And if you were to address to put the deadlock to do deadlock prevention
or avoidance,
will require very expensive algorithms,
will dramatically increase the complexity of the system.
Right?
So preventing deadlocks,
like I mentioned,
you have enough resources so that no one ever runs out of resources.
Right?
And other things,
every source can be shared.
Like the CPU you have100,
you have one thread,
fine, you have ten threads, fine,
you have 1,000 threads, fine.
Everyone will be slower, but still,
you are going to get your share of the CPU and finally,
like you don't allow waiting.
I this is what happens in many cases,
right?
You knew when you call,
the other part is not available,
or when the system is overloaded,
you get a busy signal,
right?
Failure.
Try again.
The same in internet, in the networking.
There are collision between the packets.
Try again.
Okay?
Again, it's inefficient.
And in some case, you cannot do it.
But it can be inefficient in some cases.
But it's a very simple method.
This is an example.
If you having been resources, in our case,
in which that will happen because limited resources,
no longer a problem.
Another way to do it is to prevent the deadlock is to require everything
at the beginning.
Everyone requires everything at the beginning,
and therefore,
exactly what everyone is using.
So you can allocate from at the beginning resources to everyone so that you
make sure there is no prevention,
there is no deadlock,
and then force all stress to request resources in particular orders like we
discuss.
But here,
a it's a very,
very interesting important things is that one thing this happens when you
acquire the locks,
x and y and y and x is because this two operations of
acquiring the tulips,
they are not atomic.
But what if the operation of acquiring these locks is at home?
Then everything will work,
right?
Because only one of the thread will be successful.
The strategy is successful is going to run to completion,
is going to release the two resources to locks.
The other trend is going to come up and run.
And how do you do that in practice?
Well,
use another lock to make sure that acquiring the locks x and do and y are atomic.
That's why I have to do it.
You can also do it, like I said earlier on that by enforcing order.
So in this case,
if your boss threats a and b acquire the resources, the same order,
again, you are fine.
Does it matter in which order the locks are released?
Now?
Because the release is not awaiting operation?
Okay.
We are going to stop here,
and we are going to continue talking about deadlocks next lecture.
Good luck with the project one and see you all on virtually on Saturday.