Hello, everyone.
So today, during today's lecture,
we are going to finish the discussion on the deadlocks and then continue
to start to learn about the visual memory and address translation.
Last time, we spent quite a bit on deadlocks is a very important concept.
And if you remember,
there are four requirements which needs to happen to have a deadlock.
The first in mutual explosion,
that means that only one thread at a time can use a particular resource.
The second is hot and white.
That is a thread holds a list on resource and is waiting to acquire additional
resources which are held by other threads.
So this means that this thread cannot make progress,
because it means the other resources in order to make.
He needs a computation,
which, again, are owned by other threads.
No preemptions.
Resources are released only voluntarily by a thread holding the resource.
You can a thread cannot be emptied another thread to get the resource
to finish the computation.
Then in circular weights, you have a cycle,
which is a cycle,
which is defined by the pattern that,
like aa thread is waiting for a resource that is held by another thread.
And that thread is waiting for every story that is held
by another thread and so on.
And you're going until you get a cycle.
Okay?
Also,
last,
there are several techniques we listed last time to resolve a deadlock.
One of them, it's and to recover from the deadlock.
So one,
some of the things we mentioned last time was to terminate the thread.
Therefore, you can terminate a thread which owns a resource.
As there are other threads,
can acquire the resource that can finish their computation.
This you don't always want to do that.
In some cases.
It's pretty hard.
Like, for instance,
you can kill a thread which is modifying some sensitive data or important data.
Then you can it like, for instance,
are updating your bank balance, right?
You don't want to do that because you may end up with garbage,
pre and resources without killing of a thread.
This means that the system is the ability to suspend a threat.
And then you can preempt that resource while that thread is suspended
or is sleeping.
Another thread can get that resource and again,
complete the computation.
When the thread which are suspended ghost comes back,
hopefully there are enough resources for the threat of things of computation.
But all back, the actions, if you remember, in our example,
is a bridge and you have two cars on an online bridge coming,
had to head in the middle of the bridge.
One way to resolve the problems are deadlocked is for one,
a car to back up.
And when you look at the operating system,
some of them use some of these options, right?
It's like, for instance,
one system, hanks,
but I typically one system hanks,
and you can do anything about it.
In some cases, he said a lot bad luck.
In many cases.
So how do you do it?
You report it.
Right?
So you get everything.
And preempting resources is the operating system is doing that.
As you now, threads are preempted,
are put on the slip.
Ii put on the waiting queue.
We set a few examples.
So also we talk about another example.
Last time, another way.
Obviously, you can solve the deadlock problem.
You have infinite resources, right?
If even the resources means that every thread at any given time has
all the resources,
it needs to continue to progress and to finish its computation.
This is relevant.
Here is an example about the second part with the second part of the lecture.
And we are going to talk about virtual memory.
And because virtual memory,
it provides you a memory,
which is much larger than the physical memory at,
you can think about, like,
for most applications,
the same like infinite space, like infinite memory.
The one thing, though, is that,
as we will see,
and there is a hood of the virtual memories or the virtual memory it's implemented.
You are going to load different parts of the virtual memory
in the physical memory.
And then you are going to offload to move some of the parts of the
of the virtual memory of the threads,
which are not running of the physical memory,
maybe put them on the disk.
And in doing so, you basically,
the solution under the hood is to preempt.
Right?
You preempt the physical memory,
a storage,
which contains a virtual memory data from one thread with another,
a a with a virtual memory content of another thread.
We'll talk more about that.
It's something,
it's an isolation between the deadlock solutions and virtual memory.
The next is the next mechanics of us resolving the deadlock problem.
It's deadlock avoid us,
right?
And this is different from the deadlock prevention,
which we talked last time quite a bit.
Deadlock prevention.
If you remember, you design your program that you never run into deadlock,
like all the resources are going to be acquired in the same order by everyone.
Right?
Thing like that.
Now,
deadlock avoidance is basically is that it's a more dynamic way to avoid,
sorry,
that lock avoidance is a more dynamic way to avoid deadlocks.
And this basically is your operating system.
In this case.
It checks at everyone you make every resource request,
whether it can result in a deadlock.
If the operating system convince itself that if if grant is request,
there is a way in which you don't,
you don't get into a deadlock state,
then he's granting the resource is a threat which asked for it.
Otherwise, it does not.
Let me see the question here.
Sorry.
That's a great question.
The slides is my mistake.
On me.
Let me give me 30 seconds to upload them,
and they are going to be available in a few moments.
I apologize for that.
Okay, so I push them.
So it's after a bit of time that are going to be available again.
Sorry, and thanks for flagging it up.
So let's see how this in these examples like we gave.
This is a canonical example.
We used last time to illustrate the deadlock.
And here, if you remember,
you have two threads and both threads,
a and b acquire resources,
or the lock yx and y but they acquire them in a different order.
Let's say, is that a acquire x and let's b acquire b it's a thread,
b acquire y in this case, it's not working.
You have that lock y because
if a tries to acquire y we can no longer do that,
because b already holds y
this doesn't work,
right?
This is what we want to avoid.
In this particular case,
a point here is that if you go back,
one is a system allocated x to a
then he shouldn't.
When we ask for why he should not grant access to that resource,
you shouldn't grant that the resource why or the lock.
Because if you grant it,
now, there is a potential for that.
Look.
Okay.
Now, intuitively, you see,
if the operating system doesn't grant y to b then a
has your opportunity to request y now,
the operating system can grant y to a a now has both x and y can complete this
computation and then release boss x and y that's kind of what you want to
happen.
And this is exactly what the deadlock avoidance is trying to do.
In three d is the deadlock avoidance.
You have two states,
a safe state, and a deadlock state.
In the safe state means that there is a way to allocate the
resources to the existing threads,
said that every thread is going to complete.
So there is no deadlock.
Deadlock means there is a deadlock in the system.
So the four requirements we talk about are all hot.
These are the two main states,
and then there is another unsafe state.
There is no deadlock yet,
but stress can record resources in a part,
in a pattern that unavoidable leads to deadlock.
So basically, right now,
there is no deadlock,
but the deadlock is imminent.
You cannot do anything about it.
You are on the way to for the deadlock to happen.
So this is what i'm saying.
With a deadlock avoidance,
you just try to prevent the system from reaching an unsafe state.
Because if you reach an unsafe state,
eventually you are going to reach a deadlock state.
The main idea here is on a thread request, a resource,
the operating system checks,
if it will result,
if granting that resource would lead to an unsafe state,
if it will not lead to an unsafe state,
is going to grant the resource.
If not,
it's not going to grant and is going to wait for the existing threats
to finish and release some resources.
So like, again, look,
and as a previous example,
I already mentioned to you the solution,
but let's do it again.
Thread a acquires x now,
thread b ask for why,
but we do not give y to b until a finishes.
Because if we give grant y to b it can be results in the book.
The classic algorithm for avoiding deadlock.
It's a banker algorithms.
And basically,
what you,
the idea here is that each thread,
it stays a maximum number of resources in india in advance,
right?
And allow a threat to proceed only if available resources
in the system minus requested resources in the system is
greater than the maximum number of resources
required by a threat.
Right?
And this is important.
You need to stay up front how many resources you have.
Because if you don't,
the system doesn't have the information.
And at any given time in the future,
you being a thread, ask for more resources.
All right.
So there is no way actually to protect the deadlock in this situation.
And so banker are going to allocate the resource dynamically,
so is looking at each request, resource request.
And then you decide whether to grant a request,
a resource or not.
If the resulting state,
it remains a safe state.
That and the techniques is very simple.
You pretend that each request is granted.
Then you run the deadlock detection algorithm.
You remember the last time we are looking,
we learn about deadlock detection algorithm.
It's very simple in the deadlock detection algorithms you are looking was
the requested
resources by a particular thread.
It's can be satisfied.
So it's less than the resource available.
Right?
In this case,
we are looking at how many more resources a thread needs in the worst case,
which is a max node,
is a node in the graph.
That's why it's called not here.
But you can replace node with a thread,
but the maximum number of resources that the thread still needs is
a maximum number of resources overall,
that thread me needs minus a number of resources,
the thread already else.
Okay?
Again, if you remember,
this is the algorithms to detect the deadlock.
The only change you need to make here is that we are going to replace
request number of request resources
with the maximum number of resources,
that node or thread.
Can we still need in the worst case?
So that's what it is.
Right?
Just to look a little bit more of the code,
you put all notes, again,
all threads in unfinished state.
You have available resources,
which is amount of the number of resources which are free in the system.
Then you are going to look at all nodes and finished,
which are still computing.
For each of them.
You are looking at that.
Can if the mark,
if the amount of resources that thread is going to require in to ask for,
in the worst case,
is less than the available resources.
And if is fine,
you remove from unfinished,
because we know that we allocate those resources to the thread will finish
for sure.
Right?
And we'll never ask for more resources than that.
And then you iterate.
And it's until you are done.
Can you explain what a lock means?
A lock means allocate a lock.
A lock is the resources which are already allocated to a threat.
So say,
I have a thread.
So let me just go.
Let me guess nothing better than an example.
In this example,
both threads,
the max will be two,
because they require x and y right?
Or it's a vector, depends how you want to look at.
But in this case,
we understand Both threads requires x and y this is the max initial.
Now, when the thread a gets x in this case,
x is a lock in a lock.
Allocated vector is the number of resources which are already allocated
with a threat.
Max is still x and y when you do max, max,
x and y max minus a lock.
In this case,
you get what you get y because max is x and y are log,
is x you get y in this case,
in the worst case,
that's thread a still is going to ask for a while.
Okay?
Just, again, to summarize,
keeping the system in a safe state means that there is this a sequence
of in which your grand request to the threads,
which are unfinished,
so that all threads are going to finish.
So let's apply these algorithms
to the dining philosophy philosopher problem or lawyers problem.
What is the deadlock here?
The deadlock here is that when each person picks a chopstick,
and they have only one chopsticks, they can,
there is no other chopstick available,
no one can eat.
What is a safe state here?
Is that and when you can grant a request a chopstick,
you can grant one is that there is not the last chopstick,
because if we have still on chopstick,
we can give that chopstick to someone who has already on chopstick.
That person is going to finish eating.
And now you get two chopsticks.
So you can give the chopsticks to other people to eat.
Okay?
Or this is the last chopstick,
but you give to someone who already has a chopstick.
Because if you do so,
then that person you gave the second chopstick can finish eating.
What happens?
If you have that?
You generalize a problem with gay handed?
People like octopus,
think about like you have octopus which are dying.
You can generalize that.
So basically,
the last one and no one could have k is the second to last one,
and no one has k minus one,
and so forth.
Right?
Because otherwise,
if you allocate,
if you grant the chopstick by violating any of these conditions,
then you can end up in that lock.
So in summary,
there are four conditions, by the way,
any questions about bankers algorithm?
There is a high level.
The idea is very simple.
Each thread is going to tell you in advance,
to say, in advance how many resources it needs.
And then what you do is the operating system is going to grant a request
to a resource.
If by granting that request,
you remain in safe state.
And in safe state means that there is a way to grant the request to the
existing threads says that every thread is going to finish.
What is k minus stuff?
So here,
k minus two here,
you assume that instead of having two hands,
that person or entity will have k hands.
And in order to eat that octopus,
it needs or k chopsticks.
If you have one chopstick left,
someone else asked for the chopstick.
You do not give that chopstick to that person unless that
person has k chopsticks and the same.
Next,
if you have two chopsticks which are not allocated,
you would not give that a chopstick to a person,
unless at least on as a person,
has k minus on chopsticks.
Because otherwise,
if you give the chopstick to another person,
none of the person has k minus on chopsticks,
they have k minus two or less.
Now you are in an unsafe state,
because you have only one chopstick left.
No one else has paid my more than k minus two chopsticks.
No matter to whom I am going to give the last chopstick.
No one else can it?
No one can it?
So there are four conditions for that.
Look to happen.
Mutual exclusion, hold on weight,
no preemption, and circular weight.
And there are several techniques to addressing the deadlock problem,
deadlock prevention.
You write your code in a way that it's not prone to the deadlock.
You set up some rules,
right?
So that if everyone respect these rules,
you cannot have that lock.
For instance,
deadlock, recovery.
You let the deadlock happen and then figure out how to recover.
You can preempt a thread.
You can suspend a thread,
you can roll back,
deadlock, avoid us.
This is what we just learned,
the bank of our banker algorithms,
which time you did,
you basically delay resource requests?
So that look doesn't happen.
And finally,
deadlock, then denial,
he just ignores is deadlock because it may never happen.
What is happens so infrequently?
And when happens,
there is not a big issue.
Announce announcements.
Project one, congrats for completing your first project.
We are planning to release the grades for your midterm by monday,
like I mentioned last time,
and project two will be released today.
So good luck for project two.
Now i'm going to switch gears,
and i'm going to talk about virtual memory.
We all started to remind everyone to recall about visualizing resources,
right?
Memory, just another resource which you visualize.
But before then,
I let me stop and ask you whether you have any questions about what we've
learned so far or any other question?
So it seems there are no questions.
So let's go ahead.
So remember that what do you want in the operating system?
Once to provide the application?
Is the illusion that each application has its own machine on its graphs.
It has its own resources,
but the physical machines have limited resources.
Therefore, you need to kind of visualize this virtual machine,
this physical machine,
two different applications,
different processes,
which means that visualization means that you need,
if you have more application or more processes,
which is a common case,
then the physical resources,
the only way you can visualize the resources is to multiplexer.
You can multiply them in space or in time.
Right?
So one classic example about visualizing in time is cpu you multiply the
cpu so that in time qanta,
so for each time qanta,
you let another process to run.
And therefore,
each process has illusion that it owns as acpu the a slower cpu than
the physical cpu the second one is
another important resource is memory.
This is what we are going to start learning about today,
how to visualize the memory.
And the other important one is a disk or storage nine.
Why memory is important?
Why do you want to visualize memory?
It's very important because the entire state of a process or application
is stored or not entire state,
but most of the state or the active state,
the state which is used by the process on europe when it runs,
is stored in the memory and the registers.
Okay?
Therefore,
you cannot have two threads,
use the same memo,
always use the same memory,
because it's, again,
like two different pieces of data cannot go by the same location.
And sometimes you don't want stress to have access to each other memory.
Right?
Here, you have memory protection.
And remember, how do you provide memory protection?
You provide them.
We are going to see the mechanics here.
But the abstraction is a process.
Right?
Each process in its own memory,
all the threading the same process,
shares our memory,
stressing the different processes,
cannot share the cannot access each other memory.
Now, going back and recalling the four fundamental lawyers concepts,
we have thread with the execution context.
It represent the control state,
which is program counter registers,
everything which is needed to execute that threat,
then in the address space,
which is owns the entire memory accessible by the program for accessing in sweden,
right?
Then is a process,
which is an instance of a running program.
And the process,
its address space plus one more threads.
Then we have this dual mode operation between the system and user.
The system has the ability to access more resources than
the user programs.
So let's talk then about visualized memory.
First,
let's start with the concept of address space and others translation.
An address space is a set of contiguous set of memory addresses,
which have seen by the process or the application.
Typically, the unit for memory is byte,
and the size is expressed in power of two.
For instance, if you have to power 10 bytes,
this means you have1,024 bytes,
which is one kilobyte is b capital b stands for byte.
A byte has 8 bits,
and then you have an address,
and the others choose to access individual bytes in this outer space.
Again, the number of bits in the address is basically, in this case,
is k or ten,
in this example,
is the exponent right of two when you define compute the memory size.
And this should be very easy.
But I do remember, right?
If you have and addresses how many bits you need to encode this analysis,
a bit has to value zero and one.
You need log of n in this case,
n is to k log base two of two.
K is k how many bits of others?
Each byte, but a bit of others,
how many bits you need to address each byte in a 4 kilobyte page?
Is 12, right?
Because two power 12 is four kilobytes.
And obviously,
if you have20 bits to address,
you can address 2.2 power 20.
But bytes,
you have 32 beats.
You can address the power of 32 bytes and so forth.
But this is what?
A process ca contiguous set of addresses,
typically one at each other.
As you have 1 byte, you can store 1 byte.
1 byte is 8 bits.
And then the process uses this address
space to store various information,
code and data.
And axis you will address.
Accessible addresses are all the addresses.
A process can read and write or write and the state associated with them.
What is stored as a particular others?
In some cases,
we are also measuring or give the size of a memory in awards.
And award typically has more than 1 bytes.
For instance,
a forward is 32 bits.
One question here is how many 32 beats numbers or 4 byte words you
can feed in an address space of,
right?
We set it to beats,
You have 72 beats,
so you have two powers,
32 bytes.
You need to divide by four,
because award is 4 bytes.
You get to power circuit, which is 1 billion.
Now, we are going to learn more about that,
but that's for you to know that when you read and write to an address,
there are many things can happen.
The most natural thing is that you read and write that particular piece of data,
which is associated with the address that we should read and write.
But other things could happen.
You can actually, when you write or to special designated addresses,
or you read from special designated addresses,
you can read and write to some device like more like display.
And these are memory mapped,
io operations that we can,
cause a program to aboard when is a program or do second.
When this can happen,
when does programs at fault?
You should know by now you've done homeworks projects.
I'm sure that this is many of you had this unfortunate experience and map memory.
Yeah.
So basically,
if i'm going to try to access an address
which I don't is not accessible to me,
i'm going to read from and write from address which is not accessible.
That's fine.
Or the some addresses owned by other
processes.
As you are now,
in the address space, there are three parts, four particle,
four important segments for each process.
You have the code segment which contains the code.
You are going to execute the stack segment,
which you now is used to push the return addresses when you call
a function and also pass
the arguments or to that function,
is a heap for dynamically allocating memory
and its static data,
which is for what?
For a static data is implied like global variables.
You seen this picture many times,
apologize for showing you again.
But as if you remember the relation, this shows you again,
the relation between a process and a threat,
a process can have multiple threads,
all threads in the same process,
share resources,
including most of the memory resources,
including heap,
static,
and co segments.
The only one segment they don't share is a stack.
And the registers obvious.
And the reason you don't share the stack, because again,
the stack contains the state of the execution.
But if you call a function in the thread,
then you have to push the return On the stack.
So now that represent the execution state of that thread,
you can also have a single threaded process,
which has a single thread.
There are three important aspects of memory multiplex.
One is protection.
You prevent a process from accessing the data of another process.
The second one is translation is the ability to translate from a
visual address space to a physical address space.
We'll learn about.
And when this translation occurs,
you are going to have these future others.
This can be used to avoid overlap or talk next,
provide a uniform view to the program to the process.
And also can be used to provide products.
And the control overlap.
Its separate state of the thread should not cause colliding physical memory.
This means that, again,
we have only one physical memory in the same a a on a single machine.
So you have different processes,
different threads,
they shouldn't collect.
But I they shouldn't,
for instance, share the same, I don't know,
share the same data segments.
An alternative view is to have to look at at what is the allowable process behavior,
right?
What do you allow process to go?
And this,
what is allowed to do?
It's regulated by the operating system.
The operating system, in one way,
is interposing itself.
So to make sure that the processes are well behaved.
That's why and the processes don't do anything back.
The operating system is handling the eye operations on the behalf of the processes.
It makes sure that every process get access to the cpu,
like you'll see,
is going to make sure that each process,
it gets its own physical memory under the hood.
Okay?
The question is, how do you enforce that?
In the previous two cases,
the operating system,
it's like this requires a context switch.
Right?
I operation.
You is a cisco.
It's a context switch for the cpu we share them to multiply the cpu
between different processes or threads.
You need to do context switch,
right?
And context we can remember,
it's expensive.
It can be tens of thousand,
hundreds of thousands of instructions.
Now, the question here is,
what about the memory?
It doesn't seem, there's a memory.
You can do that.
Whenever you access to the memory,
it's too expensive.
You need to have another way to make this kind of translation to interpose,
to have this interposition layer between the virtual memory
and the physical matter.
If there are exception cases,
like you'll see like page four,
you'll see that then you can give the control to the operating system.
You can have the opposite operating system,
interpose interposing itself.
We learn about that.
Again, this is a previous picture.
You've seen.
One of the first lectures,
everything here in this big box.
It's harder in the operating system.
And it with this big box provides a visualization of the os
and of the machine to the application.
That's all of the operating system.
And just to for big picture of what happens under the hood when you execute
a program.
To remember, if you remember,
your copy is a program.
It's on the disk that you copy the code in the memory,
and then you start executive.
Let's see what happens when you execute.
And here a it's a a snippet of assembly language.
And basically, what happens here?
You allowed some from this address data one,
the data, which is there and register at one.
And depending on the value,
you are going to jump to this address.
Otherwise,
you are going to decrement the value.
And then you are going to, look,
you go to until it's not zero,
b and z means r one is not zero.
You go back.
Basically, as long as it's not,
when it's zero, you jump out of you terminate.
Basically, in this code,
take a piece of data,
checks it.
And then you take advantage,
and then you go back.
So what is in memory for this program?
Or do you start?
So in memory, you have only beats.
This is an example here.
And you have 2 columns for the physical address.
The column on the left are the addresses.
And the column on the right are the content is the content of the novels.
In this memory layout.
We are using 4 byte words.
How do you see that?
You see this number here on the right, 0000.
You have 1234560cents, and20.
You have eight characters.
Each of these characters,
a sorry,
represent4bits,
right?
It's a hexadecimal format.
It's from zero to f each of these is from zero to f we have eight of them,
8times for its 32bits.
They have 32 bits worth,
or for byte work.
The sink with a red are the addresses which also appears in the program.
You have three addresses,
four addresses.
One is the address for this data one.
This is red.
The blue one is check it,
address the green one.
It's a loop.
Others now,
tell me now,
I said that,
say, take with the red,
I said that z zero zero, c zero,
which is a program,
refers to this0300.
Can you figure out how these are connected and why they are connected?
Why basically the same thing?
So here it is.
If you address the memory at 32 beats boundaries,
so an address as the word granularity,
each order is 4bytes.
You need 4 times fewer addresses.
That's what it is.
That's basically what happens here.
Right?
When the program is going to,
look, you compile the program.
And when you allocate the memory,
everything happens at forward for the 4bytes,
granite or 32 beats granite.
There are four as this granularity.
We need 4 times fewer so to speak,
addresses or beats.
This is what happens here.
00, c zero is0300,
but is absurdity, rupees, granularity.
Instead of at the 8 bit or background.
Indeed,
if you multiply c zero by4,
you get300.
Any questions here?
The same for the other one.
If you multiply grade zero,
you are going to get a00.
If you multiply 0to42×4,
you get0908.
Now, this is how these values are stored in the physical memories,
another way in another representation.
Right?
You have the values in these boxes.
And the address is on the side.
Now, here is a question.
Say i'm running this program,
and this program loads into physical memory.
And these addresses, right?
Because these are the addresses,
maybe in the program on the disk.
If I run again this program,
what will happen?
But I if I run again this program,
I don't want to load to be loaded exactly in the same place,
because a different instance of the problem by different data.
So that's one of the problem we need to solve.
You need this translation.
So one way to do the translation.
So instead of I modify these addresses with this nuance,
now,
all these addresses will not overlap with a previous instance.
They are going to not overlap to be non overlapping.
And you are going to be able to load the second time you run
the same program at a different address space.
So the two programs now they don't step on each other.
So there are many way to possible way to translate.
This is only one possibility.
So translation can happens at 2times the link time,
when or before in our execution time.
I it's compile time, link time, and execution time,
but link or lower time.
So compile time,
it's very hard.
We are not going to talk much about it.
The link and low time.
It's we are going to talk briefly,
and then we are going to focus mostly when the translation happened and execution.
So before talking about link low time translation,
let's remind ourselves what is the lifetime of a program?
You start with the source,
you compile, you get the object modules,
then you link response possible other modules and libraries,
and then you load it in the memory.
And in the process, you are going also to the link with some system,
libraries and some libraries.
You can actually link them at the run time after you started executive.
Okay.
But here is our previous example.
Actually, what implicitly done?
You modify the addresses before loading to memory.
This is linked load time when you modify the others.
Right?
Remember, here,
we said this is our program,
right?
Maybe this is on the disk.
But when I am cooperating system is going to load this program in memory,
is going to override these addresses that is not going to overlap
with other programs,
which are already in the physical amount.
So this is what happens.
Okay?
Make sense?
It's any questions?
Now, a little bit of history,
again,
the earliest operating systems for personal computers were very simple.
You have only one other space,
and you have only one application and you got a given time.
The application was owning the entire physical address space.
You have the illusion of a dedicated machine,
because you have a dedicated machine.
How do you do this?
Now is the next step.
If you start to work to run multiple programs,
you want to run in the same computer.
It's again, if the operating system doesn't provide your support,
like you see for translation,
the one way you can do it,
like we've just seen,
it's basically translation.
You translate the addresses of the program before you load it to avoid overlapping,
conflicting with another program.
This was a case for early version of the microsoft windows, three,
the windows, the early version of the windows.
With these things,
it's risky.
There is no protection to the buggy code and applicable all applications
here have access to the entire memory.
One application can read and write the data from another application.
So it can also crash another application.
The next level is to provide protection is still one other space.
Still, the applications are going to be,
the addresses will be overwritten when you went by the louder
before loading the application,
the program to the memory.
But now you do have protection.
How do you have protections?
Base and bound?
Do you remember about this?
We talk about that.
You have a base and a bound and associated with each application.
And you make sure that when the applications is going to a access,
a memory,
that address is going to be between base and bound.
This was in 31 super computer,
one of the first super computer.
This is what we do.
If like we have address of the program here,
101.
The base you have base is 1000 is bound1100.
When you address, you are going to check.
Sorry, you are going to check whether it's between100, and110.
If it is, you can access a memory.
Otherwise,
you are going to set for you protect and isolate programs.
But this is requires you to, again,
override the addresses of the application before the program,
before you load it.
This is also called relocating louder, a louder,
like that is doing that.
Rewriting is called relocating louder.
Can be very fast.
The basin bounds are going to be implemented in harbor.
And there is its only comparison,
no addition or nothing can done extremely fast.
Okay.
To summarize, we saw unit programming,
no protection, one program at a given time,
multiprogramming, no protection,
but you have multiple programs at a given time in the same physical memory.
And you need relocating loader to make sure that the programs,
when you load them,
you overwrite their addresses so that they don't step on each other.
Finally, here we have, again,
no protection,
one physical memory,
no visualization.
You have also base and bounds to,
sorry.
In this case,
again, you have only one address physical memory,
only one other space,
which is shared by the applications.
But in this case, you provide protection by using base and bounds.
This is provided in harvard.
So now,
it's a time.
This is a pretty complicated,
like relocating louder and so forth.
It's pretty complicated and it's pretty limited.
So next,
we are going to start discussing about the general address translation.
Okay?
The general address translation is happening this way.
You have the cpu.
Remember this because sometimes it's little confusion.
When the cpu issues an instruction.
In general,
the instructions contain virtual addresses.
So these virtual addresses are then mapped to the physical address.
And they are done, typically,
by cheap or part of the processor,
which is called mmu memory management unit.
The programs,
because they are running on the CPU they see mutual address spaces.
Okay?
From the memory side,
you have only physical addresses.
In translation,
it's a generalized technique,
which helps you is many things.
But if you really want,
if you only want,
like I mentioned,
protections,
control, overlap,
and sing like that.
But if you really want to implement only one of these things like protection,
like you've seen in the past,
things are easier while you're on protection,
because if task a cannot gain access to speed data,
no way for anr to adversely affect.
Now,
if you have the translation,
then every program can be linked or loaded into the same region of the users.
Again, you have two applications.
In this case.
Both applications have different virtual addresses,
virtual address space,
because they have their own process.
And each process has its own address space, visual address.
These boss applications,
they can see the same virtual memory.
Both of them, they see visual memory, say,
from 000 to fff the trick here is that these two address spaces are
going to be mapped to different locations in the physical memory by using translation.
That's what the translation gives.
Let's consider examples.
It's a one way to do it.
It's a very simple change of the previous
basin bound technique.
Here is a difference.
Let me just go back to make sure that it's different, right?
This is the difference.
In this case,
the base and bound,
right?
Are absolute addresses.
And the program address is also absolute address.
You have 1010,
and absolute meaning.
I am referring to physical addresses.
You need to compare 1010 with the base and with a bound.
With translation,
the program address is not absolute,
is the relative to the bound to the basis.
Actually, the real address,
physical address is a program address plus the base.
In this case, a program address is 0010.
Base address is 1000.
If you add them up, it's 1010.
These addresses are translated on the flight.
Right?
Very convenient.
So you still now,
this program addresses,
they don't need to be changed.
The only thing I need to change in order to make sure that programs
are mapped into different address spaces.
Physical address spaces is the just chains of these others.
Right?
Indeed,
right?
It's harder for location.
It's also called, then basically,
a question here, can you touch the program?
Can you touch the os but if you are careful,
we are not going.
You cannot touch the os because the os will be outside the base address
and the bound address of any
up any user process.
Can you touch other programs?
Now, if you are careful,
that's how you provide protection.
Again, it's a very simple idea.
Any questions about that?
Do you see how now I no longer need to override the program analysis?
When I load the program in memory,
I just do that as a runner when the program I give.
Any questions?
Okay.
What are the issues with this basin bound method?
The issue here is about what is called is about fragmentation.
And this is a very simple example,
because each process requires different amount of data,
the different amount of space, memory space.
They are not uniform,
because they are not uniform,
like in this case process to requires a lot.
And you process to goes away.
Another process nine comes,
you are locates a memory spatial process,
9+5 goes away.
And now look at this situation,
you have process 11,
and you have enough physical memory for process 11.
But the point that this physical memory is scattered and process 11 needs
a contiguous region of memory.
That's a problem.
How do you do it?
What is your solution here?
There are many solutions.
But one simple solution is to have,
instead of only one segment for each program,
you can have different segments.
Typically, you can have code segment,
data segments that had segment sub segment.
You do this independently.
This gives you a little bit more flexibility.
Also, another problem is the solution I show you here,
the original solution, the ban,
the basin bound is that remember about threads and processes.
You can have multiple threads in the same process.
The site is the same process.
Here is a code.
But how you are going to do it here,
right?
Because right?
And even like think about, actually,
you can think about maybe a better example than what I said is libraries.
If you have common library system libraries with these libraries,
they are used by multiple applications.
So it makes no sense to allow the copy of the library for each application
set up against share system values.
Right?
How are you doing?
Again,
now we can alleviate this problem.
Like I mentioned that instead of having one segment per process,
you have multiple segments,
right?
But process a typical one, like I mentioned,
you have code data stacked heap segment.
But in general, you can have a segment at one extreme.
You can have a segment for each function.
Right?
For a segment, you have a base and a bound or a limit.
Now, because the segments are smaller,
you have more flexibility how to place them in the physical,
in the physical memory.
Let me go back here in this process 11.
If this process 11,
maybe it had been consisted by from two segments.
Then you'd have feet.
You could have feet.
Process one in physical memory,
because maybe one segment of process one would have fit in one of these gaps,
and the other one is the other gap.
So that's how multiple segments can help.
This is one version.
You have then a map.
How would you implement it?
Now you need a map,
a segment map,
which needs to reside in the processor.
And then how do you address it?
How do we know we segment?
We are in.
So one way to do it is to divide the address space,
a virtual address into two.
The first beats of the asset advice are the most significant ones represent the
segment.to this segment map.
And the second and the other part of the address is a quality of.
So when the processor issues such virtual address,
the processor take the first,
the segment beats its indexes in the segment map,
then it gets the base and the limit the offset is added to the base.
And now this you have the physical address,
and then you need also to compare the offset to the limit,
right?
To see that you are within the segment.
If not, it's an error.
You are done.
Now you can chunk the memory in as many chunks that you have
in this map map table.
And this is what very early versions of intel 86
are implemented.
86.
We are going to stop here.
We are at time.
And we are going to continue our discussion on virtual memory.
Next Monday.
Until then, good luck with project two is good to start early.
I'll see you then on virtually.
I'll see you on Monday.
If you have any other questions, please, let me know.