Hello, everyone.
So welcome.
We are going to continue our lecture on a virtual memory.
We are going to start discussion on caching and tlb so it's time for the translation.
Look aside buffers.
So if you recall,
address translation,
as a name implies,
it's about translating the addresses which are viewed by the application
by the cp us into physical addresses.
There are a couple of reasons why we want to have this different kind of
addresses for the application and versus of the physical
addresses.
Some of them are about providing the illusion to each application.
It has its own machine,
its own resources,
including the memory,
which means that then you need to map the address space of each
of the application in the same physical space,
which is physical memory.
And also,
another reason is protection,
because you want to protect the address space and of one application from another,
and also sharing, control, sharing, if you remember,
in which actually some parts of the address space you want to be shared.
For instance,
the address space which contains a code of a shared library of a library,
which is a code of a library,
which is used by two applications like windows library on your own windows machine.
You do not want, but it begins that code in each application.
You want to share that.
Typically, you do the sharing.
It happens.
It's handled by one of these components are cheap,
which is called a lot of this memory management unit.
This was originally a a a was a standalone chip,
which is you put near your between the processor and the memory.
But in the more than processors,
it just a component of that processor.
One of the modest one of the techniques to do address translation was
a segment using multi segment.
And in this case, if you remember,
reach a segment is represented by a base and a limit.
Okay?
Now, the visual,
the address, which our address is against the address,
which is seen by the cpu and is seen by the application.
We split into two,
the first part of the first few beats represent an index in the segment table.
And then there is an opposite.
Okay?
When you have a virtual address,
you look at the first field,
which is the segment number.
The first speech represent the second number,
use up to index into segment table.
And then in that segment table,
you are going to find the base of the segment and the limit.
And you are going to compute the physical address by adding the offset,
which is the second giving the virtual address to the segment base.
These are the address.
And you are also going to check whether the address is generated is
less than the limit.
So it's within the segment.
You also have in some architecture, actually,
in intel eight x 86.
Instead of having the first the beats in the virtual address,
presenting the the base,
the indexing into the segment table,
you have just a bunch of segments,
you have the initial,
you have four segments.
And these segments are men,
are base segments,
are stored in special registers.
Like es this is s is for the stack and three other registers.
Then you compute the address by taking the virtual address,
and you are going to add it to the segment register.
That's how you are going to compute the physical address.
A finally, there is a bit valid or not valid.
This one is at the segment,
not all segments of all application can fit in the physical memory
at the same time.
So when you run out of space in the physical memory,
and you want to load,
you start a new application on your program that it needs to.
You need to allocate spacing.
The physical memory presenting program is a segment, is a new program.
You may take one of the existing segments of an application.
It doesn't run, and we are going to store it on the disk.
Okay?
Then therefore, the segment is no longer in memory.
So then you can say it's you can use this bit to specify that.
So whenever next time,
when you are looking for something in that segment,
then you are going to you are going to get an exception,
and the exception is going to be treated by the operating system.
The operating system will bring the segment from the disk to memory
before executing that instruction.
This is some examples.
Here.
It's a simple.
An example of an architecture is four segments.
The address is 16 bits.
The first 2 bits of the address are used to specify the segment number,
because we have four segments.
We need only to be.
So this at least 15 and 14.
The rest of these from 13 to 0 represent the office.
On the left hand side, you can see the address space,
the virtual address space.
So as seen by the application,
we have our traditional four segments,
a code segments,
the data,
the stack segments.
This is also we added a shared segment.
Think about this is either that 8 hours a code,
which you may want to share with another application.
So here with in green,
you have the table,
the segment table,
again, four entries for code data shared and the stack.
And you have the base and the limit for each of these segments.
Now,
let's see what happens,
for instance, and on the right hand side,
you have the physical address.
For simply things like, in this case,
the physical address and the virtual address spaces,
they have the same size.
Say, you are going from the code,
you are going to execute in instruction in the code.
Where is that going to be mapped in the physical address space?
If you look about in the segment table,
because the first two beats of everything in the code segment at zero.
Therefore, you are going to identify the first entry,
right?
In the segment table,
you have a base of four salad in hex,
a specimen format.
Therefore, you have to add an 4,000 to every address,
a virtual address is a code segment.
And to get the physical responding,
physical address for the code in the physical outer space,
then for data,
the data starts in the visual of the space at 4,000.
This means that what are the first two beats of any address in the data segment?
Why don't you tell me?
It should be a very simple answer here.
The first we have 16 bits when we use a hexadecimal representation,
right?
4 bits represent one digit.
Now we have four here for us.
What does it mean?
What are the forbes?
The first forbids,
the forbids representing the 4th.
How do you write for in binary presentation?
Here it is.
I'm writing this in our chat,
foreign binary representation.
If you want to represent it,
or in using 4 bits is 10100.
This is it, right?
It's 100 is 4 in the binary presentation,
which means that the first beats for any address in the beta segment.
The segment number here is what?
01.
Now it's not 00101,
because it's only the first to beat,
but it is for its product.
It can go, okay,
it's 01.
This is what is one?
This is what you have.
Therefore, to translate any address in the data segment.
What do you need to?
Do you go to the second entry in the segment table?
The one, which the segment id number is one,
and the base here is 4,800.
So what you need to do is that you are going to add,
in order to translate any address in the data segment,
you need to add to it for the 800
for the shared segment.
This is the things go.
This similarly,
for the share of settlement,
they started 800,000.
So the first four beats is eight,
represent eight.
What is the binary presentation of eight?
It's exactly.
The first two beats at 10.
The second one number,
one, it's 10 is two.
Right?
Because you take only the first two beats.
And finally, stack c what is ac the representation?
Binary representation of c you should remember this.
Right?
Is the review.
It's 1100.
Exactly, very good.
The first two bits are 11.
It's three.
Number three is the last entry in the table.
And for go to the stack,
the base is zero, right?
You add the base offset to the base.
We started from 000.
Does it make sense?
Let's look at this as an example.
By the way,
you should you should try.
These are some very important slides,
because you may expect not only to understand how the address translation works,
which is one of the fundamental mechanics in used in the existing
in today's processors and leverage
by the operating system to provide virtual memory,
abstraction,
but also because you can expect problems like this in your next meter.
Okay.
Now, let's look at this piece of code and see what happens under the foot.
And we are assuming this piece of code is going to run
on the previous architecture from.
Ii just showed you in the last slide,
you have the segment table is the same.
Now is a code.
The code starts that to 40.
We don't basically the entire address is 0240,
but you don't show the first four beats which are zero.
Okay.
Now let's see what happens.
And this is a serial language,
theodore assembly, language, code.
Let's see what happens when we start with the disco.
The first instruction is a main,
and basically what his instruction is doing.
It loads an address which is bar x into register a
zero right now,
this code is run in the user process,
the user process.
See virtual addresses.
So all the addresses you see here are virtual addresses.
Okay?
But now the code and the data they are actually stored in the physical memory
in order to read the instructions and access a data,
we need to translate the virtual addresses to the physical address.
So they address the instruction, firstly,
to fetch the instruction in order to execute the instructions instruction.
Again, it's in physical memory.
The address of virtual address,
it's 0~40.
We discussed.
Here is a binary representation of the address.
The first to beat are zero.
The segment id the sigma number is zero.
Is that a four in order,
translate this address for virtual address to 40,
to a physical address,
we need to add the base address corresponding to the segment.
So the basis 4,000 and the virtual offset,
right?
Is 240.
The virtual officers.
The offset is the other side of the black beats.
In the address,
the beats encoding,
the segment identifier are the green beats.
Obviously,
you have to add all the offset,
which is 240 to 4,000,
which is a base.
And therefore, you are going to get the physical address 4,000, 200, 40.
Now,
you are going to use this address to fetch the instruction from the memory.
And the instruction is basically like I told you,
it's to load the address,
which is barracks address,
which is 4050 is the virtual address into a registration.
Now, after that,
you execute the instruction, you would know very well.
What happens next?
The program counter.
It's increment by four,
because he are assuming that there are instruction,
they occupy 4 bytes.
The next instruction address is 2, 44.
So let's execute the next instruction.
It's again,
in the next instruction,
you are going to see you have now the other sister for,
like I mentioned,
again, the physical,
if you look at,
this will also be in the code segment,
we need to add the base, which is 4,000.
The physical address would be 4244.
You are going to get the next instruction,
which is jail to jam to this string,
land address,
label.
All right?
And this is exactly what you do it.
But before the jumping here,
we store the return address.
After we execute the function string land,
we need to return, well,
to the next instruction after the jump,
the next instruction after the jump would be zero,
x 248.
Therefore, we are going to,
we assume here that we have a return address registers,
Which stores the return address.
So we are going to load into the return address,
0248.
And this is done automatically by the compiled code,
by your obligation.
Then you move in the priest program,
counter the address,
or you want to jump.
So the address you want to jump,
the label string line is corresponding to the address360.
So you're going to jump there,
and you are going to execute that next instruction,
which will be the address 360360.
Its, again, is in the segment code.
In order to compute the physical address,
you are going towards the base,
which is 4,000 of 4,000+360,
is 400, 660.
And then you are going to read from the physical memory.
You are going to read,
and this instruction is basically initialize this account, put a zero,
a in a register v zero.
Once you execute that to go to the next instruction,
and the next instruction,
the other is 364.
And this next instruction,
it loads what is at this particular address,
which is stored in a zero?
Remember that what is stored in the a zero?
It was bar x address.
This is a bar x address is 4050.
Now we are one to load in register t zero.
The content of the address barracks of the address 4050.
When we want to do that and we want to access it,
to see what is the content of that mutual address.
The mutual address is 4050.
This is a binary representation.
The first two beats are 01.
The segment index,
which corresponds to this address is one.
Therefore, the base address of that segment is840 800.
Therefore, you need to add the 4,800 to what?
To the offset.
So what is the offset here?
The offset here, notice is 50.
The virtual address is 4050.
But remember,
the first 2 bits of this address represent the segment id that's one.
And the last, in this case,
14 beats represents the opposite,
but the last 14 beats is 50.
Now is the offset is 50.
It's, again, offset is a black digits,
like 01.
Then you are going to add the offset to the basis,
4,800.
The physical address you are going to compute is 4,850.
And you are going to load the bite from that address to d zero.
And you increment the program count.
The main thing to note here that everything,
which is in what the processor sees,
everything,
what is in the registers of the processors?
All these are virtual addresses.
The translation happens only where you are going to access a memory.
So the memory management units really sits
between the arithmetic logical units and all the registers and the memory.
Any questions?
We spent quite a bit of time on this one,
but this is important.
Please make sure that you understand this example,
as you'll see, from the previous years and previous exams,
you are going to see a lot of problems like this one.
So a few things about some segmentation.
The one problem with the segmentation is nice.
It's a very elegant solution,
but you are going to translate on every instruction,
everything even in fetching instruction,
access of read some data,
write some data from the node.
And virtual address space has halls, right?
Because you are not going to use everything in your visual address.
That's why I use a segmentation in the first part,
in the first thing in the first in the first place.
Because if you think about,
if you have the code and the segment,
the segment grows,
you put the segment as a high addresses,
because it grows to the smaller,
grows downwards to the smaller addresses.
For instance, a data segment,
you have to be as a lower others,
because it's going growing up.
Okay?
Whilst the stack growing down,
so you need to separate them and between them, there is a gap.
Right?
If you have segments,
if you don't have the gap,
if you're sorry, if you don't have the segments,
that gap will occupy space in the physical memory.
Facebook would have been used empty space,
can be used to allocate to other processes,
other applications.
However, if I have these two segments,
now each segment can have the one segment can have data,
one segment can serve the stack.
And then they are going to be mapped on the physical memory.
The gap I don't need to map it.
I don't need to just waste the space on the physical memory.
So now,
the one thing to notice here is,
I said you are located segments for the stack and the data.
But if allocate and how allocate the stack has a certain size and allocate that
physical memory for the stack at that given size.
What happens when the stack growth and that stock growth?
Because they call more functions of, say, recursive programs.
Every call puts the arguments and put the return values and supports
on the stack.
How do I do that?
Well, in the sense that when i'm going to grow the stack, for instance,
then i'm going to access and others outside the limit that will generate
an exception.
The exception will be treated by the operating system,
which is going to grow the stack.
There is a limit on modify the base and provide more room now.
So the program can add put more things on the stack,
the same thing for the kids.
There is a question,
why did we not translate barracks in the first line on the previous slide?
That's a very good question.
Why didn't translate barracks?
Remember, what I said,
everything is in the registers,
is virtual addresses.
These are all virtual addresses,
because the rule is that the addresses are only translated when I
am going to access a memo.
In this case, I am not accessing the memory.
Virus is just a virtual address.
Right?
I don't need to access the memory for that.
When I need to access the memory is when i'm going to read the content
as a virtual others.
And then I need to call to find the corresponding physical address,
and then on a good translation.
But everything what is in the process,
in the registers,
it's a virtual address space.
Of course, you need to put to protect the segment table.
Only the operating system has to be able to modify it.
And also,
it provides us the operating system provides protections for different segments,
for instance, to make the code segment being agreed only.
Now,
let's say we do a context switching.
Now.
What do we need to do to say very start on contact switching when you have
a process context switching?
Besides that we need to to save a
bunch of things like file identifiers and things like that.
The other thing we need to torn out the segment table,
because the segment table, as I shown, you,
in the previous slide,
in the previous example,
you have one segment table per virtual address space,
and you have one virtual address space for the process of the application.
You switch context with your process.
You have also to save the segment table,
because the next process is going to run,
is going to have its own segment table.
Also, like I mentioned earlier on some of the segments of the process,
which is is which is no longer running,
can be stored on the disk in order to make room for the segments of the new
of the next process being around.
Again, this is what happens is that, again,
if not all segments within memory,
you save them on the disk and you swap them.
So basically,
you say p one, c process, p one.
It's is we switch from con this process beyond to be two,
then we can save the segment of process p one on the disk to make room
for the segment of process p two to be brought in the memory.
If you have to do that,
the context switch costs will grow dramatically.
Okay?
You need to be very careful about what you switch off or what you swap
out and swapping on swapping,
because you really want to minimize your operation on the disk.
And we are going to learn about that.
The next, a couple of lectures.
Problem is fragmentation,
problems with segmentation.
One of the biggest problem is fragmentation,
because now you need to start a different,
you need to have to be able to have to store and to fit segments
of different sizes in memory.
If you remember the last lecture,
we had an example in which you gave,
you believe a lot of gaps.
You can get to a point in which you have many gaps in the physical memory,
but none of the gaps can be big enough to start a new segment,
rather to start a new segment.
Despite the fact that if you add them all the gap, if you add up,
all the gaps is much more than what is needed by one by that segment.
But I think about you have 100 gaps, each gap.
It's one gigabyte.
You have 100 gigabytes in total of available memory.
But now you have one segment which requires two gigabytes.
You have plenty of available space,
but none of the available spaces,
contiguous basis.
It's large enough to start that segment to gigabyte segment.
So how do you do that?
You can take one of the segments which are there to addition to one
of these one gigabyte gap.
And you are going to start on the disk.
You are swapping out to make more room,
or you can move segments around.
So there are 2 kinds of fragmentation.
Both of them were space,
internal fragmentation.
You don't need all the memory within allocated chunks.
And this is also,
this is all this and then external,
which is free gaps between allocating chance.
So I think this example I mentioned to you,
I was talking about the external fragmentation.
And next, we are going to talk also about internal fragmentation.
Okay.
So basically,
this is about another view about the general how the address translation happens.
This providing a little more intuition by showing two visual address
spaces mapped to the same physical address space.
Okay?
And the these programs on and programs to or this process on and process
to the virtual address spaces to each of them.
You can look absolutely identical.
Think about your on the same application to instances of the same application.
But the translation,
while in the virtual spaces are identical,
you have in both virtual spaces,
the same thing as the same addresses,
virtual addresses.
When you are going to map these virtual addresses to the physical outer space,
when you are going to translate them,
you are going to translate in such a way that they are not going to conflict.
So now, with segmentation,
we have this with external fragmentation.
Sometimes it's harder to to allocate storage to variable sized chunks.
There is a solution for that,
and a solution for that,
which is very simple.
It's about, instead of allocating variable,
says chunks,
you allocate fixed size chunks.
And these are called pages.
Every chunk of physical memory is a cable and be the same that it has
the same size.
And this can allow you to specially to simplify a lot of things.
For instance,
how do you handle allocation?
One way to handle the allocation is to have a bit vector.
And each bit in the vector represents 1 page.
The value zero is that whether that page has been allocated
from the physical memory,
one, if it was allocated.
So if you want to find a page,
you in physical memory, you can allocate,
you just find a zero in this bit vector.
Now, what about the size of the pages?
If the pages are too large?
Again, all pages have the same size.
What is the problem?
What is the problems that pages are too large?
Waste, spice, internal fragmentation.
Excellent.
So I buy beef and edison and and cost of context switching can be higher if
you need to swap that page out.
Right?
That's correct.
But the main thing is about internal fragmentation,
because if you think about,
if you have this page, you say you have a page of one gigabyte.
If your program is only one megabyte,
you waste enormous a lot of most of the space.
So you want small babies.
The problem with the small pages,
what is the problem with the small pages?
Any guess?
Lots of accounting, more translation is, yes.
Lots of accounting.
Ii wouldn't say more translations and larger base table.
You already know about it.
Yes.
But it's accounting is hard like you have to deal with more things.
Let's see.
Now, how do you do the translation?
But there are no men more translation because in theory, right?
Because you still need to be every virtual address.
You need to translate your physical address.
The little bit of truth of that the higher overhead per translation could be.
But the number of translation is basically the same.
Yeah, some cash can be that as well.
So how is a translation we spend works with beijing?
It's very similarly segmentation,
but with a few differences.
So first of all, you have a base table.
And the virtual address, as again, is in two parts.
We have a virtual patient number and an officer,
but there is a difference.
The offset is not added to obeys address.
The offset of the address remains the same.
So is be with translation when you use beijing.
What happens?
It's only the virtual page part,
the first field changes.
Right?
A virtual page number is replaced by a physical patient.
That's it.
So the same like previously,
the first speech, in this case,
a virtual page number,
in the previous case,
was a segment number,
are going to index in the page table.
But in the page table,
what you are going to fail,
if I find you have a page number,
which is a physical page number,
you are going to take that physical patient number,
and you are going to concatenate with the offset of the visual address,
the offset of the physical address,
and the offset of the physical address are the same.
Typical page sizes are between four kilobytes and 16 kilobytes are quite small.
Four kilobytes means what?
12 beats you need, 12 beats,
and 16 kilobytes you need.
But another14 bits.
So if you have even smaller pages,
right?
This is where you see the number.
The problem is a small pages.
So you have a 32 bit address.
You are going to use one by one kilobyte pages,
so you can need 10 bits offset.
It's what you need a 10 bits offset.
Therefore, the gift,
the virtual page number,
the number of visa is 22 bits,
32-10, 202 bits.
Therefore, the base table have 4 million century huge.
And just think about if you have 64 bits, others,
in order to do that, for instance,
you are also going to not allocate space for the maximum size space table.
So you are going to just grow this page table as you add not more pages to it.
Therefore, you are going to have,
in addition to the page table pointer,
which represents the start of the page table,
also the paste stable size, which is,
as the name implied,
the size of the paste table,
which can be increased that you add more tables,
or as you allocate more pages than you have a lot.
So that afforded your allocate more entries,
you add more entries to the base table.
Also, with this page,
you are going to have a bunch of bits which represents some.
We are going to discuss them or a little bit later.
Keep in mind about these beats.
We are going to give an example,
a few slides.
Later.
It's a very simple page table.
You have a four by space.
It's a trivial example.
You have this on the virtual memory.
You have 4 pages from starting from 04, and 8.
Then you have a page table only with three entries, right?
Because you have 3 pages in the virtual memo.
Assume that the address space here it has equivalent of eight beats.
So he's 64 bytes.
So the address,
if you need for the page table, again, if you have four beats,
you need only two beats, right?
To represent 4 bytes,
to address 4 bytes.
Therefore, the last two beats represent the offset,
and the first six beats to represent what represent the page number
for if you want.
A is that the other is zero here.
If you want to translate that at zero,
then the page number of identify the first entry in the table.
The first century in the table contained four.
Now,
four is a new physical patient numbers who are going to conquer concatinate,
these four with the offset, which is zero.
You are going to get zero,
x one zero.
The same thing,
similar things happen if you want to access the first address,
the address for the virtual address for the future address for now
is going to lead you,
because the offset which one is going to lead you to the second entry
in the page table.
The second in being the base table contains threes who
are going to concatenate three with zero,
which is the offset.
You are going to get to the address zero,
c physical address, and so forth.
Any questions?
Question here?
Why were space size issues and between four kilobytes and 16 kilobytes?
This is, again, always a trade off.
The smaller is a table,
the smaller the page, the smaller the internal fragmentation,
so the less wasted space.
However, the smaller the page,
the larger the page tables are.
So therefore,
it's much more context switching actually can be more expensive.
Good question.
And these are some other translation,
translating the address five.
It's going to translate to all the others,
in this case,
is basically 11717.
And I think there is another example.
Nine is going to be the same.
Sorry.
Previous case, the address six was trans translating to the address one,
16.
And the second case,
the address nine is going to translate to address five,
physical address five.
There is anonymous question asking about if the zero,
x 12345678,
the others could,
the first 123456 can be the offset.
Now,
the again,
the offset are are the last beat in the address.
Okay?
In this particular case, again, the offset,
if you look at the first one example here,
the offset is 10,
are the black beats.
The page number are the bits,
are the red bits.
So the offset is two, in this case.
And the page number is one.
And basic number one selects the second ending the base table,
which is three.
So it's 11.
And the offset remains 10.
Now I have 1110,
which is basically e what about sharing?
If you want to share a page between processes?
These are pretty easy.
Right?
You have each of the processes has its own page label.
If you want to share the same pages,
then the corresponding entries are going to point to the same physical table.
It very elegant.
Where is page sharing?
Yours?
Generally, region of the processes of every for the processes,
you have a general region, as you remember.
So every process has the same,
all the processes they have to see that you are going to share this code,
the kernel code across all the processes,
because the same code is not going to change.
You can,
by the way, this is protected, right?
Is like the kernel will have.
The process only can access at the user level and are talking
about the kernel region.
I'm not talking about kernel region being accessed by the process.
I'm talking about the kernel regions associated with the process,
which is accessed by the kernel during the context,
which during different processes running the same binary,
you don't need to duplicate that because the code is read only user level libraries,
like I mentioned,
or even sharing the data between you,
you can share the data between the processes.
You can use a share memory.
This is another example.
This is a summary of beijing.
On the left hand side,
you have the virtual memory view.
On the right hand side.
You have the physical memory view.
In the middle, you have the base table.
You see that many entries in the tables are now,
but this is a full page table.
And here we are assuming and eight beats address.
And now the offset are the last three beats.
So the base size, it's about three,
it's 8 bytes.
And the patient number is 5 bits.
You are going to have 2.5.
You have 72 entries in the page table up to.
Okay.
Now, the one thing,
and on the right hand side,
you have, again, like the physical memory.
One thing here, I just want to show you.
And i'm so earlier on,
I said that the stack,
how the stack and the heap grows here.
Now, the stack again, grows downwards.
So gonna go grows,
going to lower addresses.
And you see here,
the stack,
it's on the right hand side.
And with with what I represented here is a gray,
the pages which they are all the allocate,
only the pages which are white are not allocated yet.
So let's see what happens and how you are going to grow the stock.
Now,
the problem is that let's say that I want to grow the stack by 2 pages,
I decided to grow the stack by 2 pages in the virtual memory.
The virtual memory, I can very conveniently grow the style,
because I have enough space in the virtual memory.
However, is a physical memory.
If I am going to try to grow it,
I can allocate page.
You can allocate another page.
Maybe you have only room for another page there if you want to locate
continuously that the pages to the stack.
But the point is a page a with a translation that these pages
do not need to be allocated continuously.
Right?
Therefore, the only thing you can do,
the only thing you need to do,
you need to find the room for two other pages.
And you are going to allocate these pages for the stock.
But again, they don't need to be contiguous, right?
Whatever is contiguous in the virtual memory,
doesn't need to be contiguous in the physical.
Now,
the biggest problem is the challenge,
the type of table size.
If you in the simplest version,
in the simple instantiation,
in the simplest implementation,
the type of size,
but if it's equal with a number of babies in the virtual memory,
and this can be absolutely huge.
Let's give take an example.
You have 32 beats address space,
you have four gigabytes at others,
mutual address space.
These are just a unit for you to remember.
The one things to remember here.
And one confusion i've all seen often is that when you are talking
about the memory,
we are talking about the power of two units.
One kilobyte is ten to power ten,
one megabyte to power ten,
and gigabyte to power set.
I when we are talking about bandwidth,
and how much capacity network capacity we are talking in power of that?
1 kilobyte or 1 kilobit.
It's 1,000 bits,
one gigabyte,
one gigabit represent,
but it's1 billion bits.
So now assume the typical pay size is four kilobytes.
It's to power them.
We need ten beats for to address any byte in a 4 kilobyte page.
So there are four.
Sorry, we need to have what i'm talking about.
If the page is four kilobytes,
this means to power 12.
Therefore, I need 12 beats to address any bite within a page.
So the offset is stern beats.
And therefore,
if the offset mister beats,
the page number,
it's 30.
2-12 is 20 bits.
Now,
the base table size can have as big as 4 megabytes.
Right?
Why is 4 megabytes?
Because each of the entry in the page table needs to have 20 bits.
Then you are also going to have some other,
like you see some other flags associated.
So you have 30° for each end.
So it's 4 bytes,
and you have to power 20 entries.
So it's 4 megabytes the top.
This was a lot of memory.
Now think about this was in the past,
and you have said little bit as the standard.
But now the standard is 64 bits.
There is no way, right?
If you try to do the same thing here,
you are going to have 30 extra bytes,
which is only for the pace table.
Actually,
you don't have enough physical memory for that physical to store
that the pace label.
This is really a lot of space.
What is the solution here?
By the way, all this space is empty.
Most of this, no, not always,
most of the space is empty,
because they don't have as many base tables,
but I do have very few space tables,
right?
Which are actually allocated a so this is a big problem.
And we are looking out for a solution,
a little bit of a discussion about base table before going forward.
So what do you need to switch on the page label?
What do you need to do this?
When the context switch happens?
What do we need to do?
You have a page for the table point as the page label pointer,
the beginning of the page table,
the limit,
the size of the page table.
Again,
remember about the dual mode operation.
And because you these space tables can be only
modified and accessed by the kernel,
you cannot let an application access the space labels,
because then they can change the page table,
and they can.to anywhere to any other address,
including the kennel or the address of another applications.
And now let's look at the pros and cons.
On the pro side.
It's a very simple memory allocation.
Remember, you have a bit vector in zero or one,
whether the page is allocated or not in the physical memory.
The bit vector contains 1 bit for each physical,
for each page in the physical memo,
easy to share the cons we seen.
The other space is very sparse.
The base table can be huge.
It's again, if the base table is peace big,
then you need also probably the context which you cannot keep all the time
in the memory.
If the process is painful,
is that there is a base level of a process.
If the process was is now switched off and is no longer using the cpu you
may want,
it was preempted.
You may want to take the page table of that process and swap on the disk.
But if that is large,
then the overhead is very large.
So the deal we are here,
the best table,
the paging as a technique,
it's elegant solution,
very simple to implement,
provides low internal fragmentation.
If the pages are small.
On the downside,
the problem we encounter is when we have big,
it is because the page tables can be huge.
So what is the solution?
Right?
The solution is you repair that the same technique I do like you recursive,
they do it.
It's multilevel beijing.
Right?
Look, if the page labels are very large,
then why don't we have a base table for that base table?
Right?
Or you can combine painting segmentation?
These are the two solutions.
A segment mapping, you are going to have segments.
And in the segments,
you are going to have,
you page the segments,
and then in the page table as you are going to the page tables.
And let's look about how this is work.
As a core remembers that the page table is a map
between the virtual page number and the physical page.
This is where it is.
A simple page table is just a look up table.
Vpn, the virtual page number.
It's an index in this table,
which contains a physical page number.
By the way, what are the map structures?
When you think of?
There are many of them, trees, hash table, and so forth.
But obviously, these are more complicated,
means higher overhead,
even though they can have slower storage overhead.
The beautiful things about the very stable is very quick to access it.
Right?
It's just a needless.
If you use the trees and hash tables,
and we'll see about that.
They are much more space efficient.
You don't need to maintain all the entries,
which for it, there is no table.
But accessing those is much more expensive.
There is a trade off here.
One simple solution is like we alluded, we mentioned,
is to have to do the problem of having very big page tables is to page
these page tables.
Basically, here is a two level page labels.
And here is that instead of now,
the address has three fields at the end of the offset, like before,
no difference here.
But what was previously corresponding to the page number?
Now you split into two fields,
which corresponds to virtual page numbers of page indexes for the two level
pages.
The first ten beats,
in this case,
represents a virtual p one index in the index,
in the first level table,
page table.
This is going to take,
you is going to contain an address to
a page containing the page table entries at the second level.
Okay?
In order to compute now the entire physical address,
use a few an index to find the address of the page containing
the physical page number,
which is stored in the second level.
This physical page number is going to be concatenate with the offset like before.
And now you have the physical address.
Okay?
It's the same thing.
The only difference is that now you split the physical page number into a part,
which is going to index into a page table,
first level page table,
which contains the address of a second level page table.
And the second field in this page number is going to index
in this second level page table.
And at that entry,
corresponding entry are going to hand physical page now.
And you can have many moral levels.
Now, these are some announcements.
We are just 15 minutes before the class ends,
but here are some announcements.
We release a midterm scores,
and please check piazza for degrading policies.
I think you did quite well,
the scores and the distribution is very much in line with that of the past midterms.
In the recent years,
the project two design documentary member is due by this at the end
of this friday.
The homeless three is due on sunday at the end of the day.
If you want an extra credit.,
please feel free is a mid semester survey and check on piazza for details.
So it's free.
Three extra credit.
The next lecture,
i'll be out of town at nathan pemperton with a senior phd student,
which you expect boston architectures and systems is going to beach this class.
He's a fantastic teacher.
Fun.
I really urge you to attend his lecture.
He is there going to be a lot more fun than my lectures?
He's a great presenter.
I remember that iii mentioned to you now that in a page table entry,
besides the besides of physical page number,
we are going also to have some bits.
And here is an example.
Let's take our previous examples.
If you are going to have an offside offset of the or you have a 32 beats address,
the offset is 12 bits,
so the physical page number is 20 bits.
So now,
in a base table,
what you need the physical page number,
which is this 20 bits.
So what about the rest of the rest of 12 bits?
For the rest of the 12 beats?
You are going to have a bunch of flags which are used.
They have different use that they can use it in different ways.
But here it's an example.
And this is from intel architecture.
So these are examples about this beats.
And we are going to start from the this significant means zero is p this
is present.
It's the same as valid.
Is a page present in physical memory or not?
W write a book.
Can you write on this page or not?
If it's zero, then it's read only its user accessible,
this page accessible only by user.
Pwt page write transparent.
This is related with a cash.
Typical you have cash is to to reduce the latency to access the data.
Right?
When you have caches a problem,
the question is about how you are going to update the physical memory,
the data in the physical memory.
Right?
There are two ways here we are going to learn.
But one way is that whenever we are going to access and we
are going to write to the cache and modify the data,
we are also going to modify the data in the physical memory.
And this is page writes, transparent,
bcd space cash disabled.
You cannot catch the pages.
A its access page has been accessed recently.
This is used also for cashing.
But I think it's accessed recently.
And the next two is the same, first of all, cash.
You want to know whether the pages access recently and whether is dirty
was written,
and the physical memory associated with physical memory was not updated.
So you need to know about that.
And then you are going,
we may decide to page that to this is.
Okay, how do I say?
So these two beats,
the only thing you need to know now are used when deciding what page
to swap out of the
memory to make the room for me pages.
Fundamentally,
you do not want to swap up a page of a process which will be accessed india.
I it's a question.
The pcd means,
the question is obesity means it's about obesity means the pcd means
that the page is not cached.
Again, the reason you may choose to not cash a page is that, for instance,
in multiprocessor systems,
multicore systems,
when you have concurrency on on the same page,
you have a page with a shared to different processes,
which run on different processors.
And they can concurrently access that page.
And if you want to update the page,
if it's cashed each process in each process of cash,
then you have a cache coherence problem.
If you want to simplify that problem,
if you want to remove that problem,
you can say this page is never going to be cash.
Example of how to use pd invalid pd es is that it's, again,
even this one can in the imply different things and the operating system
besides how to use these flags
once.
And one we use is that which I didn't mention is that the address space
is actually not valid,
right?
It doesn't is not allocated.
But another way is basically say the page director,
it's that page,
it's not in the memo, it's on the disk.
Right?
In that case, you need it a it's a a it's a trap to the operating system,
exception.
It results into a trap to the operating system.
And the operating system is going to figure out where is the biggest start,
and it's going to bring it to memory.
This is going to be used by the main page.
We are going to learn about that.
Another use here is about copy and write for the pd basically,
when you fork,
remember that the fork,
when you fork a process, a fork process copy,
actually the parent process, right?
It has everything.
And now the question is that do you want to copy it right away?
Right?
Are you going to copy everything?
And it's not smart to do it, because,
for instance,
the code of the process of the parent process is the same code.
You are the child process is going to execute.
The code is read only, so you can only to copy.
But the same is also true about the data.
But I I do want to copy to move that to copy the data from the process
at a space to the child at the space.
The answer there is that only if the child ideally only of the child access,
right?
And write it, right?
So when that's what,
so initially,
when you are going to create,
if you because you want to reduce the overhead to create at the forecast process,
the four process can share the entire address that via address space
to the parent process.
So the reads are very,
there are going to the same memory is memory efficient is fast,
right before.
But then the only one you can start doing it is when you write it.
So when you write a page, now,
only now you are going to create a copy of that page for the child.
And now the child can write and read from that copy.
But as long as you want to read,
you can read from the same memory, physical memory,
which is shared a a with a balance.
Another use case here.
It's a zero field on demand.
So say,
you allocate,
say, ten gigabytes of memory and you want to initialize the zero.
Just that it initialization can take seconds many seconds.
Just to do this initialization,
you don't want to pay the overhead,
then when you are going to order allocation,
instead of you can do zero fill on demand.
The os now that this pages needs to be zero,
but initially doesn't make them zero.
It may seem zero only on your axis average.
And that's perfectly fine,
because you amortize zeroing it or even better,
maybe the application is not going to ever touch every bite,
which is allocating these standard devices.
Right?
Say this, again, some smart ways to use this video.
So sharing with multiple level pages,
sorry.
Oops.
You can see here,
you have two processes.
You have this each process has its own base table at rt
the first level page,
you can see for each process,
it's pointed from you have the base table pointer for employees, part,
base table pointer, crime,
for the two base labels,
different base labels,
first level base tables.
Each of them, they have point to second level page tables.
And what you can see here that some of the second level page tables are shared.
Obviously, all the pages to each entries in the shared space tables,
.2are also shared.
Right?
And finally,
you remember,
I we started with this solving this problem that the page tables
can become extremely large.
If we have,
and many of the entries are from these huge base tables are now,
so contains no Information.
And we said that the two level page table is going to solve that,
address that problem,
or at least alleviate that problem.
Here is an example.
If you remember, this is an example,
and let me just try to go back here.
This is a previous example.
So this is the example which are going to have,
if you can see you,
this was a 111 level table.
So you have, I think, 32 entries,
many of these centuries are now.
Right?
This is a corresponding example.
That's this is a corresponding example you can see.
And you can count.
You have much fuels.
It requires to appear less storage for storing these space labels.
Right?
And certainly, you have much more fewer malignants.
Let's continue.
We have just a few more minutes.
And this also tells you about how the translation is done.
In this particular case,
we have for the first page, the level page table,
we use three beats for the second level two beats,
and for the offset 3 bits.
So in the best case, an article,
the size of the page tables is a number of pages used by the program
in the spiritual memory.
Unlike the previous case,
in which the number of pages was the one available in the physical memory,
the price to pay here is that you have one more additional memory access,
right?
Because they need to do index on both space labels,
advanced level.
How about about segments and pages?
Right?
This is another way to do it, right?
Like we have two level tables.
But another way to sell to solve similar problems is have to combine
segmentation with spaging.
In this case, again,
you have the address is split into three fields,
but the first field represent a segment number.
The second field represents a virtual page number,
resumes a segment,
and then you have the offset.
It's a very similar approach.
It's again here.
What do you need to save and store?
When contact switching?
You need to store the segment table.
You need to start the page table for that process.
How do you share the data across different segments?
When you have these both segments and pay and Beijing?
It's the same very similar way that I you are going to have
from two different processes.
They can share the pages by simply having the base
by sharing the segment,
right?
If you understand a bunch of pages,
you are going to put all these pages in the same segment,
then you are going to share the same very soon.
Let me do this one last slide,
and then I am going to stop here.
When you have multilevel translation pages,
what are the pros and cons?
Okay?
The big PRO is that you get to is much less space for the page labels.
Right?
That's it.
The phone number, the Beijing in themselves,
they have the big advantage that it's fixed size.
So they retain to some simplicity,
you have no external fragmentation,
have only internal fragmentation.
The cause is that the page tables can be huge,
because they need to be continuous because you need to indexing with them.
Therefore,
you need to have multiple level of labels in order to get
the memory allocation with the two to get
efficient memory allocation for the page tables.
But the big problem is that now you need to have multiple look UPS for translation,
because you need to look to have a look up for each page level.
Let's stop here again.
Please attend Nathan lecture on Thursday,
and i'll see you next Monday.
Thanks.
So we are done.
Let me just some recording.