Cool.
So we're recording.
And I can do stuff.
Great.
So i'm gonna try and keep my eye on the chat.
But i'm not very good at this yet, so this is all new to me.
So i'm gonna do my best.
So i'm nathan, i'm filling in for yon today.
I'm a grad student,
I work with yon.
Sometimes.
I study a lot of stuff.
I do like kind of cloud stuff,
serverless computing.
If ever heard of that, I goof around with some hardware,
lots of stuff like that.
But today we're gonna be talking about more stuff to do with a dream
and virtual memory.
And particularly today,
there's a big focus on how paging actually works kind of in practice.
So a lot of the tips and tricks how the hardware deals with it.
Some of the more kind of advanced,
detailed concepts around that.
So starting from what you guys saw last week,
and you guys can interrupt me in the chat if if i'm sort of off and sink,
I think young told me where he left off last time.
We talked about flat page tables.
We talked about first level,
single level page tables.
A single level page table is gonna have one entry for every virtual page
that you could possibly have.
If you have a 32 bit system,
that's gonna be 2 to the 32 entries about4 billion,
4 billion divided by the page size,
just four k if you're on a 64 bit machine,
which is obviously the most popular today,
at least for high end,
sort of systems that's gonna be 2 to the 64,
which is a completely outrageous number.
Single level page tables are just not practical.
You'd have to have an entry for every virtual address.
And the reality is that and no program uses
anywhere near all available virtual addresses.
The vast majority of programs use a tiny fraction of virtual memory.
What do we do?
We go back to our data structures class that we learned.
We learned about all these neat data structures,
and we remember that there's a thing called a tree.
What we do is instead of having that first level page table address everything,
what it instead does is it points to child nodes in a tree.
This isn't a binary tree.
It's aa tree with as many leaves as you need in order to cover
the virtual address space.
But it's the same idea, just like a tree.
And instead of treating your virtual address bits as an index
into a single table,
we split it up.
Now there's two parts here.
So you can see there's one part that indexes into the first level page table.
And then the second half of it we're gonna use here to index
into the second level page table.
It's just an index scheme.
It's just a scheme in order to structure a page table,
more like a tree than a page than a single table.
Then this one here is actually like what you learned about before.
This is your standard page table entry.
We call that apte for short,
i'm gonna use that word a lot today.
So page table entry is apte this is the normal one we saw,
just like when it was in a first level page table.
So you got the physical page number here.
In linux.
I think they call this a frame,
so they call this the physical frame number of pfn you might hear me say
page number,
you might hear me say frame number,
often frame is tends to get used for the physical,
just to make it a little more clear that whether we're talking
about virtual pages or physical pages,
also, when you say frame,
you tend to refer to an actual literal like particular address in memory.
Either way we have a physical page number in the table,
so we use the virtual page number.
So that was this part.
This was what you thought the address was.
We use that in order to find the physical page number.
And then because pages have multiple bytes in them,
and you're trying to address a particular byte,
there's this offset part you provided,
and that offsets gonna be the same,
whether it's physical or virtual.
It's just the offset in here,
whether it's here, right?
Okay?
Multilevel page table is pretty sure we talked about this,
or you talked about this last week.
But they're pretty cool.
And one of the nice things here is that I don't actually have to have
every one of these,
right?
So I could have,
maybe this doesn't even have to exist.
Right?
If I haven't allocated any pages,
why should I even bother creating the leaf node yet?
What you might do is you might just sort of mark this as empty.
Right?
In this entry might have some sort of bit that you said that's enough.
This doesn't actually exist.
Ignore it.
In which case we didn't have to allocate this other one.
We saved ourselves some memory.
So with multilevel page tables,
we no longer have to store.
We don't have to allocate memory for all the empty spots in the table anymore.
We just have to allocate memory for the ones that actually have been assigned,
or at least1 page is worth of ones that have been assigned.
We still are gonna have empty slots in this second level page table,
but there's a lot fewer of them.
So it kind of works out.
What are the pros and cons here?
So the pros of the multilevel page table is that,
like I said, sparse address spaces that are mostly empty, mostly unassigned.
This is reasonably good at because you don't have to store all the empty ones,
because we're using paging rather than something more complicated like segmentation.
Then it makes memory allocation a lot easier,
because you have fixed size pages,
you have these fixed size allocation units that makes life a lot
easier when you're writing memory allocators.
Now I don't know if you guys have a memory allocator project in this class,
or if you've done one yet, but when you do,
you're gonna start to realize how incredibly annoying it
would be to try and allocate variable size things.
It's much easier if they're fixed size and aligned.
The other nice thing is that every process has its own page table.
And so it makes it really easy to share.
So even though two people might have different virtual addresses,
it's pretty neat.
We can actually just have those virtual addresses mapped
to the same physical address.
Then people can share physical memory without even realizing it.
And that's pretty neat.
So we'll talk a little bit more about that later in the lecture.
It's not perfect, though.
I there's down sides, right?
One of them is that because they're not variable size,
because they're fixed size,
we actually have to have an entry page,
even though I might allocate you like a gigabyte in one shot,
actually gonna have to have one entry for every four k in that big,
four gigabyte section.
So I can give you these big allocations,
but i'm allocating a lot of kind of redundant information with segments.
You wouldn't have that problem, right?
Of segmentation.
I could give you a base register and just a four gigabyte down,
and then everything would work out.
It's kind of a drawback of this paging approach.
The way people deal with that is they tend to allow for different sized pages.
There's still a line, but today you can do things called huge pages.
Maybe you could allocate a one megabyte or even bigger page size.
That is a trick that modern systems use,
but we won't really go into too much more detail beyond that for huge pages.
They have to be contiguous.
It's not such a bad a bit.
So not such a problem.
When you have multilevel page tables.
All we do is we make each one of those levels.
So each one of those,
let's see.
So each one of these,
what happened here?
Sorry, guys.
So getting used to this,
okay?
We make each one of these happen to fit precisely in 1 page that makes life
an awful lot easier for everybody.
So it's not really that big a deal,
but it does add us another little constraint that we have to have
a very particular organization of our page table.
Because we're gonna talk about later,
the hardware has to be able to interact with it.
It's a little bit of a constraint.
But the big the one that really screws us up here is this last point.
So the problem we have is that when you have multilevel page tables,
then you have to kind of hunt around it.
You gotta read that first level page table first,
figure out where the second level one is,
and then go read the second level one to find your answer.
And if you have more right,
like some things have more than two levels,
there's four level page tables or more,
then it's like four hops.
And every time you have to follow a pointer,
that's time that takes time, right?
Jumping around memory, chasing pointers.
And we have to do address translation on every single load store.
Every time you load, every time you store,
including instructions.
So every time you fetch the next instruction,
that's kind of like a load.
You have to do address translation.
It's important that it be super fast and hopping around is kind of slow.
So this is a big issue that we're gonna have to figure out how to solve.
The next question is we talked about how they're organized,
what they're kind of doing at a high level.
The next question is,
who's managing these, right?
How are you actually filling in these translations?
We got to remember that this is an operating system,
the operating systems, job,
one of its big jobs is allowing multiple applications
like multiple processes to safely share machines.
They can't screw with each other.
Right?
Like, even if you have a process running some sensitive information,
other processes that you're running at the same time aren't allowed to read
that.
So its security.
And also, if one of them screws up, right?
You have a mistake.
You start writing to some random address, you get a seg fault, whatever.
We don't want to be able to screw everybody else up.
So if one badly written program can take your whole system down,
you kind of have a problem.
The trick we do with most any sort of cpu that really supports,
or any isa that really supports,
an operating system is gonna have this dual mode operation.
Instead of letting processes set up their own page tables,
we have kernel mode.
In kernel mode, you can do anything you want, right?
You have super high privilege to do anything you want.
And then in user mode, there's a bunch of stuff you're not allowed to do.
A lot of the stuff you're not allowed to do boils down to like
what memory regions you can write,
and which like control registers you can set and things like that.
When the system first boots up, it's in kernel mode.
When you first press that power button,
then your operating system loads.
And it sets up anything.
It wants to set up page tables, ctrl bits,
all this kind of junk.
And then it decides to run a program.
So it's gonna jump into that program.
It's gonna say, okay,
let's go and execute some pc that represents some process.
And when it does that,
it's gonna deselect the privileged bit,
so it's gonna turn off that privilege bit.
Now, we're in user mode and users not allowed to do anything.
And the only way you get back to kernel mode is through a trap.
There might be some hardware event,
or there might be some software event that says it's time for the kernel
to do something.
The colonel has registered very specific things that it's allowed to do.
So it says, if I get trapped five,
then you should run this code in my kernel.
If I get trapped six,
you should run that code.
The user can't touch anything,
but they can hand control back to the kernel in a very controlled way.
It's obviously more complicated that than that.
And there's gonna be this caveat through this entire lecture.
In this class, we're mostly focused on x 86,
because that's the one you're using in your projects.
Basically,
x 86 is like thousands and thousands of pages for its instruction manual.
It's old.
It's grown very organically.
And so things tend to get a little complicated,
not too important to know,
but what you can realize is that we have a lot of flexibility here.
Traditionally, ring zero would be kernel mode.
Ring three is user mode.
There's a ring one and two that nobody really uses.
And then when they wanted to add hypervisors,
right?
And then there's-1,
and there's more right like this-3 that michael is mentioning.
In risk five, what you have are also different modes.
I don't think they call them rings and risk five,
but you have machine mode,
which is kind of like this intel management engine style thing,
where you're setting up very low level stuff.
It's where you might like emulate instructions that you haven't implemented
it or other stuff like that.
Then there's supervisor mode where the kernel runs,
and then there's user mode.
And I actually don't know a lot about how risk five handles hypervisors.
So I can't talk too much about that.
But the point is that the cpu has control modes,
they have protection modes,
and that's how operating systems work.
In practice.
That's how they're safe.
Okay?
We're gonna just take a quick detour into segmentation.
I just talked about how intel has got all sorts of old stuff floating
around in it.
And one of those old mobile things is segmentation.
It's not really used a lot these days,
but it does still exist.
So just real quickly,
I think the slide will be mostly good for your reference after.
So i'm gonna go through it real quick,
but x 86 supports a bunch of different segments.
You have these registers, the register,
so registers are right in your pipeline.
They're right next to your cpu you can't have very many of them,
and they can't be too complicated because you have like limited number of bits,
limited number of wires,
and flip flops and whatever,
right next to your cpu so you can't have too many.
So what they do is they have a register to write represent segments.
And then that register is actually a pointer to a more rich description
of the segment that you want.
And then that segment has a whole bunch of details in it about the segment.
So it's got permission bits.
It's got a base and a limit,
which is the bottom line for segments.
You notice that they're like the address bits are spread around in funny places.
You might remember from 61 c how risk five does the same thing for,
I think,
loads like certain loads or certain jumps have kind of a funny layout.
These are all just micro architectural details.
At the time.
When they wrote this,
it was easier to put this wire here or that wire there.
It tends to be sort of boring reasons that it's shaped funny.
You can come back to the slide to understand what all these bits do.
But let's just quickly talk about what they're actually used for.
There's different ways that you can use the segments.
The most common use originally was in the old 16 bit version of x 86.
The very first time people were writing 16 bit processors.
Having more than a few kilobytes of memory was a ridiculous concept, right?
Nobody having a megabyte of memory was insane.
Nobody ever thought that could happen.
They had this 16 bit addressing mode,
and they had a lot of segments.
Again, you can't have page tables if you only have, like,
less than a kilobyte of memory.
So they would use segments originally.
Then we use the word modern here loosely.
Most application level sorts of processors are 64 bit these days,
but some embedded low power that kind of stuff would be 32 bit.
I don't think there's a lot of 32 bit x 86 processors out there,
but in risk five,
there's lots of 32 bit risk five processors floating around.
So in this case, they kind of weakened the segmentation support.
It's still there, but not great.
The one exception is spread local storage.
So a process is not like a super precise concept.
I it is in the spec,
but a process is just some sort of logically connected set of things
that all share most of their resources.
So they have one process id they most for the most part,
they have 1 set of like virtual addresses, things like that.
But sometimes it's handy to have a little bit of private memory space per thread.
The threads, in this case,
are like different p cs that you could potentially be jumping between.
Right?
So different program counters into the same basic program.
On x 86, they used segments in order to implement that.
On risk five, they something different.
I actually was looking for that earlier.
I couldn't find it.
So i'm not sure how risk five implements thread local storage,
but i'm sure it's not with segments.
And then on 64 bit mode,
which is the most common x 86 mode today,
they have been basically nerved.
So like they work in like the most limited possible way,
except again for thread local storage which still gets.
But otherwise,
just keep in mind segments kind of made sense when you had very,
very little memory.
And they make a lot less sense as your virtual address space starts to get bigger,
and you need like more and more flexible management.
And you have enough memory where the memory overhead of keeping a bunch
of page tables around isn't gonna kill you.
Okay?
So enough about segmentation coming back to paging,
I mentioned that you could have more than two levels, right?
So if two levels is good,
then four levels is good.
And there's really nothing different here.
So there's nothing special,
whatever you learned about two level page tables,
just like recurse on that a couple more times than you've got
multilevel page tables.
So you still have your base here.
You have your top level page table that is gonna point
into some lower level page table,
which is sort of like this one.
Now it points here, and then it points here.
And then finally, you get your pte here.
It's not fundamentally different.
In any way than a two level page table.
You just have more hops.
That's gonna keep shrinking this top level page table, right?
Every time you add a hop,
that's gonna exponentially drop the number of entries you have to have here,
which can be handy.
But again, otherwise, nothing special.
Just like you saw before,
you keep going, right?
We had four.
Why don't we do six?
It starts to get ridiculous.
Basically, I there are drawbacks, right?
We talked about having to do all this pointer hopping, right?
You have to keep following through each level, and that takes time.
There's a point where you're just not saving anything.
It just starts to get out of hand.
So six level page tables aren't really common.
I think italian might have.
Italian was an attempt by intel to create a new isa it went horribly wrong.
It's a long and tragic story and somewhat funny involving lawsuits between hewlett,
packard and intel.
And it's a great story that I won't tell you now.
But it basically,
they did a lot of crazy things,
and some of them didn't work out,
including 6 double page tables.
Okay, so what else can we do?
And then i'm gonna ask for a little bit of audience thought here,
if not participation,
the problem we're facing here is that these page tables are have drawbacks.
You have to have an entry for every virtual memory address.
So there's still a lot of space.
Every process gets their own page table.
And even with multilevel page tables,
you still have a lot of empty spots.
Typically, your address space is way bigger than your physical memory,
right?
You might have two for32 gigs of ram,
but you've got 2 to the 64 virtual addresses,
so it's not even a competition.
So the question for you guys is,
let's look at what is the problem we're trying to solve.
The problem is given a virtual address,
I want to be able to map that to a physical address.
One of the data structures we thought about for doing that was a tree trees,
have this login sort of traversal pattern.
They have these properties,
but we want to have better than login, right?
We'd we'd like to have fewer pointer chases.
We want to faster look at what data structure might we consider?
That isn't a table.
We have a lot of data structures you all took.
I guess it's 61 b that teaches you these.
I'm gonna give you 10 seconds to think up what data structure you would use
other than a tree.
We got it hash table.
Hash tables are super cool.
Hash tables are great.
They've got constant access time,
at least big o constant access time.
And we can do some cool tricks with these.
So one of the things we do here is we can have a hash table where it has
an entry for every physical page.
Like we don't need more virtual addresses mapped.
Then we have physical memory because like it doesn't make sense.
You can't map more than physical memory anyways,
because you only have that much memory.
So you can have one hash table for the entire system.
You can use that to look up your virtual page,
so you can index into this hash table using virtual page number and get
this physical page number back.
And this has been used before, right?
This is nice when you have these big address spaces,
these big virtual address spaces.
And so it has been used in a couple of places.
It has some nice properties,
but it's not perfect either.
So the big problem here,
there's two big problems here.
It actually probably three big problems here,
but we're gonna list two of them here.
One is that keep in mind from your algorithms classes and stuff,
the limitations of big o notation.
Right?
We say constants don't matter in terms of asymptotic complexity.
But like insertion sort is way faster than quick sort for a small enough list.
Right?
When you were doing merge sort,
there was a point where you bottomed out on merge sort
and just switched to like selection sort of insertion sort.
The same thing applies here.
There's a point where the complexity of looking up a hash table,
the constants involved algorithm, again,
looking at the hash table are actually gonna outweigh the benefits.
So that can happen.
This is particularly true in hardware,
because these look, ups are happening on every axis.
We need to do that in hardware.
We're actually designing a circuit,
a digital logic to access this hash table.
It has to be sufficiently simple that you can implement that hardware.
That's a problem.
The other problem is locality.
Hash tables kind of by their very nature, right?
That's what a hash function does,
is it's pretty random.
It's pretty evenly distributed.
There's no locality.
So I can't like effectively cash this hash table.
Every lookup is gonna be in a pretty random spot in this hash table.
So it's not very cash friendly,
and that's pretty annoying.
The third problem here actually,
is that it makes things like sharing really difficult.
This assumes there's only ever one virtual page,
virtual address map to a physical page.
But for sharing,
we might want to have multiple virtual addresses.to the same physical
address that makes this a lot more complicated.
If you want to do that.
Nonetheless, it's still pretty handy.
And people have used them in the past,
but they're not especially popular in processors.
Today.
I'm not aware of any make a really popular process,
I guess power pc might still be around.
We've got options here.
We've got a whole bunch of options and how we can do paging.
At the end of the day, we're all trying to solve the same problem.
You have some virtual address,
and you want to map it to some physical address.
That's all we're trying to do.
Right?
These are a bunch of different algorithms and data structures that we
could consider using.
In order to do that.
We've got segmentation.
Segmentation is great, for simplicity,
in terms of implementing acpu doesn't use too much memory for the meta data,
but it's very hard to allocate all these arbitrary size things,
and it really screws with your ability to share memory and accurate
and allocate memory.
Paging works a lot better.
It's a lot more flexible.
It's a lot easier to allocate.
But if you have single level page tables,
you can really fill up your memory of a lot of empty space.
We use multilevel paging to get around that,
or you could avoid all of this sort of tree walking and use
an inverted page table,
which works pretty great, but has limitations of its own.
So enough about the high level strategies and the problem we're trying to solve.
Let's get into the nitty gritty.
Let's start talking about how you might actually physically implement this.
How does this work in practice?
The thing that is in charge of this is called the mmu this is the part
of your architecture,
the part of your cpu or your chip that is responsible for handling
this virtual address to physical address translation.
So we call that the memory management unit.
Everyone just says in mu it's the one that's in charge of all of this.
So it needs to do different things.
We're gonna focus on paging.
So we're gonna focus on page tables probably from now on,
because it's by far the most common approach,
at least in the sort of high end or medium end,
application processors that you're likely to see.
If you have page tables,
the mmu is gonna have to do the walk.
So it's gonna walk that tree in hardware.
It reads the page table entry,
the pte from the first level page table,
checks all the meta data that it needs.
And then it goes and finds the address in the second level page table.
Looks that up.
It rates as many times as it needs,
gets the final pte then it can form the actual physical address and send
that request out to the rest of the memory system.
The mmu is just translating logically.
The cpu doesn't know about physical addresses.
So the cpu is just issuing virtual addresses.
And automatically,
the mmu is making them behave like physical addresses.
It's doing this every, at least conceptually.
It's got to do this all the time, right?
Every single time you do a read or write,
that includes fetching the next instruction that mmu has to do
that translation in order to get to memory.
This is aaa bit more of a physical representation of it.
You can see you've got all these buses floating around,
so you've got your core,
you're like core cpu pipeline.
You've got a bunch of buses,
and they're going through these hardware blocks.
And if you take 152,
you're gonna see a lot more of this,
or maybe some of your digital logic classes.
A lot of this can take time.
So loads and stores, if they hit in the cache,
can be really fast.
Maybe they don't stall the pipeline too bad.
But if you miss or you have to go out to physical memory,
then your pipeline has to stall and you get those bubbles.
If you remember seeing bubbles.
I think in 61 c you hit a little bit of that.
And I can cause problems.
We have to make sure that this translation is really fast.
And in a really naive sense,
if we didn't do any fancy optimization,
a single loader store could turn into like three or four reads,
and then the loader store.
It's multiplying every memory access by like four if you have
a four level page table.
This is a problem and we're gonna have to solve this problem.
Okay, so this is really, really slow.
I unreasonably slow for any high performance cpu what do we do?
If we have some sort of data access,
we do that data access multiple times,
and we want to make it faster.
So I already kind of spoiled the answer here by switching slides.
This is caching.
Caching is one of those like fundamental core computer science concepts
that just comes out again and again and again.
You're gonna see caching everywhere.
It's just everywhere.
So that's what we're gonna have to deal with, is caching.
That's the trick we're gonna use to solve this.
So i'm gonna spend a little bit of time now reviewing caching.
I know you learned a little bit about this in 61 c if you've taken like 152
or something,
you're gonna see caching in a lot more detail.
But i'm gonna take some time now to refresh your memory,
because catching is super important.
And you're gonna see it.
Just in this lecture alone,
we're gonna see three examples of caching just in this lecture alone.
Then every class you're gonna see it.
A cache is a smaller,
faster memory in which we store copies of some original data.
It's everywhere, like I just said.
And it really only works if you have some sort of locality.
So basically,
you have to be able to predict whether you're gonna reuse some memory.
If you can predict it,
then caches are gonna work.
If you have completely unpredictable access is then the cache isn't gonna work.
Is what do you store in the cache?
Every single one is like totally random.
They won't work in that case,
but as long as you have,
some locality catches are great.
Here's a metric, there's a metric that's really important to keep in mind.
This is another one.
It's sort of like the iron law.
There's a bunch of these equations that seem really dumb or like.
And elsa, right?
They're almost dumb, right?
They're just obvious like of this is the time.
But they're easy to forget,
and they're really helpful for thinking and like understanding how systems work.
In this case, we're talking about average access time,
so that is the hit rate times the hit time,
plus the miss rate times the miss time,
is gonna be your average access time.
So on average, a memory access is gonna take that much time.
So keep that in mind,
you may be asked to do that on homeworks or tests or things.
It's important.
And I think we're gonna walk through an example here in a second.
It is we need to put into context a little bit why we're talking
about cashing and how effective it can.
Right?
I think humans brains are really bad at reasoning about scale.
We just can't handle things that are like orders of magnitude apart.
Our brains just aren't wired for.
Here's an attempt to put it into perspective,
an attempt that will probably fail,
but you should keep these numbers in mind.
That's really important to always have this in your head.
We have multiple ways of storing data in digital logic or a in a computer.
The fastest one here is registers,
and also kind of the l one cache.
Their l one cache might be a little slower than registers, but it's closed.
Both of these are about about the cycle time.
These are running about the same speed as like your computer processor cycles.
That means that we want to interact with these in hardware.
These happen at sort of hardware time.
Scales, right?
Then we've got all this stuff in the middle, so we've got all these,
and they're just getting slower and slower and slower.
At some point, we're gonna get all the way to your hard disk.
And when you get to your hard disk to a first order approximation,
the amount of time it takes to read from a hard disk is forever.
Like from a hardware perspective.
It's not even worth thinking about.
I it's an absolutely absurd amount of time.
I was gonna need bread, but then I cut my finger,
so I haven't done that recently.
Okay.
So basically think about hard disks as taking infinite time
from a hardware perspective.
If i'm cycling at 4 gigahertz,
10 millisecond is just a ridiculous amount of time.
When we're gonna go to these time scales,
we're just gonna deal with it in software.
Right?
Because it doesn't make sense for the hardware to even deal with it.
It's so slow.
And then there's this stuff in the middle,
and all this stuff in the middle are gonna be shades of grey.
Right?
And depending on how you want to deal with this,
you might have hardware deal with it.
You might have software deal with it.
You might have some more complicated mix of things.
A lot of my research has focused sort of in this space and understanding
where exactly that barrier between hardware and software can be.
And it's a pretty interesting question.
But way over here definitely want to deal with that completely
in software way over here.
Definitely want to deal with that completely in hardware.
There's like millions and millions and millions times difference
in the performance here.
So that's why caches are important.
L one cache miss is not a big deal.
It's gonna happen.
You're only gonna lose a cycle or something.
If you try and read something from disk,
just give up, right?
Like, go, put your laptop away, go home,
come back, right?
At least the hardware thinks it's like that.
And then address translation.
Because this is so fast,
address translation has to happen.
Right here has to happen by the time you get into the court.
So it's got to be fast.
Worst case scenario,
page tables live here,
or maybe even here in extreme cases.
But for the most part, your page tables are here,
we need this caching in order to be able to access them effectively.
Okay?
Just real quick,
because I think it's really important to understand this equation.
We're gonna go through an example.
Let's take a real example or a made up example.
That's real enough.
And say that it takes about 100 nanoseconds to get to d ram.
This is about right?
And then say it takes 1 nanosecond to get to your cash like you're a one.
Again, it's about, right?
What's the average memory access time here?
I'm gonna go through it now just in the interest of time,
but this is something that you guys are gonna have to get
a little bit comfortable running.
Actually, I let people sort of think about this for a second,
and i'm gonna answer this question.
What do I by letting software deal with it?
We're gonna talk about that in a little more detail later in the lecture.
But basically,
what I mean is that the hardware might notice that it needs to go to disk,
like it might notice that the data it needs is not available.
And rather than some circuit,
figuring out how to read from the disk.
So some digital logic issuing requests to the disk,
what it's gonna do is it's gonna throw it what's called a trap,
just like how the user process is able to switch back into kernel mode.
The hardware can decide what I can't deal with this right now.
I'm gonna run some code that the operating system provided.
I'll let that code deal with this.
When we let software deal with it,
that means we hand control to the operating system to make
some more complicated decisions than you could in a dedicated
like digital logic circuit.
We'll go into more details of this later on.
Assuming we get there,
we're looking at the average memory access time.
This is hit rate times hit time,
plus miss rate times miss time.
The hit rate plus the miss rate.
Obviously, they've got a match, right?
If I didn't hit, then I missed.
If I didn't miss, then I hit.
So these are just ratios.
So let's assume that our hit rate in this cache is 90%.
That means that our miss rate is gonna be 10%.
If we hit,
then that means it took us a nanosecond to read.
So that will be 90% times 1.
And then if we missed,
it's gonna take us 100 seconds to read,
but I just wrote 101 here.
So why did I write 101 and not 1 hundred for the miss time?
Give you guys a few seconds to think about that.
So the reason I did that was that in order to notice that I missed,
I had to try in it.
So not quite.
So the exactly.
So I think brian's got it here.
The trick is that I had to notice that I missed,
and that took a nanosecond all by itself.
Then I noticed that I missed and then I could start trying to read
from the next level,
right?
Or actually, that might be what they was trying to get at, too.
So that's why so you have to keep you have to account for the fact
that missing takes extra time because you have to notice that you missed.
And so we can look at what happens as you change,
hit rates and miss rates.
Notice that a relatively small increase in the hit rate can have
a very large impact on the overall performance.
Hit rates become very important.
Again, I talked about why caching works gonna move a little bit fast here.
That's kind of an important concept.
We talked about locality.
So caching works because we have predictability.
We can guess what memories are likely to be accessed next.
So there's different types of patterns that we might detect.
And the most common ones are temporal lookout, temporal locality.
So if I read or wrote some address,
i'm probably gonna read or write it again.
Most likely.
Imagine if I have a loop instructions are memory.
If you remember your whole von neumann thing,
so you're the program itself is memory.
And if I have a loop in my memory,
then i'm gonna be reusing those instructions over and over and over,
because I got this loop.
That's temporal locality.
That's a pretty good guess.
That tends to work pretty well.
If I access something recently,
i'll probably access it again.
The other one is spatial locality.
This is like, imagine scanning an array.
Right?
If i'm reading an array from start to finish,
if I read an array from start to finish,
if I access 1 piece of information,
it's pretty likely that i'm gonna read addresses that are nearby.
That is spatial.
Locality stuff tends to cut cluster together physically,
like in the address space.
That's not always true.
I talked earlier about how hash tables aren't very cash friendly.
This is why?
Because hash tables don't have a lot of spatial locality.
You jump around them a lot.
And so things that are acts,
things that are physically near each other aren't necessarily accessed together.
But then having an array or a table lookup or something like that,
you have more spatial localities,
so they tend to behave a little nicer.
Right?
And then the final thing here is that we have multiple levels,
and so we can stack these together in order to keep track of things.
So what is the trick here?
Why was I just talking about caching?
Translations are slow, really painful.
And the trick we're gonna do,
the trick we always do is we're just gonna slap a cache on it.
Right?
Caches are everywhere,
and this is no exception.
We're gonna stick a cache on the mmu and now every time we do a translation,
we're gonna save that translation in this cache.
Now the cache is smaller,
and it's faster to access.
So we don't have to do all this table locking.
We can just look it up in the cache.
And the cache is relatively simple.
It's just gonna have the virtual page.
Right?
That's what you're using to look up.
That's gonna have the physical frame number.
That's the answer you want.
Then it's also gonna cache a bunch of other like metadata.
So pt es have a bunch of extra information in them,
like whether this mapping is currently valid,
or whether you're allowed to read or write to it.
It hasn't been accessed recently.
There's much a little metadata.
We'll show you a picture at the end of the slides,
but a lot of little data that you want to keep around to keep track
of extra information.
That's what you're caching.
So keep in mind here.
This is not caching data.
This has nothing to do with what's actually in the page, right?
We're not caching.
The information contained in the page.
All we're caching is meta data.
We're catching information about the page.
So that's what we're trying to cash here.
And it's gonna save us every time we hit in this cache.
We get to avoid walking the table.
And that's pretty nice.
Okay.
This cache, for largely historical reasons is referred to as a translation.
Look aside buffer.
It's just a fancy word for a cash.
Turns out it's a very old idea.
They came up with it quite a long time ago.
Before the word cash was really coined,
it has kind of a funny name.
But either way, it's storing these translations.
If we hit in that cache,
we get to avoid all these slow look up.
So that's really nice.
Like I said,
it was invented actually quite a long time ago before the word cache
was even being commonly used.
Hence the funny name.
And we call it the tob so I don't think anybody ever says translation.
Look aside buffer out loud.
They only ever say tob you have to get used to hearing that word.
But keep in mind, tlb is just a funny word for cache.
It's a cache for your page table, lookouts,
a cache for her,
for virtual to physical translations.
How does this work?
Let's go through just sort of a flow diagram,
a workflow of how this actually goes.
Cpu is gonna ask for a virtual address.
It's gonna try and find it in the tob or the mmu is gonna try and find it
in the tob if it does,
great,
immediately,
it's just gonna push that request all the way through to physical memory,
and everything's on theory.
If it's not, so there's nothing cashed,
then you're gonna have to go to the interview.
The mmu is going to have to go back and forth to memory a couple times
to walk that table.
But once it's walked the table and it's looked up the translation,
it can save that translation and the tlb and then go and do the translation
for the cpu and everything starts back up.
Why does this work and does it work?
It's a question of page locality.
Is there locality?
Or is the caching gonna work?
Is their spatial locality?
Is their temporal locality?
It turns out there is.
So it turns out that physical memory,
the pages in physical memory,
tend to have quite a lot of locality.
Actually,
the biggest, a really big source of this is your code.
Right?
Code is data.
I talked about this before.
When you're reading a program,
like when you're running a program,
the instructions that make up that program are all close together.
So that's spatial locality.
And they tend to get reused a lot.
You have a loop, you're reusing the instructions.
If you call into functions,
one of the whole points of having sub routines or functions is that you
only have one copy of that code and you call into it lots of times
tons and tons of temporal locality and code.
You also have other spatial and temporal locality.
Your stack gets reused again and again and again.
A lot of this sort of hard data stuff.
The heap is more variable,
whether or not your heap has locality.
It's the same reasons.
It has cash locality in your data caches.
It's up to you to write a program that has good cash locality,
but it tends to and all the tricks that we play for caches apply to tl bs
as well.
They're just a cache.
Maybe they got a few different decisions you might make,
but ultimately,
their caches and all the same tricks work.
We can have a multilevel tlb if we want.
We've been talking for a while.
I'm gonna take a break.
I'm gonna get some water and do a stretch,
and I will allow others to do the same.
We're gonna take a 2 minute break.
I'll be back at 1:28.
Here's a bunch of announcements.
I'm just sort of stepping in for today.
So I have no idea what any of these announcements mean.
It's just what young gave me.
So talk to your t as or whatever128 will be back.
While we're waiting, you guys can ask questions and stuff.
If you want
ok and we're back,
it's a quick break a lot of content to cover.
Okay?
Starting again,
let's start moving on.
Okay?
We talked about catching a lot real handy to keep this in mind.
This is a concept that comes up again and again.
So let's talk about,
we talked about why caches work.
You talk about temporal locality and and spatial locality.
So let's talk about what makes cache is not work,
what makes us miss in the cache.
So let's categorize them.
So recall the one of the types of cache miss that you can get is called compulsory.
This means it's a myth that you really just can't do anything about.
Right?
Like, i've never seen this data before, therefore,
I don't have a cache,
so called compulsory misses are mostly unavoidable.
There's some tricks you can do with what's called prefetching,
where you try and guess what you might need in the future.
And that's really the only way that you can avoid compulsory misses.
Another one is called capacity misses.
In this case,
I basically just ran out of space.
I have cashed everything, I can cash,
I have no more room.
I had to kick something out of my cash because I ran out of room.
And therefore I missed the next time you tried to read it.
I saw this data, I cashed it,
and then I ran out of room and I had to kick it out again.
The way you deal with capacity misses is you make your cash bigger,
and you make it bigger and bigger and everything's great.
But keep in mind as you make your cash bigger, it gets slower.
So there's a point where you don't want to make the cash.
Another one conflict.
In this case, with a conflict miss,
i've seen the data before,
so it's not compulsory.
I have enough capacity for it so that i've empty space in my cache,
I could store it.
But because of the algorithm and the data structures I chose,
because of the way I chose to design my cache,
I had to kick something out.
We're gonna go into those details again here in a minute about what sort
of algorithms you might choose and why those might have conflict misses,
even if there was enough room.
The bottom line here is that ii couldn't store it,
because the algorithms I chose,
there's different ways of dealing with conflict misses.
You can make the cache figure so that you're less likely to have one
of these conflicts,
or you can change your algorithm.
You can make your algorithm a little more sophisticated.
And then you're less likely to have conflicts.
There's one more,
and I don't think this was talked about very much in 61 c if at all.
It's been a few years since I since I taught that class,
but the last one here is called coherence.
This is one that's gonna come up a lot in tlb this is kind of a big one
for tlbs what?
A coherence one is basically that a cache is a copy.
So I have a copy of data,
but the data that's up in like, say, main memory,
that's the real data.
Right?
That's the official official,
real ground truth of what that data is.
And my cache is just like a copy of that.
If somebody changes that data in main memory, for whatever reason,
some other cpu does it,
or some other process or circuit or trigger or whatever did it?
If it changes for some reason,
then I have to invalidate my cache.
I have to tell the cache.
You have a copy of this data, but it's not true anymore.
You need to throw it out and read the new data.
So that's called a coherence miss.
This is one that doesn't show up much in data caches for single cpu systems.
But if you have multiple cp us, it happens a lot.
If you have things like tl bs,
have it more often,
because there's more things that change page table entries until these are
kind of separate from the data cache.
But we'll go into that more detail.
False sharing is a particularly degenerate cause of coherence misses.
This is a question in the chat.
Basically, false sharing causes unnecessary coherence misses,
but you can have coherence misses that don't involve false sharing.
So if you have true sharing,
right?
Like,
so let's say i'm sharing,
like you see this a lot in locks, like when you're right,
when you're implementing walks, this is really common.
You have lots and lots of entities, let's say,
lots and lots of different cores.
They're all trying to read and write the same piece of memory.
Maybe it's to set a lock,
maybe it's just to communicate.
Right?
That's real sharing.
And that would cause lots and lots of coherence misses.
What happens with false sharing is that caches store an entire line
at a time you store blocks.
Right?
You store cache line.
Let's say that you're not actually sharing data like core zero is writing
the first byte.
Core one is writing the next byte,
core two is writing the next byte.
So they're not sharing data,
but they are sharing the same cache line.
So they're saying sharing the same block.
So that's why it's called false sharing.
The caches can only detect conflicts or coherence issues on a cache line granularity.
You're not actually sharing data,
but you are sharing the same cache line,
and that's causing a bunch of coherence misses.
Albert asks,
how do we know if there's been a coherence miss?
That is an excellent question.
So there's a famous quote that I love.
I'm sorry, I can't think of the originator of the code off top my head,
but he says there's only two hard problems in computer science,
naming things and cash invalidation.
The answer to your question,
albert is that it is an extremely difficult and complicated problem.
One that makes my head spin when I try and understand it,
and one over which many ph ds have been written.
So cash coherence is hard,
very tricky to do.
And if you take 152,
they'll go into it in quite a lot of detail.
The different algorithms they use to detect coherence methods.
That's for data caches.
And I particularly think 152 is a great class,
and you'll learn a ton.
If you take it.
To bs are interesting because they tend not to participate in all those schemes,
because the only time the data changes is when the operating system
chose to change the page tables.
To bs tend to rely on manual cash invalidation.
I know risk five does or at least all the risk five implementation i'm
familiar with do.
And i'm pretty sure x 86 does as well.
In this case,
the os has to tell the cpuai invalidated this line go and throw it out.
In that case,
there's like the operating system is manually detecting it.
But for data caches,
it gets very complicated.
And for distributed systems, too.
If you take a database class,
you'll learn about dealing with cache coherence in like a distributed systems,
networked cluster,
kind of perspective.
It's the same problem.
Slightly different constants.
The solutions are a little different.
We're gonna go through a quick here overview of caching.
Again.
This is,
I think, largely a duplicate of what you learned in 61 c but obviously,
that was quite a long time ago.
And 61 c is a ridiculous class Where you learn way too many things in one shot.
So it's worth revisiting.
How do we find blocks?
We're using blocks.
Sometimes we use the word cache line.
How do we actually find them in the cache?
Most caches are organized this way.
This is aa definitely, by far,
the most typical way to organize a cash.
I guess in theory, there's other options,
but i'm not really aware of anybody that does them in hardware in a way
that's different than this.
So what you do is it's very similar to what we've been seeing for virtual
to physical translations.
I've got my address here.
This is the top part of the address.
This is whatever i'm asking for.
There's also a part, and this is the offset within the line.
I'm storing a block or a cache line.
It's some fixed size.
It's bigger than a byte.
Maybe it's 64bytes, whatever it is.
I've got a 64 byte cache line,
so i'm gonna need some offset to figure out which byte that is.
Then you've got the block address,
and the block address is gonna help you figure out which cache line it is.
You're looking at.
Typically, we break this blog address in the two parts.
We'll call one the index,
and we'll call one the tag.
The index is the one we're actually gonna use to find the block in our cache.
And the tag is the one we're gonna use to make sure it's the block we think
it is.
So caches are very,
very similar to hash tables.
And a lot of what you can learn learned about hash tables also will help
you understand caches.
This tag is like in a hash table,
you hash the value,
and you use that to find it.
Then you compare the actual value against what you found to make
sure it's the one you wanted and not just like a conflict.
Same thing here.
One of the options we could do is called direct map.
In a direct map cache,
we are going to have exactly one place that we could put any particular address.
So in a way,
you're going to use the index to choose exactly one slot.
Let's see.
If i've got a one kilobyte direct map cache,
I got32 byte blocks.
There's an index,
and i'm gonna use that index to pick a particular line,
a particular place in this cache that I want.
So let's say that the index here is one.
We're gonna use that to select one of these entries.
Then we're gonna compare the tags.
So i'm gonna make sure that the tag I have in my cache is, in fact,
same one as the address i'm looking for.
And then if so,
i'm gonna use the byte select to pick a particular byte
out of that cache line to return.
This is direct map.
The important thing here about direct map is that you have exactly one option.
This index has exactly as many bits as you have entries in the cache.
It's just a direct index.
If it's one, we go to the index number one.
If it was two, we'd go to index number two.
That's direct map.
Direct map has the issue of direct map is that it's got lots and lots
of conflict misses.
Since I only have one option about where i'm gonna put a piece of data,
it's pretty likely that somebody's already there,
and i'm gonna have to kick them out in order to fit the new thing.
They have lots and lots of conflict misses,
because you only have one choice about where you're gonna put anything.
What we do instead is we come up with set associative.
In a set associative cache,
we give ourselves more options.
Instead of having exactly one place that we could put a particular piece
of data,
we have in places that we could put it.
So you can think of this as having two direct map caches side by side,
sort of conceptually,
you can think I have two direct map caches,
but i've set them next to each other.
So each is half the size of my total cache,
but I now have more options.
We do the same thing.
I'm gonna use that cache index to pick which line in one of these caches it
is.
But i'm gonna have to check two tags.
If i'm a two way set associate of cache,
then I have to check two tags at the same time.
And then I get to pick whichever one matches if any.
So the set associative caches are giving us more options were
less likely to have a cache miss,
right?
Because the data that could go here, but this is full.
So I guess we'll just put it here since this one's not full.
So we have options,
and that's gonna reduce conflict missiles.
But a there's a cost.
The cost is complexity.
If you remember your larger sim project from 61 c like imagine writing
a marks that could handle like a thousand inputs,
just think about how narrowly that mucks would look.
Right?
It would have just the billions of wires.
It would be huge.
It would be like completely impractical to implement on like a physical chip.
There are a limit to how many ways you can have before this stuff
starts getting so complicated,
that your cycle time goes out the window.
You can do it.
In the extreme, we could say, all right,
what ii don't care.
My cache is small enough that multiplexer isn't gonna be too unreasonable.
Why not have as many ways as I have lines?
In this case,
the whole thing is that the entire address part of your address,
the entire selector part up here, is your tag.
You just don't even have an index, right?
You just search the entire cache simultaneously to find your tag.
And these work, if the cache is small enough,
you can get away with a fully associative cache.
But it starts to wear out pretty fast, right?
You're not gonna have like even a multiple kilobyte cache.
You couldn't have direct or a fully associative.
It just wouldn't be possible to implement hardware.
Let's see.
So let's put them all together and kind of compare and contrast what
would happen here.
So let's say i'm trying to put block number one, I guess,
or two, whatever.
I'm trying to put this block here into a cache.
If it's direct mapped,
i'm putting block number12.
I'm gonna look at what the index here is.
12.
I've got eight blocks in my cache.
I need to split 12 up into eight potential places.
So I do 12 mod eight.
That's mod in binary is the same as just like picking some bits.
Turns out 12 mod eight.
That's three or four s four.
We're gonna find it.
Direct map said associative.
I have fewer slots.
Now.
I I have four sets, right?
Because i'm two ways set associated.
So I have four sets.
Each set has four entries,
4×4.
Or they have two entries.
Each set has two entries.
I have four sets.
You have eight lines total.
In this case, i'm gonna do 12 mod four and pick which set it is in.
In this case, turns out it's in set zero.
Then i'm gonna compare both tags simultaneously and pick whichever one it is.
And then for fully associative,
i'm not even gonna bother looking at the address.
I'm just gonna compare that address against every single line until I find it.
So that was a quick kind of whirlwind review of cash organization.
You can go back and kind of follow that along a little slower.
It's worth keeping in mind.
It's worth remembering.
Caches are really important.
The next question you have with the cache is about what happens to it.
When you miss for direct map cache,
there's really no choice.
Right?
Like if I have to replace a blog,
I only had one option.
So that's the one i'm gonna kick out.
Whoever was in my slot gets kicked out, and I go there.
Your only option for set associative,
we have a choice.
I have multiple ways.
I have multiple sets in my cache,
which if every entry in that set is full, who do I kick out?
I can cook out any of them and still be correct.
Which one do I choose two big strategies here?
Can do it totally randomly?
Not the worst idea.
Or I could do it using the least recently used algorithm.
This ends up being pretty true in practice,
like the thing I used,
the longest to go in the past is the one i'm least likely to use in the future.
So whichever one hasn't been used recently,
that's probably a good choice to kick out.
We can go through some examples here.
I we don't need to look at these numbers too detailed.
You can come back and stare at these, if you'd like.
But the trend here is multiple things.
So you can see that as you increase the associative city,
so when we go this way,
miss rates go down,
as you go this way.
And as you go this way, as the cache gets bigger,
miss rates also go down.
So this is removing conflict misses.
This is removing capacity misses.
Right?
There's a question here about how we keep track of lru the way you keep
track of lru is you assign how like a shift register,
you basically have a few bits.
If I have a two way set associative cache,
I can have1 bit in there.
And every time I read from that line, I set the bit,
and I set the bit,
and I clear the other bit.
If I read from set zero,
then I said it's recently used bit to one.
And I said way ones that false.
Right?
I can just alternate.
If you have four, you can you do it that way,
but you basically have a counter next to every line,
and you update the counter on every absence.
And that helps you keep track of all of you.
There's other tricks, too.
You can do things that shift registers and whatever you can do
approximate lru if it's cheaper,
that when you don't have too many sets,
it's pretty easy just to have a couple counters that you update on every access.
What happens on a right?
This is another aspect of cache design,
another design choice we have.
We have what happens when I need to write data the cache.
So reading data from the cache is no big deal.
That's what we've been talking about pretty much this whole time.
But what happens when we want to modify that data?
One strategy is called right through.
So in a write through crap cash,
every time I write to my cash,
I also write to the higher levels, too.
So I write to the next tier of the cache at the same time.
The reason this works is that I I can return as soon as the data is sort
of being written.
I can stick it in a queue and just have faith that it will get written.
Eventually.
When we're doing right through,
we're not limited by the latency of the cache.
We're only limited by the bandwidth cache.
It turns out bandwidth is a lot easier to achieve than latency.
But it still has a problem.
It's still using a ton of bandwidth to do that.
We're writing a ton of data and keep in mind.
Locality is a thing that's the whole reason caches work.
If we wrote to an address once,
we're probably gonna write to it again soon.
Why should we be wasting all of this bandwidth?
Writing over and over and over?
If we're just like it, a rating on the line?
The way to avoid that is called right back.
And a right back cache,
what we do is we only bother storing the cache line that we've written to.
We only bother writing it back to the higher level layers in our hierarchy.
If it gets evicted,
when we come in with a new line and we said we have to kick this block
out this cache line out,
but we've modified it.
Great.
Now we have to write it back as we evicted.
So that's called right back.
The way you do that is the same trick.
As I was just explaining for lru you just keep an extra bit around.
Right?
You set a bit if you've written to it.
So if that bit is set,
then i've written to it.
I need to write it back.
This is what I just said.
But the bottom line here is that there's issues with right amplification,
that if I with a right through cache,
when I evict a line,
it doesn't cost me anything.
So there's no additional work.
Done it.
That's required in order to evict a line.
You get to just delete it right away.
No thought, just meant it's gone.
Because I already wrote it higher up.
So I can just delete it whenever I want,
and it won't break anything.
But with a right back cache,
it's more complicated.
Right?
If I need to evict a line,
now i've got to figure out it was dirty.
Let's figure out where to store it.
Now.
It messes things up a little bit.
But the real problem, though,
is that with the right through cache,
you could get hung up on bandwidth.
So I could spend way too much time doing rights that didn't even have to happen.
And maybe that interferes with my ability to read or write data that
actually needed to be written.
So pros and cons, I think, right?
Backs are more common,
but depending on the organization of your cash and the relative speeds of things,
right?
Through my be a reasonable choice.
Okay?
A lot of stuff here, man,
a lot of stuff caches are a really rich thing.
There's a a lot of different strategies around caches,
coming back to the theme of this whole lecture,
which is virtual memory.
We have to ask the question,
what are the addresses that we're using to look stuff up in the cache?
Are we looking things up with physical addresses?
Or are we looking things up with virtual addresses?
With a physical cache?
The way you would have to implement that is you'd have to figure out what
the physical address is.
First,
once you've figured out the physical address,
then you can ask the cash to go ahead and look it up.
That would be a physically index cache.
With a virtually indexed cache.
I could access the cache directly.
I would only need to access the tob if i'm going higher up in the memory.
Right?
I could have a cache that only keeps track of virtual addresses,
and that saves me having to go through the interview every time i'd be
able to just read and write from it directly.
So that's pretty slick.
That seems really nice.
But it has problems, right?
It adds a lot of challenges.
One is remember this whole right through right back thing.
If I wanna write to this,
so if this cache needs to write to memory,
it then has to go through this mmu through this tlb and that can be kind
of messy.
The bigger problem here, though,
a much bigger issue is that this cache,
because it's during virtual addresses,
the cache is only valid for one process.
If I switch processes,
the cache is like totally wrong now,
right?
Because it was keeping track of virtual address.
That's a real problem with virtually address caches.
There's tricks you can do.
You can store which process that particular cache line corresponded to.
There's a lot of different things you can do.
None of them are pretty right.
They're all kind of messy,
and they all have their own caveats and problems.
It's very tricky to pull this off,
but it does make sense if you're willing to write all the complex circuitry,
if you're willing to make those tradeoffs.
If your workload supports it,
maybe a virtually index cache makes sense.
I think physically indexed is more common.
Ii wish I could tell you off the top of my head,
what risk five does,
what i'm not risk five,
what the rocket core implementation of risk five does.
I believe that their l one is some sort of goofy hybrid
where the mmu and tlb are super tightly integrated into the cache.
So it's somewhat virtually indexed,
but I i'm not 100% sure how that work.
Okay.
But for the most part,
we're gonna talk about physically indexed,
because that's definitely the most common design.
So all of this talk about caches,
all of this that we just spent a bunch of time talking about was in service
of tl bs.
This lecture, still,
in theory is about virtual addresses.
Let's get back to why we brought this up in the first place.
And that is tail beats.
Again, remember, tob is a cache.
It's just a cache of translations.
It's just a cache that keeps track of those virtual to physical mapping.
What are the properties we want out of atlb the first one
and really important one here is speed.
Tob needs to be accessed on every single instruction
and sometimes multiple times per instruction.
It's very important that the tlbc fast.
So that means maybe we want to keep it direct mapped or loss
of suitability or something like that.
But we'll see why that maybe isn't the greatest idea.
The other issue is that we want to keep conflicts down.
I we always do.
But the problem is that like missing in atob is pretty painful, right?
Walking those page tables is really slow.
So the miss time here is not pretty.
And the hit time is dictated by the clock cycle.
So again, we needed to be really fast in the common case,
but we wanted to not miss very often.
The trade off between those two properties is
what hardware designers and architects spend a lot of their time doing is
deciding how to trade off these goals.
Oops, right.
I don't know what i'm doing here,
whatever moving on.
The question is, how big do we make it?
In what organization do we use?
In practice, people usually make tl bs fast by keeping them small.
That's the trick that hardware designers tend to use when they try and make
atlb fast.
Because it's small.
They get to be highly associative.
And because they're highly associative,
their miss rate is pretty low.
This is just a trade off, right?
You can make a lot of different decisions,
but the hardware designers who have done all the math,
they've done all the profiling,
all the experiments,
they decided that what this is probably the best way to make the teal be work,
the way we want it to.
Right?
Again,
because it's a cache, we can do all the same tricks with caches.
Right?
We can have a multilevel tob why not right?
We have multi level caches.
Why not have multi level to be?
It'll still work.
Right?
So we can look at this example.
I think I want to just get through more content.
But ultimately,
atob is gonna store a virtual address,
a physical address, and metadata.
Right?
I guess 1 piece of meta data worth mentioning here,
there's two particularly important ones here that we'll talk about later.
One is asid that is the address space identifier.
We want to be able to support multiple processes.
This asid is what we use to keep track of that.
You can think of this kind of like the kind of like a pointer or the index
of the page table.
So it's like a process id who does this virtual address belong to.
And then the other one that's important here is the valid bit.
So the valid bit tells us whether or not this mapping actually exists.
So we might have a page table entry,
but that page table entry might not point me where real or maybe it's been revoked,
or maybe it's been changed.
A lot of different reasons why it might not be valid, but we have to know.
And that's gonna prevent us from doing the translation if it's not valid.
Just so you understand the to bs are tightly integrated into the core.
They have to be really fast.
They have to be very close to the core.
We have actual different stages,
different designs of the tlb there's parts of it that are spread
around different parts of your core.
So actually implementing tl bs is quite a very interesting digital logic.
Here, architecture question.
There's all sorts of tricks you can do.
Again,
just your computer architects are full of this kind of thing where they
have all these little tricks that make things faster.
For example,
you can imagine that you have a physically addressed cash and atlb maybe we
can play a trick and do something in parallel.
We can maybe overlap.
So i'm gonna show an example here of how that might work.
You might imagine that i've got this address here that i'm trying to translate.
It turns out that the, say,
these top bits here,
these top 20 bits,
that's the virtual page number.
That's the only thing that tob needs to look up.
Right?
The tob doesn't care about this chunk.
It only cares about the virtual patient.
We'll send that to the tob it'll start translating.
And if we have the right size of caches,
if everything lines up,
we might be able to have the index here,
be these lower bits,
and we can send that to the physical cache.
Then now the physical cache tries to find a line.
The tob tries to find the translation.
And then once they've actually done it,
we can trick, we can look at the tag and the physical page number.
And if they match, we have a hit.
So it's a dirty little trick,
and it works if all the numbers line up.
But as soon as the caches don't line up, it stops working.
That's a little tricks.
Highly recommend taking 152.
If you're interested in all of these tricks,
because there's a ton of them,
we only have a minute left.
Let's talk about context switches, and then we'll finish.
So what happens when I change the process?
If I switch processes?
I have to be careful to keep track of which process this tob entry goes to.
Maybe I flush the entire tire tlb if I didn't keep track of address spaces,
we saw in the rs 3,000,
which is just an older processor that they do keep track of addresses a lot
of tricks,
a lot of different ways you could do it.
But you have to pick one.
Either you invalidate the whole tob on each context switch, which is slow,
but simple,
or you create,
you keep a process id in the tob that might slow down the hit time
of the tob but it won't have all these misses when you context switch.
And then this is the last one.
This is what I was talking about.
It's possible for the os to change page tables on you.
Right?
It does it all the time.
If you do,
then you have to go and invalidate the tlb those coherence misses
that the tl bs really have to deal with.
This is a really big design decision in operating systems.
Operating systems spend a lot of mental energy trying to understand this
and make this not happen too often.
Yeah, so i'm gonna end it there,
because we're out of time.
I'll let the next lecture kind of do this.
This is a great slide to start the next lecture on anyways.
You guys will start with this overview,
and then you can get into more interesting stuff around paging.
People asked about what happens when software has to deal with the disk.
All that stuff.
You can look forward to that in the next lecture.
So i'll end it there, I think, right of time.
And i'll stick around for a few minutes if anybody wants to ask questions.
And then i'll end off the recording.
So thanks for
listening.