Hello, everyone.
So today we are going to talk about demand beijing and before starting
thanks a lot,
everyone for filling in the survey about the class great feedback.
And we are going to try to act on it.
Before let me start with the same figure,
which I think you went over last lecture.
But let me do it again,
because it's a very important figure,
because with everything together,
all the memory related concepts,
we have learned so far.
As always, if you have any questions,
please do not hesitate to,
let me know.
So here we have the virtual address on the left.
And you remember the virtual address is what the programs and what
the processor sees.
On the right hand side,
you have the physical,
the memory address.
What we learn, we learn,
we learn about the address translation in which these virtual addresses
are translated to physical addresses.
And one way we did that is through page multi level page.
In this example, we are showing two level beijing.
And therefore the virtual address have consist of three fields.
The last one,
the blue is blue in this figure is the offset.
The offset, the beating,
the offset remains unchanged in the physical address.
Then the first field of the visual address,
it's an index to the first level in the first level bay stable.
And at that address, in the first day,
at that location in the first page table,
you find the address of another page table at the second level.
The second field in the address of ritual between index denoted here.
It's an index to the second level page table,
which is referenced from the first label level page label.
At the corresponding location in the second level page table.
You have the physical page number.
And now your concatenate is a physical page number with the offset.
You got the physical others is the physical page number,
as you see here,
the big did.
And the offset represent the offset within that page.
So this is virtual address,
the address translation from virtual addresses to physical addresses using
two level pages.
In addition, what you also learn about is about translation.
Look aside buffers.
Can someone tell me why do we need a translation?
Look aside buffer or tlb for sure?
What problem does it solve?
It's exact.
Thanks, allison and gilbert.
You are correct.
So fundamentally,
as you see,
with the page two level page tables,
you need in order to do the translation,
you need to do multiple memory access is we need to get a location
from the first page,
from the first level page table,
then to access the second level page table,
a bunch, this means a bunch of memory access is,
right.
When you are going to look to a physical,
to try to just look a location in memory,
to fetch an instruction or to access data,
you have to do multiple memory axis, which is very slow.
So translation look aside buffer, solve this problem.
So it's a small table,
which takes a virtual address that takes the first two fields
in the virtual address,
which contains a page information and maps that to the physical page number.
And this is happening.
It's in harder.
So the translation is very quick.
This still be in the processor.
Then what is the other way we are going try to improve the performance?
Because even if we make one access to the ramp to the memory,
that the time to make that access a latency is much larger than accessing,
say,
registers or in the processor.
Its order of mind,
you slower to access physical memory.
To solve this problem,
what you learned last lecture, we can.
And also at 61 c earlier on,
it's about you are using cash,
right?
A cash.
So cash, it's a smaller memory.
And because it's smaller,
it can be either closer,
or it can be directly on the chip, on the processor.
Therefore,
the latency to access this cache is much lower than the latency to access
the physical memory.
If the data you are looking for,
it's already in cash,
the access will be much quicker.
And here we show set associative cache.
You remember that the set associative cache,
you have multiple sets of this kind of multiple
sets of of blocks.
And each of them is identified by a tag with any set you
can associate with me,
identify.
One of this is here is represented by a line.
One of these arose.
How do you do that?
So now,
the cash is addressed with a physical address.
So the physical address now is divided into other three fields,
which is very tag index and byte.
And the index.
If you have a memory set associated as set associated cash,
the index points to a particular set of such rows.
And then the tag is going to identify a row in the set.
And finally,
or in a bite,
will specify an index of the byte you are looking for in that row.
We also refer it as a block to these cells.
This is it.
You have address translation to speed up the address translation.
You use atlb which maps in hardware,
the virtual pace number to
the physical pace number.
And then to farther speed up the access to the memory,
we use a cache and to locate the data in the cache,
we use these three fields,
tag index and buy.
Any questions?
Just remember that the tlb you address atlb with a virtual page number,
and you address a cache with a physical address.
So now,
the one question,
if you remember,
is there is a virtual address space can be larger than the physical address.
Also,
you have multiple virtual address spaces which are going to multiplex
the same physical others,
because each process has its own virtual address space.
This means that at a given time,
you may not be able to store all the virtual address,
all the data in the virtual address space,
across all process processes,
in the physical memory.
And if you cannot do that,
some of these pages,
you need to put somewhere else.
Typically, somewhere else is on the disk or ssd now,
the question is about when you need a page,
which is not in the memory, it's on the disk.
How do you go about getting that page in memory?
That's what we are going to learn and focus on is the remaining of this lecture.
And when we are going to access a page,
which is not in physical memory,
what it called, you, it,
then what happens?
You have a page four.
And the way this is indicated,
remember that when you do the batteries translation,
you look in the page table, in the page table,
you find a page table entry corresponding to that page.
So that page table entry has a bit,
which is saying, for instance,
it's invalid bit.
And if that be dissect,
this means that the page is not present in the physical memory.
Okay?
Now a baseball will occur.
And what happens?
So on baseball,
you have to engage the operating system,
and the operating system will make sure to bring the right page
from the disk to memory.
So then you are going to be able to continue the execution of the program
to bring a page from the disk to the physical memory.
You need to find a place to put it.
If you have free space,
you bring it down.
If you don't have free space,
they need to take an existing page and replace it with a new page.
You want to bring in memory.
Now, if that page you want to replace has been written,
has been modified,
then you need to put it on the disk,
save it on the disk.
Before you replace it is on your page.
That's what it is.
We are going to go through this process several times during this lecture,
to make sure that the concepts are clear.
And before going forward,
notice that a it's a fundamental inversion here that you have the hardware.
It causes a page fault in this case,
because the invalid bit or in the page table entry set,
which then this fall is treated in software,
right?
As opposed to interrupts where the interacts are treated in hardware.
And then once you select the handle of the internet, only,
then you go into software.
Again, to put things into perspective.
Right now,
this is you have different levels of memory or storage.
You have our own cheap cash.
Here is a processor.
And in today's processors,
you actually have multiple cash cashes level of cash is even known
as single processor,
because you may have a cache for each core.
And then you may have a unified cache,
which is across all course.
Then you have second level cache.
It's a main memory.
Then is this like secondary storage?
Of course,
you can even have tertiary storage tape or some kind of storage in the cloud.
What is the key here?
You like?
What we are trying to do is catching with everything else.
We're trying to do something very simple.
We want to try to have the cake and eat it too.
So we want to have,
we want to build a system which behaves like it has a storage of the largest
storage device.
It has access to,
but the latency to access that storage.
It's the same as accessing zone, cheap cash.
That's a holy great.
Right?
And again,
at the key here is that at every level,
the key technique is a cash is using cash.
You catch the data from the next level,
and you hope that for the mass,
most of the vast majority of time,
the program will only use the data in that cache.
You don't go to the next level.
And if the program exhibit locality,
therefore,
he spends most of the time in a reasonably small portion of the code
or touching small portion of the data.
You are in luck,
because as long as you put this heavily accessed a region of memory
of a program in the cache,
you are fine.
And the last point to make here,
the way to think about the main memory,
it as a cash for the secondary storage, for the disk.
But it's, again, at each level,
you can think it's a cache for the next level.
But we don't call it cash,
we call it paging.
So here is, again,
another figure showing user baseball to what I described earlier.
In words,
this is using some animation to drive the point how so have say you have
an instruction and you do the instruction fetch,
then you go to the memory management,
you need the memory management,
you need to handle the base table,
tlb and all of these great stuff to do address translation.
Now, you go,
you find the page table entry.
And then from the patient, the entries,
we are going to have the page number and the offset.
The offset keep coming from the virtual address.
The page number comes after translation.
But now let's assume that you do when you execute the next instruction,
you go to the page table,
but the entry doesn't exist or it existed by and it's invalid.
So then you have a page fault.
You go to the operating system to take care of things.
The page table, as i'm sorry,
the operating system on fault,
is going to do what is going basically too loud to locate the page on the disk,
which is required by the program.
Load that page in the physical memory,
and then update the page table entry.
Finally, you restart the program,
and the program will retry the previous instruction,
which calls a page fault.
Now,
the previous instruction is going to have the same look to do the same page
from the same virtual address.
But now,
the page it's already in the memory,
so you are going to access that page and continue execution.
Is that clear?
Any questions?
So now we just said that the main page beijing is like cash,
the memory act as a cash for the persistent storage like these courses or sst
now let's look from the. of your the cashing as from the point of
view of a cash and characterize
demand beijing.
First of all, what is the block size?
What is the cash granada?
The block size?
It's basically, in this case, you,
as a joke.
Now, it's 1 page,
which is, say,
four kilobytes between one kilobytes and 16 kilobytes.
Typically,
what is the organization of the cash?
We learned about direct map cache,
fully associative set associated.
The answer here is that it's fully associated provides you the most
is the most efficient in using the cash.
If you remember,
why Why is a fully associative memory,
the most effective in using the cash storage?
You can place it anywhere.
There are no conflicts,
there are no conflict misses.
Like you remember his direct map cash,
you have conflict misses.
You don't have conflict misses here with the associative cash.
There is a question here.
So the page fault we see in the error message happen on the demand,
beijing does not save the program.
Maybe you can ask again the question.
I am afraid I do not understand whatever we are talking about here.
We are talking about the please ask the question again,
and i'll be happy to answer.
Now, how do you locate the page?
First to check the dlb then you do the page traversal if it's
not in the tlb right?
Is how you locate the page.
What is the page replacement policy?
As you'll see,
it's we want allah you,
at least recently used,
as there are others.
We are going to look at other replacement policies,
but typically, we try to have an approximation of al rego.
We have to have an approximation of area,
because you just implementing area can be too expensive.
We learn about that.
What happened on a miss?
You saw that.
Right?
When there is a miss,
you are going to find the page on the disk and bring the page in the memory.
What happens on the right?
Remember that the cache is a copy of the data from memory.
If you modify the data in the cache,
you need also to modify as the copy of that data in memory.
And there are two ways to modify it.
One is right through.
This means that as soon as you update the cash,
also you update the main memory.
The second method is right back.
You just update the cash when you really want to replace the data
in the cache with some other data from to bring it in,
then you are going to write the data from the cache to the
memory before replacing it.
In this case, we are talking about memory and the disk.
We are definitely talking about right back.
Why did I arrive back in this case?
Tell me why don't we do right through?
Excellent.
So allison and tyro.
So this is because it's very expensive to read the data from the disk.
It can be order of magnitude more expensive.
Just to give you a sense,
the latency to memory
is maybe between 15 nanoseconds and 100 nanoseconds.
The latency to read and write from a disk can be 1 million seconds.
What is 34, or that are minded?
So it's huge difference.
So that's how you avoid.
You try to minimize the number of times you write data back to the storage
to the risk.
I see, so this is a question.
It seems like when the baseball happens for the first time,
it tries a program again after the man paging instead of killing
the program right away.
But on in zimbabwe often see page fold message,
the painful message you are seeing when you are debugging is different.
That is, for instance,
when you are going to try to access some invalid region in the memory,
like something you didn't allocate,
for instance,
then you have faithful that is like you just have an address which
doesn't belong to and to read or write to another address,
which doesn't belong to the program,
because it's not allocated yet.
So that's different.
The special fault I was talking about is not visible to the program.
This happens under the hood.
And what you said is correct.
That is on this page fault happens.
Yes, you are going to do a trap,
an exception trap to the operating system,
the operating system,
get the page from the disk,
put in the memory.
And then you retry it and you restart the program from the same instruction.
But remember,
we want to provide with the virtual memory,
the illusion of infinite physical memory.
This is one example.
Virtual memory is huge, is for your byte,
you have 32 bits addresses.
But now most of the machines,
even including your phone, has 64 bits.
So it's a huge amount of memory of virtual memory.
There is no way you can have a physical memory,
large enough of all the entire visual memory of an application.
Then you map this kind of pages from the visual memory using the page table
to the physical memory.
Then some of the page are,
which are the not fitting the physical memory are going to be on the disk.
Why is that?
Because the disk is much higher,
even sst is much harder than a physical memory.
You have a lot of more space.
It's, again, going to the disk and getting the pace.
So demand beijing happen,
transparent is not visible to the application.
The only way the application may notice is that it's a little bit slower,
because you need, instead of getting the data directly from memory,
you have to go first the disk,
move the data into memory, and then get the data.
This is a page table entry.
If you remember, from two lectures ago,
you have the page frame number,
the first 32 beats addresses address,
the first page, the page frame number.
This represent the surface20 bits.
The last 12, 20 bits,
12 bits are some a bunch of bits of
each bit has a different semantics.
And for the purpose of this lecture,
we care about 2 bits.
One is p which is called present or valid.
This basically says that the corresponding page is in memory.
If p is zero, the bit is zero,
then the page is not in memory somewhere on the disk.
And d is a dirty bit.
And this says, as a patient has been modified recently,
this has been modified since it was brought in memory.
For instance, for example,
this means that why do you think,
how do you think you are going to use a dirty bit?
Why do we need it?
It's exactly is to determine it's if you need to write the page back,
if we have to replace that page,
because we no longer have room in the physical memory to bring a new page,
then if the page we want to replace has been modified,
we need first to write to the disk,
not with the information.
That's great.
This is a demand.
Paging mechanism is very simple.
Again, it's like repeating it.
You look at the pde baseball entry of the page.
If the bit of the pd is valid than the means that the page in memories,
you go and access the data from the memory.
If it's not valid,
then this means that the page is not in memory.
It's on the disk.
And when you do that,
you these results in a trap,
it's a page fault.
And 1 page fault,
you choose an old page to replace.
If you don't have enough room in the memory.
If that old page has a dirty bit set,
this means that you have to write that page to the disk.
Then once you are done with that,
you also need to add to invalidate the pt entry for the page,
because now you are going to remove from the you are going to remove it
from the memory.
And also you need to invalidate the tlb entry for that page.
Once you are done with it,
you are going to bring the new page from the disk to memory in place
of the old page.
And once you bring the new page,
your update to the pdu of the new page.
And you are ready to go.
And by the way,
when this happens and operating system is doing all this kind of work
to bring the page from the disk to memory,
it's a lot of io and in the meantime,
you try to scandal and run other processes which are not blocked.
So at those origins of the beijing and the origin of the beijing is states
long time ago from 70s and in 70s.
It was a time before everyone has a personal computer and what you have a terminal.
It looks like a computer, but it's just a terminal.
And they are connected to the computers.
You have many people running their programs on the same computer.
And they are using the computer from these terminals.
Now, because you have so many users,
and the physical memory was quite small.
Again, not all the users programs could fit in the memory.
So now you need to do you need the ability to
swap and to put some of these a pages of these pages,
which are not used often,
or they haven't used for a while to put them on the disk.
Right?
This is what happened early on.
That's why you have paid.
This is basically the model you have,
we should we are going to have in mind,
and we are going to continue to discuss the image, pay,
demand, paging for the rest of the lecture.
Now, what happens when the pieces with the personal computers?
Actually, it's personal computers.
Initially.
You don't have visual memory.
You have one program only running a on a machine,
and that program taking the entire physical memory.
However,
as personal computers became more and more sophisticated and you run
multiple programs on the same computer,
now you're still,
you are back in square one,
because like we discussed several times,
the aggregate memory required by all processes,
all the application running at a given time exceeds the physical memory.
Again, what is a solution here?
Individualize them as a memo, the memory.
And you need to keep some of these memory of this application on the disk.
The memory, hopefully, which is not accessed very often,
all these.
And now machines are connected to the cloud,
all of your phones and laptops.
And you have the same situation in the the cloud.
You have very powerful computers,
and they run a lot of applications.
And they also,
obviously with virtual members.
This is, again,
if you look at one machine,
if you do the ps program status,
this is kind of what you get.
And here i'm just showing the memory in this particular case is pretty utilized.
I say that you have 13 gigabytes of memory.
It's used, and only 2.7 is not used.
So it's more than 80% it's used.
And some of them is shared memory.
Remember that different application can share memory.
For instance, if they use the same libraries,
they share the code of those libraries,
because it doesn't make sense to make a copy of the same code for each
of the application.
So there are many uses of ritual memory and demand beijing.
I remember that in the virtual memory or one segment,
you have is a stack.
The stack grows downwards from the high addresses to the lower addresses,
as you allocate and to push more data on the stack,
you may have to extend the stack.
So this is how you are going to do it.
If you are going to want to expand the stack,
then it's, again, what will happen?
You have a page fault.
You are going to go to the operating system,
and the operating system is going to increase the side of the stack,
ok and allocate more memory for the stack.
Another way is process fork.
We discuss about that.
Here.
We are going to re discuss again.
When you do a fork,
you remember that the child process has the same code as the same in science.
And it has the same resources as a parent process.
But because you have the same code,
one simple solution will be your copies,
the entire code,
and the data from the parent process to the child process before you
can start the child process.
The problem is that it will take a lot of time.
So instead, what you do here is that when you create the child process,
you create it immediately and you have it.to all the memory of the parent process.
So they share the same memory.
The only difference is that from the point of view of the child process,
all the memory is marked as read only no rights.
Right?
Now when you read everything is perfect, right?
Because you are going to read the same content,
which is not modified as not modified as from the parrot.
But now,
if the child wants to modify a piece of data,
then because the pages are read only,
then it's going to cause aa trap and exception is going to be intercepted
by the operating system.
And the operating system now is going to copy the page.
Read on the only page is going to create another copy now for the child.
Now is going to give access to write to its own copy of that page to the child.
When you exec,
you only bring in parts of the binary inactive use,
you just brings few pages in the memory or don't bring,
cause I am tired program into memory,
because that can be too big and sample some parts of the program you may know,
but never touch when you are running it.
The similarly with a stack,
you can extend the heap so forth.
This is another example about an animation about what happens
when it's an end to an example and show you what happens.
When you start a new program,
you have a new program.
The program is on the disk.
It's not exact, is an extension.
You have the code,
you have some data, static data,
and then for some other information,
you need to bring that in memory.
You need to bring the code in memory in order to run.
And when you are going to start,
you are going to bring some part of the code in memory.
And then you are going to bring some data in memory.
And then you are going to allocate heap and the stack for that particular program.
This is the view from the virtual address space.
Bus stands for virtual address space of the process which was
instantiate to run the program.
And let's see.
Then you obviously are going to back all these virtual addresses,
everything in the virtual address,
which is used by the program.
You are going to be backed to the disk.
Finally, between the virtual address and the memory, you need to do,
the translation is done with the page table.
Some entry from the page table are going to.2 pages in the physical memory.
And if a base table,
it's invalid,
that doesn't exist in memory,
use a corresponding page table entry is going to point to the location
of that page on the disk.
Fundamentally, what you need to do if that page is on the disk,
is to have a function, something like that.
It's a fine blog which takes an argument,
the process id and the patient number of that.
And and then for that paid number and the process,
you are going to get a disk location of on the disk where you can find
that page.
So this is very similarly the paste table concept,
but it is purely done purely in software.
No, dld no, nothing like that.
Why do you take the pid why do you take the argument?
Is the pid argument here?
Anyone?
Because the virtual address space is per process.
The base tables are per process.
If I give you only the page number is not well defined,
because multiple processes,
I can have a the same page numbers,
right?
Because a patient number represents something in their virtual address space.
And each of them has a different virtual address space.
So that's why you need to give the person the process identifier
to identify the virtual address space.
Where do you store it?
Obviously, you want to study the memory if you,
because if you store it on the disks and you need to bring it from the disk,
is going to be one slower.
That's pretty much it.
Any questions?
By the way, like, in the case of the shared memory,
you also can share the disk between different applications processes.
So, for instance, and I like,
i'll show you next,
the way i'll show you that is like, for instance,
here against his virtual address space for on process.
And you can have another process and another process will have
its own visual address space is owned by page labels.
Here, it's about the stack and the heap and the data of the second process.
And assume that the second process is the first process.
Running the same program are just two instances of the same program.
In this particular case,
as you can see,
the code is shared,
because the code is read.
You remember, it's read only so it doesn't change.
So if you have to programs which uses out of instances,
sorry,
it's you have two instances of the same program
than the virtual address space of the two,
the two instances,
the two processes.
They can share the same code on the disk.
They said, share the same code, obviously,
and you can share also,
we can share the same old code also in the physical memory.
Make sense?
Any questions?
Okay.
Again,
this page table,
the second process,
some of the pages have been memory, some of them,
the one which are not in memories are backed on this.
Now say the process active,
the first process is active.
Then if you are going to have fetched an instruction on access
and physical memory,
then you look in the base table.
If, say the base table entry is invalid,
then you have a page fold as the operating system locates a block
on the disk which contains a page,
and then move it to the memory.
Is another summary step by step of handling a baseball.
Again, you access a memory,
mutual memory, physically,
the and it's step one.
Say, the program, the associated page table entries invalid,
these results in a trap baseball with the operating system,
locate the block where the page is stored on the disk,
bring the page in memory,
in a free frame,
page frame updates,
a page table entries,
and restart the instruction.
A few announcements the hallmark for has been released.
This week.
Please understand the design reviews.
Remember, the design review starts at the hour.
They are not on the berkeley time.
Please.
So you give time to everyone.
They can get the feedback from the ta in mind that you need to participate
during design reviews.
A part of your grade is based on that.
And other than that,
I know that there are now many deadlines.
There are no deadlines for the next 2 weeks,
but the next following weeks of november 1st will be pretty brutal.
So as such,
please make progress on homework for a project to and start studying
about meter to,
which is mostly the materials we are learning.
We have been learned since the first meter.
So meter two will still have some of,
like, maybe 10,
20% from the materials of mid term one.
But this means that 1890% of the materials will be from the lectures
since midterm one.
Now let's switch the gears and answer the following key question.
During a page fault,
you need to bring a page from the disk to the memory.
How do you find room for that page?
If there is no room like we discussed,
we are going to find a page before it's dirty,
save it on the disk and replace it with a new page.
But typically this is quite expensive.
Writing page bring up beijing is very expensive.
What many operating systems do in the background?
They kick off some of the right back,
some of the dirty pages to the disk.
If you need to replace one,
then you don't need to write it back.
This is kind of periodically,
it's a cleaning process to reduce the overhead of the demand paging.
Now, but even if you have this background mechanism,
you still need to answer the following question,
which pages are you going to write to the disk?
For each pages?
You are going to evict to bring a new beijing.
And the way we you think about that by now,
when you talk about scheduling and so forth,
you need to come up with a policy.
When you come up with a policy to dictate which guides which pages
are written back or are evicted from the main moment memory.
There are certain properties you need you think about about utilization.
You want to have high utilization of the memory.
That's because it's a scarce resource.
You may want fairness between different processes or immune to enforce priority.
So that's kind of you keep in mind that we are not going to implement
different policies here.
But this is for you to keep in mind that is a typical questions you
are going to be faced with when you are going to design a base replacement
policy.
So is a key model.
You have in mind when you run a program,
11of these models,
it's about the working set.
So that what is a a working set, roughly speaking,
is the set of addresses whose content,
if you have in the physical memory,
then the programs works well.
There are very few baseballs.
If any,
right?
And this tried to show a depiction of a this is for a program.
On the x axis, you have the time.
And on the y axis, you have the address.
And each rectangle is the height of the rectangle represent.
What addresses are accessed at a given time by the program.
And the length represent for how long you access content from these addresses.
Right?
So this is,
and as you can see here,
this is execution.
The thread.
Stuff is execution of the program.
And at different times,
you have different working sets.
So working set here is that if you,
if you draw a vertical line at a given time,
then everything,
all the blue rectangle it enters this line,
intersects represent the working set,
represent the addresses whose content should be in the physical memory,
so that we do not have page faults.
And the working set.
One property, in general,
is that is much smaller than the entire address space of the program,
and also is changing over time.
Obviously, if you can keep all the working set in memory or in the cache,
then is great.
The heat rate will be one.
If you cannot, then the hit rate will not be on.
And you are going to have also some mistake.
This also shows the cache size,
how much of the program is stored in the cash for this previous example.
And you start with very little,
and you have here a lot of come,
and the hit rate is also very low.
Sorry,
let me back that here.
When the x axis here is a cache size,
you are looking here at caches of different sites.
On the y axis,
you have the hit rate.
If the cache says is infinite,
the heat rate will be one.
So when the cast size,
or in other words,
on the cast size is larger than the working set,
what is the working set is in the cash?
Then the hit ladies.
And then, as if the cast,
I say it's very small,
then the heat rate will be very little,
because probably all the working set will be doesn't fit in the cash.
Right?
Any fetch of an instruction,
every access of the data will result on.
It is going to result in a miss.
Right?
Any questions here?
So if the cash it's a shared between different processes,
like, is a second level cash,
then you need to feed multiple working set in the same cache.
And actually, this figure shows,
when you have multiple working sets in the same cache,
each of these inflection points is when a new working set is
fitting in the cache,
obviously are going to have a very similar behavior for demand painting.
Again, demand painting is as cash.
Now, when we are talking about the working set,
we have this kind of nice model, like I mentioned,
that actually the program is spending most of the time or all the time,
a in a relatively small region of the other space.
And this makes the cash very effective.
However, there are other models for locality like ziff and distribution.
In this case,
you do have this is, for instance,
on this figure, what you see.
Here it's a rank.
This represent, say,
think about each of this is a page.
There are pages are ranking the decreasing order of their popularity
about how often they are accessed.
The popularity of access is on the y axis.
They say that the first page is accessed20% of the time.
You access a memory,
access the first page.
This is what it says.
Right?
Now,
the problem with this distribution and this popularity is shown
by the blue line.
The problem with this one is that with this distribution is
a very challenging distribution,
is that it also has a long tail,
mostly axis.
Most of the axis are on a very few pages.
But there is some a lot a huge amount of pages are accessed infrequent.
And this creates problems,
because no matter,
even if you have a big cash,
we are still going to have misses because of these very rare items.
But what this shows you is that even if you have a small cash,
you get quite a bit of value because a few pages are responsible for most taxes.
The second thing is that if you have a very large cash,
it's a diminishing return.
It may not benefit a lot.
You still have substantial misses.
Questions?
I don't know that video,
but there are many situations in which you are going.
This distribution is very common.
One, it's our web pages.
I'm talking about web pages, right?
When you access the web pages,
they have as if we are distribution.
And is very common,
is a population of cities.
There are a few cities with very large population and a few of them.
But there are many of them with a smaller population.
It's a very common distribution model.
Again, what we care about is estimated access time.
And the estimated access time is a hit rate times hit time.
It's a latency to access the data in memory,
plus miss rate plus the miss time.
And the miss time is the time it takes to bring the data in memory
from the disk if it's not there.
And it's not there, because they missed the heat rate plaza,
miss rate is one.
You can also rewrite the equation by having this penalty,
by denoting, miss time,
my minus hit time.
This is the overhead where to miss.
This is miss penalty.
You can realize the equation at hit time plus miss rate times miss penalty.
Here is a very simple example.
Memory access time is 200 nanoseconds average page for service time.
So bringing the page from the disk into memory.
It's 8 million seconds.
Let's say p is the probability of miss one minus ps and the probability of hit.
This means that we are using the same the second equation.
The access time is made like this time is 200 and seconds
plus p times 8 million nanoseconds.
If just one out of 1,000 pages,
page axis is a fault,
this is 0.1%.
The access time is of over eight micro seconds or 40 times
more than just accessing the memory.
So the slowdown is huge.
If you want to slow to have a slowdown only by ten per or to 10% slow down,
then you can physics in the equation.
And the p is a probability of miss should be lower
than 1 page in 400,000 axis.
That gives you a sense about how important is
a patient replacement policies in minimizing the miss,
right?
And that's how you use.
This is right here.
It's an example of why here was a demand.
Beijing is fully associative,
right?
Because you just want to avoid any misses are at any cost.
Or it's a question here.
What is the intuition behind why the hit rate is higher for the lower ranks?
It's all here, right?
Let me see.
Actually, a it's a rank of popularity.
Right?
So actually,
these pages are ordered in the decreasing order of their popularity.
So that I get to go is a popularity.
So there is nothing subtle here.
Okay?
That doesn't mean anything else and being pop a major of popularity.
Okay, again,
see you remember about catching,
what are the type of misses,
compulsory misses,
pages that have never been paid into memory?
This is when you start a program,
you need to read the code, right?
For instance,
capacity misses.
You don't have enough memory.
What do you doing this?
In this case?
Obviously, you can increase a number,
increase the memory size.
Or if you can share the memory between processes and
give each process certain amount of memory.
Or in some cases,
as you'll see,
one solution is to kill one of the processes.
The remaining processes,
they have enough physical memory conflict misses.
You don't have those slides, technically,
because a it's a fully associative cash,
right?
And policy misses,
it's about depends on the replacement policy we are going to use.
Here we just want a better replacement policy to minimize the misses.
Okay?
So pay deployment policies.
It's again,
those you learn a few of them last time.
The same similar are here,
54.
First in, first out,
you throw out the oldest page or a big the oldest page is some degree
of fairness in terms of the access.
But it can be also bad.
Why when it's five or bad is when you have a very popular page which is
access over and over.
Right?
This is also one of the pages which are going to be the oldest in the
could be the oldest on the program started.
It loaded this page,
like, for instance,
the code like for these powerpoint slides,
the code which go is responsible for going from one slide and displaying
the next slide.
This is,
I am a using that code from the beginning of the lecture.
That was one of the first pieces of code which was loaded in memory.
But if I use 54,
that will be also a piece of code should be evicted.
And if you evicted,
it just to be loaded again next time, I went on,
i'm turning to the next slide at random is very simple.
So they are very fast to implement also in hardware.
Typically, you have this is still be when you need to be super fast.
Or the downside is random,
it's not predictable.
It's minimum.
And the minimum.
It's the optimal one.
Right?
What is the optimal replacement policy?
You should know that from cash,
what is the optimal replacement policy?
You want to replace the page,
which won't be used for the longest time.
It's as simple as that.
The problem with this is that you need to predict the future and you don't know.
And the way around it is to use the past as a good predictor of the future.
That is, if a page has not been used for a while,
then the page will not assume that the page will not be, again,
access for a while.
If the page was just used before recently,
it's going to be likely used again in the future.
Any questions here?
This is approximation is the least recently used.
Right?
Just replays a page that hasn't been used for the longest time.
If the programs have every locality,
this is a pretty good policy.
How we implement it.
One,
you can simply implement it.
You can keep a list of pages.
And you a when you access a page,
you put it as a head of you move it to the head of the queue.
And the pages as the last in this,
least, is a page which hasn't been accessed for the longest time.
Okay.
It's a great question.
Is there anything you can do when you are writing code to help decrease
page misses?
This is a great question.
Yes, you can do it.
I'll give you one example,
like, for instance,
and this is used and known by people do high performance computing.
Say, you have a matrix and say,
you want to multiply the matrix or do some operation on the matrix.
You can iterate on browse,
or you to iterate on columns.
Now is very important about how this matrix is stored in memory.
Typically start row by row.
You start first row,
then the next row and the next row.
If the matrix is large,
right?
If I want to greet, say,
to all the elements of the matrix,
if I can, i'm going to italy by row is going to have a good cash locality.
Because I start to with the first row matrix,
i'm already going to start to bring.
The first page contains a lot of elements from the first row.
So they are going to be all already in the cache when I am going to access them.
Now say, I am going to write the same program,
but i'm going to access columns.
I am going to access the first element.
I'm going to bring a page.
Now, the next element i'm going to access is going to be from the next row,
not in the same row.
The next row that can result in another miss.
And I need to bring another page just to access only one element
from that page and so forth.
By the time I go back to access the second element from the first row,
that page may be already gone,
right?
Because may not all the pages may fit in cash.
So that's what you can do.
Like that's an example you want.
Or the dldr here,
you want to write your program to preserve locality,
another things which kind of destroy locality.
If you have goals, if you write a program,
he jumps around to go to.
That destroys a code locality.
I know that a large number of random access is on the hip is
generally bad for cash hit rates.
That's the same generally applies to minimize page misses.
I again,
it's like random.
It's not going, you will use random because it's fast.
But in this particular case,
because it's so costly to the baseball is so costly,
you really want to avoid random.
We still plb use random because you want to be extremely fast, right?
That happens actually in hardware.
Hopefully, I I answered this question if I didn't answer,
ask it again.
And maybe rephrase, what do you think?
I I I may have missed from your question.
Wouldn't this mean?
We have to take a software fault on every axis?
This, I think,
is refers to the examples I gave you about matrices going by columns.
In the worst case,
this means that you can take us a baseball on every access to a record.
No, is allah.
You're not.
It's again, it's like,
if you have something which is used very often,
then every time when you access it,
you are going to, again,
when you put here in this example.
Sorry.
When you put here in this example,
is, again, if I access space seven,
I am going to put it as ahead of the queue or the head of the list.
Accessing page on.
I'm going to put it ahead of the list, assessing page two.
Now the pastry is going to head off the list.
If I access something very often,
then they are going to be close to the head of the list.
So they are not going to be removed.
They are not going to be available.
Question,
does that mean that we have to work all pts and scan the valley beats?
Every so often begins the list?
That's a great.
Access fits, use, beats, they use, beats.
You refer, you are referring to the use beats.
That's a good point.
You could do that.
As we are going to see.
Next,
this is a precise implementation of the list,
at least recently used,
but it's expensive to implement what we are going to implement.
It's an approximation of allergy,
right?
That's what you are going to implement.
But before it goes there,
and we are going to show how we are going to implement an approximation of allergy.
Again,
we want to implement and as approximation ideal because we
don't want to manipulate point that is to do many memory access is
whenever we access a page before that,
let's look at a few other replacement policies.
This is 54.
And here we have a cash,
or which has three slots,
or you have three frames.
And this is your order in which we access the sequence.
We access these pages.
As the pages are denoted abc ds,
there are 4 pages.
I'm going to first access a's and b's,
and c and so forth.
Let's access a initially,
the cache or memory is empty.
We are going to save use the first page frame
to start a then b still have you available slot available frames?
I'm going to use the second one and to use and then use the server.
Now, things become interesting here.
Now I am going to come to access a again and a it's already in,
so it's fine.
I'm happy.
I'm not going to do anything.
I'm going to access it.
It's already in memory.
B is the same.
But now is b d is not in the memory.
What do I need to do?
And the memory is full.
So I need to make room for it.
Each page i'm going to evict here is in first out.
So i'm going to evict the page,
which was the first,
the first, which was brought in the memory,
right?
Which is a I'm going to replace cpcd now,
after d it's a well,
now a is against this.
The memory is full.
So I need to pick a page to ab and I'm going to pick which on b now,
the next one is the, again,
it's in memory, not only to do anything.
Then b now I don't have b in memory.
I have only ac and d right?
I need to replace one,
which one was the oldest?
We see,
I am.
And then ci am going to replace d with.
And then finally,
BB is already here.
How many page folds I had?
1234.
These are capacities.
And in addition to that,
I have three, other.
Mrs.
And these are what kind of misses are those compulsory misses?
So I have three compulsory misses.
Four capacity misses,
seven faults,
seven misses.
And here just noticed that this was a bad decision to replace a when we
brought the d in,
because the next axis was there.
So let's keep this in mind.
And with that,
i'll stop here.
We are going to continue to discuss about the patriots placement policies
next lecture.
Thank you.