Hello, everyone.
Welcome to today's lecture.
So today we are going to finish our discussion on demand beijing
and on memory in general.
And we are going to start the discussion on io if time permitted as always,
please ask any questions anytime I will try to answer them as quickly as possible.
If you remember the last time,
we ended with showing this five,
for example,
policy for pace replacement.
Why do you need pace replacement?
Why do you need to evict pages out of memory on the discord ssd this is
a question for you.
It's exactly.
So the main reason you need to evict pages from memory on the
disk is because you are going the memory allocated by
processes is going to exceed the physical memory.
The memory allocated by processes is there which we are virtual memory?
Each process is its own virtual memory that locates part
of that virtual memory for its code,
for the stack and for his heap and data.
And then this all these have to be stored in the physical memory when they
are accessed,
because the sum of all this allocation for overall processes on a machine
is going to,
in general,
be higher than the physical memory.
Then sometimes you need to move the day the pages from the physical memory
to the risk.
And because you want to do that,
then the question about which page you are going to decide to evict,
it's an important one,
because evicting different pages,
will I have a significant impact on performance?
So which page of you are going to choose to be is going to have an impact
on performance.
For instance, if you have bigger page,
which you are going to access next,
then he's not going to be a good idea, because remember,
then there is a pretty high overhead in bringing the page
back from the disk to memory.
And on the other hand,
if you remember the optimal replacement policy,
the eviction policy is basically evicting the page,
which will be accessed the farthest in the future.
So, but that's hard to implement.
And we discussed,
as we discussed.
So we are now going through a few simple cash pay replacement policies.
And we started last time with a 501.
The fight for replacement policy is very simple.
You always a be evict the page,
the first one, which was brought to memory,
but I have to brought in memory.
We went through this simple example.
This is just to refresh your memory.
Here we have the physical memory has 3 pages,
3 page frames.
And we are accessing4 pages, so not all of them,
abcd not all of them,
are going to fit in memory at a given time,
because they have four and the memory has only 3 pages.
This is a sequence in which you are accessing these pages.
So you remember, it's abc these are all compulsory misses.
You.
The baby is not in the memories you need to brings a page from the disk to memory.
That's a miss.
Now, after you asked the first three,
now the memory is full.
Now you access a is great.
It's already in the memory.
You don't need to do anything.
Then you access b is the same thing with your memory.
Don't need to do anything.
Now, you are accessing db is not in memory.
What you are going to do,
you are going to have to choose the week to one of the existing pages
to bring b into memory.
And a was the one, in this case,
because it's five for you are going to evict a because a as you can see,
in this figure,
was the first one which was brought in memory,
should be a so now you have bbc in memory.
A comes.
So a is accessed again.
So unfortunately, as you can see,
here was not a great idea in hindsight to evict a because now you
need to bring it back.
But again, according to the fight for policy, now,
you are going to evict be right?
Because from the existing pages in the memory,
b was of one,
which was the oldest is the oldest song.
Then d again, you don't do anything,
because these already in memory,
now becomes you access bb is no longer in memory.
So you need to replace the oldest page which you see and so forth.
Okay?
As we looked at that,
and if you remember again,
from the last time,
we have seven misses or 7 page faults.
Three are compulsory misses,
abc and the danbc are capacity misses.
We had the miss because the memory was not large enough.
Okay.
Now,
let's look about how this optimal policy mean or at least recently mean
will work.
So suppose we have the same reference stream.
Again, the same memory with 3 pages,
abc the same thing happens.
Nothing changes, right?
Until you fill in the memory,
because obviously,
before you fill in the memory,
there is no miss is a story.
There is no ambition.
A again, nothing happened,
b nothing happened.
So now,
tell me without looking to the slides,
please tell me now I have b now I am going to access after b i'm going
to access d which page i'm going to replace and why?
So I want to access to replace a page which will be
accessed far as us in the future.
I'm here md so after that,
i'm going to access adbcb
the answer c because abbc
okay?
That's correct.
So after I am going to access b I am going after that,
i'm going to access a then b and b and c so c is the one which is
farthest in the future.
I'm going to replace d now next,
I am going to access a nothing happens.
Now I am going to access d again,
and now i'm going to access b nothing happens.
Now I am going to access cc is no longer in memory.
I have only ab and d which which I am going to replace which page
i'm going to replace.
Now.
I'm here b then following on rc and b a okay.
Do you see another page I could replace?
You can replace a is fine.
What I if I would have replaced d yes,
b is also an option.
Okay?
Because if I replace these the following two axis,
rc and b again,
I have no miss,
no pace fault.
Now, you can see that instead of seven,
now you have only 5 page faults.
Right?
Remember, abc were compulsory.
You are going to have them anyway.
So from capacity misses,
before we have four, now we have two.
It's quite an improvement.
Now, we said that with minimum, with mean,
while it's optimal,
it's very hard to implement, right?
Because it's assumed that the future,
but you don't know the future.
And what people do,
it's approximated.
And the one way to approximate it is using least recently used.
So they assume,
basically is that the axis are local also in time or in any space.
And basically, they say the assumption is that if I am going,
if I access a page recently,
I am also going to access it soon.
If I haven't accessed the page for a long time,
I am no longer to access that page for a long time in the future.
By this one, this means that I am going through big pages,
which I haven't accessed for a long time.
That's what it is.
So let's see what happens here.
Again,
let's now see.
This is a stream.
Let's see,
abc the same b now,
d which one i'm going to replace?
I have to replace,
remember the pages,
which was which has not been accessed in the past for a long time,
for the longest time.
Which one i'm going to replace here?
A
got it,
right?
Because a was has been not accessed for whatever two time units
for 3 time units events.
How to come?
I replace a so now I have dbc now, a comes.
Which one i'm going to replace?
B right?
Very good.
Somali a and now it's come c no, sorry,
it's can be beats again.
Is I need to replace,
i'm going to replace c because he wasn't access for a long time
for the longest time.
Now I have c i'm going to replace c i'm going to replace d and so forth.
Now,
the things about about this scenario,
it is that I love you for this particular input doesn't behave very well.
Right?
And it's, again,
the reason it doesn't behave very well.
It is because you don't know the future.
This means that the assumption behind are you is broken.
Right?
Again,
remember that the assumption is that the paintings which
haven't been accessed for a long time,
they are not going to be accessed in the future.
But this is exactly wrong,
right?
Because after the here,
i'm accessing a which hasn't been accessed for a long time in the future,
I longest time in the past,
and so forth.
Now, the one thing I should have said in the previous slide,
if you look in the previous slide,
let's look in the previous slide and do the same thing.
First we tried mean.
Now let's try to think about how will allah you work?
So let's see how allah you work for this, the same strip.
So now think is allah you this recently used.
So now I ai am accessing a right?
Now I have bi am accessing b and now I I am having b according to our real policy.
When I get d which page I am going to replace?
Correct?
I'm going,
i'm going to replace, actually,
allison is correct.
I'm going to replace c and brian and eric and others.
The reason I am not going to replace a a was accessed right here.
Do you see my cursor?
Do you see my pointer?
Great.
You see a was axis here,
and b was axis here,
which means that when b comes,
c is a page which was not accessed for a long, longest time.
So the difference is at risk fivefold.
The time which matters is when the page was brought into memory.
With other you,
the time which matters is when the page was accessed,
there's a difference.
So I have to replace this here.
Now a i'm going to access a i'm bn and now d i'm going to access d
now i'm going to b
i'm going to bring bb is already in memory,
and now i'm going to get c c is no longer in memory,
but let's say when I get c which page i'm going to replace,
again,
it has to be the page which has not been accessed for the longest time
in the past.
Right?
Bo is access here,
dos axis here,
aos axis here,
which one i'm going to replace?
Aok
now be,
it's already memory.
In this particular case,
the point here is that min and allah,
you behave the same.
But this is not necessary.
Like we've seen in the preview in the next example.
Actually, I love you can perform quite badly.
Right?
If the assumption is violated,
obviously, meaning this case that's much better.
When I am going to access the i'm here,
i'm accessing d which is a long as a page,
which is not access for the longest time in the future.
Is c right?
I am going to replace c now i'm going to get a and b i'm going to abr
already in memory.
Now, cc is no longer in memory,
c but i'm looking at c when it's accessed by looking in the future,
I can look in the future.
Then axis dab and c again.
The longest the one which will not be accessed for the longest time
in the future is b i'm going to replace b and then so forth.
In this particular case,
I is going to have six false or
missus while allah leo is going to have12.
Good.
But still no matter like you're seeing the rest of this lecture.
Still,
you is considered a very good already sticks,
because many programs are exhibit locality in their memory access.
Okay?
As you'll see is a problem it will be then to approximate allergy.
Because allergy itself is it's expensive to implement.
But before going that let's look about a little bit more that take a step
back and look about
what is if the number of page faults Versus the number of frames?
This is our memory size on the x axis.
We have the memory size in terms of the number of frames.
On the y axis,
you have the number of page faults.
As you'd expect.
As the number of frames increases,
you'd expect the number of which falls to decrease.
Does it make sense?
More memory, fewer pitch faults.
However,
it turns out there are anomalies to this.
There are certain page replacement algorithms.
We do not have these properties,
which means that I increase a memory.
And for the same workload,
the number of page falls increases,
very counter intuitive.
You have more resources, you perform worse.
Right?
And here is an example.
Okay?
By the way, this is not for ok all page replacement policies.
It's only specific ones like five.
Like, for instance, it turns out that for our alert real and mean,
this is not the case for other you and me,
whenever I increase the memory size,
the number of baseballs is not going to increase,
either stay the same or is going to decrease.
But now this example,
an example in which using 54 will result in more baseball.
So I increase the basis.
Here you have abcdi have now 5 pages.
I'm asking 5 pages.
The memory has still three frames,
123.
This is for this particular access patterns.
This is what the page falls of.
The page falls I have.
Now, there are 9 page faults,
but now assume that I am going to increase the number of pages
or the number of frames in the memory from 3 to 4.
And as it turns out,
again, with 5454 is very simple to look, right?
Because you always,
when you have a baseball during place,
the one which was brought first,
and on this graphic is very simple to see the one which was brought first.
You just look on each line,
which is the first in memory.
Right?
Okay.
You replay and you can convince yourself and you get e here.
You are going to replace a a you are going to replace b and so forth.
And by doing,
if I have now instead of 34 frames,
then I get 10 page faults.
The number, the memory size increases from three frames to four frames.
And the number of phase faults increases from 9 to 10.
Any questions?
It's a cool example, right?
It's like, you don't expect that.
Now is a reason for other you or mean the reason this doesn't happen
for larry and meaning because they have these
properties that if say,
I have a as a memory size,
it's x frames.
If I increase the number of frames by, say, one,
then the subs,
the i'm guaranteed that the pages I have in memory,
when the memory side goes x it's a subset of the pages i'm going to have
in memory.
When the memory is x plus one,
because you have the subset property,
then the number of baseballs cannot increase.
So that's the reason.
Now, as I mentioned, if you remember,
you mentioned that in the last lecture that alu is not easy to implement,
because alu requires that you one way to implement,
at least recently used to have a least.
Whenever you access page in this list,
you take that page,
and you bring it at the head of the list.
Then when you have to replace a page,
you take the page from the end of the list.
And that's the one you replace.
But just on every access,
manipulating the list and taking the page you accessed to bring us
ahead of the list,
is very expensive, multiple memory access.
So you do not want to do that.
Next,
we are going to talk about some approximation of least recently used one
of such approximation.
The first one we are going to start with is a clock album.
Okay?
We'll have some examples.
So this is imagine that the all pages are arranged in a a in a ink.
And you have a clock like a hand,
a clock as a clock hand,
which advanced one by 1.
And you look at every page.
So, and when you need to evict a page,
this clock hand will move to the next page.
You check for babies which are not used recently.
And then you also mark the pages which are used recently.
And with all this approximation,
the way you approximate,
you still replace an old page,
but not the oldest page.
Okay, here, how things are working?
So remember that you have a use bit,
right?
Or access bit,
you speed in the pdpd is a page table entry for each page, right?
If you remember.
And that beat,
whenever you ask as a page, is set to zero.
Right?
Sorry.
Whenever you ask what if it's whenever you access a page,
you said with one.
So if I see a one, this means that the page was used.
Now this clock is looking at the page.
And if he sees 11 it's reseting,
it and or to zero.
If he sees a zero,
then he's replacing that page.
Because this means that the page hasn't been up access in a while.
If it's a one,
this means that it was access recently.
So you give a chance second chance to that page.
Let's see how it's worked.
Here.
I'm showing an example.
And I have with
with these all district angles,
obviously, there are pages or sorry, or frames.
The one with the dash rectangles represent free frames.
There is nothing there.
And then for these pages,
for a few pages, I also put the value of the use.
You have 1101.
This is now I want to bring a page from the disk.
So I want to find the page i'm going to replace.
Okay?
When i'm going to go through this,
the hand is going to move.
Now remember this first page,
the usb+1.
Okay?
I'm going to reset it to set it to zero because use one mean,
it won't be meant that it was access recent.
Then i'm going to the next page.
And again,
a it was said, as a you speak to us, one, i'm reseting.
I'm setting it to zero.
And finally,
now this next page,
the use bit was zero,
because the u speed is zero.
This mean, this means that the page hasn't been accessed in a while,
at least is it wasn't accept since the last time the hand visited that page.
So we are going to replace this page.
If is a page was written,
since was brought, was modified,
you save it on the disk first,
then you allow the page and update the pt by the way,
when you evict the page,
you also invalidate the pity of that page and invalidate the tlb entry
of that page.
And now I just loaded,
i'm going to access it,
so you speed its one.
And now assume that, in the meantime, for instance,
when I access another this page here,
which has a bit set u which had the us be set to zero.
By this, when the hand visited the last time,
I am going to set up the usb to one again,
because it is accessed.
Now, finally say that we have another page fold.
And I am going to go to the next page.
It has used by uusb towards one.
Now i'm going to set up to zero.
Then i'm going to go to the next page.
And that frame, it's actually a frame.
It's an empty frame.
I'm just going to load the page,
and i'm going to set up to one.
I'm going to initialize it pt and so forth,
typically.
And this is a little generalized here, a little bit.
You only the free frames are in a different list.
Okay?
I put it here to have a global example,
but typically, frames are in,
three frames are in different list,
just for you to keep in mind.
So i'm stopping here.
And any questions
whenever a page is accessed,
the usb is at one.
Whenever a hand visit a page,
because there was a page fault.
If they use beatles one,
you set it to zero.
If they use beat is zero.
You have bigger page and brings a new beijing.
Let me ask you this question.
Say the hand is moving very fast.
What does it mean?
Is that good?
Is it bad?
Yes, gilbert and alexander,
it's bad because this means there are a lot of page faults.
Right?
If it's moving slowly,
there are very few base faults.
Good.
The other thing is not is that if all the bits are set to one,
that's still okay, because the handle move,
while moving is going to set up each use bit of each page to zero.
When it comes back,
after one, rotation,
is going to find a page with aubu bit of zero.
That was a page who is hand set the b to zero first time.
Alison, it's a question here, actually,
about the hand,
whether it's moving back fast, it's bad.
Is she says that might just mean that we have all our page pages being used.
And so that hand has to step over a lot of in your spaces.
This can happen,
but then it will still be,
again, there are two reasons.
The hand is going to move fast.
One absolutely is because of beige faults.
If there are no base faults,
the hand will not move.
Pity it.
Right?
As a reason,
it's obviously because you need to step over a lot of pages which are used
like there is bd set.
And that can be the case,
but it's also unlikely,
because if you assume that will happen only if all the pages
are very uniformly accessed,
which is not the case.
Right?
You have to have all the pages being uniform access,
right?
At least since the last time,
the hand visited them in order to be a one.
And if you have locality that it's unlikely to happen.
But it's a good question,
a good..
So I discussed what if hand was moving slowly,
good sign or bad sign.
This is not many pages false,
or fine page quickly.
What if hand is moving quickly?
Lots of page faults or lots of reference with that, right?
We discuss both of them,
but this is what it is, right?
It's like you have a lot of reference besides only if you have.
It's pretty uniform memory access.
One way to view the clock algorithms is that you group the pages into 2 groups,
one with your access recently or one or access longer time in the past.
Obviously,
you are going to pick one from the ones which are accessed longer in the past.
So an obvious question,
because you think about these 2 groups,
you have these 2 groups is why not actually partition it.
And instead of having this kind of clock algorithms,
just have two groups.
We are going to talk about that.
But before that,
let's look a lot about a version of the coke algorithms.
We generalize it, clock algorithms,
and its ends chance version, right?
With any chance think about right now,
you are going to evict a page,
right?
You give only so to speak one chance,
because you set the beat once the
hand sets the use bit of a page to zero is going to evicted the next time
unless the pages and access in the meantime.
So another way is to have more than 1 bit.
And this is about ends chance algorithms.
So now the os keeps a counter per page,
which is a number of sweeps,
a number of times it was visited.
While the page was not accessed on page four,
the os check the you speed.
And if it's one,
you clear it,
right?
Like before, is zero.
You also initialize you clear what it is sweep counter.
If it's zero, you just increment the counter.
And only if the counter is equal is n you replace the page.
This means that the page has any chances.
So it can be visited by the hand and times before being evicted.
Here i'm talking about the page which is not accessed
while these end sweeps happen.
So obviously, one question is, how do you pick up?
What happens n if n is very large?
You can actually better approximate alert.
You say n is 1,000.
That is really good approximation.
What is the problem we speak in?
Gallar?
Gens?
Why wouldn't you pick a larger?
Is less efficient.
Danny, why is less efficient?
Sweeping will take up lot of rotation, right?
Because think about you need to go,
you need to visit a page and times and sweeps before you can evict it.
So it's a lot of pages.
Then this will take a long time.
It's exactly.
So it's not efficient.
Takes a long time to find free pages.
What about modified or dirty pages?
Obviously, it takes extra overhead,
like we saw in the previous example to replace the dirty page, right?
A dirty page,
meaning that was modified since what or since when it was brought in memory,
right?
Because they need to write it to the disk.
So these algorithms has something some improvement here.
And basically,
before a page,
counter guessed to the end,
you or write it back to the disk.
So if you are going next time to decide to replace that page,
it was already written to the risk.
So for instance,
one approach is for the clean pages to use.
And it's always one,
which is basically the original clock algorithm.
But for the dirty pages,
use any college to for any core is one.
You write it back.
If you look at these algorithms now.
Right?
If it's a page,
it's clean,
it has not modified.
If the counter is one, you replace it.
If it's a dirty page,
then when the counter which is one, you don't replace it.
You just write it back to the disk.
And when the counter is still, you replace it.
This means that hopeful is the next time.
When you come by the time you decide for this,
you either are going to find a page which is clean.
So you don't need to write the disk,
so you pick that to replace it.
Or in the worst case, you come back to the page,
you decided to write back.
But this, by that time,
hopefully it's clean.
So then the overhead is going to be low.
Any questions?
Okay.
Let's this, again,
the pd this is out of the
page stably,
the page table entry.
Again, these are the beats,
which are in the pd so we have aa bit which is present or valid.
This means, if you remember,
whether specify whether there is a page,
it's in the memory or not,
if p zero,
then it's in valley,
it's a page for the they should be on the disk.
It's a writable,
its access control.
This is about whether the page is.
You can write to the page or not.
Like, for instance,
if the pages which contain the code,
they are not writable,
right?
Because the code is immutable or it should be immutable,
then it's access bit or use bit.
We talk quite a bit about it.
This was what is using the clock algorithm.
It's a dirty bit, right?
Modified, which is used,
sorry, by any page replacement algorithms.
Because if the page is dirty, was modified,
you need to write it back to the disk.
So this is what kind of you have.
And here,
so again, for just to summarize for the clock algorithms,
like the way as we discuss so far,
we use bit and the dirty bit.
But this being said, is it the same thing?
P and w are almost always used.
They are going to be used by the operating system.
Obviously,
now here these are some interesting questions.
Again, b and w they are a must in general, right?
Because its protection,
w is protection and p you need to know whether the pages in memory or not.
You cannot go around those.
Now, the question is about these other bits,
right?
And the question is that are they really necessary to implement,
for instance, a clock algorithm?
And yes, that's great.
Harrison.
You can use a valley bit and always set it to invalid to force a fault
on each axis.
Is super slow, though.
That's correct.
So the trick here is that if you do not have these bits in the hardware is
these registers.
What you can do,
you can maintain this bit in software.
Now you need to find a way to modify to look at the speeds and modify them.
And allison is correct about how you can do it.
Here how you can do it in more details.
You can do it.
Also for now, let's assume we can do it using the beat only bit.
So basically, when you we are talking about the modify bit,
so basically,
what you have here is that when you read a page,
you market read only no matter whether is that they contain data or code.
And then when all of them are italy,
and then when you are going to access it,
and you want to write it,
then you are going to have a an exception,
right?
Because you want to write a page which is read only.
It's a trap in the operating system.
And in the operating system,
in the software, you maintain this modified bit.
First time when you bring the page in,
you make and you make it read only.
You set this modified bit to zero.
When you write it,
you get an exception like we discussed,
traps operating system.
The operating system is going to measure to make the page read, right?
And set the modified bit wrong.
Right?
Again, modified building software.
Whenever the page is written back to the disk,
right?
You reset the modified bit to zero,
because now is a but you have in memory is exactly what you have on the disk.
And your mark, again, redundant.
So that's pretty cool.
Now,
it turns out that actually,
you don't even need the use bit,
right?
Like, again, in this case,
if you have the use between the pte you have to keep it in software.
So the canon is to keep it the way you do it.
Now, you can mark all pages as invalid,
even if that in memory.
And then you set the use beat and modify beats, which are, again,
in software you set up to zero.
You bring a page in.
And even if,
again, I was a biggest memory,
you still keep the invalid bit being set for that page.
However, in the software,
you keep in mind that you brought in the page,
you set up the beast for years and modified to zero for that page.
Now, any read or write to this invalid page will drop to operating system.
Okay?
Now is the operating system.
Then it's going to set the use bit one,
because you access it.
Right?
And if it's a read,
you are going to only if it's a read,
you are going to set the page to read only like before to catch the future rights.
If right,
you also set the modified bit to work,
and you mark the page are writable when the clock hand passes and they
would be to zero.
You can, again,
mark the page,
you when the clock hand passes,
you reset the b to zero,
use b to zero,
and mark the page again as being invalid.
Sorry.
The modified bit is not, obviously,
you are not going to right on that bit.
You are not going to modify the modified bit unless the page is written
back on the disk.
Any questions?
So it's very cool.
So basically, the tldr here is that you can get away by not starting the
modified and used by not having the modified and use bits in the
page table entry.
Because you don't have that.
You need to have them somewhere.
So you are going to keep them in camera.
But now you need to modify a need to look at those speeds.
So you need to go to the kernel to do that.
In order to go to the colonel,
you need to force that trap to the kernel.
The way you do you for that trap using the other bits like invalid bits,
or write, only beat,
or read, write beats,
or writable beats.
In order to force that trap,
you force,
you are going to give the control to the operating system to handle
the modified and use beats.
Make sense?
Okay?
Now let's talk about the second chance list algorithm.
It's a variation.
Another early sport is another approximation of our area.
This was implementing in backs vms you do not know about that.
You haven't seen it.
Probably maybe you're only in the museum.
But this is a very popular computer.
It was called mini computer.
And before the personal computers,
it was in 70s,
80s,
but it was vex was a very,
very influential computer.
In this case, you have two lists,
you divided into lists.
And the first list is direct,
mapped pages.
And they are all marked, read, write.
And you keep 54,
y 5454 is very fast,
right?
With 54 is very simple, right?
You're one, and you bring a page in memory,
you put it at the end of the list.
When also you put at the head of the list,
when you remove a page,
you remove from the end of this.
Very simple.
While things in this list are accessed,
you don't know how to don't do anything.
But then you have a second chance list.
And they are marketing valid and this is allergy implements allergy.
This is how you speak the memory have directly my page
and the second chance list page ok so let's see how it works.
So if you access a page in this one of these green pages,
they are also called activists,
right?
Then you access it, no problem.
If you don't access a page,
which is in the active list,
you are going to have a baseball on the page fold.
Always you are moving the page from the end of the activist to front
of the second chance list.
And market is invalid.
Right?
This is five.
And then,
if the pages is a second chance list,
you move that page to the front of the activist,
and you market to rewrite,
because all the pages in the activist.
I read right now,
if the page you are looking for is not in the second chance list,
you page it directly in the active list as the front of the activist,
your market as a read, write,
and your page out and a victim from second chance list.
Allah you using allah you.
So let's take a step back and see what happens here.
What happens here and why we do this.
It's because we I love you.
It's expensive to implement.
And obviously writing back to the disk and reading from the disco page,
it's also expensive.
So,
therefore, what we say, well,
let's take a bunch of pages from memory and organize them in a 554 is
super efficient,
very simple to implement.
But the problem is 54, obviously,
is that I do see and is not pretty good in limiting the number of page faults.
And now the second thing comes,
they say I have page faults with five.
I know that i'm going to have a lot of page faults,
but let's make them cheap.
So the way you make them cheap is that with the second chance with a list,
and because you hope that a lot of times the page you are looking at is
still in memory,
is this in the second chance list?
That's the key.
And for the second chance list,
you can afford to do allow you.
Because anyway, in order to you,
you expect your experience are paid for to get to
get a page from the second chance list.
So increase the number of page faults,
because you have 54,
and you are using only a subset of frames in this active list.
But you reduce the overhead of the page folds,
because many times the page fold will beijing at least aa base,
which is already in the memory?
Make sense?
Now, the interesting things to notice here and like, for instance,
what happens if the second chance,
least is zero?
All the memory frames are allocated to the active page activist.
Then you have five.
There's a recreation policy.
What if activity is zero?
Right?
And you allocates everything to the second chance list,
then you have allergy,
but it's very expensive.
This is what it says.
But because you are going to page fold on every page reference,
you pick an intermediate value, obviously,
in terms of how many frames you are going to have in In the activist.
And this theory,
this will reduce the number of these classes,
because fundamentally,
if you look from the.of view of the entire memory, now,
you use alleria, not an approximation of the real approximation of alleria.
If you are very efficient in terms of the number of disk axis is,
but you are going to increase the number of contact switching.
You are increasing the number of vessels.
Any question?
Again,
with aa base translation will see that you can adapt to any kind of access
to program of
any access patterns of the products.
One interesting tippy here was that when vax was originally designed,
the use bit was not the part of the pd
the story that a striker,
the architect actually went to operating to the software people and ask them,
always people say, no,
we don't need it.
So they didn't implement it.
Of course,
eventually, when they implemented the cash replacement policy,
had they needed it?
They always use it what they did about it, of course,
because it doesn't in the pde they have to keep it in software.
So they need to make sure that we get a trap to the operating system
to the kernel in order to modify the bit,
like you've seen in the previous few slides.
And obviously, he was also not obviously,
but he was also blamed for this omission.
So don't trust the operating always people.
That's kind of the moral of the story here.
The other things which didn't we alluded,
but we haven't discussed so far.
It's, in general, even a with a with the algorithm,
with all these algorithms,
even in the clock algorithms.
In practice, you do have you maintain also free list,
and the free list is a list of frames which are available.
You can allocate, they are not allocated yet.
And so therefore,
if you initially and the way you do that,
you use it again as a sort of cash.
For instance, with the clock algorithm,
when you are going to evict a page,
you are going to fly this,
ride the space to the free list.
Instead of writing it,
it directly to the disk.
And then in the background,
there is a demon,
which is going to look at the free list and to look at the pages which are
dirty in the free list,
and then write these pages to the disk.
The advantage of this is that it's, again,
it's like when I need to replace a page,
even if the page was modified,
I don't need to wait for it to be returned to the disk,
because it's going to be written quickly,
just move in another list in memory.
This is very similar with the wax.
The second chance is to just learn about any questions?
Obviously,
this high level, right?
Is the high level pictures.
There are many details we haven't discussed.
So let's discuss a few of them.
Remember that when you are going to evict the page,
you need to invalidate its p ds.
Because the next time,
when you are going to access that page,
you need to bring this page in memory.
So you need to get the kernel, do that for you.
So it has to be a trap you need.
So then for, therefore,
you need to keep the reverse mapping.
So that when I am going to evict a page,
I need to know with what is,
which is its pd to invalidate.
The same is true also for the tlbok so how do you do that?
And there are many ways to do it.
You can keep a link list of page entries.
Actually,
in some sense,
again, there are many software solutions here.
But in some sense,
the things one gets complicated.
It's when you have shared pages across multiple processes,
right?
Because then remember,
each process has its own virtual address space.
And each process has its own page table.
So there are four,
if a page is shared by two processes,
then,
like we've seen in the last lecture,
you are going to have two entries,
two pt two base tables, entries,
right?
In the base table of the two processes pointing to the same page.
So you need to evaluate.
They took it is when you read that page.
So you need to find both of those.
Right?
Just keeping the simple reverse mapping is not enough, no.
And one way to address this problem is like,
it's you can see on this slide is basically you can have a list,
right?
Of a page table entries for each page.
If there are two or,
say, four processes,
we share the same page.
When the page is for that,
then for that associated with that page,
you have a linguist of the four p ds of these processes works as a page.
You invite you.
Now, you go back to this list and you validate everything,
which is the list.
And there are other solutions here.
Any questions?
Okay?
Now let's with the gears.
And now we are done,
in some sense, with this kind of low level pay replacement policies.
Now,
we are talking about how the memory will be allocated across processes.
But before then,
any questions?
So memory is resource.
It's like very much like the cpo right?
And we are talking about all these policies or scheduling policies,
which page replacement policies,
because the resources are oversubscribed.
If the resource is not a versus oversubscribed,
we don't need to do anything.
We have enough for everyone.
Right?
We've seen all these scheduling algorithms about how to allocate the cpu
to across multiple processes threads,
in a fair manner,
whatever you can imagine.
We have the same problems to solve.
We have the same problems to solve in the case of the memory as well.
Right?
The same questions, right?
If you have multiple processes competing for the physical memory,
how you are going to allocate the memory across processes,
you are going to allocate fairly,
right.
The same number of pages.
Also,
we need to keep in mind that each process needs a minimum number of pages
to work.
We cannot work without having a certain number of pages in memory.
So, like, for instance, is one case.
This is ibm 370, 370,
which for one instruction,
you can need a up to 6 pages to be in memory.
And this was an instruction to move a bunch of bytes from one location to another.
First, the instruction is 6 bytes,
my span 2 pages.
And then you can have
you can have the region spanning the source region from oriental copy,
can span2 pages and the destination where you want to copy that
data also can spend the pages,
so 6 pages in total.
Right?
And the other things is again,
but here is the only the difference.
And you have to appreciate that the difference between the cpu and memory
is that with cpu actually,
it's more fungible that I disappear is more fungible.
It's memorabulous.
In some sense.
It's like, I am going to decide when squad processed the squad to schedule.
I am going to schedule it.
Every time start, i'm going to pick an another process, right?
Every times it's, when I say,
is stateless, is that because every time quanta,
I can pick another process to schedule.
But here,
i'm not going,
i'm going to start.
The decision is not what for which process to bring a page in.
It's only the memory is full with pages from all the processes.
I have to decide which page to evict,
right?
Which it's more difficult.
And eviction policy can be global,
meaning that when I am going to pick up page to evict,
i'm going to look at all across all the process of all the biggest memory.
Or another way to think about it can be lock off.
When i'm going to decide which space to evict,
I am going to look only a more across the pages of the process,
which calls a page one.
I'm going to bring a page from the disk for the new for a process.
And i'm going to evict a page from that's the same process.
Here are a few policies which are kind of obvious equal allocation.
One way to say it is to be super fair.
You just divide static is a memory across processes.
You have five processes,
you have 100 frames,
then each process gets turned different period,
right?
Or you can have a proportional location,
also fixed scheme in which you have a weight.
And you are going to allocate the memory according to that weight.
Now, what is the problem with a fixed allocation?
Can someone tell me what is the problem with these fixed allocations?
These are very good question, very good answers,
michael and allison.
So one problem is that if a process requires more less than its allocation,
then memory is wasted.
The other thing is that what happens when a new process is created?
Okay?
Then you need to redistribute all these pages across the processes.
Then it's a priority allocation.
You can use a priority,
and you can assign priority to each part to each processes.
You can use the same priority which areas for scheduling.
And then when you need to decide which space to evict space to evict,
you are going to evict a page from the process with a lower product,
or you can use any adaptive skills.
Another way to think it is about a frequency allocation.
Basically, here you think about,
I want everyone to kind of get the same performance.
The performance is dictated by the frequency of the page faults,
1 kind of to equalize the page faults that each process experience a frequency.
In this particular case,
you can look at to have some thresholds.
And if a if a process,
the number of frequencies of the page faults is lower than the slower bound,
then you are going to evict pages from this process.
We are going to reduce the number of pages allocated to this process.
If the number of baseballs for the process exceed another threshold,
then you have too many page faults.
You are going to allocate more pages to this process.
So that's what you can go.
And but still,
no matter what you are talking about here,
there can be still cases in which you don't have enough memory.
When you don't have enough memories,
what happens is kind of trash and trashing.
You can actually identify that in a simpler way.
You see a lot of io activity and the cpu very little utilization.
Because trashing meaning that you have a very high number of base falls.
The program,
or the processes spend most of their time page folding than doing useful work.
And in that case,
no one is making progress.
So what is a solution here?
Right?
By the way, how we do take the trashing is very simple, right?
It's like I mentioned to you, right?
It's like you have a lot of io activity,
and the securitization is basically zero, right?
What you can do here,
no one is making progress.
So what you can do, well,
one simple solution you can do is to suspend one process or killer process.
Very good.
We went over this last time.
You remember that we have a similar plot here,
and this represent the access pattern of a program of a process over time.
On the y axis, you have the page number on the x axis.
You have the time.
And you have a dot at every position where you have an access
to a particular page offset at a particular time.
Right?
So that's kind of what you have here.
And it's again, when the program executes at different times,
you are going to access different location in memory.
And the group of pages,
which are accessed together at a given time,
as they are called working sets, right?
The working set defines a minimal number of pages that a process
have to have in memory in order to work well.
So do not spend his time too much time in page folding.
Okay?
Therefore, this means that if you do not have enough space in memory to
accommodate the working sets of all the active processes,
then you have a problem.
The solution like we discuss is to swap out a process.
Now,
how you define the working set when you design a group of pages access
at the same time,
we need to define the same time.
And typically, this is a time interval.
So basically, look at the current time,
and you are looking in the past for some time interval about all the active,
all the pages which are access during that interval.
And this is what you call the working set.
Okay?
Obviously,
about how long is the interval which is also called working set window,
is that it's a good question,
but you need to take a good,
because if it's too long,
then it's encompasses all the pages ever access by the program.
Right?
So that's not good.
If it's too little is going to encompass only the most recent pages.
And you are going to miss made me as of many other pages.
It should be accessed a very in engineer in the near future.
Right?
So you miss the locality.
But anyway, so once you set up this window,
now you can define the working set.
Then the simple thing is that the sum of the working set of all programs,
let's say,
if is defined by d and if d is greater,
then the memory size you have trashing.
If d is less than the memory size, you are fine.
This is the last slide I'm going to make about, like we dis.
We remember that only discussed about this page replacement policies.
And about these examples, always,
we are going to,
we started these compulsory misses,
right?
And obviously,
compulsory misses are unavoidable in some sets.
But the question, can you do it better?
The answer you can do it better.
Like, for instance, for clustering the pages,
when a page fault,
you do not think only 1 page in memory.
You are bringing a set of pages as consecutive pages.
Because if you assume locality,
assume that if you ask,
say, instructions is in the current page,
you are also is likely to access instruction in the next page.
So you are mortar is the cost of of baseballs by bringing more pages in memory.
Right?
And the same things about the working set.
If you're now kind of the working set and you have some knowledge
about the locality,
you can try to,
for instance, when you stop a process on the disk,
your swap is working set.
And when you bring the process in,
you bring its working set,
all the biggest in the working set,
we are going to stop here.
And thank you very much.
And let me know if you have any other questions.