Hello, everyone.
Welcome to the 18th lecture of cs on ct two,
2021.
Today, we are going to talk about general input output.
And just to summarize so far,
we have studied abstractions,
the api which is provided by the operating system to the application to run
a process.
We talk a bit quite a bit about the virtual memory,
demand, paging,
how to manage the physical memory and about visualization.
We also talk about synchronization and scheduling.
So and how to manage the cpu resources and how to synchronize to have
multiple processes and multiple threads,
accessing the same resources and how they can cooperate
in order to implement some more complex functionality.
Now, one thing we haven't talked as my so far is about input and output.
Obviously, the input output is a fundamental part of any computer system,
because that's how we interact with the computers
through some input output devices,
like keyboards, mouse,
cameras, and things like that.
And also this is how the computer itself interact with the environment
and with us displaying information on the screen,
printing information.
And other things like that.
Right now,
the biggest problem, this is,
what also makes this also this lecture a little bit may be harder,
is that it's there a huge variety of this input output devices?
Like, actually,
if you think about others like memory memory is pretty simple.
It's an ra of addressable bytes.
Right?
That's pretty much what it is.
If you think about the cp us and so forth,
from our perspective,
it's a it's a resource which we want to probably time slice in time slice.
So then we can visualize it.
So he created the illusion that every process has access to its own machine,
virtual machine.
But if you look about input output devices,
this is a huge variety.
And not only in terms of the sizes,
not only in terms of the speed they operated.
You can have a networking which is hundreds of garbage per second versus keyboard,
which is one character,
but whatever second.
But also in terms of reliability,
in some cases,
you can lose information like packets on the network can be lost.
So you need to recover in all aspects.
In low dimension, you have a huge variety.
Yet,
the operating system needs to cope with this variety in a reasonable way.
Right?
You don't want to be exposed.
And what that means,
you don't want your program.
You when you are developing a program to think about each
of these input devices in a different way.
And this is the role of the operating system.
Again, despite this huge variety to provide us with an interface,
which is a reasonable sculpt,
you can make sense of it.
And you don't need to think about different concepts.
So you are going to operate a different diode for entire devices.
A if you remember,
this is a figure we have shown a few times in the past.
And here,
this produce protection boundaries,
which is down here.
It's also abstract away this input output devices.
Today, we are going to talk about how you are going to get the empire,
how you are going to get this kind of input from these devices.
And eventually, where do you need to get this input?
This input from these devices,
you need to put in memory,
because your program in order to operate the input,
it has to find the input in memory,
because the program operates only on data in memory.
And that's pretty much it.
Now this is one example,
and this is an old example.
Many years back,
this is from sun enterprise, again, sun.
It was a big company of workstations.
It was acquired many years back by order.
But in the headache, this was aa great company.
And if you think about the devices and only looking in terms of the speed,
you have keyboards, like I mentioned,
and the system bus is learning the system bus on the machine,
which connects different devices,
which are in the same enclosure on the machine, like, for instance,
this storage.
And things like that.
There are differences to others of manager.
So you need to provide interfaces which can cope
with such a huge variation of
in the speed.
So this means that you need to have something which works very well.
When you have high throughput,
the overhead for transfer per byte should be very low at the same time.
You shouldn't, if it's something very slow,
you shouldn't just waste time waiting for the flow slowly basis.
Right?
It's like,
if something happens one per second, you cannot wait.
Once.
For the entire second, we get on corrupt.
This is another way to look about.
And this is to put everything in one picture about what we learned
so far and what we are going to learn today.
On the left hand side, you have the processor.
And the processor obviously has the cpu but in addition to cpu has some storage,
right?
The storage is comes into registers.
Then a bunch of caches,
l one and l two cache,
which added to the start better core.
And then you have another three cash and the three cash typically shared
across multiple course.
Then you have memory and secondary storage,
and maybe another tertiary storage or and so forth.
Right?
And the is the difference between this kind of story.
Generally.
It's obviously like going from registers all away from this to disk storage.
You have,
at each level, is much larger capacity,
but also highlight latest.
Right?
So we learn about that.
We learned that about cashing,
we learned about demand,
paging and so forth.
In addition to that here on the top with a yellow,
you have all these devices,
which, again,
needs to be available the data,
which is read from these devices to be available to processor.
And then for the processor to write the data to these devices,
like the storage to screen to for you to see an image.
And typically,
all these devices are,
they have a controller.
This controller is what the name implies,
control these devices,
because these devices are different.
In some sense,
this yellow box provides magical interface,
which is reasonably uniform across all the devices to the processor
and to the programmer.
But in the bank is doing this heavy, leafy,
doing uniformly sap is by dealing with such a heterogeneous,
a set of devices.
Now,
let's look a little bit into more details to see how things are on a computer.
This is what you have on your computer.
This is actually on your laptop or ipad.
At some level, this is what you have.
Okay?
And you have a processor.
Obviously,
we may have agp us.
You might have another card here.
You have some storage devices,
you may have big speakers,
internal and external speakers.
You may have a printers,
the keyboards, you have the monitor and many more.
Right?
Again,
you need to take all this information from these devices to get into process,
and then to write back information,
at least to some devices.
Some of these devices,
they can only do write back information to the keyboard.
It's only an input device as a printer.
It's only an output device.
How do you connect them?
Right?
First of all, how you hire them?
It turns out that the way you hire them is through this bus,
you have a bus.
Right?
Everything goes to a bus,
everything, including actually even the memory on the machine.
And the data is sent through this bus.
This is how you get the data into the processors.
This is how you get the data out of the processors through one bus.
And more precisely,
what is a bus is represent the set of specifications.
You specify how many wires they have.
It has,
and how you connect to it.
And then on top of that,
it has to provide an api read, write,
how do you read and write from this bus?
And you also have how you are going to address a particular device
for the particular device.
You also have not only data reading data,
but you have also control data, right?
Like, for instance, for a disk, like you'll see,
you need to tell the disk where a particular block is on the disk
to read or to write.
Right?
This is happening is the counter control lines.
And the controller,
like you see the yellow box is going to decide and instruct using
the control line,
a device what to do and what to get the data from or to write the data to.
And then there is also the protocol.
You have multiple devices which are going to send the data on the same bus.
What do you need to do?
Right?
Not all of them can send the data at the same time.
In general,
you have only one device being able to send data on the bus at a given time.
This means that you need to arbitrate if more than 1 device,
1% the data on the bus at the same time,
they need to arbitrate who is going to be allowed to send and who
is going to wait.
Okay, and of course,
you are the devices here I will chat again,
remember about they are very different in speed.
The devices which are the close to the processor like memory,
like things like that.
They are very, very fast,
the one which are very remote.
I must slower like say keyboard or printer.
Now why a bus,
this and this is very important?
It may seems that this is obvious.
It's a bus, right?
But think about what is the alternative.
So an obvious alternative here,
it will be to connect every device to the processor.
Right?
If the two devices have to communicate among themselves,
you're also going to connect between them.
The problem is that then you are going to have,
in the worst case,
you have any devices and you can have all n square connection.
You don't want that.
It's very complicated.
So that's why what you want.
You have this bus and everyone is connected to the bus,
and then you is beautiful.
Then you multiply that the bus in time.
But the problem is that if you multiplexing time,
then it may be very inefficient, because remember,
all these devices have very different speeds.
So like, for instance,
if i'm going the keyboard right,
is like a key, right?
You click a key and it takes a game.
It's like every 1 second.
It's very inefficient way of that bus, right?
Because in the same time,
you may send,
if from memory,
you can send hundreds of garbage per second, garbage per second,
or or which means a few tons of gigabytes per second.
So it's very inefficient.
Like you don't if you have slow devices,
very inefficient for very fast devices.
And that's one of the big problems advantage against simplicity.
Everyone connects to it.
The standard bus is today's,
but it's pci is called peripheral component interconnect.
It started as a parallel bus,
meaning that at one device at a time is going to use to be able to send data,
and it can send data in parallel if he sends.
And the weights of the bus represents how many beats you can send in parallel.
For instance, if you have128 beats,
this means that you are going to be able to send in 1 clock cycle,
128beats,
and multiply this bus like we discussed.
But now is a problem.
If it's a slow device,
then you are going to yours.
And also he doesn't have,
he sends only eight beats while the bus,
so it's 128 beats.
You are going to waste on 20 beats while this device is alone using the bus
for sending just eight beats.
I'm going to stop here.
Any questions about so far?
So this is a little bit, again,
it's like very descriptive,
a lot of heterogeneity.
So maybe a little bit boring,
but it'll change.
So now,  You may have heard about pci express bus.
What is this?
Again?
The problem is that it's parallel.
This is great.
It's simple, but only one device can use at the same time.
And if it's a slow device,
you waste so much time for the five devices.
So pci express, it's pretty smart.
So it's no a longer parallel bus.
You still have multiple lights,
but there are serial channels.
And you can,
now a device can cures how many lines is going to send 2 years to send.
Right?
For instance,
if you have a very slow device like the keyboard,
the right,
you can use to send everything going online,
right?
And you leave all the other lines for others like memory.
But I have access to memory or the storage.
So this allows the slow devices to share the pci bus with fast
devices in an efficient way.
And again, the beauty of this of linux and eunuchs behind it be before it,
was that the ability to support all these,
not only to migrate from bci to bci express,
but again, to provide a pretty uniform interface across all these devices.
Okay?
And also, the api itself remains the same, most, pretty much the same.
And this is quite amazing.
Right?
If you think about it,
because unix, when I was designed unix,
I a lot of see things you have today.
Maybe you are not available there.
You didn't have gps for instance.
I'm sure you didn't have a lot of this kind of game gaming inputs devices.
Right?
And many other things, right?
Despite that,
we started to connect sinks to the computer to the to the computer,
which are not envisioned when people designed the operating system
in the first place.
The operating system are still being able to preserve the same api you
need to to implement controllers or drivers,
which are going to provide so to support these devices and provide
the same kind of
abstraction like before,
right?
We'll talk more about that.
Okay?
Here is an example of the pc architecture.
Today, you have apci number zero,
pci number zero here.
And the this is very fast one.
This is connected to the cpu.
The cpu is also having a memory bastards around.
Then there is apci breach here.
You have another pci bus.
This pci bus is a little bit typically slower.
This is connects the storage devices, for instance,
a scandal and all the webcam mouse and keyboard.
And then you have another british here from bci to a so isi it was
an older bus standard,
so you still have devices.
For instance,
this hardest drives which support which implements this,
stand out and come to connect to this isi bus.
This is a bridge.
So then you can use these devices on apspsppci architecture.
So here let's go into a little bit more into a little bit more details.
So how there's a processor that talk to all these devices.
Here is about is acpu and you have the memory.
You have a memory boss here.
And now you have this is connected through a bus adapter to get
data from this device controller.
Right?
To remember each device has a controller.
And to go to the device,
you send the instructions about what data to get or to write.
And the control is doing is talking with a device to get what the program
asked for.
Right now,
within a device controller is quite a device controller is quite complicated.
Actually, many device controllers.
They have their own processors.
So it's like their own computer.
Right?
They have arm processor and so forth to implement the program,
which is going to control that device.
We have a bus interface to send the data in and out to connect
to the other buses in the system.
It has a memory.
You can, for instance,
for doing for caching data.
Right?
For instance, when you send data to the printer,
you can assume that it's not like you send one by this printed,
you send one by this printed.
No,
you send a lot almost the entire file.
You can send the entire file,
which is kind of store that is part of it in local memory,
and then is spreading from there.
Right?
And then this is very important.
You have a set of registers here,
which these are the register storage.
You you is there used to interact with this controller?
They are used to tell us a controller what to do.
Right?
And read,
write or configure to configure the control in a particular way.
It's also to get the status of the controller.
The status of the controller can be busy, right?
The printer is busy,
right?
Showing the status.
Not sorry.
This is the status of the device controlled by the control.
Another important things,
if you remember,
we have this kind of interrupts,
but I can remember about the interrupts.
One of the main series of interactions is to react when something happens
in the external world.
And one of the main use cases there is about when you have some data to get
from a device,
from the network, for instance,
or when some device needs attention,
right?
That's what the interrupt control.
And the value is.
A controller is going to raise some interrupts.
And the interrupts are if you remember the operating system,
depending on the interrupt,
is going to have an interrupt handler which is going to handle that internet.
Right?
The metal card has another controller has pack his new data is
going to interrupt to raise and interrupt.
The os is going to handle that interrupt and is going to leave the data
from the control.
Now, how do I interact?
How do I program?
These controllers?
There are two ways,
both mapped io in and out instructions,
basically here for the intel architecture.
In particular, you have say out zero x 21.
This is an address.
This is io so each io has its own address.
Each and io each.
Io device has its own address.
Basically, out zero,
x one comma ail means that the content of register al is a register.
So the content of that register will be written on that out at that address
to that output will be written to that output.
And you have the corresponding in and from a particular port address.
And then the data from that port is going to be written in registered air.
For instance.
So you have special instructions here, right?
And special addresses for these devices.
On the other hand,
you can have memory mapped io this is pretty cool.
You basically reserve your configure some addresses in the memory is around.
Okay?
As and this being got connected to these input output devices.
The only thing you do,
you use load and store because it's memory.
Load means if I am going to put the data there at that particular address,
that data is going to be sent to the corresponding device.
If I get,
if I read the data from a particular address,
which is memory mapped address,
then i'm going to read data from the corresponding device.
Make sense?
This is an example of our memory map.
This is really used for graphics.
Typically, here,
what you have is that like your screen is a bit math,
right?
That right?
So the screen,
the control of a screen,
see, the same memo have a region.
You devote a region of your ram.
You devote to that to the screen.
And when you are going and then when you are going to modify this memory,
see what you modify.
You see immediately on the script.
So from here, display memory is from this address, 800, whatever,
10,000 to8,000,
whatever f 000.
This is a disclaimer.
In addition to that,
you may have also comment you,
because you can provide some comments to the display,
for instance,
because you may have like higher level abstractions,
rather than just writing and reading the writing individuals
in the individual bits,
like, for instance,
generating triangles.
Right?
You are going to basically come and give a comment to the controller,
which is a graphic card,
is going to to generate this kind of,
say, triangles to create much faster to render much faster,
some impressive objects.
Okay?
What this is one thing.
So again,
from in somebody here,
in this very simple example,
you are going to have a region on the ram,
which is seen both by processor,
and is seen by both and also by the controller,
the the video controller.
Right?
And when you write when the processor rise to this address,
go to this memory,
you meet your seat on the screen.
Right?
So,
any questions?
Now,
it turns out that today with this,
everyone knows about gps graphical processing units and the gpu they
have actually their own memory.
So is you don't have this sharing.
The reason for that because the memory thing on because the memory is a tip
if the memory is on the gpu that is much faster.
So you can render much, faster, much quicker.
That's one of the reasons this is for you to know.
You can protect this memory regions using address translation like we know.
Now here is an interesting thing.
So far,
we saw we told ii told you how it's that you have this processor and you
have all these other
storage devices and io devices around it,
and they are connected by the bus.
But if a look in the processor into a processor itself,
you see some similar things,
because in a processor is not a monolith.
In a processor, remember,
you have multiple cars,
you have multiple caches and so forth.
How?
And actually many cp us today,
they'd also have graphic unit, right?
Or nearly unit,
like some of the apple chips have.
Right?
And then how do you connect us?
The answer is through a bus.
Right?
Okay.
Again, it's like,
what you see is there outside outside the cpu it's
also pretty similar inside the cpu you have different components,
like here are a few examples, like I mentioned.
They are connected by a bus, by the way,
adx is a software.
Got extension.
This is basically it's a software.
It's a hard rank like for people of you,
for people who took a security course, a class.
Then you are going to connect outside the city.
You are going to connect to the memory,
ddr this is a memory.
And you are going also,
you see here you are going to have aabci express.
This is how you connect to the pci express to the rest of higher devices.
Is another way to look at.
This is against sky lake system configuration.
This is the same chip here.
It's pretty old, but today's on the ones.
So they are not very different.
And you have you have here.
Basically, you have,
this is a core.
This is connected to memory.
Then you have this pci express.
It's again to directly connect to other io devices.
And then you have this abridge,
and you have another chip which connects to other io devices.
Still, this is typically say these are a little bit slower devices,
in general, right?
Usb audio video line and so forth.
So it's, again,
the same picture emphasizing this pattern of multiple components being
connected by bus fast buses.
Any questions?
Now,
ii mentioned to you that one of the beauty and the successes
of eunuchs and linux,
obviously, is that they were able to provide an api which remain pretty
much the same over time despite applauded proliferation of higher devices.
And the reason for that is because obviously they got abstraction,
right?
And they already recognize early on,
there are different type of devices,
and they are going to handle these different with this device is slightly different.
So how these devices are segmented.
First Is data granality when I am going to read and write from a device.
What is the granularity of the data I am going to use?
Lowest granularity is like byte.
In some case, there is a bit,
but it's rare is byte.
You read 1 byte at a time,
you write 1 byte at a time.
But there are other devices,
many other devices where you write at a higher gallery,
like a block,
like to disk,
or reading or writing from a disk,
or reading or writing from the network.
It's a level of product.
It's a pack.
So now, let's make a little bit this class more interactive.
Why do you seeing that?
Why bite is not enough?
Why not just have the ability to read and write only at the background?
Eric?
Anyone can tell me?
It's exactly ruth ban.
And actually, and this is correct.
So if you're right and to read as a by granularity,
then you need to.
This means if you think about from the perspective,
this is an api to the publication.
And I want to read and write a bite.
This translates to a system,
call a system called translate to a context switch.
The overhead,
right?
To read and write a bite is nontrivial,
You cannot sustain,
keep up with very fast io devices.
So that's the reason.
So bytes is fine for keyboard,
right?
But it's not going to be fine for ascending.
They died doing a bit per second,
because a fixed cost of send operation or receiving operation is too high.
But they got it right from day one,
because they have to support the disk.
And the disk couldn't do it efficiently at byte level.
So they have to have blocks good,
access pattern, sequential versus random.
Some devices must be accessed sequentially if you have a tape and others
are random.
Now,
also, there are devices which are under this axis pattern beyond is like,
are you going and we are going to talk more about that?
Do you need to monitor that I io device all the time to see what happens
where you are going to get interrupts when something happens?
Right?
Like with a keyboard or another card.
But now let me ask you again, it's like, for instance,
of our sequential best to the random.
Why not have only one?
Forget about tape for now?
Like remove tape because that restate is obvious, right?
It's like,
is that you have to access data on the sequential.
But even without that,
tell me why not have random, right?
Because if I have random access pattern,
then it does make sense.
I I can emulate sequential, right?
I start from one,
and then I say one.
Now I want to get23456×323456.
After all, in memory,
I have only random access.
I don't have sequential assets.
So why sequential access?
Why not random?
Yes, michael.
It's good.
Because the random may involved some nontrivial overhead to locate
as a random piece of information.
That's right.
Like we'll see with the disks.
Therefore,
if I am going to store the the bytes and I can read or write them sequentially,
it's going to be much faster.
So you see, in both these cases,
you can get away only have read,
writes as the level of byte and only accessing randomly.
But you are going to leave a lot of performance off on the table.
So block and sequential broken rightly and sequential access factor.
One of the main reasons they are used,
it's for performance reasons.
Okay.
Now, the transfer mechanics,
how is this program io or dma direct memory access?
Program?
Io means the processor takes a pipe from one device and transferred
to another device.
Like, for instance, they think that they survive.
Trump takes a block of data from the disk and put it in memory is doing in
out and love stuff is simple.
You can program everything through the computer.
The disadvantage is that you are going to use acpu for doing that.
You are going to consume these resources,
just moving the rate around not doing useful or the second or is
direct memory access.
And now this is a smartphone.
In this case, you say you are going to deal with these two devices.
Basically, you are going to tell one controller from one device.
You have to transfer the data directly to this other peoples.
This acpu is going to send instructions how the transfer should happen.
But then the transfer happens between the devices without the city
of being involved.
Here is an example.
Typically, this is one of the devices is typically memory.
Right?
Here, what happens?
You have apci boss and what?
And you have a memory.
And here you have a disk.
I want to transfer the data from the disk,
the memory to read the data from the disk into memory.
These are the steps.
The cpu number one,
the cpu is going to
the program starts to say,
I want to read the data from the disk.
Now, and there is a good,
the os is going to handle that and is going to send
a message control message to the idea is the controller.
There is controller telling it,
you need to to get this data to this address in the memoirs
address x now,
the controller is going to tell this,
I need to be to,
iii was instructed to move this data to transfer this data to memory,
to this address x now the dm might do that.
You're doing the rest.
The dma not the cpu is going to handle the transfer from the dis
controller to the bar to the memoir.
Right?
The dma is going to read the data from the id and then drive the data
on the cpu bus to the memory.
Once the transfer is completed,
the dma is going to send an interrupt to the cpo telling i'm ready.
Any questions?
Critical, right?
When do io devices are notifying the operating system?
Right?
Teresa tour when it was.
The os think about from the os perspective, what do you need to know?
On one hand, you need to know if you are instructed,
you have instructed a controller,
io controller to perform some operation.
You want to know when that operation, whether that operate,
when that operation is as complete.
The second is if there is an error,
right?
The like you mentioned,
one way to handle that is I will interact whenever there is one
of these events that always needs to know about,
the iod the io controller, raise an interrupt.
Why this is good?
The cpu doesn't need to worry about.
I'm going the cpu is going to.
Now the divide the air controller is going or it's going to let the
cpu now and something worse knowing happens.
Also,
you can handle unpredictable events like a new packet arriving one another.
The disadvantage is that the interacts are expensive.
It's a contact switch.
And when the city,
when I raise and interrupt,
maybe another are most likely a process,
a user process was executed.
You need to do a context switch to go to the operating system,
handle the interrupt,
and then to go back in the user mode to continue that running the process.
The other one is falling.
This is operating system,
politically check a device specific status like, say,
to see why there is, right?
And I remember that ii show you his eye or controller.
One of these register was called status,
for instance, is going to be a printer.
I I want to know when the printer is done,
when the printing is done, they can like that.
I can tell the user.
The printer is that the whatever you send to the printer is that right?
So in that case,
the controller has this status register and it's going to be updated
and that the printer is no longer me
you busy when a file finish being printed.
And then the os it's periodically going to check on that.
And when he's no longer busy,
is going to come to the application.
Okay?
Now, the pro here is low overhead,
because the os is going to check on this between context switches.
It doesn't need to do a contact switch to just to check this one,
the operating system gets the kernel gets controlled.
It's also going to check this.
Right?
Now, the coins is that you check and nothing happens.
Then that's wasted time.
Right?
Cpu cycles.
So now,
typically or combines us,
there is no right solution.
That's why you have to both of them.
Right?
If you towards only one solution,
ii why would have I told you about boss?
But let me take a step back now and ask you,
when are you going to use our interrupts?
And there is a little bit of an answer here,
but I just want you to give the answer in your own words.
When do you think you should use our interrupts?
When do you think you should use falling?
Give me another this one example you have here on the slide,
give me another example.
Let me ask you keyboard, right?
Are you going to use polling or interrupts?
Human eye offer interrupts?
Okay, that's good.
Why is that?
Why human I offer in drugs rare and slow?
And is it here?
Sorry,
unpredictable.
Right?
It's unpredictable.
If it's something unpredictable,
it doesn't mean,
but the excess to pull forever, right?
For something right to happen.
Yes, said gilbert.
So you interrupt, falling, frequent, sinks, falling for stuff.
We need to continuously check.
Yes or no?
If something happens.
Yeah,
this for polling is someone you say this for polling sometimes actually you
don't use,
we'll see,
but it's not necessary that you are going to pull the disk
for the keyboard.
Eventually.
It's again,
you have to use the internet because this is to tell the operating system
when some key keyboard is pressed.
If you watch a movie for 2 hours or whatever on your computer,
you don't type anything,
right?
Or zoom like right now.
You got you right?
You are listening to this lecture,
right?
I hope that you are not doing a lot of many things other than listening
to the lecture.
But still right, it's like, if you're listening,
you don't touch it, don't tell the keyboard, so it's very rarely,
but doesn't make a lot of sense to pull where you pull when one
of the things the reason of your pool is like,
in this example, when things happens extremely frequent,
right?
Once you get, for instance, a packet here,
you get so many other packets on after another.
You cannot afford to have a contact switching per packet.
When the context switching is the overhead of context switching is larger,
then the time between the events,
it probably it's not worth to do contact switching.
It does not means it is not worth to do it.
Right?
Let me put in another way,
so it could say contact switching gets 1 millisecond and picking
some random number.
Right?
And then say an event happens every 10 microns micro seconds.
It makes no sense to go,
interrupts for event.
Right?
We just fall to see for that.
Okay.
Very good.
So this is a structure in the kernel.
For the device.
You have the system call in interface.
We'll talk more about them,
and you have some for memoir for.
This is what we will learn for.
We have process management,
memory management,
file systems.
And then we have the device control.
This is for io devices.
And the networking typically is different enough.
So the api also wanted to be slightly different.
So the device control what it's when I say or so,
the device controlled the controller who for the device,
this is typically implemented on the device itself.
But this device now has to also interface with your operating system,
the piece of software,
which the piece of software,
which bridges,
the operating system,
api with the controller,
api is called device driver.
And it's a piece of code which runs in the operating system is a cam.
Is this the piece of code?
It implements the unique ioabi what is that?
Abi this is a things which survive so many decades.
Remember, open,
close in order to communicate to a device,
you open your clothes,
then read and write.
You can read as a program or80.
You can read as a binary,
and ioctlio control.
This is a scape patch,
because each device can have is a little bit different,
requires a little bit different configurations.
This is what is our city alice is more for device specific control.
Now, the device driver is 2/2 one,
which basically is executed in the user mode and the other one which
is disagreeing the catalog.
Right?
I'm not sorry.
Both top and half,
bottom and half of the device drivers are executing the camera.
The board, the top one,
it provides,
it helps to provide the kernel ioapi on with which is used
by the user program to interact with these devices.
So let's see what happens.
Let's say you have a user program and request an eye operation,
say, to write a data to the risk.
It's, first of all,
is that is a request already satisfied or something like that.
Right?
It's like this happens when this happens.
For instance, if I am going to read some data from the disk.
And when I read the data from the disk,
is a good idea which the data is transferred from the disk is
larger than what I read.
So I read only 10 bytes.
But when i'm going to transfer from the disk,
i'm going to transfer 1 pages, four kilobytes.
These four kilobytes is already stored in memory.
Now, I am just going to,
if I had the first and bytes, then I can read the next.
And by zero in memory,
I don't need to do invoke to touch the device again.
But let's say now is not satisfied.
So now i'm going to send the request to the device,
right?
Send the request to the device driver.
The device driver is looking at the request and from here on this code.
Right?
Its bottle, its device specific.
I process,
the request,
then you send it to the device harbor.
This is a device struck harbor,
this is on the harbor, right?
This part is on the kernel, in the kernel.
This part of the bottom can be in the device driver.
Right?
In the divisor, it can be in the device itself.
And the device controller is going to execute the operation.
Say, for instance, instructs that this where to read the data from,
then read the data.
Once there is a data,
it buffers, you send an interrupt.
Sorry.
The interrupt is sent to the kernel.
The kernel is going to handle this interrupt,
is going to get the data from the device.
Then it's going to see whether I the io is completed.
If it's completed is going to let the application now
sounds the goal of the io subsystem io it's,
again, is to provide this interface,
uniform interface,
that a uniform interface means uniform api means that the code you wrote
for one
particular device should work.
Potential is money with very minimal changes for other devices.
For instance, for this code,
this switch opens some scold and then prints some output.
It works on multiple devices.
It works on this terminal.
If fd is a terminal,
the file descriptor is a terminal.
It works for the disk.
If I wait for file descriptor is a file,
right?
And you can also work on the printer,
the same code.
Now, let's talk a little bit more about this interface.
Why the interface it's a game is so has been so powerful.
And so general,
like I mentioned to you,
you have blog device,
you have blog devices.
For these blog devices, you write, read and read,
write the data as a blog granularity,
and you had open, read, write, and seek.
Right?
Then you can have had the character devices.
And this is the level you read and write the data at the level of color
of a single character.
And for this, you have also opened read,
but you have also for getting a single character,
you gotta get and put abi and then some of the network devices.
This is different enough that you have
a different api slightly different api you still have open and close,
but you have the concept of sockets,
and you still have reads and writes,
breed, right?
And open and close all of them.
Are you still have those?
But in addition,
you have other richard api if you remember,
you have connect,
you have accept,
you have also something else which is select,
select this when you are going to listen on connection from multiple computers,
you are going to learn more about that.
But these are the three standard interfaces provided by the operating system.
And each of the devices falls in one of these categories,
blog device, a character device, or not a device.
Next,
how you are going with respect to timing?
How do you interact with the devices?
There are few ways to interact.
One is a blocking interface.
The blocking interface,
when you are going to perform an operation,
you are going to wait for that operation to finish.
Right?
When you the request, say, for instance,
when you read some data,
you are blocking until the data requested is available,
then it's non blocking interface.
You just write some data,
and the call returns immediately before the data is written.
Okay?
Now,
so this is,
obviously don't know the result,
but then you don't block.
So you are very efficient.
You don't recycles of the cpu and then it's a synchronous interface.
Then this basically says,
I am going to request the data,
by the way, here, what you need to do.
And let me know when you are done,
I wanted to read the data, and you need,
ii also read the data from this device.
And i'm telling you that you need to put the beta after this address in memory.
You put that in the address in memory,
and you tell me111, you are damaged.
This is a synchronous interface.
So some announcements,
unfortunately,
next week will be quite a week for you.
So the good thing is that after the following week,
after the next week is going to be easier,
and the thanksgiving is coming soon,
but next week will be hard.
You have a homework for mitten to the review will be how old will be on monday.
The time we are going to let you know the time the midterm will be
on wednesday between 7:09 pm standard pacific time,
as a project is due on at the end of the next week.
And tomorrow's, unfortunately, yesterday,
I had,
like I mentioned,
a flight which was cancelled and then rescheduled between 11:30 and 12:30.
I'll have my office hour.
Let's move a little bit.
We have another 15 minutes.
So let's move quick storage devices.
So storage devices are always store the data,
but persistently,
right?
They typically have much larger capacities than memory,
but they are slower.
Right?
We have magnetic disk and flash memories.
There are two type two types.
Magnetic disks are they saw traditional ones.
Flash memories are newer,
but now are dominant.
They are more expensive that have provide better performance.
That's kind of the way to still look at them.
These are some examples,
this drive.
You see, here a bladder,
you have here the hands we can read and write the data.
And then you are going to have here is another hard drive.
This is the heads.
You have multiple bladders furniture, either data.
Therefore, you have hats on each bladder for each bladder.
Here, it's a microwave this.
Now, just to give you a sense,
the first ibm personal computer,
which was released in 1986.
So that was75 years ago, right?
It has the harvest was $500.
It was 30 megabytes,
not gigabytes megabytes.
The sick time is how long it takes a random access.
Is those 30 to locate to write the data randomly,
or iterate are really random.
You are between 30 and 40 million seconds.
And the speed,
the maximum speed of transferring the data was one megabyte per second.
So how it looks like this is how hard I hard drive it looks like.
You have the bladders,
you have the platter, has two surfaces,
the up and down surface.
So you can write on both of them.
On each of them, you are going to have tracks.
And the tracks are divided in sectors.
So the sectors stores a block.
And this is a unit of storing,
reading and writing data from the disk that is written and read the
reads and writes are performed by the head.
Okay?
Let's now show this one by one is a sector.
You have this ring of, say,
of ring of sectors.
This is a struck.
And then the corresponding tracks on all
platters represent a cylinder.
What is important about cylinder is that the data from a cylinder can be written,
written, and write a read, a written,
and read without moving the heads,
because the movement of heads,
which is called sick operation.
It's expensive.
So some numbers,
the disk track,
the tracks are around one microns wide.
This is very small as a wave by wave wavelength of light.
It's only half of micro.
A resolution of mike of humanize is 50 microns.
You have typically 100,000 trucks on a2.5 inch disk.
And you have these tracks, in general,
separated by some quad regions because you don't want right on a track
to influence that beats on the others and caught up.
Therefore, the beats on the nearby tracks.
Now, the tracks linked varies.
The one which are closer to the edges are are larger than the one at the center.
And so typically,
we are the only using half of the radius,
the only that the tracks at the edges of that,
because you have more space to store information.
If you started too close to the center,
the sector is too late, too small.
You are going to get a lot of errors.
This card obviously huge.
Right now.
There are terabytes in terms of capacity.
In general, only small part of this data,
which is not on the disk,
is active free drive that all the rest is use for our being archived.
This is important.
Before, in the early days,
your kinds of data are not on the disk,
because it is quite expensive.
Your kinds of data and mathematic tapes.
One note for this is more like a footnote.
There is something which is called a a single magnetic recording.
In this case, instead of having a guard between the trucks,
are you remember that?
I told you that between tracks you have the guards,
you avoid writing when you write on a track a bit to influence the nearby tracks.
Right?
But in order in the race to add,
to add more and more bits,
to increase the capacity of the disks,
people came up with this technique, which actually,
in some sense,
attracts kind of almost overlap.
And obviously,
now you need to be very careful and need to have
much more complex digital signal processing techniques in order
to make sure that you avoid a bit being corrupted by writing a bit
in a nearby track.
So minority disk,
it's, again, you have the head selling their sectors and tracks.
And now let's see what is a time to read or write data.
First of all, this is how the architecture looks like.
So the disk is actually has a controller,
right?
Like we mentioned many times before.
And you are going to get a request,
right to the controller gets a request.
Let me just to show you where this request is coming from.
Is here you see the request.
This is a request.
Here we are talking about this device harder,
get the request.
Then you have a cure because multiple application can request data
to read and write data from the same time.
You need to cue this request,
and then you have the harder controller,
which is going to take requests from this queue,
and that's going to satisfy the request.
Now, a request, when you satisfy the request, what happens?
You need to figure out and assume that you already know where is the data
you need to read and to where the data is located.
Right?
In order to once you do that,
you need to move that.
So you need to identify what you need to identify.
You need to identify a sector.
The sector means to identify the track.
Right?
In order to get to a track,
you need to move the disk,
to move the heads,
the more the overhead to move the disk is called sick time.
Then once you are above the corresponding track,
you need to wait for the proper sector to come under the head.
So you can read and write installation time.
Finally, the transfer time,
the time to read and write the Information from the second line.
Here are, again, some numbers from some other magnetic disks is a space.
You like 14 terabytes with the eight bladders.
Typically, the sick time is 4 to 6 million seconds.
The salutation like a rotation speed,
the rotation per minute is like between thirty six hundred and seventy two hundred.
There are also some of the new faster disk at even 1,500 rotation per minute.
Average latency of rotational latency is between four and a millisecond.
Right?
This is,
if it takes 8 million seconds for a full rotation,
then on average, you need to wait for 4 million seconds, rotation, latency.
In order for the sector.
You are looking forward to come under the disk
and under the head and transfer time between
50 and 250 million megabytes per second.
The transfer a sector is typically between a 512 and one kilobyte
and things like that.
They used to drop because the cost used to drop by a factor of two.
Every 1.5 years is no longer true.
Now, let's go through this example,
assuming that we ignore the queuing and the controller types.
Okay?
We ignore the skewing time and the control of time.
Let's look only on the media time.
Assume they are very sick time is 5 minute seconds.
Assume that the rotation speed,
its7,200 rotation per minute.
This means that it takes 8 million seconds for a full rotation.
The transfer rate assume is 50 megabytes.
So then the, sorry, this is the transfer rate of 15 megabytes per second.
If it's a block size of four kilobytes,
but I assume the transfer is 15 megabytes per second.
If the block size is four kilobytes,
then it takes 0.0.8 millisecond to transfer one sector.
You divide for kilobytes,
the size of a sector on the transfer rate, like to get that by.
So then reading the block from a random place on the disk,
you need to seek first to the track.
We need to wait for the sector,
and then you read it.
So it takes 9 million seconds.
A little bit more than 9 million seconds,
is a kivalent to 450 kilobytes per second transfer speed.
If you read the block from a random place in the same cylinder,
then if you do that,
you don't need to incur the sick time.
Now, the latency is only 4.08 millisecond,
which means the data.
Now,
rate is one megabyte per second.
But now assume that you just need the same next sector on the track.
You sequentially,
then you don't need to incur the rotation delay either.
So it's 50 megabytes per second,
CC 3 times bigger,
or 100 a time bigger.
If it's purely random.
So now you see why you have sick.
Also, you have sequential access and versus only random access.
If you can sequential access of data is so much faster,
at least for the risk.
The key to use a disk effectively is to make sure that you as much as possible,
you access a data sequential.
Now, there is a lot of Intelligence in this embedded into this controller.
The sectors, for instance,
you have sophisticated error correcting codes,
right?
Because to avoid data corruption,
this is very important because if you store the data on a disk and you
trust at this,
because you start persistently.
So if the data is corrupted,
you lost the data sector spanning.
So again, it's like,
if be,
sometimes some sectors becomes bad,
you can no longer read and write data reliably from them.
In that case, you remember that you forget about those,
and you remember that to transparent to another spare sector on the disk,
this is done by the controller transparent to the software,
sleep spanning.
Now,
if there is a bank,
if the a sector goes bad,
the problem is that in now,
you no longer have sequential access.
If you want to preserve sequential access,
you may want to remap multiple sectors to preserve the sequentially.
The last thing is track screen,
and here I have a figure for regard as a mint track screen.
This means that I I if the data is stored sequentially on nearby tracks,
then I want to make sure that when I move from one track to another,
I don't waste time.
So here is these are the sectors on track one.
So say I'm going to reach on track one here.
The head I'm just finishing reading everything on the track one and I want
a move to track two.
The tractor is the one inside.
Now, when I want to move,
then the first sector on track one,
I'm going to shift.
So then this time,
when I'm going to move the head to track one,
by the time I moved,
now sector zero comes is ready to be read.
I if I don't do this,
then while I move this head from one sector,
from one track to another,
I miss the sector zero,
and I need to wait for an entire evolution of the disk.
Before I start reading,
I'm going to end up with this slide.
This is an example of Karen had this drive.
It's like2020,
eighteen terabytes is a hard drive, nine players, 18 hertz.
Each bladder has two sides.
So 11 head for each side,
4 millisecond are very sick time.
A sector is four kilobytes,
70 two hundred rpm and so forth.
And 270 megabytes per second maximum transfer cost 562.
Now let's compare with IBM personal computer drive.
The first drive.
This was 86.
The sick time is 10 times better.
The transfer time is 300 times better,
but the capacity is 600,000 times better.
And the cost, it's almost the same 600,000 times better.
So this is a progress we are able to get in 36 years.
Okay, so it's quite impressive.
So we are going to stop here.
And next time we are going to start talking with about a solid SS DS.
Thanks, everyone.
Okay.
I'm going to stop here and I'm going to answer the questions.