Hello, everyone.
So today we are going to continue the discussion about the storage devices.
In particular, we are going to talk about ss ds or solid state devices.
We are going to start the discussion on queuing theory.
Last time, we talked about this drives or the spinning disks.
And these are the main technology used to store data
for the first few decades of
personal computers and computers in general.
And with starting with kind of two decades ago,
a little bit more than that.
It's we started to see the emergence of us another technology to start data
persistently.
That was memory based.
And the first efforts was in 1995 is the emergencies of you have d ram.
But how you make it persistent,
you have a battery.
You have been empowered by a battery.
As long as a battery lasts,
you are going to store the data persistently in that memory.
Even when the computer or it's unplugged.
After that,
things change with this new technology and multiple cells.
So basically, this allows you to store is like a memory,
but it allows you to start data is to start information even when it's not power.
Okay?
So that was kind of the key technology innovation.
As a high level.
There are many tell us,
we don't have a lot of time to go into it, tell us.
But the big sink was about
having this commercially available the technology to store data
without in this kind of new kind of memories,
without needing to power them on.
And this ss ds,
these are going to,
they have they story information and gravity of a memory block and a memory
block.
It's consist of four kilobytes page of between 4and64 kilobytes pages.
Remember that 4 kilobytes pages is basically more or less like a sector
on a disk describe.
It's also may can be the size of the page for of a virtual memory
implementation.
You have virtual page, the pages of visual memory, the pages,
individual memory,
typically four kilobytes.
The same, the size is a sector size.
And then when you translate those to this as these,
you are going for this formula by stage are part of a memory block.
And a memory block consist of four between four and cd four.
Vegas.
This is an important detail.
There are no moving parts.
We just like memory.
This has a certain advantages,
big advantages.
First of all, eliminate the sick and the rotational latency.
Remember, from last time,
there's a sick and rotational latency,
where the biggest culprits of a long latency to access data on the disk
that is randomly.
But that's why we have a huge difference between the throughput of a disk
when you access a data sequentially.
Because in that particular case,
you do not need to pay for the sick and rotation delays,
versus when you access the data randomly,
when you need to pay for a boss of this delays,
six elevation,
they also have requires even lower, very,
very low power and anything,
and they are liked wet.
This is not just memory.
It's not like a disk matter, always.
Bladder as soon as spinning and heads and things like that on the downside,
it does have limited right cycles.
This means that limited the right cycle is when you modify a sadly,
when you modify a bit,
you cannot,
if you modify it too many times,
if you write the same, but a bit,
too many times, then it works out.
You can no longer ride that bit reliably.
And so that's one the challenge you need to deal with.
And obviously,
things are introduced their own rapid advantage,
and the capacity have increased.
And today,
to give you a sense,
obviously,
today is that I am not sure any of your devices you are working
with still has a disk unless you are working,
you have a big workstation home or you are using.
But certainly your laptops,
obviously, the phones,
ipo ipad,
or they no longer have these drives as to start data persistently.
They only have ss ds.
Here it's again how as the architecture look like,
this lands is where on the right hand side is a memory,
the banks of memory.
And each of these could present a block.
And then you have a flash memory controller,
which basically decides where to write and or to read the data from,
you have a buffer manager and a softer queue.
This is about when this is where you buffer the reads and writes requests.
Say we have many reads or write requests at the same time,
and you cannot serve at the same time.
You have to buffer them and it sell them1×1.
It's also ad ram here.
So when you cache some of the information, right?
When you read, if I read only a few bites,
the granularity, if you remember,
to read and write from this ssd it is one of this memory blocks,
which can be between 16and256kilobytes.
You have to read the diagram of granularity.
And once you are reading it,
you are going to cash it.
If you are going to or write,
if you are going to read again,
the next few bytes,
then it's already in the alarm.
You don't need to go and fetch it, fetch it again.
Now, and this is the satire.
It's a bus technology,
and or can be bc bs which is connected to the through a bridge to the pci bus,
like we discussed last time.
And then it's connected to the processor and is a memory.
Here are some numbers for you to read a four kilobyte page.
It takes around, say,
between 10and25 micro seconds.
Again, there is no segal rotational latency.
Now, the transfer time for that four kilobytes page,
for the satire interface,
you have between three hundred six hundred megabytes per second.
Actually,
the best interface is today you have two gigabytes or mega two gigabytes
per second.
So a few times larger than this.
But even for us for, say,
400 megabytes per second to take a number,
then the transfer time.
So the time to read 4 kilo by spade is send micro seconds.
And the latency, if you remember,
what is atlanta and latency is a queuing time.
So the time it the request has to wake in the cure for other requests
to be satisfied plus a controller time,
whatever the controller needs to do and to make the decision.
It's a fixed time and the transfer time.
Right?
Because this is a memory is basically around.
You can randomly address.
There is not such a big difference between sequential and random reads.
Now, this was about the read.
Now the writing is much more complex.
And you can only write empty pages a in a block.
Right?
There is a there are three states of these pages.
It's written those two stages,
whether it's redone and or it, whether it's erased,
and you can or empty.
And you can only write empty pages.
So if a page is,
you want to overwrite the page,
then before doing that,
you need to erase a page.
Now the bait becomes empty,
and then you're overwrite it.
Now,
the problem with that is that these operations are far more expensive,
far more expensive.
Remember, it's like the reader say 25microsecond.
The writing data on an empty page is 200microsecond.
Right now, if you want to erase a page,
if you need to erase a page,
if you don't have an empty page,
they raise, they're raising.
The page takes1.5millisecond.
Okay?
The rule of thumb you can think about the right is 10
times more expensive than the reeds.
And the rangers are 10 times more expensive than the rights, right?
So25 than 200microsecond,
it's around 8 times larger than 25microsecond,
which is a time to takes to read a page.
Then1.5millisecond is what?
7.5times larger than 200 microsecond is a time to read to do, right?
An empty page.
So therefore, you need to be very careful about that, right?
This is a thing that took constraints.
You have to operate with the two constraints, which are different,
make this ssd is different than the d ram,
the traditional memory.
It's one.
It's about, you can only write empty pages.
And breed and rights are asymmetric,
are not taking the same amount of time,
a range of the cuban one longer.
This is one then.
And the other one is that you can only do a limited amount.
A number of rights,
typically is like 10,000 rights or something like that.
So you need to be careful.
Now, in order to avoid the cost of eurasia,
when you need to write,
do you raise first before writing what the controller is doing?
It maintains a pool of empty blocks.
So you bring the use pages,
put them in a put together in a blog.
And then you have these pulls of empty blocks.
And then you can write them,
and then you can pay only 200 microsecond per page instead of1.71millisecond.
Ss ds provide the same interface as hardly strives to the os the same api
which is great,
because you can just swap and describe with an ssd and your computer will work,
but will be much faster.
Right?
Like I said, when you override the data,
when you the karanoid of writing,
a it's a block,
and the block can be 16 times larger than a page.
Sorry, 67,
64times larger than a page.
So you have a pages four kilobytes,
and you have 64 pages in a block.
Then 64 by time times 4is256kilobytes.
This is what?
The25060~50,
256 kilobytes is coming from.
So I will only discuss about it.
Why not erase and rewrite new version of the entire 256blocks,
because eurasia is extremely slow.
And then each block has a finite lifetime,
like I mentioned to you,
you cannot, you erase and rewrite all the time.
You can only do that for, say, ten,
a few tens of the 10,000 of times.
Therefore, if you have heavily used blocks,
you do a lot of rights.
They are going to wear out quickly.
Now you have this problem, right?
It's like,
if you have,
how do you are going to solve it?
Right?
And against the problem is that I I can do iii am allowed to do
only a limited number of rights.
Now I have some heavy blocks.
So what i'm going to do about it,
do you have any suggestions here?
Remap?
That's exactly.
So that's very good.
So basically, when you are going to the right,
you are not going to write in the same place.
You are going to write to another page,
which was not so used in the past.
And then you are going to remap the page to the new block.
You used to write the new information.
This is a layer of indirection.
It is called flash translation layer or fdl in sst I see your map,
the virtual block numbers,
which is uses.
These are the blocks actually said the patient numbers,
the physical patient numbers,
which flash memory contributes.
That's the way it's working.
Right?
From the is perspective,
you still have the same page as the same page numbers and everything.
But now on the physical pages,
you have a map.
And the page number as seen by the cpo is going to map to a physical page number.
And the mapping is this,
it's handled by the car.
It's managed by the controller.
So the controller can remap and basically say page number one is go to fit
to physical page number ten.
Next is going to go to physical page number15.
That's how i'm going to load balance the rights for the same page as seen
by the cpu
this is pretty much,
it's, again, copy on the right.
This is or should be obvious, right?
Again, I do not want to copy to rewrite the same page.
Even if I want to modify a page,
I don't rewrite it because I need to erase it first.
If I need to erase it, first is expensive.
So what i'm doing,
i'm going to just create a new version of the page and then i'm going to remap
Isn't the lifetime of ten ka ratio rights quite small?
Consider that we can use a laptop for for multiple years.
It's not really I because if you really do load balancing,
really loud balancing,
this means that you need to write or update.
You can read and wrap and update like say you have one one terabyte of disk.
Right?
So one terabyte of disk then you can write,
they are equivalent of 10,000 multiply with one terabyte,
so 10 better bytes.
Right?
I think it's so mad.
This is right.
I can write and better bytes,
and it's hard to write and better bytes.
But it's, again, this works.
If you are going to be able to load balance, right?
And these rights.
Right?
This is what the controller is doing.
The flash translation layer also ensure that there is no need
to erase and rewrite the entire 256 blocks when making small modification
or changes.
Ssd controller can assign mapping to spread or notice or to talk about you
want basically to load balance the rights.
This is called world level ink.
And you are doing that by the mapping and doing copy and write creating
new versions of the page,
or hopefully using a page of physical page,
which was not written many times.
If your old version of the pages,
which are you delete a file, what happened?
Then they are very garbage collected in the background.
And in the background, you are going to raise them, so to make it,
prepare them to be written again.
They are ready to be written again.
Any questions?
This again, was something some of the most.
Now, how's it?
Is a compare like hardest drives with ss ds.
We'll have that in the next slide,
but about ss ds themselves,
these are you can buy,
these are pre are sold some of the data,
but you can buy 16 terabytes.
You remember that we have 16 terabytes.
The disk we considered last time was this kind of the hard disk driver
was having the same size,
16 terabytes, the same capacity.
But that was,
if I remember correctly,
you can check that was around $500,
$550,
or something like that.
This is $55,000.
Okay?
So it's 10 times more expensive for the same capacity.
However, if you look at,
if you look at the reads and writes the number of sequential reads and writes,
it's800 or 900.
In that case, was,
if I remember sequential rights,
it was 260 megabytes per second.
So this is up to almost 4 times faster.
And random breeds.
And rice is, there is no comparison.
You can have 100,000 breeds per second.
While a read, in the case of a disk, if you remember,
can take a few million seconds.
So if you takes even, you're a few million seconds.
And in a second, in the in a second,
you can read a few hundreds,
do a few hundreds retail rights in order of lying to bed.
And if you really want to go to the top ones,
we have 100 terabytes.
So this is the 100 terabytes.
You have 500 megabytes sequentially and rights.
The same kind of I ops,
100 kilobytes,
or I ops means are input output or input
of open operation or input operation per second
unlimited rice for 5 years.
So you get this guarantees.
But it costs four thousand,
$40,000.
But my far more expensive, right?
Is like 1/4 of dollar per gigabyte.
Why would random versus sequential have different performance?
This is these.
As if you read at the level of pages, there is no difference.
And you can do probably you can do the mask here or is very little difference.
But still, if you read at the level of page,
because you transfer from the ss ds at the level of page or block that,
I think blog on a granality,
if you read only 1 byte or from that page,
you are still going to lose in terms of performance for throughput.
The difference between a random,
the different reason rises.
The reason is different here is because remember that the rights are slower,
10 times slower, almost.
Here is a comparison between hardest drives.
And I says this and this is a nice,
interesting plot,
because why wouldn't use as it is?
They have all they are faster.
They can have bigger capacity,
they consume less power,
so they are more reliable.
So why in the world you wouldn't use that?
The answer is simply is cost.
Right?
However, and here,
what you see or is a blue line,
is a flash cost.
It is and for the same capacity city for the terabyte is a flash cost or a terabyte.
And here is orange is hardest drive cost.
So the hard drive cost much cheaper than ss ds.
With green, the green is the most important curve.
Is basically what is a ratio between the cost to store one terabyte
on an ssd versus the
cost to store a terabyte on hardest drive.
So it was 37 times in 2013.
Today, it's around 56 times,
so it's much smaller.
And many people predict that sometime in the future,
these predictions are almost always wrong.
But somewhere in the near future,
the ssd will match the cost of harvey stripes.
And at that point,
there is very little reasons to use harvey stripes at all.
Okay?
In summary,
this,
they have low latency, high throughput,
no moving parts of more reliable,
lower power consumption,
and read much faster it,
read their memory speeds.
You get it even faster.
If you have a wider bus,
by the way,
that was one of the main limitations of how fast you can read and write.
The cons before02 is expensive between 3 and 20 x more expensive.
In a few years back,
like certainly 10 years back.
The ssd is sort of much smaller than harvey stripes.
That's why here it's smaller storage.
The people by exam,
they are combining the hardest drive with ss ds using ssd as a cash to get
the performance of ss ds and to get the capacity of hrd stripes.
But now there's no longer needed, right?
Because as you've seen from the data, now,
the hardest ss ds can have higher capacity than hard disrupts.
Quite amazing.
Right?
This says tells you this technology,
if you are to build a company based on that,
they totally do not have been a good,
great idea because the trends are not in your favor, right?
By because they're your product to use ss ds to speed up,
the hardest drives would have become obsolete.
There's a a is still a reason to do that,
because if you want to get the cost of the hardest stripes to do cheaper,
right?
To be cheaper,
and still have almost proper performance compare basis as these.
But that's probably true today.
But in a few years,
again, if ss bs are going to drop at the cost of how these drives there is,
no reason for these optimization.
You have a symmetric block rights performance.
We know that.
And we learn about that.
You have where the limited lifetime in terms of rights, writing, rights.
But I still need to be careful.
Average final rate is 6 years,
life expenses between 9 and 10,
11 years are actually better than hard these drives.
It's again the deal they are here.
Ss ds had a battery in almost every respect.
You need to be more careful.
You need it's more complex.
The algorithms are more complex to go around these limitations
that the agents are very expensive,
and you need to erase a page before writing it,
where you need to take into account the wearing of pages.
It's more expensive about the cost of dropping.
So the prices are dropping.
So is a question here,
just wondering how much overhale generally is
there for the hybrid alternative system involving
both society and hardy stripes?
It seems like it would be a lot more complex keeping track going
between both in the same computer.
It's more complex, but the way that you buy this like you buy that like,
it's like,
is the same enclosure,
the hardest drive.
They are not two different devices.
You buy, like, it's like a device which you plug into your satire bus, right?
And like you'll buy a hardest drive or ssd and you buy this kind of highly devised.
And inside the device,
you hide all the complexity.
You have ssd you have the hardest drive,
and you have complex logic to deal and to use ssd basically like a cash
for the harvest stripes.
Did answer your question, gilbert?
It's complex, but it's hit up.
The complex is hit up announcements.
How much story is due on mondays?
You now meet them too.
But if you now we have a time between 5:00 and 6:67 pm on monday,
a meter to its wednesday between 7:00 and 9:00 pm please read
the updated proctor and guide.
You can have an additional a cheat sheet for this exam.
Remember that this exam will cover everything from the beginning of the semester,
but we have more emphasized on the materials in the first meter.
The project is due next friday,
so next week it's a hard week,
but it's again, after that, it will be easier.
Now let's switch gear.
Any question now about a storage device is what we learn over the last
and this lecture?
Harvest drive and solid state drives.
Right now,
we are going to swiss gears,
and we are going to talk about performance and how to model performance.
If you saw this kind of even like device drivers are pretty complex,
you get the request, you in queue,
the request because you may have multiple requests arriving
at the same time yourselves,
a request.
And by from the point of view of the per the program who made the request,
he cares only about the entrant latency.
But the center and latency is divided or support is divided
between multiple components.
We are going to learn a little bit about how to model those.
And let's try first to define what are the metrics we care about.
The response time or latency is time to perform an operation is the end
to end time.
You have the bandwidth or throughput is the right to which you can perform
operations operation per second for different devices.
See, the operation can be different, like, for instance,
a it's a different metric here.
But all the metrics are over second.
It's some quantity over second like files.
For files when you read and write is megabytes per second.
For a network is megabytes per second, right?
When you said megabytes is power of two, if you remember,
megabyss for the network is power of ten like this.
So you like, for instance,
one megabyte for,
but one megabyte for files is one thousand twenty twenty four kilobytes.
One megabit for network is 1,000,
sorry, one megabit for network.
What i'm saying?
One megabyte for files.
It's1,024 kilobytes.
I I said correctly.
One megabyte per second for network.
It's 1,000 kilobits per second.
And then you have giga flops operation per second,
floating point operation for second,
for automatic computation and things like that.
Then you have a startup or overhead.
It's a time to initiate an operation.
This can be think about like something like context reject.
I mostly,
operation are roughly linear in the number of bytes.
So basically, what happens by so basically, for instance,
you if you are going to the way you can model this operation,
there is an overhead or aa fixed cost to initiate the operation.
You pay on that operation.
No matter how much you transfer,
then it's a variable cost and the variable cost is.
And how many bytes,
in this case you transfer over the bandwidth?
If you remember, we've seen this pretty very much in the last lecture.
For hardest drives.
You remember, you have the overhead,
which was the sick time and rotational latency.
No matter how much you read or write on a disk,
you need to pay for that cost, right?
When you do that read and write.
And then once you locate and you do that,
the rest a sequential right read and write,
then it's about how fast you are going to be able to repeat from the disk.
And that is given by how fast is the dis rotating The rotation of the disk?
That is a variable part.
You need more.
It's going to take more time.
This is a way to look at it.
Again.
Basically, you have the user thread,
which is going to initiate.
And i'm input operation.
Then you have a queue,
you can have queue.
This is can be in controller,
or it can be in the operating system.
It depends on the implementation.
It depends on the device.
But there is a cure along the way where the request started cured.
If there are multiple requests at the same time,
then it's a controller,
and then it's finally the io device, right?
Io device service time, right?
This is how long I got the request,
how long it takes to satisfy that request.
The metrics here are response times,
and so put response time we saw in the previous slide,
it's s plus n over b what is the bandwidth?
Now, the bandwidth is that require one, the bandwidth,
which one of the bandwidth we really care,
and is from the from the user thread perspective.
It is that we call the effective bandwidth.
Right?
And the affecting bandwidth is when we are saying, like, for instance,
if you remember, like hardest drives,
the circuit is very different when we are reading
randomly random reads or sequential reads.
That is very different, if you remember.
And and that's effective bandwidth.
So effective boundaries for random breed is
much lower than effective boundaries for sequential rates.
The reason is and effective boundary is basically it is how many by sims
send iii read or operation I
performed over how long it took me to read these and bytes that I
don't perform an
operations.
The time it took to perform this operation,
this latency from the previous slide is s plus n over b or you can
also a little bit of re factoring is b over one plus sp over n right?
So now you can see, exactly right.
It's like,
if you read only 1 byte,
this is the denominator will be dominated.
This will be dominated by s by the overhead, right?
Which is include controller time, queue, delay, and things like that.
If you are going to have read a lot of bytes,
this will be dominated by n actually,
the effective bandwidth becomes as similar with a bandwidth of the io device,
like,
or in the case of a hardest drive with a bandwidth of sequential access.
Any questions?
We'll talk more about that plot.
You see, on the right hand side,
the only thing and i'm going to repeat that a few times.
The only thing to keep in mind is that this is the kind of curve you
are going to see.
This is on the xy axis.
You have the utilization,
right?
How much utilization is about the load which is offered to the device,
the system over the capacity of the system.
Right?
How much I can handle?
And if you on x axis,
you see the response, the y axis,
you see the response time.
This is how it looks like initially is going.
And the system is not very loudly.
You have very little loud.
You get very good performance response time is very good.
But you try to grouse,
and after some point is going to shut up,
if the load is equal to the capacity of the system, actually,
the response time can go to infinity,
right?
Can go extremely fast.
Right?
This is the same, like, remember, it's like highway.
When the highway is free,
very late in the night or very early in the morning.
If you go very fast, right?
As a speed like legal speed, hopefully, right?
And if,
on the other hand,
if you start like rush hour,
right?
The delays can be shut up.
Right?
And that's a big,
obviously, is a big problem.
And then is the capacity of the system, right?
Because you're still out at the capacity of the system,
because eventually all the car still get home, right?
So it's not none of them is stuck indefinitely.
Let me give me 1 second.
I think it's the sense of light.
Let me just start the light again.
Sounds good.
I need to move more contributor.
So the factor to latency,
like I mentioned, this kind of s it's about harder control the
the io service time,
device service time, and so forth.
But the most interesting part,
one of the most important things here is a queue,
right?
Because queue here, you have a lot of requests coming in.
You kill them, so you can spend a lot of time in the cure.
Actually, there is a response time shoots up.
It's not because the device,
the aisle device time, service time,
serving a request,
still take the same amount of time.
So this is very important to remember the reasons the response time
shows up is because a cure because they have more and more requests
as they have to wait for the previous request.
To be said, it's like you go into a grocery store.
So the time it takes a clerk to serve a customer,
doesn't depend on the queue size.
Right?
It still takes the same time.
Maybe if the queue is long,
maybe it's going even takes less because going to be hurry.
But it's,
in logic, it ideally doesn't depend on the q size.
However, if there are many people in the store,
you are going to eat more.
Why?
Because the queue is longer.
One of the most interesting and relevant aspects,
it's a queue is of a system is a queue,
and this is what they are going to analyze a little bit.
This is a way you typically present.
You can model the system,
you have arrivals and rivals, use that request,
which arrives like read requests, write requests, packets.
That can be packets which arrive at the outer and things like that.
Then you serve this request like the server.
You send the data out,
you serve the reads and writes and things like that.
Then you have 2 times the queue,
which is a queuing time,
and ts is a serving time.
And the response time is basically dq plus ds the queuing time
for the service time.
Now you have another one.
It's ta which is in this is obviously you have here in this figure.
It's on the x axis.
You have the time.
And the ta is an inter arrival time.
Basically,
in the difference between two consecutive between the arrival
of two consecutive requests,
this is the arrival.
Now, on the y axis,
which is not shown,
I should show here.
If you go down,
you move from down is a time it takes.
It's basically,
it's a response time.
Right?
So what this shows here is that,
sorry,
what it shows here is basically,
you have d queue is like,
it's a time you spend in the queue.
Then ds is a time you spend to service ps to service that request.
After a while you have another request,
which is skew is very little.
Here is a queue.
It's empty.
But it's still probably a time.
Because you still need probably maybe to even if it's one element in the cure,
you need to incur it and then get it out of the cure,
just checking whether the queue is empty.
So there is still a little bit of time you are going to spend.
Right?
But here you are dominated by the service time.
And you see,
whenever if you have a new request,
at least in this example,
you are going to the queue something.
Every response time that it could,
the response time on february quest is going to take the same time.
But now let's do,
so let's introduce a few more metrics.
So a few more metrics here are basically the service rate is
basically is like how
many operations you can perform per second.
Right?
Basically, this is one over ts right?
It's like, if, for instance,
if it takes me to serve a request,
it takes 10 million seconds to serve a request.
How many I can do per second?
1 seconds over 10 million seconds is 100,
then its arrival rate.
And this is one over ta right?
This has request per second.
The request per second.
It's the same, right?
It's like if I am getting every one request,
every 20 millisecond,
then the lambda,
which is request per second.
It's 1/20 million seconds,
1 second over 20 million seconds is 50, right?
And then its utilization utilization is the arrival rate over the service rate.
Or if you plug in this equation,
the formula for the service rate and arrival rate,
you are going to get the service time over the arrival time.
Right?
Basically, what is this saying is that, for instance,
if you have the arrival time,
it's 20 millisecond.
The service time is 10 million seconds.
Then you are going to have 10 million seconds over 20 million seconds.
It's 0.5 utilization will be50%,
which kind of makes sense, right?
If I have one new request arriving every 20 millisecond and one request,
it takes me to process one request,
10 million seconds.
This means that for each request,
i'm going to spend 10 millisecond and i'm going to wait
another 10 millisecond to get the new request.
And I am going to be free half of my time.
Make sense?
What happens on lambda is greater than the mu,
and the arrival rate is greater than the survey.
The rate.
What do you think it happens?
It's a good question.
If it's a for short interval of time, what is a burst?
Then you are going to have the cure to absorb that burst.
The q delay were going to increase.
If it's longer is for a long time,
is it just average arrival rate is greater than the average service rate?
Then the queue will grow indefinitely.
The system is called to be in a stable state.
In general,
what we are going to analyze now in this lecture are our systems which are
a stable means
that the arrival rate is not greater than the service rate.
Good.
This is basically tells you is about if ds over
da it's small,
then we are fine.
And the queue time,
the queuing delay is slow.
But after some.,
if you are going to get one, this is loud.
You see, the loud is for this plot from 0 to 1.
This is the sa over da right?
Before one is fine.
It grows, but it grows a little bit.
But if you are going to go over one,
then it's going to shut up.
Right?
This is a cure delay.
It can be unbounded.
This is the answer to your question.
Gilbert,
if the arrival rate is greater than the service rate,
then the cure will grow unbounded.
Now, let's see how the requests that i've been abused.
And let's see what happens.
Here on the vertical axis,
I have q depths on the horizontal axis against the time.
Here, basically, ii see here the queue depth.
I'm going to have the first requesting the queue.
It's empty.
It's going to be service immediately.
This is where it's going to be.
Server is the server,
the timeline for the server.
It's a rather, I get the queue, I get the request,
i'm going to serve it here.
But now I get the second request.
If i'm getting the second request,
I am going to have to cure and cure it because the survey is already
it's satisfying the previous request.
And now I get a new request.
So a new request, again,
I need to cure it.
Right now, I have two requests in the cure again on the vertical axis down.
You have the size of the cure.
Also I have two in the cure right now.
Now I get another one.
So it's again the first request hasn't finished, being serviced.
So the cure is increasing by another.
Her one request.
I have three requests in the queue.
Now I don't get anything more.
Right?
If I don't anything more,
i'm going to start the set of being say it's a fivefold.
So i'm going to sell the first requesting the queues a wide request.
While I serve the wide request like you,
I still have two requests in the queue.
The light blew on,
and they're all ranger on.
Then when I say I when I finish serving this request,
i'm going to serve the orange request.
Finally is a light blue request.
This is what happens.
And I have a new request and things like that.
Any questions?
The point here is that even the utilization is slow,
even in the average arrival rate,
is lower than the service rate,
much lower level.
You can still have occasional burst.
A lot of events,
a lot of operation alive at the same time.
It's like rush hour,
right over the entire duration of a day.
The arrival of the number of cars on the highway is
significantly lower than the capacity of the highway.
There are some bursts in rush hours is a number of cars.
It's almost at capacity.
And then you experience large effects.
How do you model the birthday arrival?
Now, there is a lot of mathematical models,
but one of the most elegant one,
it's is poisson distribution or distribution.
Exponential distribution.
This is f of x is slumber where lambda is the average arrival rate,
in this case,
or an average mean for that distribution times e power minus
lx this is how it looks like.
This f of fx and this is a lambda.
It's actually the mean arrival rate.
So the mean arrival rate for this distribution,
it's one over lambda.
I'm actually lambda.
I'm taking back.
The lambda represent the inter arrival time between the events I
arrival time in sandova lambda.
And is a nice thing about this.
The exponential distribution is it is what is called memory less.
Memory less means that the future doesn't depend on the past,
right?
And is counter intuitive,
because you are not used with that.
This will say, and maybe sometime this happens,
if you go,
if you arrive at the station like bus station,
how long it takes for the next train to arrive doesn't depend
of when the previous train arrived,
whether it arrived.
The last minute was that he just leaves the station where it was 15 minutes
ago.
This is what?
But because it's memorized,
it's much easier to model.
Right?
It also says,
if you look at this plot,
that this means that a lot of events which are arriving in burst,
rise at interval between them is short.
There are some also very long intervals between events.
So if you look at the events on the timeline that are burst of events
arriving together,
inter arrival between these event is small,
and then you have long pauses,
right?
Long gaps.
Any questions?
You did learn an exponential distribution?
Ii hope in some of your math classes,
right?
Or statistic classes.
Okay?
And now,
with this distribution is,
what are the main mode matrix?
My one of the most important matrix is a mean.
Obviously, the mean of the distribution,
how to compute them in,
like,
it's an integral or the sound you pay for the discrete distribution
of the p of t what is the probability that
event happens that time at t what is the probability that you
are going to have?
In this case?
For instance, an arrival after exact in exactly titan units.
And then you are going to multiply with the t because the inter arrival time.
Right?
This is the mean.
If you have this variance of the square of the standard deviation,
which is you multiply its sum of p of t multiplied by t squared minus m squared.
And m is against the mean.
P is about how long the entire arrival p which
happen is probability p of t and then you square coefficient of variance,
which is a sigma squared by the mean square.
I'm not going to derive this to you.
I'm going to derive something more interesting to you.
You are supposed to know from some of your previous classes.
If not.
This are just the formula you can write on your cheat sheet.
But typically we are going to give you, if I am going,
we are going to ask you in a problem.
But the most important things here is to look at the value of sea,
the sea capture, the burst mess.
It turns out if c is zero,
there is no variance.
This also means the variance is zero square squared of standard deviation,
which means that you have the inter arrival between two events,
between two requests is the same.
Then if c is one,
this means that you have exponential distribution.
Is a memory less distribution.
Completely random, doesn't depend on the past.
If c is 1.5,
you have even adversarial distributions.
The majority of sikhs say, for instance,
or the majority of the inter arrival times are much smaller than the average.
The more c increases,
the more birthday.
You have the distribution,
meaning a lot of events coming,
a lot of requests coming together,
and then long gaps.
And a fuel is obviously the more person, as you have,
the larger the cube will be.
That is during these events.
Right?
If there is no variance,
and if your third load is lower than the service capacity,
than you have no cure,
let's talk more about king's theory.
The queuing theory is very simple.
You have to make some assumption about the distributions.
You have to make some assumptions about how long it takes to serve the request.
What is the distribution to serve a request?
What is the distribution of arrivals?
And based on this,
then you are going to get some formula which will give you
the service response time as a change between delay.
That's what it is.
Okay.
Before talking more about this queuing and giving results
formulas about response time and everything,
let's go through this law.
Little law is called,
it's a very powerful law.
It's very simple, deceptive, simple,
and very general.
This is what it says.
He says you have a bunch of arrivals,
and which are served by a system,
a bunch of requests coming to a system.
They are serving the system.
And what is the average mean of?
What is the average arrivals for the request?
What is the average service for the requests?
And what little law is giving you is how many,
on the average,
how many requests are waiting in the queue to be set?
That's all.
And the formula is a number of requests.
Here I pick jobs.
It's sequel to the mean arrival time,
lambda time,
the response time,
mean response time.
This is what it is.
That's it.
And the beauty of it is that this is true regardless of the structure
of the arrivals.
How it is a burst doesn't depend on the distribution.
Doesn't depend on the distribution of the arrival.
Doesn't it depends on distribution of the service style,
because the results hold for the means.
Right?
It does assume, though,
that their rivals are not larger,
the arrival rate is no larger than mean arrival rate is not larger than this.
Mean service right here.
It's an example.
Just to give you the to capture that intuition on x you have times,
let's say you have a new job or request.
For some reason here,
iii put jobs coming to the system and being serviced.
You have one job every second,
so this is deterministic arrival.
Everyone, every second, you have a new job.
Exactly.
Every second.
Any jobs takes to serve.
5 seconds is what you have, right?
You have the first job starts here, you set 5 seconds,
the second job starts set 5 seconds and so forth.
Now, how many of the jobs you have in the system at any given time?
You can draw a line and the number of jobs you have in the system.
It's the number of jobs this line is going to intersect.
And how many have five?
What is the formula saying?
Number of jobs, a very number of jobs in the system.
It's equal with the average or the mean arrival rate to just 1 times
the mean service response time,
which is five.
It's fine.
Let me try to derive this formula for you.
Okay.
Let's say now we are going to be general,
right?
The jobs can arrive at any time.
They can take any amount of time to be into that are going to be in the system.
Let's talk.
L of I is the response time of job I and n of t is a number of jobs
in the system at time t
this is n of t at this particular time.
You want to see what is the system occupancy?
How many, on the average,
what is the number of jobs in the system?
This n the average of n and n of d this is what you want to compute.
The average of n of d before this, remember, is what I want to get.
Now, let's do some a little bit of math.
Let's assume,
for the simplicity that the height of one of these things, jobs,
which I represented here, each one,
really, the n of t zero n is represents the height of this shape,
the blue shape.
Let's say, in this case,
the hype is forced.
You have four jobs in the system.
Right?
Now, the area of each of these boxes is what?
I so phi, its ally, the length,
is how long it takes.
The job responds time for that particular job.
I times one,
because we said that by convention,
we say that the height is one.
The area s is s one,
the total area here,
for these all the jobs within the time capital t it's s one plus s
two plus csk
it's equal to its l one plus l two plus lk because si it's equal is
li times one.
It's equal is li and why do I do this?
Right?
Now?
What I want to compute this to cure?
Remember that our average pure copenhacy is, what is this?
It's this area over t that is not ending.
I have this shape which I have this area.
And I need to divide on the length of the area,
which is still, in this case,
to get to the average height of the area.
The n average,
the average number of jobs in the system is the average height of the shape,
which is s over p but now we know that s is l of one plus l of two plus l
of k over d now,
now is the beauty of it.
I need to do only the one thing I need to divide by n total and
multiply with n total.
Right?
And total is another number of jobs which arrived during this time being
our service during this time.
It's the same equation,
the equation from the previous one.
But i'm going to divide by n total.
I'm now going to multiply by n total and total.
In this example.
It will be k right?
Because what I showed here like it.
But now I just reverted one,
but is the same thing,
is n total over p plus l one plus lk over n total.
But here is the things right now.
What is n total over t I have
n total jobs arriving during their time t in total over t it's the average.
It's how many?
It's n total over t it's arrival rate mean arrival rate.
If I have one, if I tell you I have 100 jobs and they arrived in10 seconds,
right?
And I ask you,
what is the rivalry?
What do you say?
100 over 10 seconds is ten jobs per second.
This is lambda.
What is l one plus lk over n dot?
L one is the average response time for a job.
L two is a very response time of the second job.
If I had all these jobs up,
the response time of all the jobs,
if I sum up the average response time of all jobs,
and I divide by the number of jobs,
what do I get?
The average response time?
Here you are the average occupancy or the average number of jobs in the system.
It's equal with the average arrival rate of the jobs plus at times, sorry,
the average response time of a job.
Make sense?
Any questions?
Okay.
So again, I ii want to emphasize like this is a great,
a very elegant law,
because it's so simple.
And yet is so general.
Again, doesn't make any assumption of distribution.
You need only to know the average arrival rate and average response time.
Any questions?
Okay?
Now let's do a little bit of hearing theory.
And unfortunately, and I apologize here.
I am going to give you some results.
I'm not going to derive anymore.
So hopefully you enjoy the previous derivation.
But let's talk a little bit about that about this to give you some queuing results,
queuing theory results.
First of all, like I mentioned,
here, we only assume that the system is what we call in equilibrium,
which is Basically the number the arrival rate is not larger,
is no larger than the service site.
We also assume that the cure has no limits.
So therefore, we don't rob requests.
Okay?
Let's assume that the time between two arrivals is random and is memorabulous,
it's exponentially distributed when the time inter arrival time between
successive requests,
it's exponentially distributed.
We are saying that arrival is for us all.
By the way,
if you hear that arrival rate,
lambda service rate is mu one over the t survey.
This is ATS previously we thoughts denoted by ps is that time yourself,
the request.
So you have lambda mean number of arriving request,
customer jobs per second.
Meantime to serve as a customer,
it's say, m squared coefficient of areas of variance.
This is one.
In the case.
Remember, in the case of exponential distribution,
mu is a service rate that one of the TS time to service at request.
Utilization again,
that you saw the formula is a number is arrival rate
over the mean arrival rate over mean service rate,
which is lambda over mu or lambda time.
Deserve I hear?
I just replace mere definition,
which is one of the over the service time.
Now, and if you do that,
you get the utilization its arrival rate times I service time.
What do you want to compute?
Time is spending the queue.
That's what I want to compute.
We also want to compute the length of the queue.
What is the length of the queue?
The length of the cure is lambda of QQ because the system here is a cure.
This is what I'm saying.
The system here is a cure,
right?
You can apply little law to the cure itself,
or you can apply to the entire system.
Here is for the cure yourself.
Okay.
Let's see.
Like I said, when you have exponential distribution for the arrival rates,
inter arrival rates for the requests,
this is also called poisson arrival process.
We assume here that we have one server,
right?
We can have us, there are scenarios,
and you have multiple servers,
and you send the request to if one server sells a request to consider it,
send a request, another server.
And it's memorized service.
So again,
let's assume that the service distribution,
it's also exponential.
It's memory bus.
This system with poisson arrival process,
memory said memory less, service time,
and one server is called mm one cure.
It's again, one server,
inter arrival times are exponentially distributed.
Service time are exponentially distributed.
In this case,
the queuing time,
it's equal with the service time
times u over one minus u what u is activation.
Now, for general distribution,
if you have the service distribution,
if the service time is a general distribution.
And for that,
one only the variance,
the square root of variance,
the c then this is a formula.
It's very similar formula.
One over, let me just move.
It's service time times one over two plus one one plus c this is, again,
square root of a square of variance times 11 over 1 minus 2.
Is it important?
Take away from here.
This equation is a very important aspect here.
Is this fact?
Is this 1 over 1 minus you?
Why it is important?
Because this tells you when the utilization is small,
this factory is small, right?
It's it's basically one u over one if u is very small.
But what happens to the utilization approach is what?
Which is a kiva land with a service, right?
A several arrival, right?
Approaching the service, right?
What happens?
It
gets very large.
The cube becomes very large.
Another important aspect here,
this is food for thought,
is something which is not intuitive, either.
If you goes close to one,
although it's not yet one,
the queuing time goes to infinity.
And they may ask, well, but, hey,
wait a minute.
The you if you eat swan, we should be fine,
because the arrival rate is not greater than the service rate.
But if you is one, the queen is infinite.
Why is that?
We'll talk more next lecture,
and you don't need,
we are not going to be asked this during the exam.
But if the system is very bursting,
there can be gaps.
And during these gaps,
there is nothing in system.
You lose that time, you lost,
you never comes back because of births,
you are going to get in the future,
are going to,
then if you eliminate that gap,
the number of arrival you are going to get in the future is going to be
greater than the server capacity,
because it's kind of these gaps where the system doesn't do anything.
When you have a very bursting arrival.
This is a wasted time.
It's a wasted capacity.
So that capacity cannot get back.
That's why you can you fall behind in terms of capacity,
and you remain always behind.
I I'm trying to give you an intuition,
so it's like,
it's not easy to get the intuition,
but this is good.
Okay.
What else I wanted to say here,
by the way, you notice that for the general service time distribution,
the formula for the queuing delay,
if exponential, you remember for exponential distribution,
what was c one.
If c is one,
the equation,
the queuing time for the general service distribution,
is going to reduce to the formula which you should expect
for the exponential distribution.
Let's take now our simple examples,
and then we are going to conclude the lecturers.
Let's say the user request.
You have ten requests of you want to want a kilobytes disk,
write that request of each or 48 kilobytes data,
and the request.
And the service are exponentially distributed.
Average service says 20 millisecond.
This is controller six time rotation latency and transfer time.
And how utilize is a risk?
Utilization is a formula, remember,
is lambda times the service time.
Besides a formula average time to spending the qdq average the number
of requesting the q now,
this is a cure,
not be noted here.
What is the average response time for this request?
This is the average response time.
It's very simple that the sum between the time is spending
the queue and time to service the request.
Let's do the computation.
Lambda.
It's you have ten requests of a kilobytes,
this per second.
So lambda,
you have a very driving number of customers or request is ten per second.
Ever, it's time to service the customers or a request 10 millisecond.
It was given here.
If you remember,
this is one that I have a very selfish time.
Server utilization is lambda times the service time,
is 0.2 queuing time.
Now you are going to apply because everything is exponentially distributed.
Then you use a formula which is
ATS service standard service time utilization over one minor stabilization.
And you get 5 million seconds.
Average length of the q is lambda times TQ is 0.05 seconds.
Average time, the customer spending,
the sister sister system is a queuing time plus a service time.
So it's through 20 million seconds plus5 million seconds.
Here is 25 million seconds.
There are a lot of materials.
Here you have some pointers.
If you are interested more in the queuing theory,
is great.
This is a fair game.
This is a mistake.
You are going to get this in meter two, not three.
Sorry, for the Tai Po.
This lecture is included for me to do.
And with that,
I am done.
So in summary and remember about,
we look at this,
how we are going to model the systems.
And these systems are modeled are they have a cure?
He said, you spend some time in the cure plus have a speaks overhead,
like rotational latency and so forth,
and you have a transfer.
Then this will impact the effective bandwidth.
Effective bandwidth is not like the device bandwidth,
because of this fix overhead.
And with then we learn a little bit about this skewing theory.
And in particular,
I gave you the day as a the formulas for the queuing delay,
for mm one cures,
everything is exponentially distributed into arrival time.
And the service time and MG one q arrival times are still,
inter arrival times are still exponentially distributed,
but the but the service time has a general distribution.
And remember,
this is a formula for the queuing time,
for the general distribution of the service time.
And remember that in both cases was 71 and MD one q John cues is asking
for the when the utilization approaches one,
then the latency goes to infinity, the queuing delay, and therefore,
the response time goes to infinity.
I'm stopping here.
Good luck to at the midterm and really good luck for the next week.
If you have any questions,
please don't hesitate to ask on piazza.
And i'll see you next week.