Welcome everyone to the second lecture.
Today we are going to learn
about the four fundamental oils operating system concepts.
As always, please ask your questions on q and a channel.
I will stop from time to time to read the questions and answer them.
First, let me start with some announcements.
So I will have for now one office hours on mondays between noon and 1:00 pm
and there is more demand are going to add more of its hours.
Next monday, it's in our office towers, actually, that should be monday,
not wednesday.
It don't be an office hour, memorial day,
and we'll add,
it will be office hour,
will be a zoom.
I will add the link to the zoom on the class web page.
Just a reminder that the drop deadline is this friday,
early drop deadline.
Please.
If you are thinking about dropping this class,
do it right away,
because this will let other people from the waiting list to enroll in the class.
Finally, please,
after the drop deadline start to sign up for the groups.
Remember,
we ask you to have four people in a group and try that all people to attend.
These are the same sections.
This is preferable.
Or maybe if that's not possible,
if there are two sections taught by the same theory,
this is in order to have consistent feedback for your projects.
During the semester.
Again, there are some quick questions on the chart.
Please ask questions on the q and a channel, not on the chart, but now,
one question is that can we have today's lecture slice,
firstly to piazza due to website being done?
Well, hopefully, the website will come back up,
but yes,
we can pause them on piazza.
And a second question is,
when all the pia section preferences form would be released,
not sure any da happy a rather than if you are.
Here, please answer this question.
If not,
alan,
you ask this question,
please also proceed and get outside and we get the answer there.
What do I to section by the same ta so what I mean here is that if not all people,
if there are t as,
that would be t as or some of the t as I have two sections.
If not, all of you in the same group can go to the same section,
pick two sections which are taught by the same pa will the class
expand to get all the people on the wait list?
This class, again,
although it's online, is limited,
because the ta resources and the staff of the class doesn't actually have
any kind of is not the way we do not decide who is going to get
from the wait list,
who is going to get in at all in the class.
Is the department decision?
Please ask them.
We can do much about it when I say I refer to the staff of the class,
myself and the t as and adidas.
Let's move on.
And last thing I want to say is that please avoid private piazza posts.
Because in many cases,
you are not the only one to have a question,
many other people who have the or have the same questions.
If it's a personal questions,
you should use a private pizza post.
But otherwise, please try as much as possible,
not to use it.
So let's go and start with the lecture.
What is an operating system?
We discussed a little bit last time during the last lecture.
This is one slide from the last lecture,
basically saying that the operating system is a software receipt
between hardware and the applications.
It's implements and provides to the application.
A bunch of very useful functionality provides an easy,
convenient abstraction to the applications.
So make it much easier to write the applications and using the raw hardware,
protect access of between the application and between the application
and the operating system to the sharing sources,
provide security and application and provide communication among logical entities.
And if you remember, we also have this slide,
which basically says about how you can look at the operating system
between based on the function it provides.
I wanna on a certain function it provides.
So in one way to look at is like illusionist,
this is when the operating system magically abstract the hardware to the application.
And it provides an illusion that the application use a dedicated machine
with an infinite memory and has access to all the files
and other resources on the same dedicated machines.
So that's a very convenient abstraction for the users
and for the application developer.
In reality,
an application,
sorry, the system,
the harder is shared between multiple applications and multiple users.
So therefore,
you need to arbitrate the access of the resources and share resources
between these applications.
This is when the operating system plays a role of the referee.
So he needs to provide isolation between the processes and the applications.
And you need to protect one process from another and the operating system
from processes.
And finally,
this application in these processes often to implement more sophisticated functionality,
they need to communicate with each other.
They need to share resources.
And they need to use stimuli be used as same services.
And these are all of the operating system to provide the services.
You can think about providing the glue which keep together and make
this application to work together.
So it provides a storage, right?
Which can be used by every application it provides within those systems.
And we provide networking,
which helps the applications communicate with each other.
So that's pretty much we are.
And next,
let me just stop here to see other than any other questions.
No new questions.
And let's go a little bit through the operating system history.
Again,
the operating system abstracting away the harder and making the job
of the application developer easier making it much easier to develop
this application.
This was from very early on since the first computers have been developed.
Okay?
There are several distinct phases.
The first phase, which I alluded last time,
is that when harder was very expensive and human such, it.
So this picture shows a you see a pretty large room that's the room which
hosted the entire computer.
Right?
You need a big room,
almost like a warehouse room to host the entire computer.
Right?
These are extremely expensive.
This very early computers,
maybe you heard about like any arc in 50s,
millions or tens of millions of dollars in today's money.
Then this was a age in which you have very expensive computers and humans
are allowed to be cheap.
Right?
What means that is that you want to optimize to use very efficiently as a computer.
You don't want to necessarily to optimize the time of the humans,
because they are cheap, remember.
Right?
So if they need to,
humans need to to spend more time to optimize their programs and to make
the hardware usage more efficient than so be.
It is perfectly fine.
This was, again,
the age when thomas watson,
the founder and chairman of ibm in 1943,
was saying that I think there is a world market for maybe five computers.
Thomas watson also is calls award a greater salesman by the time
of his death in 56.
Then the next big stage is in 80s, 70s, and 80s,
and is the rise of the personal computer,
right?
In mid 70s,
that when the first apple was released seven and I think it was 76,
you have ibmp cs and compatible computers being released when hardware
was becoming cheaper and human more expensive.
Now everyone was having access wanted to a computer.
And you have a computer on every desk in every home.
That was a vision of bill gates,
a founder and of microsoft.
Finally,
we are today when the hardware is really cheap and humans are really expensive.
Here we are talking about,
you have not only about your phone or tablet of your p cs,
but we are talking about more and more of devices around you.
They have they have processors,
your tv your automotive,
your car,
and each of these platforms and devices,
they do have an operating system on which they will implement,
or developers implement specialized application in the control
of your thermal state to your tv and so forth.
The other think what happens?
And we'll see that this kind of different phases led
to different requirements on the operating systems.
The other thing it's also was driven,
and also these distinct phases is by the hardware,
becoming more and more plentiful, faster, and faster,
and cheaper and cheaper.
This led to from computers who are hosted in one huge room to compute a
switch can be on your watch,
right?
And this lead,
for instance, when in the early brace of the big computer,
the main way to use them as batch processing.
Right?
And what was bash processing means is that you put your job in a cure,
you can actually have you went there to some punish cards,
which one is your ipo program?
And you gives a program to the operators,
and you come the next day to get the results.
Right?
This is what we mean is that from time of the program or is not that important,
then because it was cheap.
And the computer time was very expensive.
You want to have very high utilization.
And one way to have high utilization is that always you have a program to run,
so you have a queue of programs which are submitted,
and you run it one by one,
and then you are going to get the results and it finished.
It takes hours for everyone sometime days.
Then it's going to be multi programming and the multi programming beans.
Now you have they are a little bit cheaper.
And then you want to start to use,
there are computers in a more interactive way.
Multi programming means now that instead of one program at a time,
you have multiple programs running at the same time.
You have that one.
So the time you wait for the program to finish can be reduced.
And then it's time sharing,
which now you are using the computer in a more interactive way.
But as you have terminals which are connected with the computer,
and in that case,
the computer after wait after the human to type to write the program
and then to execute the program,
you have, obviously,
the personal computer is where you have a computer dedicated per human.
In that case,
the computer now is either 99% of the time,
because it's waiting for you for the humans to take some action,
so for the computer to respond and so forth.
And then obiquitous devices are obviously the devices I mentioned rio,
like your thermostate and devices in your car and things like that.
Okay?
The operating system is a huge variety of operating systems in terms of complexity.
You can imagine that the operating system to control on your thermal state
is probably much simpler than operating system
to control super computer.
A small lawyers can be just have hundreds of lines of code
while larger ones can have tens of million slides of code.
And they are very,
very expensive to develop because of the cost of development or is from scratch.
It is very high.
Actually, most modern operating system have a long lineage.
Right?
You can trace back the lineage long tens of years,
the decades ago.
But I saw that in linear means I was there for that.
Operating system from today are some improved version
of some very old operating systems.
This is one lineage,
which is mostly aa stink.
Now, this was from baltics.
It's so the one of the most the first operating system,
which was multitasking multi program and time shared.
This is an ancestor of unix,
and this is then you have adnt unease.
Better claim is bsd unique is old critics annoy us in absd then you have actually,
from mike, he says, michael, ken,
we are going to to learn a little bit about.
It is still developed by kennedy mellon universities and ips this is
plus unix bsd you see here up.
This is berkeley standard distribution is what will be as this stands for.
Then the source used to develop next step.
I'm not sure how many people heard about next step.
They saw the company that steve jobs founded after.
He was pushed Out from apple the first time around.
And eventually next step was acquired by apple,
I think,
in 1997.
And this is how steve jobs came back to apple.
And then like they say there is this history and this now is next step is
as a basis of apple or
s ten and iphone ios then is this other a lineage
from in linux?
The stars developed by andrew tannenbaum from region university
or free university in
amsterdam.
Again, I think in 80s,
this is engaged and linux and android operating system,
and many flavor of linux fuel.
Now, and you use today.
And then,
finally, this lineage from,
again, this is operating system develop for home computer is very early on.
This is first on acpm again, in 70s,
this is an bolster ms does.
This is microsoft,
does is a microsoft first operating system.
And the reason for why microsoft is a company which is today,
and then windows,
this is a lineage,
microsoft operating system, lineage,
ok it's again, a very few,
obviously, all the operating system are going to work today.
You can track down back to probably two or three ancient operating systems.
Here is a question.
What are examples of tasks that computers will be used for in the batch scenarios?
So even today,
when some of the supercomputers, which are, again, very expensive,
today they are using the batch mode.
For instance,
today you can submit a job which perform a very expensive simulation.
Fluid dynamics.
For instance, you want to simulate an airplane engine,
or you can submit a batch to process some huge amount of data which
will take hours.
These are some examples of batch scenarios.
This is another figure by physically showing how in time,
some of the you have on the x axis is a time,
and then on the y axis,
going from very large main frames of very large computers
to handheld and obiquitous devices.
Right?
You can see here also showing you different functionality provided
by the operating systems
and the progression of the operating system here from olympics to unix.
Okay?
So the main thing we are going to learn in this lecture are
these four fundamental operating system constants.
We alluded to them in the last lecture,
but now we are going to go in more of that.
The first one is thread.
This provides you execution context like it fully describes a program state,
which means it's all the state which is needed to run the program,
then is address space.
The other space is the program,
the set of others,
memory addresses within which is a program executed, right?
The code of the program has to be studied in memory.
The data of the program is going to be started in memory.
The output has to be stored in memory,
then is a process.
A process is basically consisting of this other space and a threat.
Right?
But it's consists of all the resources which are required by a program
and all the state,
which is required by the program to run.
And finally, the dual mode,
operation and protection,
this is refers about how is your operating system coexist
on the same hardware with the processes?
And how is the operating system protecting protective from the processes?
Because they use their processes.
If there is no such protection,
it can change the state of the operating system.
The operating system can crash,
so everything hurts like,
so how you are going to avoid that.
So,
sorry,
so let's look a little bit about all the journey from writing the program
to executing the program.
You are writing the program.
This is you already wrote now many programs by now,
you edit the program,
use your editor in max,
or your favorite editor,
or by charm or visual code,
or things like that.
Then you compile is a code.
And as a code is interpreter,
interpreted like python.
But if you have ac code,
you compile it and you get an executable,
right?
Which is a code, executable,
contains a code which can be interpreted.
And it can be around by the processors understands.
Right?
And now this executable is loaded in the memory of the computer.
And then it's executive.
But when it's loaded in memory,
there are several segments of the memory or several partitions of the memory,
where a different kind of data is stored,
one as each each one part is where you keep the partitions.
You sorry,
where you want partition is where you keep the code,
the instructions of the program.
Then you have where you keep the data.
The data you statistically defined.
But I for instance, you say,
and when you create of an array or variables, this is,
and it's static,
then hip.
It's where you define.
You create dynamic data structures.
Like, for instance, this is when you allocate memory,
when you allocate memory, this happens at the run time.
Before the program,
after the program starts executed.
Therefore, the heap is going to change during the run time,
depending of how much dynamic memory you are allocating
for your dynamic data structures.
Finally, you have a stack.
The stack is it's used,
and you use, for instance,
to store the variables,
you are going to declare within a function.
It's also used to store the return address when you call a function.
After the function is done,
you need to know where you go back in the program.
Again,
we'll discuss a lot of more about each of these different types of data
and memory.
And finally, here you have the operating system, memory,
ok so that's pretty much it.
Let me stop and see ok no new questions, please.
Again.
Keep your question coming.
Great.
How you execute the program?
If you remember, and this is from 61 c if you remember,
you basically have a bunch of instructions which are in memory,
then you have a program counter calls opc which point
out to the current instruction being executed from memory.
So what happens when you take the instruction,
which you fetch the instruction,
which is pointed to by the program counter,
and then this instruction is decoded,
and then it's executed.
This is basically down here.
You see the processor, right?
A core.
And the core typically consists from an alio,
aromatic logic unit,
which performs the operation, addition, subtraction, and things like that.
And a bunch of registers,
where are the arguments of these operations?
In many cases,
and registers are very fast to address because they are there very low latency.
And then while after you execute an instruction,
the program counter is increment it.
You are going to the next instruction.
Very simple.
This is another review here about on the right hand side,
you are going to have the memory with a bunch of instructions and a bunch
of data on the right hand side.
On the left hand side, sorry.
You have what is a processor which is fetching the execution,
fetching the instruction and execute the instruction?
And there you have on the left hand side,
a bunch of registers are zero to our 71.
And you have another set of register from f zero grab 30.
The difference typically between the set of registry
because of the second set of register is for floating point operations.
The r zero to our 31 typically are for fixed point operations.
And then you have the program count.
It's, again, you face the instruction at the program counter.
You decoded, you execute it,
possibly using the registers.
Some of the argument of the instruction can be addressed in memory.
And when I say results to the registers or memory,
and then you go to the next instruction and repeat.
So let me see about questions.
The question, is there one program counterpart thread?
The program counters is typically a registered in the car in the processor?
It's typically only one program counters may be true if you have
a user program counter,
but it's one.
What happens?
And we are going to see later in this lecture that when you are going to do
context switching,
what is called when you go to another to start executing a thread.
The first traction you do you take is to load the program counter,
which he says somewhere in memory is a current program counter
of the thread corresponding to the thread into the processor program
account.
Right?
But a program counter from the processor point of view,
it's only one.
It's not perspective.
So let me
just the thread of control.
Again, this contains a state required to run the program.
What does it mean?
Is basically,
it contains,
sorry,
it contains a program counter,
and then it contains also pointers to where all these other kinds
of regions in memory start,
like, for instance, contains for the stack pointer.
The stack pointer is basically where the stack starts from.
It contains a hip pointer,
is the address from the world.
The hip starts growing.
And it contains also what is in registers that I
because the state in the register is used by the instructions.
And assert is executing,
like I mentioned earlier,
when its resident on the processor,
when the state is the stress state is loaded in the processor.
Pc read this program counter,
all the address of the greatest instruction in the thread.
And again,
register whole sum of the root state of the threat is called the state.
That's kind of the what the thread is about.
So all the state which is needed to execute that program counter state
of the registers,
key. for stack pointers and a few others.
Now, the address space is basically the memory addresses or the memory
regions where the data and the code of the programs
are stored.
The addresses are typically,
it's the size of the memory.
Addressable memories is very important of the size of the memory.
The man, the size of the addressable memory,
is given by the number of bits of the processor.
Typically,
if you have a 30 bits processor that are to power 32 or 4 billion addresses,
which means4 megabytes of memory.
If it's byte addressable,
if it's 64 bits is to power 64,
which is a huge amount of memory.
Okay?
This is addressable memory,
like we are going to see.
This is different from the physical memory.
The physical memory can be
smaller and typically smaller than the addressable memories.
And but then you are going to have a process.
You are going to learn.
It's called visualization.
And address translation.
We are going to even talk about this style, this lecture,
which is going to create you the image and the illusion that you have
access to the entire addressable memory in a smaller physical memory.
What happens when you read or write to an address?
Maybe nothing,
or you act like a a regular memory means that you read the value
from that memory and you write the value to that memory.
But perhaps you can ignore rights.
For instance, if you if you are processes writing to address,
it doesn't belong to that process,
then maybe it's going to be ignored.
Or maybe it causes eye operations.
As you'll see that other memory mapped input output
designs and architectures in which,
for instance, if you want to communicate to a device like a keyboard,
you want to read from a keyboard or you want to communicate with a printer.
There are certain defined,
pre defined memory addresses where you have to write.
For instance, it's a pretty fine memory address you read from.
And that's what you are going to get the input from the keyboard,
or is another pretty defined memory address or a range of addresses
where you can write.
And that data is going to the reader.
Or perhaps it causes an exception,
like an example I gave to you earlier on.
And you are going to write to a data to address which he doesn't belong to you,
or say, to the address of an own owned by the operating system.
It can be ignored.
But in many cases, you get a segmentation fault.
You cannot cause the exception.
One exception, the offending program is going to basically stop crashed.
Again, you have a bunch of region or segment.
You have the code segment.
The score segment that already pro mentioned to you contains
the instruction of the program.
You have the stack segment.
I told you what,
again, earlier, what it contains, it contain.
It can contains The variable you are going to declare within a function.
And also the return addresses from a function.
And the stack grows from high to low to grow,
so to speak downwards.
Because you add,
when you call a function,
you are sinks on the stack.
Then you have the heap,
which is for dynamic data when you allocate data during the program execution,
and you're growing from low level of low addresses to high addresses.
So let's see,
there are some questions here.
Where does os save all the state and registered values when changing as task?
It's a thread control block,
pcb this is where it said it starts.
You have a data structure which associated on issue with each thread,
which is managed by the operating system.
And in that block or region,
you save all the state associated with a thread.
When we say that the process has a virtual address space,
zero to ff it doesn't imply that it has free reign to write with our services.
Absolutely.
Let me there are two views of the memory.
And again, this is very important to,
and this is about arbitralization.
It's about creating the illusion.
It's a memory, it's a physical memory,
and the physical memory is partitioned between different processes.
Now, there is also what the illusion, actually,
of the process.
The illusion of the process is that he has an address from 00 to ff he has
an entire outer space.
And the application, in principle,
can can write at any of these addresses.
Okay?
Typically,
the operating system takes care for cells so that the application does
a shoot in its foot.
Right?
For instance, you cannot right on the stack,
because if you can't write on the stack, the program will crash.
Right?
The operating system will put the only post some restrictions.
So you don't have a free ray.
You do see the entire other space.
Again.
You don't have free rain,
but I just come to and to plant the seed.
Now.
We are going to do this to say this over and over,
because there are two views of a memory.
You have physical memory,
which is partitioned between different applications.
They have data code from different applications.
Residing is a physical memory at the same time.
And then you have the virtual memory,
which is basically what is presented to the application.
And there you create the illusion that each application is process,
has access to the full address space with some constraints,
like I explained.
So so here is exactly what I mentioned earlier about the physical memory.
You see, on the right hand side,
you have the physical memory in the physical memory.
As you can see.
You have, on the left hand side,
you have the operating system with and processes, right?
Green, yellow, orange.
Now, in the physical memory,
you can see that you have instructions,
a code and data from different processes.
And they are all is riding in the same physical memory.
Each of this processing is only going to see only its own data.
They shouldn't see the other as a process data.
Now,
what is the multi programming about multi programming about is about having
different processes?
Like ii said earlier,
I said about jobs,
but the process with the process is the same thing.
They have different processes running and share running at the same time
on the same on a single machine.
Right?
Now, how do you give the illusion?
Because so breaking system provides the illusions that despite you have
different processes running at the same time on the same harbor,
each process believes that it is allowed.
Right?
The only way you can give that you have to share,
you have to multiplex resources.
And there are multiple resources.
One is the cpu right?
And if you have a single processor,
how do you provide illusion of having multiple processors one for each processor?
As we discussed last time,
you split the processors in tank quanta.
You give it all time slices,
and you give a time count or a time slice to a different process.
Right?
Say it's 10 million seconds.
The time size is 10 million seconds.
For 10 million seconds,
you around process one,
then we switch to for the next 10 million seconds to process two,
for the next10 million seconds to process three,
and then come back to process on.
This is one way to do it.
So multiplex it in time.
And each this kind of ritual cp us needs to hold this program counter,
start pointer registers and things like that.
So this is a state was associated with the thread,
because when you run something on a problem,
this visual cp us is a threat.
Right?
Obviously,
the question now is about how you switch from a virtual security the next time.
Right?
This is what you do, right?
You use you you save the state of the virtual cp us.
And here on the state of the virtual cpu is the same as a state
of the thread running on that virtual cpu right?
In that time sliced.
And you allowed the state for the next mutual secure,
the next thread you are going to execute.
And then you execute,
you run the next thread.
So it's, again, I just wanted to make sure here it seems i'm not confusing.
You have only once if you,
in this particular case,
and you want to multiplex it,
so you are going to multiplex it in time.
And that for each process is provided with an illusion that it owns a processor,
albeit a slower processor.
Right?
And by the virtual cpu hearing,
means that part time partition,
part of the cpu which is kind of on a by a particular process.
Right?
And when you from the process,
when you have each process,
if you remember,
has a thread,
and again,
we repeat that soon,
and that thread is a part which is running on the process processor
or the visual studio.
Let me you said a program can write on the stack,
but when you write assembly,
we often move the stack pointer and write.
Yes.
That's true.
When basically,
you said the program can write on the stack,
but when you write assembly,
you often move the stack pointer and write to the stack.
You are a bit confused.
So when you write an assembly,
you don't go through the compiler so that you don't have anyone to put
any kind of constraints of what you are going to do.
So you can indeed do almost everything you also need to.
So you need to do that.
But when you write a typical program like in high level languages,
you compile it.
And the compiler is going to put additional constraints about what you
can do with the program now that the cpu is time partition.
Now, in general,
no,
what is exactly slower when in reality, it is multiplex.
What I mean slower is by when I slower,
I imagine that you have acpu and it's,
and if the cpu is partitioned between two processes,
then each process,
and if each process will,
alternatively use a 10 millisecond run for 10 millisecond.
This means that each process will see a processor,
which is half the speed of the original processor.
Right?
Because, for instance, out of one,
second, each process will use acpu only for 500 meters ago.
So it's half cost so half slow as slow as the real cpu
what is done differently for context switching between threads
of the same process versus different processes?
Again, this is probably too early.
We learn a lot.
But so in short,
the answer here is that when you change,
when you switch content to contact switching between the thread,
you only need to switch.
A context switch is a state of the thread,
which is a bunch of registers.
And pointers is very light.
When you are going to switch between different processes,
you need also to switch the state about all the resources, for instance,
memories.
There is aa memory table to ensure the translation
between this virtual address space and physical address space.
There is a file descriptors.
So it's a lot of more state you need to to switch on your switch between processors,
between processes.
Where are these state blocks start?
So strapped block,
slight strap control blocks,
or all this state is stored in the operating system by the operating system
and managed by the operating system.
Isn't there overhead with switching from on virtual cpu to another?
Yes.
Absolutely.
There is an overhead one switching from one village choice abuse to another,
because we need to save on low states like the person who asked the
question correctly identified.
And is it just a necessary inefficiency we accept in order to multiplex?
Yes.
It is.
How about those programs that are time sensitive?
When the programs are time sensitive?
Typically,
you may have an operating system which has real time support
in these operating systems.
You can specify by when a particular task should be executed,
and they are going to ensure that task will be executed by that time.
Or you can other ways you can specify.
And the operating similar guarantee that you are going to get
a minimum share of the cpu if you get a minimum share of the
cpu then presumably,
you are guaranteed that you can finish some of the operations
or your operations in time.
For instance, this is a continuation,
this is question from your friend.
For example, some programs receive data from network,
wouldn't contact switching the program during the transmission caused trouble.
Now, you will is the other way around.
Actually, when you get something from the another,
there is an interrupt.
You are going to interrupt the processes which are
actually application processes which are actually running.
And then after you do the work,
you get the data,
you return from the internet.
And you are going to continue the processes.
Typically,
it's a little bit the other way around.
It's not like a process interrupted transmission or receiving data.
Where is the current start block information being stored
for individual cpu like I mentioned,
this is in the operating system following up on the assembly,
giving you free ring questions.
Are the segmentation faults?
Receipt things, or will you also be prohibitive on the assemble?
Assembly level?
The segmentation falls are the seas?
See things as see thing, right?
It's like an assembly level,
because it gives you a lot of more flexibility, right?
We see you can write all over the place.
But again, when you have like, for instance,
if you run java or things like that,
you cannot do it.
And this is enforced by your compilers.
It can be type is can if you probably heard about being their type safety,
type safe,
then they verify that actually, when you write the program, you cannot,
for instance,
overwrite on the stack, right on the stack.
In short answer, assembly language,
c language, you can do it.
Higher level languages, you cannot do it.
The compilers will take care of that.
What is the state block?
I it is,
maybe if I say state block it,
it's this is not the correct term,
is a thread control block and this process control block.
And this is, again,
the state control block contains all the state,
which is associated with a particular threat,
program counters, stack, pointer,
and addresses and the registers.
What was the difference between a thread control block and process control block?
Like I mentioned,
the process control block has all the state associated with the resources
associated with that process,
right?
Like filed a script daughters and based translation information
and things like that.
Let's move on.
We are the, but thanks for that question.
This is great.
And if I don't answer a particular question,
you can repeat it,
feel free.
Let me see.
Now,
when you have obviously multi,
when you have multiple processes running on the same hardware,
you need to multiply the hardware.
And the basic problem,
what is called this concurrency?
And concurrency meaning,
again, multiple processes wanting to access the same hardware.
Okay?
Because you want to multiplex single cpu memory,
io devices, and things like that.
And remember, again,
the role of the operating system at the same time is to provide
the illusion that each of these processes
own a on a single machine is the only one executing on the machine.
The operating system is in charge to arbitrate,
to coordinate,
to manage all these concurrent activities while providing
this a single machine abstraction to the processors,
the processes.
So that's kind of hard.
So one of the main abstraction,
one of the main resources needs to be multiplex.
A is a physical memory.
The way this is done,
it's using the concepts of virtual memory.
And we can extend that concept to the virtual to the machine,
right to the entire machine.
What we call,
when I said that we provide the illusion to a process that it owns
is dedicated machine,
that machine is called virtual machine.
Or we also referred to it as a virtual machine.
Okay?
Then the question, then,
it's about how to multiply these virtual machines.
The virtual machines has its virtual skip years,
virtual memory, and so forth.
The first system doing this was the system short and interesting name.
It really was a few thousand lines of code,
the os 360,
which arguably was one of the first and probably the first commercial,
successful commercial operating system created by ibm was having at that time,
1 million slides of code.
It was huge.
Today probably you have windows has tens of million slides of code or even more.
It's again,
they just show you another data point
about how complex a separating system came
grew over time.
And this is a funny thing, right?
It's like probably.
And the number of bugs in os 60 were probably the same or larger
than the number of lines of code in the system.
So now,
what are some of the consequences of sharing?
Right?
If you have only threats,
the threads are going to share the same address face,
which means that the threads can have access to the other threads.
Data, for instance.
So they can share,
but these means that they also can change the data of a different threat.
Right?
So that's very important to keep in mind.
And here is a question.
Can threads overwrite operating system functions?
We are not in the class to ask the class and people to answer.
But the answer here is no because the operating system doesn't run
in the same address space.
But it's, again, all the threads in the same operator,
in the same address space,
they can see each other beta.
They can drive read each other a bit as I can write each other a bit.
And this is, and actually,
there are systems in the past,
which have this mode like windows 3.1,
which was most the first really successful windows operating system from microsoft,
and the early mic miking posh operating systems.
This is before oil stand in which you have this kind of threads are the
are in the same other space even more.
They are.
The operating system didn't actively share the cpu among the applications.
Okay?
Instead,
the application have to use this kind of common yield to relinquish the cpu
so other application can wrap,
right?
A misbehaving application who never use yield can monopolize the entire
system and hang every other application.
This kind of,
therefore, what do you want?
Though we want to have this product to have protection, right?
We want that we have two processes.
And this is the concept of process,
is kind of encapsulate the protection,
because the thread in each process can see each other data can modify
each other beta,
but stress from different processes cannot have access to the data
from the other process.
Because the process contains the address space,
the address space.
It's a unit of protection of the address space in the memory.
And here it's here again,
you have two programs of two processes as a brown one and the green one,
process one and process two.
And here a process to shouldn't have access to the memory of frost,
swan shouldn't have access to the operating system memory,
or shouldn't have access to the file descriptor of other processes.
Okay?
Typically, when they try to access resources,
they don't own a process to operating system will cause
a segmentation fault and will crash the offending process.
Let me just,
if there are a few more questions,
how are operating system tested in development when the complexity is very high?
That's why there are so few operating system being developed
a new operating system,
because it's fundamentally extremely hard.
It's just good software engineering practices.
You are very aggressive during the unit testing and then testing and so forth.
Even so with all of these,
because they are so complex.
Many operating systems,
they still have bugs.
I'm not sure I have that plot,
but it is a plot in which you can see like when people debug the operating system,
your initially you are going to have a lot of bugs.
And then after a while,
the box, the rate at which new bucks are occur,
it's reducing.
This kind of ones are very flat,
and then you should the operating system.
This doesn't mean that you have zero box.
It just seems that the number of boxes rarely enough,
the operating system is usable.
All cp us share the same resources.
It is ii was saying problem,
he spoke there by saying the question is by saying they all cpu share
the same resources.
It is referring to stress within a single process
or process sharing resources and so forth.
I was referring at basically all threads in the same process,
share the same resources.
Then all processes also share the same physical resources in terms
of the cpu and in terms of physical memory.
Okay?
Power address space is allowed.
It seems inefficient to lock a large blocks or have many small blocks.
There is a big trade off here between having small blocks and large blocks.
You have what is called internal fragmentation or external fragmentation.
For instance, with large blocks,
if you don't use the entire block,
you are located, then you wear this memory,
something like and so,
but so you need to be smart about it.
Today's operating systems allocate the memory in what?
In small blocks or pages,
which are a few kilobytes,
four kilobytes, 16 kilobytes of 72 kilobytes.
And then you have many of these small blocks,
then you need to manage them efficiently.
And we are going to learn how this is done.
Ideally, would application use yield when they are performing?
Absolutely, that's a great..
Sorry,
that to read the full question, ideally,
what application is yield when they are performing our operations.
That's exactly the case.
When you are going to send some data,
then you can do yelled because you can wait for, excuse me,
or when you are going to execute the yield,
or you can when the interaction on the application is interactive,
like an editor on a click on the keyboard,
then you see the characters appearing on the screen.
In that case,
the editor will do yield after each time after he displays a character.
And it's going to wait for the next character to be typed into what I
have to get from the keyboard.
What does threads can share instruction mean on the previous slide?
This means that again,
the threads are in the same address space.
And,
for instance,
even between processes, you can share that.
But if you have the same user, same libraries,
and multiple study,
the same libraries,
you are going to have only one copy of the library,
which is going to be shared by the threads.
You are not going to have multiple copies.
Here is another picture showing the boundary protection boundary,
and how the row resources access to the row resources is protected
from the processes.
And like I we discussed last time,
I we already said a few times this lecture and this lecture,
the os operating system isolate processes from each other,
make sure they don't read and write data from each other.
The operating system also isolate itself from other processes.
Again, the challenge here because all of those run on the same harbor,
this is, again,
some,
again, summary and repeating what was in the previous slide,
maybe with a little bit more details.
The operating system must protect itself from the user programs,
from the user processes.
And what does it mean?
I need to and why is that needed?
Is obviously for security,
if the operating system is not protecting,
and then it's easier for an application to break into another application.
This is the confidential data or private data.
I just mentioned about the privacy in the same example.
And one of the amazing is reliability, right?
If the operating system fails,
then the computer it's any unusable,
the operating system.
It better runs at all times.
And fairness,
it's, again,
the operating system is the one which ensures that the processes,
different processes get a fair access to the harbor program.
Like I mentioned,
the operating system is to protect user programs from one another.
One of the primary mechanisms of protections.
It's a translation.
And we'll see that next.
And the translation ensure that the process can only touch
its own address space and cannot touch
the address physical addresses of another process.
There are a few of other mechanics,
like political edge instruction that can be only executed
on by the operating system.
There are some special registers.
Only operating system has access to the circumstances.
So far.
We talk about threads,
we talked about addresses,
we also talk quite a bit about processes.
This is, again, to make it explicit.
Once more, the process is basically another space+1 or more threats.
So processes allocate resources.
Then it has a thread,
which basically is a unit of execution.
Why do you have processes?
Because the processes protect from each other?
Stress do not protect from each other.
They share our same other space.
They share all the resources within a process.
However, threads are more efficient like we discussed.
The context switching between the threading the same process is
much quicker than between threads and different processes.
Also, so communication between studies in the same process much faster,
because you can use share memory.
You can use the other space which is already shared between the stress,
to communicate, between the stress,
between processes.
You need to communicate through other means,
and you need to contact you between the processes,
which is far more expensive.
And typical in application consist of one or more processes.
A process consists of one,
more one or more threats.
Here, you can see in this figure,
on the left hand side, you see one process with a single stretch.
Right?
You can see what belongs you have.
The process owns is that you have the memory,
others, other space.
You have the code data, file,
card file,
descriptors that I used to stack.
This belongs to a process.
And now on the right hand side,
you have different threading the same process.
Here you can see notice at the top,
the code and the data and the file descriptors,
all these resources are shared across all the threads in the different
in the same process.
What is not shared is the execution state of his thread.
So his thread come its own registers from its own stack.
Right?
Registers includes a program counter as a stack pointer and things like that.
Okay?
And the address encapsulate protection.
Right?
It's a passive part of the process.
The thread is an active part,
concurrent concurrence,
encapsulate concurrence.
Why?
Multiple stress for other space?
Too bad?
You cannot.
It's hard to have this question answering.
You have in the class on this web another.
But you want to have more because you want to
build higher performance applications.
Like, for instance, if you have an application which is doing,
you have waiting from the keyboard and they're doing some processing
like rendering graphics and things like that.
You are and a as a result of what are the users?
It's users input.
Then you are going to have two threads.
You want this stress to communicate between others to send the user input
To the thread,
which is being rendering.
You want these two threads to be in the same process.
If they are not in the same processes,
then you're going to be in a different process.
You need to incur contact switching and see like that,
which is going to be much less efficient.
That's one example.
Some example, some questions.
Now,
how can application have multiple processes?
Is it if it needs multiple instances of a CPU or something?
What the practical reasoning for this,
I thought it was 1~1.
There are many reasons,
a multiple and application can have multiple processes.
And let me give you an extreme example.
And then you can imagine that will happen also on a single machine.
An application like Facebook has obviously multiple processes because runs
on different machines.
You have one part which is running on your machine.
It's the front end,
and then a path which is running on the back end.
Right?
You can imagine many of these applications like that could be client and server.
Some are part of the application is handling, say,
an access to the database.
And some part of the application is handling the front end.
Then you can have a multi user application,
and then you want to isolate the user from each other
in the same application for each year that you are going to provide
the different process,
right?
Or you want to process to have stronger isolation, like, for instance,
in your browser,
in your browser, you have different taps.
And if every tap is,
you run it in the same process,
then you have no protection.
Therefore, a misbehaving web page can crash your browser.
If you have each other process and you have strong isolation between processes.
So these are quite a few examples.
Now,
we are not going in details,
but there are more things between processes and threads.
There are actually other ways people try to maintain the efficiency
to preserve the efficiency of the thread,
but are some protection which you have for across from processes.
We are not going to discuss about this, though,
but hopefully answer that question,
that attack doesn't depend on waiting,
can take over while the other is waiting,
even if the superior is multiplex.
I'm afraid I don't.
This is a statement I
that.
But what the statement said is correct.
The task which doesn't depend on waiting,
can take over the task which depends on waiting.
Is it going to be suspended to wait for some part and so on and on a task
which a process which waits for an event to happen?
Like getting an input event from getting some data from the network
is suspended and waiting for that event to happen.
And during that time another process can run.
The operating system can takes care of that.
Okay?
First, finally, the force operating system concept is dual mode operation.
The old mode operation is fundamentally concern about how you are going to share
the hardware,
the machine between processes,
the user processes and the operating system.
Typically, this happens.
You have 2 months for that.
You have a user mode,
which is used when you run a user process.
And the kernel amount,
which is used on the operating system runs.
The reason for that is the operating system actually has access to a lot
of more resources and
even to processes resources during when it is running.
Right?
The way to differentiate between these two mouths is you have a bit.
It's a user system mode beat.
When you set to zero, for instance,
it's a user mode.
He said to one is kernel mode,
how the transition happened from a user process to a kernel to the happens
from the user to kernel.
You set the system out now,
save the user program counters.
And all the state of that particular thread execution state.
And then from the care number,
they use their transition.
You clear, the system and restored as an appropriate user program counter.
Right?
And you return from the interrupt.
And here how you,
as a user mode and the kennel mode interact with each other.
So on one hand,
from the canon mode, you have exact.
And this is how you run a process that throw you the kernel.
And the operating system is launching a new process.
Then when the process exits,
you return to the kernel.
The kernel is taking care of freeing all the resources,
allocated that process.
So these processes, these are resources,
can be used by other processes.
Then it's a system call.
This is one operating system.
I'm sorry, when the user process requires some functionality,
some services invoke some services from the operating system.
Example of some services like accessing a file,
sending some data,
reading input data from the keyboard.
This is return,
this is after the operating system satisfies this request,
then is returning control back to the user.
And then there are user interrupts.
The user interacts.
One example is basically you can have a secure,
you can actually kill a process.
That's one example, a of a user interrupt.
There are also interrupted,
come from the hardware,
like when packet arrives,
when you click on a keyboard,
then you have an interrupt.
The operator gives a mystery, the symbols.
Okay?
Then you can return from the interrupt.
It's a user level interrupt.
You return to the internet from the interrupt,
the returns, a control,
eventually to the user.
And finally,
there are exceptions.
And exceptions are when the user of somehow
the program is doing something which is not allowed,
like or for instance,
you can have division by zero.