Hello, everyone.
Welcome to today's lecture.
And today we are going to wrap up the discussion about the performance,
and then we are going to spend the main bulk of the lecture on file systems.
Let me start.
So just to recap from last week,
last week, we talk a little bit about performance.
This is one way to model the performance, in particular,
for something like a network.
We are talking then that, for instance,
if you send a packet with a certain number of b beats, say,
small b the network capacity,
it's b capital b beats per second.
Then this is a formula for latency a you have a factor s which
is overhead to send that packet,
for instance, of the system call.
And then plus a variable part,
which is b is a number of it in the packet over the capacity of the link,
capital b this formula also works reasonably well for transferring data
from the disk.
In this case,
a thick the s it's represent the rotational latency,
plastic time.
This is one, and this is a formula for the latency.
And you see, here is shown on this plot with a blue line.
The intercept of the blue line with the y axis represents the s in this case,
it's1,000 micro seconds.
And then here,
the slope represent the bandwidth of the particular link.
In this particular case,
we are going to have a link of 100 garbage per second.
S was 1,000 micro seconds or 1 million seconds.
Then b is here on the y axis.
B it's 5,000 beats.
Then then you are going to get the corresponding 5,000 of our
I think that should be bytes is 5,000.
It's 5,000,
55100,000÷12 hundred one,
2121hundred twenty five megabytes per second.
That will give you 4,000 micro seconds or 4 millisecond.
If you are to s which is 1 millisecond,
you are going to get 5 millisecond or 5,000 microsecond ok and then the other
important matrix here is the effective bandwidth,
which is basically,
if i'm sending a packet of this length,
what is the effective boundaries for that?
Sending that packet?
And that obviously is a packet size.
In this case, b over the time,
it takes to send a packet,
which it does includes as the fix overhead.
And this is a formula,
b b capital b times s over b small b plus one.
You notice that if s is zero,
then the effective bandwidth is equal with capital b which is expected,
right?
Because there is no fixed overhead.
Then the effective bandwidth,
you can send data as fast as the capacitor of the link.
One important metric here is about its 1/2 power bandwidth.
And half power boundary is a way to think about it.
Is basically what is the size of the packet?
In this case,
I need to send such that the effective boundary is to be half
of the capacity of the league.
The overhead is not that very high overhead.
It just cuts my effective.
My capacity to have.
Right here is red.
You can see this curve with red is the effective bandwidth,
again, versus the capacity of the link when the number of bits,
when the number of vc zero,
obviously, here you have effective bandwidth.
It's zero.
On this plot, here on the right,
this is a plot which has two y axis.
On the left hand side is the latency, is a blue one.
The blue curve of the blue line,
and the right hand side,
you are going to have the bandwidth effective bandwidth, which is a red.
Any questions?
Next, remember that we also did a little bit of queuing theory,
mostly providing you some formula,
just summarize them here.
This is topic it's covered.
This is part of the exam,
the midterm topics sub you may get the problem,
which is about doing theory or about performers.
I have performance.
Anyway,
here,
you remember that this is a a queuing model.
Obviously,
it's called the queuing model for a reason.
It has a queue.
You have a bunch of requests here with the arrival rate,
lambda a lambda is a number of requests,
average number of requests per second arriving to the cure.
The requests are removed from the queue as fast as they can be processed
by a server.
And the server process each request as a service rate,
mu mu is over and over the service time.
How long it takes to service a particular request?
The way to think about if the server takes 100 million seconds to server request,
then obviously, mu,
it's 1 second over 100 million seconds is then,
because you're gonna set of ten requests per second.
So then another important parameter is square coefficient of variance
to characterize the systems.
The several utilization,
the several realization is basically the average arrival rate
over the average service rate.
And fundamentally,
you do want these parameters to be less than one,
because this would mean that the system is in the stable regime that
and the stable regime,
if the arrival rate is slower,
then the service capacity about how fast the set the request can be set.
If you send more, obviously,
the system will not be in a stable region,
which means that the queries,
the cure were growing different indefinitely,
right?
As more request comes in.
And the subsystem cannot keep up with serving these requests.
Okay?
All the results, typically,
in the queuing theory,
assume that raw is great,
is less than one.
Then the parameters you have to compute is at times you spend in the queue.
Do we know how long it takes a request to be settled?
He still is on the settle.
So now we need to understand how long it takes a request to in
is going to spend in the queue.
So then by adding that,
do we know the service time for the queuing time?
We know how much a request trend in the entire system,
which is what matters from the user perspective.
And then we also went to,
we learn about the little law.
The little law is allows you to compute the queue line of by
just multiplying the mean arrival rate
plus times this spending,
the time times the time average time spent in the queue.
This are some of the results we went over last time.
Again.
This is a recap, which may help you for the tomorrow's midterm.
Tq is for mmiq which is, remember,
mmq is one of the simplest queues out there.
It has one is for means that it has one server.
And the first time refers to the distribution of the arrival rate.
This means that into the intervals
between two consecutive requests arriving is exponentially distributed.
Or it's also called poisson distribution of the arrival rate.
And also, the service time is exponentially distributed.
It's, again, the time it takes the set of its exponentially distributed.
The formula here is the set of a times row over one minus row
for a more general cure.
Where is a serving time?
It's general.
It just characterized by this c we know only about the square coefficient
of variance.
You have a very similar formula.
Only the second parameters in the formula is different.
But the real main point to notice about this formula are this last term,
which is rho over one or minus rho.
This capture what I said earlier,
that if raw is should be less than one,
that if it's equal or greater than one,
then the system will not be in a stable region.
This is a plot showing you roughly how the response time
and the service time is looking
versus a throughput or utilization versus row.
So on the x axis is basically row is from zero, say, to one.
And this is a response time.
The response time is a queuing time for the service time.
A as a role goes to on.
This is going to be dominated by the queuing time,
because the queuing time is going to grow.
A one row gets close to one,
then this goes to infinity.
Any questions?
Now let's talk about how we are going to optimize the performance.
What are the ways to optimize it?
And this is what we are going to discuss over the next several slides.
And again,
if you look about io for an io device,
you are going to have the user strategy.
This is where the program is running.
Then you see, you are going to send requests,
say, read or write from this particular file,
which is from that part of one particular device.
And these requests are cured,
then are submitted to a controller.
And the controller is going to program the other device to read and write
the particular data,
how you are going to improve this system.
There are a few ways, one speed, right?
You can make everything faster.
Each of these components, you can make it faster.
You reduce the overhead of the context switching.
You have also some context switching here of the controller of the device
that I do buy a discreet
or taste faster with a lower sick time.
Another way is parallel is is basically you can paralyze,
you can have inside.
You can have multiple queues.
If the queue of selection are expensive.
Or instead of an aisle device,
you may have a multiply a device.
You can, for instance,
probably you can have two disks,
and then you are going to strive the data across disks.
So therefore,
or you just partition the data between disks,
when different requests can run at the same time on,
if they are going to request data on different disks,
then it's overlapped.
Right?
And this applies to different parts of this kind of pipeline.
For instance, for the thread,
you send a request,
you are waiting for the request.
You can do some useful work instead of just wait.
The same thing here is like for the controller,
as you program the current request and your programs that io device to ask
three to satisfy the current request.
Once you do that and you send the request to our device,
then you can process the next request.
The one important aspect here is that one way you to look at this pipeline,
say you want to improve the performance here,
what you are going to do,
the engineering way to look about and or soft engineering way.
The sound way to do it is to look what is a bottlenecks are,
which is a bottleneck,
which is a slower spot in this chain,
then you are going to focus on that bottleneck part to improve the performance.
Because if you improve the performance of something which is already fast,
not the slowest link on in the chain,
then the engine performance will not improve much.
Remember, the queues are here to absorb the burst.
The queues is that because the requests are not going,
where are equally distanced in time?
They can arrive a in aa bunch of requests at the same time.
The controller cannot settle this bunch of requests at the same time.
So you need to incure them,
because if they don't have a queue,
you need to drop on.
The floor is request.
You are going to fail satisfying these requests.
And finally, another things we didn't discuss last time,
it is one other techniques in these kind of systems.
Its the admission control basically says, look,
and it's an admission control.
Why you have a mission control in general,
is that you basically admission control say that I refuse to,
i'm telling you this request I cannot handle.
So the thread asked wants to submit a request and i'm saying the controller
or the queue itself,
saying I can no longer in queue this request on come later.
This also typically happens if we want to ensure to limit to provide
guarantees in terms
of the or end to end latency,
of end to end response time in order to provide.
So basically saying, if i'm going to accept the request,
i'm going to guarantee that i'm going to serve this request and say100 millisecond.
Right?
If I cannot,
I if there is no admission controls and I cannot make that guarantee
because if there are a a lot of quest coming,
which is exceeds the capacity of my system,
I cannot guarantee that each request is going to be processed within 100 millisecond.
Admission control.
Place is hand in hand with limiting the delay.
If you want to have guarantees on the end to end delay.
Any questions?
Can you give an example from real life where the admission control is employed?
Any example,
the red lights on the entrance of the highway?
That's exactly, that's a great example.
And real time systems,
although I was that I wouldn't call it real timeline,
red lights on the entrance of the highway.
That's a great example.
And there are many other examples, like, for instance,
in during when there are more restriction on during covet during the pandemics,
some shops, you limit the number of customers who are inside.
So in order to make sure that they can keep distance among themselves,
there are even more obvious examples.
Like when you fly on a plane,
here is a mission control.
It's your seat, right?
You cannot.
It's not like in a bus in which there is no mission control anyone can get in.
Ii guess it's a natural one,
no longer people who are no longer fit in a bus
and that's a natural push back mechanism.
But there are many examples in real life when you are having this.
So to speak admission control back like cross white list.
That's a great one.
Richard, that's great.
Thank you.
So any that is performance highest.
Remember, obviously, one,
there are sequential reads where and this is sample.
And we are going to see this is for the next few slides.
There is another one.
There is so much work.
You get so many requests you can piggyback.
Basically, you can have so many requests,
but can the order the request says that you can serve
this request much more effectively?
We'll see that a lot a in a bit.
Now, if the system is mostly idle,
it's perfectly fine to be inefficient.
No one cares, right?
And burst.
This is an important point, right?
When you have a bust,
meaning that you get more requires and the system can handle.
So you need to choose us is boss's threat or should be threat there,
because they can increase the latency, right?
Because it increases requests.
But it's also an opportunity because you can do this figure backing you can.
Again, the audience, the request, as we'll see,
in a few slides where you can do batching meetings,
you can, for instance,
you have many requests.
You can go on context switching or a function calls.
You can think about you can do one context switching to handle multiple
of these requests at the same time.
You are mortar is a context switching across multiple requests.
You can also waste the space for speed.
For instance, you can,
when you write on the disk,
like, let's see, what will be a a good examples.
You can have,
you can have,
for instance, for base tables.
For page tables, you can have additional hash maps,
which are going to keep in order to locate to map
the virtual pages to the page numbers to the physical page numbers.
Another way to do it is to increase the size of the tlb another way
to increase the performance in what you learn in,
we learn in the past is to increase the cache size.
In order to reduce to also improve the performance,
but for improve system performance,
program performance,
you can also increase the memory size.
There is a ballet anomaly with,
as you now for a certain a patriots replacement of policies,
increasing the size of the memory,
of the size of the cash,
doesn't necessarily reduce the number of false space faults.
But in general,
for many of these pay replacement policy,
like alu that's increasing the memory size,
always, really doesn't will likely decrease,
most likely will decrease the number of page four.
You set a few examples where you can have increase the number of the space
to or increase the space and to improve the speed.
And other techniques are reduced overheads through user level drivers.
So basically, if you can implement the function,
it is a user level,
you may avoid the context switching because you don't need operating system
in order to handle these requests.
And the other one is,
like I mentioned earlier,
the overlap.
So are you goodbye while you are doing waiting for an hour to complete?
You are doing the useful of more useful work.
And this can happen in multiple levels.
It can happen in as your operating system when our operating system on a thread
is blog on aiod by on io request,
is going to switch it out.
It putting the thread on the waiting queue and is going to schedule.
The operating system is going to schedule a new thread,
which is on the ridicule.
So now we are going to look into a beetle into the disk schedule,
right?
The disk, remember,
is quite complicated.
I do has multiple plates.
Each place has two surfaces up, down,
and then you have cylinders and sectors.
So when a request comes in from the operating system to read or write
on the disk,
is going to tell you,
typically is telling you what is a cylinder, the face,
the surface,
and what is the second.
Right?
Here we are talking,
we are considering a similar example,
or you have the just a cylinder and the sector.
Is this how the request to look like?
In this case,
you have two numbers for it requires a cylinder and the sector.
The request also is going to specify what is a read and write.
And because this is slow,
more likely you are going to have some requests which are cute.
Okay.
Now, the interesting aspect here,
the requests are, in general, are independent,
are in general independent.
So now the question is how you are going to serve this request?
A simpler story is five,
right?
You send the request in the order when you arrive.
This is fair among the request that is fair with respect to the order
in the submit the request.
But it can be very long six.
Why?
Because the head can go randomly from one cylinder or one track to another.
Right?
You don't run that, because you remember the sick time is very expensive,
as well, as, you know,
rotational latency.
So you don't want to go to,
do you want to be smarter than that?
That'll be a smart way to do it, right?
If you want to minimize a sick time,
why is yourself a request?
You are in a certain position on the disk.
You want to look in the cure and take the request.
It's closest to you,
because if the request is closest to you,
are going to minimize the sector.
This is short a 6 time.
First, right?
You pick the request that it closes to the head on the disk.
In general,
you also need to include the rotational delay,
not only the sick time,
but for now, let's simplify it only to sick time.
So now the sick will reduce the time if you look.
But what is not good?
It's got mainly to starvation.
Like, for instance,
if a lot of requests come and they are clustered close by,
then according to these disciplines,
you are shorter, sick time.
First, you are going to serve this request and the request,
which is farther a lot,
which is a farmer.
Like for instance,
at the edge of the disk,
may wait for a long time to be service.
Make sense?
So you're downtown that.
So again,
greater very sick time, but it's unfair.
Can cause salvation.
One solution to that is cap.
It's a pretty nice solution.
These are what you see here.
These numbers think about.
These are trucks or cylinders.
Right?
A cylinder is all the tracks,
which are under the heads on different bladders.
So scan is basically you start going into one direction,
either to the issues of the disk or to the inside of the disk.
You are only going to set the request in the direction you are going.
Right?
You send the request on, say,
track 53.
Then you look in the queue and you have multiple requests,
say you pick the one which is closest to you in the direction you are going
is 3037.
Then the next one,
it's 14 and so forth.
And in these times, for instance,
if when yourself the request 53,
you get the request 65.
This is closest to you according to the shelter 6 time first yourself,
this request,
because it's not in the request on track 65 is not in the direction
of your movement.
You are going to ignore it.
You go until the last request in your direction,
and then after reverse,
here, I say, no starvation,
but still retain a flavor of shortest 6 times.
First.
Why is that?
Tell me why is that?
Why do we still have a problem with this one with cap?
By the way,
it's called elevator algorithm.
Can you think about that scan?
Excavate any unfairness.
And why?
If
I listen to say you may never embarrasses,
does keep arriving at the same spot.
So basically on the same track, that's true.
That's a pretty edge case.
It's a good asset,
but it's a little bit edge.
What else can you think about some other requests which will get preferential
treatment if they are in some region of the disk versus others.
Carol, ask a question,
how do we define the initial direction for a scan?
I guess I it's a good question.
I think ii don't know,
but I don't think it matters.
You can,
you can choose any anyone initially?
Yeah.
There is more data on the outer rings.
So traveling,
it's favored.
Yeah,
you are, right?
It's like, let me see.
It's also a question here.
It's the same question.
So carl, it's, again, the answer to your question.
I already find the initial directions.
I think it doesn't matter.
You can,
but I I do not know,
and I don't see a reason.
So that's very important.
Going back now,
it is going back about when this scan is not fair.
So hearing one is not fair,
which requests are fate out of for each request,
thus can provide advantage, favor them.
So here the request in the middle,
you get quicker to the request in the middle.
Right?
Like, for instance, I can't go to a request.
I say it takes1 million seconds to go from one and to another.
Right?
If I missed a request, arrives here,
just after the scan has passed in that direction, just I missed it.
I say, goes 0.5 million seconds to one.
And I know it turns 0.5 million seconds to come to me.
I wait for 1 millisecond.
But if this happens when i'm at the edge,
so I just missed the hat which now goes towards the inside of the disk,
then you have to wait for 2 millisecond.
Need to wait 1 millisecond to go all the way to the inside
and 1 millisecond to go back.
Again, I am over simplifying things here,
but just give you a sense.
So scan favors the request which are in the middle,
right?
And not the request which are at the edges.
What is the solution here?
While the solution is circular scan or the sea scan?
This basically just go one direction.
So say, go always,
you sell the request only in one direction.
When you are done,
results immediately go to all the other age and start serving them again.
That's kind of what it is.
But I say, if I missed, if I request,
I just misses the head.
No matter what the request is,
on the average,
is going to wait for the same time for the hat to come to be back,
to be self.
This is not biased towards the pages in the middle.
Finally, I mentioned that you can hide the latency.
How do you hide the io latency?
If the blocking interface is a way to already discussed,
you have a block,
read and write,
system call, you put process operating system,
put processors to sleep until the data is ready.
The request is served.
And during this time,
the operating system schedules,
tasks already tasks,
which out of can use acpu non blocking interfaces?
Don't wait.
Basically, this, you remember,
this is a interface in which are just going to issues and requests.
But then returns immediately.
You just after you return, you do something else.
Right?
Then later you need to go and see whether you got the data or
you wrote the data to the canon.
I synchronous interface is stimulated.
Again, it's like in the non blocking interface,
it returns immediately the request,
because in this case, for instance,
when you get the data,
you allocate the buffer,
you give the pointer as a buffer.
And there is a operating system,
basically put the data when available starting from this pointer,
right in the buffer.
And then let me know when you send the data is the same.
Right?
You are going to create a buffer.
You are going there,
you are going to want,
you are where you put the data or you want to send,
then you give to the kernel to the os in the right operation,
in the right system call,
you gives a pointer of the buffer you want to be transferred.
So now recall the entire era here for the aisle.
This is a top part,
a which appraisal pre,
which provides api and the abstraction to the applications.
Whether it's streams or it's a block,
api plus the system calls open,
read, write, and clouds.
Then at the bottom were so covered.
Last time.
This is about aisle drivers, controllers, right?
These are the drivers which are interacting with the physical device.
Read and write the data to the physical device.
The middle is a system which kind of makes a conversion, in some sense,
from the api which is provided to the application by the operating system.
And the api of the aisle driver,
which is a block interface in general,
more precisely,
for the api for the higher level for the application.
You typically have a variable size buffer for the file system,
which are going to talk more about this.
You are going to have blocks,
but the blocks are logically indexed.
These are where the data is stored,
right?
Logically indexed,
meaning that the index in the operating system is not the same index,
which of that block on the physical device.
This is done by the harder device and by their controllers,
mapping from this block device,
from the operating system to the blocks,
all the sectors on the harvey stripes.
Remember that the blocks in the operating system are typically have
like 20 four kilobytes.
And sectors on the hardest drives are smaller.
There are 512 bytes.
So you have typical, you can have eight sectors for each,
but a block requires eight sectors.
And you have an ssd you remember,
you have these flash translation layers,
which again, maps a logical index of the blocks to the physical blocks.
That's pretty much what you have and also have your asian pages.
Let's look, now we are going to start looking more a little bit,
more depths to the file system.
One way to define it, like I mentioned,
it's a layer of the operating system that maps is
the api provided to the application,
which is files,
directories,
a stream of bytes into lower level,
api of the io devices,
which is a block interface.
There are a few things here.
This needs to be done the operating system.
And that's naming,
you need to find file by name.
You don't give to the osa block where the data is.
You let operating system worry about mapping between the file name and the block.
This is part of the organization.
Also part of the organization is about the file names are typically within directories.
So you need also to locate the file name within a particular directory,
also need to provide protection.
We enforce access restriction.
When do you do that?
When you open the file?
Typically?
Those finally reliability,
why do you still store the data on the disk?
Because it's durable.
You want to survive data to survive when there are crashes or when
your laptop is followed out.
So from the user perspective,
then I have some data structures which I want to restore
those data structure beautifully.
That's what I want as a user.
That was a file system.
I should offer me.
Now, from the system views,
i'm talking here about the call interface.
The api is the boundary of the boundary between the operating system and
the user face.
The system sees what it doesn't have any idea about what data structure
the application has.
It just see a bunch of bites,
a collection of bites,
the system of then it has needs to take this collection of bytes,
this bunch of bytes and write them on the this device,
on the device hardest drive.
Then the system view that it's inside the kernel.
This is the one which interfaces to the devices.
It takes a collection of block,
and it sees a collection of,
instead of takes a collection of bytes and map them to a collection of blocks.
The collection of blocks are still logically identified.
Logically, again,
means that is either identification is not the physical identification,
or these blocks are on the disk.
And like I mentioned,
the block size is typically greater than sector size.
Let's see what happens when, for instance,
the user says to the operating system,
I want buys between 2 and 12 from this file.
The operating system has to face the block corresponding to those bytes,
and just returns the correct portion to the operating system to the application.
What about on the right by two between two and 12?
You fetch the block from the disk.
You modify the relevant portion,
and you write down the block, the block.
So you take for writing these 10 bytes,
you get the block,
which is four kilobytes,
update these 10 bytes,
and then ride back the four kilobytes.
So every sink between the operating system and the devices is a block ground.
Large.
Therefore, if you you all always are going to pay the overhead of reading
and writing blocks as a blog analytic.
So let's it's again a file system.
You have directories and files.
Director, you can think about that the user visible index,
mapping names to files.
And the disk is just a linear of array of sectors.
You can look, right?
It's a sectors on,
you have a bunch of sectors on a track.
You have a bunch of tracks on a face of a bladder.
And then for each bladder,
you have two faces.
And then for a harvest drive,
you have multiple bladders.
Therefore, a sector is defined by,
like I mentioned earlier on,
by the cylinder,
the surface, and the sector.
Now, the main.protects from this slide,
and it's re emphasizing what I said earlier on is that in the operating system
doesn't track at the level,
the sector using their physical identifier.
The physical identifier.
Again, here is a cylinder surface and sector on the disk.
Instead, you have a logical block addressing.
And typically,
now the controller translate this logical block addressing
to the physical block addressing is something similar.
A with virtual addresses,
the way that the operating system is responsible for translating.
The virtual address is the physical addresses.
A it's a good.
Let me ask answer this question from allison.
Why don't we build devices and let us go lower?
Basically, ii guess,
lower the priority of rights and rights?
I guess this is a very good question,
and the answer is the overhead.
So you are correct.
Allison,
this is because efficiency.
Remember, again, just think about the hardest drives.
If you remember, the hardest drives.
In the last lecture,
there is some example.
The seek and rotational latency were like89 million seconds.
The time to transfer a block,
even if the block or as a sector,
even if the sector is 500, 12 bytes,
is not only 1 byte,
was much less than only second.
So the time to transfer to randomly access and transfer a sector is dwarfed
by the rotation latency,
by the fixed overhead.
Let a rotation latency and seek that.
So is that because of that is always an overhead?
Another way to think about is here it is another way to think about.
And maybe let me just and to connect the dots here.
Remember this slide.
Look here at this formula.
The smaller the bees,
the less the effective bandwidth is.
If b is very small,
s will dominate the fixed overhead.
This is just overhead.
It's useless work.
And the smaller the bees,
the lower the effective bandwidth is,
look at the red curve here.
So that's what you have.
Each request, pressing each request as a fixed overhead.
Even if this is on,
let me go here.
Even if these devices is solid,
its ssd not this drive.
There is an overhead for controller,
is an overhead or contact switching and things like that.
Okay, hopefully answer your questions.
Okay, let's go back.
What do you need for file system needs?
What do you know if you design a file system?
Or do you need to be careful about?
You need basically to track which for a file,
which are the blocks containing the data from that file,
you need to track it.
You need to for a particular file,
you need to now to know which directory contains it.
And then you need to track the few free disk blocks,
because if you write something new in a file,
you need to know which blocks are free, are empty.
And then you also need to decide or to maintain this information.
And the answer this information has to be persistent,
because it's persistent.
You have to maintain it on the disk.
So it's, again,
data structures on the disk is different from the data structure in memory.
The application, you have a data structure.
The disk, or even the operating system is unaware,
completely oblivious about the data structure you have in your program.
It just sees a bunch of bytes,
and later, a bunch of blocks.
That's what it is.
Again, because you access a block at a time,
is not very existing.
Access are not very efficient for when you access just a bite.
And obviously,
like I mentioned,
when you write to a disk,
you expect to be durable.
That's why you write to a disk.
Otherwise you keep the things in memory.
But here you need to be careful.
You cannot assume that if you write or disk,
if you say I wrote,
ii call a right operation.
Everything is fine.
Why is that?
Tell me why if I just call the right operation to a five,
I cannot be completely sure that the date I wrote has been
stored durably on the disk.
If you remember, we discussed early on about buffer cash.
The data is not stored directly on the disk is stored in a buffer.
If after you submit the request,
the obligation fails,
the operating system fails.
The data may be lost.
Right?
You need to call.
What do you need to call in order to make sure the data when goes to the risk?
What system called you are going to invoke flush.
Very good.
Although I would wish also to have more people answering these questions.
So again,
it's not a wrong answer.
It's about discussing it.
And you'll remember much easier if we have this kind of discussions
rather than me just talking and talking and talking and being boring.
So,
okay,
a few announcements very well.
Tomorrow this is 11:03.
Let me just think tomorrow we have the exam.
I wish you the best of luck.
All the materials is up to and included the last lecture, not this lecture,
the project deadline,
it was pushed.
So now you have a little bit, more time.
So hopefully this really helps you.
Okay?
Again, let's go delete,
even deeper talking about the file system.
So again, a few core elements,
the file system design,
if you are talking about the performance,
the dominant factor, remember,
you are talking about.
This is a bottleneck.
The bottleneck a is a disk performance.
The disk was better provide the best performance when we
sequentially read and write data,
because we avoid sick times,
and rotational latency is you're going to maximize these operations.
Remember, we can,
it's a file systems,
abstraction provided in unix.
You need to its open, close,
and in between read, write,
you cannot read and write to a disk without a file system,
without a file,
without opening and closing that file.
The cool thing about this is that you can perform the protection, checks,
admission,
control,
and or at the open.
When you open the file.
Otherwise you'd have to check for protection.
Every time you access that file,
the size of the file is variable.
When you start writing,
you start this one block.
We need more than and one sector.
We need more.
You are going, the file system is going to allocate more.
So you don't need to predefine.
This is very important.
You take it as a giver,
But it's not another design is like,
you would just allocate space on the disk.
And before you start,
right?
And why is that natural?
It can be natural,
because how do you do it in when in in your favorite programming language
like c right?
How do you manipulate the memory?
How do you manipulate the storage of memory?
Before you read,
or before you write some data?
What do you need to?
Do?
You need to allocate memory?
I'm a lock or see a lock.
You allocate first,
and then write.
Here is not needed.
You just write the operating system and the file system, in particular,
will take care of growing the size of the file is needed.
The files are organizing directory.
You have a directory structured and these directory structure,
the date the directories is and file.
It's also stored on the disk.
And then you need to allocate when you allocate fire,
when you allocate.
I think we are going to see that in the next lecture,
when we allocate there are more sectors on the disk,
you want to allocate them continuously.
Why is that?
Because when you read the data,
if the data was written on a bunch of sectors which is contiguous,
you maximize the sequential access is,
right?
Sequential read in this case,
which improve the performance.
So here, how things look like under the hood a little bit?
On one at one end,
you I have the file pass which is the file pass,
is a name of the file prefect prefix by the directory past name,
whether that or the files is residing in which the directory pass.
On the other end,
you have data blocks which are stored on the disc in sectors.
You need somehow to map from the file pass to the data blocks.
This is what the operating system file system is involved.
You take the file pass.
It is going to point in some directory structure.
You are going to find the file.
The file is going to be as you are going to identify by a number.
It's called I number.
And this I number is going to point to us data structure,
which is called I note,
which repeat which contains all the the informations about that file,
like for permissions, protection, permissions,
also information about the blocks or the data in the file is stored.
This is the I node.
Here is another view you remember about this.
So he had many lectures ago.
This is a view from the process perspective.
Here you have a process,
you have threads, registers,
and you have the address space.
Then when you open a file,
you get the file descriptors points to a data structure here,
which is in the operating summits.
Really, at the end of the day,
you are going to have the I note.
But anyway, the file description here,
in this case, you have a file name,
and you have position what the position in the file,
what is the position you are going to read and write?
Then this is going to read from file descriptor three and into this buffer.
And you are going to copy the data from position 100 in the file.
So from position 100 or five,
identified by the script or three,
read data into this buffer.
But really is the way you need to think about this,
that instead of this file,
you are going to have I number,
like I mentioned from here,
you just leave your point directly to this.
I number points to an eye note.
But let me ask you this question.
Why do you think instead of food or text?
Here I should just skip the eye number,
right?
Which is how and identified by the operating system of that particular file.
Why?
I know, but now not full text.
Let me help you a little bit.
Look at this picture while I numbers and not
file up text.
I don't want to name my fallacy random numbers.
It's again, you don't name.
It's let me very, very clear here.
From the operating system,
from your application perspective,
you open a file.
When you open a file,
you open food or texts.
And back, you don't get a file descriptor.
So the file descriptors points to a data structure,
which is open file description.
This is in the kernel.
You see everything which is below this dotted line.
It's in the kernel here.
And I show you this example.
I will show you that this file is a food or text, right?
Because this is what you opened.
But what we are saying here is that we really don't want to keep
in the open file descriptor,
food or text.
Instead, I want to keep the eye number of the food or text.
The question, why do I want to keep I number here in this data structure?
Instead of food or text?
File dot text is directory,
the directory independent.
That's a very good point.
Let's say.
It's not for dot text.
Is the entire pathway.
Yes,
the jasper is correct.
Save that the first translation step, it's exact.
You see,
I open the file and I get the file descriptor.
So then I want,
if I keep the I number instead of file pass,
then i'd save this translation step.
Otherwise, whenever I am going to access a file,
I need to do this translation because I have filed a text.
I need to do the translation to get the I number.
So I save this step.
Very good.
Let me just go a little bit quicker.
You have a fine line in a particular directory,
in a particular directory, you are going,
the file name is going.
It's you can think about a it's a bunch of entries in these directories.
The file name offset is by going to tell you,
the offset is going to tell you and what is the particle?
What is the entry for my particular file?
Then for file numbers,
you are going to have file number offset.
Basically, this is what it's I number.
The eye number is.
You have an index structure,
which is indexed by itself.
I node, each entering this index structure.
It's an I node which represents all the information associated with that file.
The index in that index structure is the I number.
Right?
You have.
And the open operation performed his name resolution,
basically translating the file name into the file number.
And the read and write operations are only referring to the file number.
So you avoid the first translation step.
You use a file number as an index to locate the I node.
And the I node is going to leave you to the blocks.
We'll see, there are a few examples.
You have three come.
Four components is a directory.
The index structure is a storage blocks and free space map.
Remember about that?
How do you get the file number?
You have to look in the directory structure in the directory structure.
I told you that in directory structure,
you have entries associated with each file.
Each entry I didn't tell you what each entry contains,
but each entry i'm telling you,
now each entry a it's a topple,
which contain its maps a file name to the file number.
Again, when i'm talking about file number,
I am also final file number is the same like I number.
This file number can be a file or another directory.
The operation system starts a mapping in the directory and interpret this format.
This double or the mapping between file name and file number is
for directory entry.
It's very important to feel to understand like again that the way we
manipulate the directory,
although in unix, a directory,
just another five,
is different despite the fact that at the lower level is directory,
just another files,
the way you manipulate the directory is different than the way you
manipulated a file.
Right?
You cannot just use the read operation on the file.
You need to have special operations.
Redirectory create directory,
or make directory and so forth.
But let me ask you this question.
I why don't I again,
since at the lower level,
the directory is just another file.
Why don't I allow the application to do read and write some directors?
It's dangerous,
right?
You can override if you override these mappings,
you messings up,
because these mapping are maintained by the operating system.
Right?
It's for the same reason.
You don't allow your process to arbitrarily modify kernel data structures
that this is how the directory looks like.
Everyone knows that.
So directories are typically organized as trees,
directory trees.
The leaves in the trees are files.
The interior now is in the trees,
including the root are directories.
Like I said,
you do not allow the application to manipulate,
to read and write directly on the directories.
Instead to manipulate directories,
you have special function called system calls,
right?
Make beer or remove beer,
create a directory.
Already dear to traverse the directory structure.
This is from the command line.
You can use from the command line.
But you also can use them.
You have lipstick support.
You can have also use a library.
So you can use this programmatic from your application link and unlink.
This allows you to actually break actually this hierarchy.
Actually, you can have a name of a file.
You can have a file,
a name pointing to an existing file.
Right?
So you have a file with a namesake food or text.
Now I can have another name called full one dot s pointing to the same file.
We'll learn more about that.
Just to give you a sense.
Now, let's assume that about the overhead which are involved,
let's assume that we want to access to resolve this,
to get the I number of the file count,
right?
And then to access the file count.
So what do we need to do here?
First of all, we need to locate the root of the director.
We need to start searching from somewhere from the root of the directory.
And the root for how do we do that?
Fortunately,
by convention,
the operating system as the file system,
put the route directory,
the route in a fixed position on the disk.
You access this block,
data block forward.
In the data block, the road,
you have you have this kind of directory entries,
file entries in that directory.
Is that a directory?
You are going to have to locate mike,
right?
How you do that?
You can linearly search.
Typically, the number of entries in the directory is small.
Now, once you locate,
you read the file header for mike,
because how do you know that?
Because the entry for my tells you what is the file number or four directory,
mike.
So from that,
you go and it read again the first data block in my you search for the book,
the self, my is going to gain.
It's a director.
It's going to keep a bunch of directory file entries.
You read the header for the book.
Again, you find book.
The book entry,
the book entry is going to have the file number associated with a book.
Directory use that in order to read the header for book.
And then you read the first data block for a book,
you search for account,
you find count,
and the count is you get the file number for count.
There is a file header for account.
And now you are done.
So how many axis is?
1234567,
just to do this resolution.
Now you see how important is to keep in the description of the file to keep I
number for the file number instead of just the file name.
Because I save the next time after I open it.
The next time when I do a read and write,
I save seven axis and that expensive.
You also have the notion of current directories and the current directories.
It's if you just refer to the file name without ignoring the past name,
you are referring that you assume that in the current director,
the current directory,
it's already cached.
So it's one way with to reduce this number of counts.
This is how happened the file structure in the memory.
And this is a user space,
a kernel memory,
and it's a secondary story.
This is what happened on the disk.
You have read when you read a file descriptor,
this a file descriptor paying points into this per process open file paper.
This each of this entry,
it's information associated with that file.
And what you are going to get here is a file number and the sick position
of the current position in the file.
You see this grazing here.
It's again, recently.
Let me show you just to connect the dots.
Oops.
Is this one?
The information in that gray area?
Is this open file description?
Right?
The I number and the position is a file.
This is what is here.
The I number points you to the I node.
This is the open file tables,
and the I node has protection bids.
And then also has all these maintains all these data blocks.
And all this is maintained,
is maintained also on the disk.
I know the Information is maintained on the disk,
because it maintains the association between that file number and the blocks,
data blocks where the data of the file is located.
It must be on the disk.
It must be durable because it must persist.
After you've finish your program after the program ends.
We talk about all of these things.
I'm going to end up with this a few interesting data.
And then we are going to continue next time with the file system.
So this is a study.
It was 13,
14 years ago,
but it still is very relevant.
And this is the point here is the following.
So what this study is looking over 5 years and is looking
about how the distribution of the file lengths.
And that's the Information about statistics about the files in a file system.
The first important one is basically show you what is the size of the file,
the distribution of the file sizes for a file system.
Basically, what this tells you,
this is on the x axis of file sites and the number of files on the y axis.
This is for different girls,
is for different years.
So you have something similar,
although as a years pass,
you have more and more files.
Right?
The main point here is,
this is showing that most of the files are small,
not is that the x axis is log scale.
These are very small, right?
For instance, most of the files are 512 kilobytes or less.
There are very few large files.
So most of the files are small files.
However, if you look,
but if I'm taking some piece of data,
and I'm asking the question from the files,
from all the file system, I'm taking a piece of data.
And I'm asking the question,
what is the size of the file which contains this piece of data?
Then this is the answer I'm going to get.
And basically, you see now that most of the data is contains in big files.
The majority of files is small,
but the man,
the big files are responsible for most of the data.
Okay?
I am going to end up with a question to you.
It's a fun question.
You see,
you see here that on this kind of this distribution,
you have two picks.
You have AA pick around 2 megabytes and another peak around one gigabyte.
You have why do you think you have these topics?
Why do you think what this one gigabyte?
What do you think causes?
And by the way, in 2000,
it wasn't such a big,
but as a time goes, went on, passes passed,
you have this big?
Let's see.
Yes, that sounds very good to answer here, right?
We know, right?
It's like,
especially that was peer to peer system and you write about it.
Yes, this is one reason is media.
The other reason this is a lot bigger and bigger files are also binary files.
The executive become bigger over time.
That's excellent answers.
With this, we are going to stop here.
Again, good luck to the middle of tomorrow,
and i'll see you again on Saturday.
Thank you.