Hello, everyone.
So today we are going to continue our discussion about file systems.
In particular,
we are going to go through a few examples to see how some of the most popular
file systems in the past have been implemented.
First, to to recall,
these are the main data structures which are maintained in the by file system.
First of all,
we are going to have a directory structures,
which is it's an article.
And here you are going to use a file pass to locate a particular file
in this directory structure.
And entering the indirectory structures,
associate the file with an eye number,
an eye number.
It's an index in index structure called file header structure.
And this index points to what is called an inode.
The I node contains all the information which is relevant to the file,
and which help the operating system to locate the data for that file
on the disk.
The first case we are going to go over.
It's a fat stands for the final location table.
And this was the first file system
employed by microsoft.
This operating system,
which is the first operating system released by microsoft all the way in 1977.
It's still quite used today.
I despise after what after 50,
50, 40 years of 44 years, right?
And the fact,
look,
is aa file system is quite simple.
Let me just so first of all,
what you have here on the right,
it's a blocks on the disk,
and that these blocks and you have a file.
For each file, you have whether the block is.
Each file has a bunch of blocks.
Like they say the 456,
31, this is where the disk are located.
And then you need to maintaining the fat table,
a pointer or the item,
the offer to where the disk is locked,
the blocks are located.
Therefore, to the I number of,
sorry, to the index of that block,
that this block,
you can think about of an array of blocks,
each blocks has a identifier,
is typically it's a logical identifier,
which is mapped, then,
on a physical identifier as it is.
And the fat maintains a mapping between the files and the list of blocks
identify as logical,
identify as.
So how does fat maintain that?
It's,
again, this is maintained in I the I note it's indexed by the I number.
Let's assume that the file number here is 31.
And the fact is just basically a linguist.
Each link, each entry in the linked list corresponds to a block of a file.
And each entry will maintain the index of a block,
and then a pointer to the next entry,
which points to the next block.
Okay?
He has assumed that you are going to have in three,
a three blocks in this 501, and 2.
You have three corresponding entries in the fat table.
And each entry will have an index to a corresponding block,
and then a pointer to the next entry.
It's the next entry in the in this
to the next entry,
corresponding to the next block in the file.
Also,
when i'm opening a file and other important data,
I need is basically the offset.
So I what is the current position in the file?
The current position in the file here is given by a the first couple is
a block in the file.
And the second and part of the double,
it's basically the offset within that block.
The question is,
what does x the second element of the two x double comes into the place?
Again, x it's offset within the block two.
In this case.
That's why in order to access the data here for from block two,
you start from block zero,
then you have to follow the link list to block one, then to block two.
Now it block two.
This is a block I care about.
Now I can read three block two.
Then i'm going to the offset x within the block two.
It's a very simple technique.
Now you read the block two in the memory,
and then you access offset x within that.
Again, it's the file,
like it's a collection of blocks.
And each entry in this link listing the fat link list corresponds to a block.
And the file number is
basically the file number for simplicity.
In the case,
of fact,
it's exactly the index of the roadblock.
In the file, in this case, 31.
It's also the index of the roadblock on the disk.
Okay.
So what about, obviously,
what about three blocks?
You need three blocks in order, obviously,
to extend the file.
Remember that the file extends expands as you write more in the file.
So there are four or four new files you need to follow.
If you want to write the new files,
you need to to look to find the three blocks.
Typically, there are two ways to to manage these three blocks.
One is to have a list of three blocks.
The other one, you can have a big map of it,
333 blocks.
So basically, in this opinion case,
you have for each block,
you have a bit1 or 01.
If it's that block is not free,
it's used by a file zero.
If it's free.
This is how you find it.
In this particular case, for instance,
you are going to write if the file for now has only three blocks,
you want to write to more data.
Like in this case,
I want to write in 571 in block c this means the first block.
Then what happens?
Again, the file of the operating system,
the file system expands the file,
and finds on bikes,
finding a new block in the empty list,
and then allocating that block.
And now that block is part of the file.
And it's also part of the linked list of all the blocks which belong
to that file.
Now,
what is passed out?
So again, this is persistent storage.
All these modifications needs to persist after I am going.
I write a file.
For instance, I modify the file,
and then I close the application, because next time,
when I open the application and I want to read the files,
I want my changes to be reflected.
Therefore, by default,
all this information is a fact, not only the data,
but also the meta data.
This has to be on persistently started in this,
and the obvious place to be started.
It's on the risk.
How do you format a disk?
Do you know what formatting a disk mean for people?
So formatting meaning,
I want to make the discus new,
right?
I want to basically erase everything.
The way you do it is basically your zeros of locks.
And in the fact,
I will you you mark everything being free.
There is a question here from gilbert.
Do the blocks not have to be in order in the linguist?
I i'm afraid I don't know understand that question.
Can you be more precise?
Gilbert about gilbert about this question?
Are you asking that because the link list is fundamentally ordered?
Like block three is before the block dough.
That's exactly why we have a linguist.
Because when you are going to read from a blog,
we are going to go along the linguist.
So that's the main point.
In this particular case,
we are going, again,
if you follow the linguist,
the link list will link the blocks in the order is your reader.
They are appended to the fact that's exactly where I need a linguist
to preserve that to start that order.
What happens if we try to insert us something in the middle of a file for fat?
Do we insert a new block into the linked list?
Or is there something more clever?
If you said you see in any file system and most file systems, actually,
you cannot insert a block in the middle, right?
Because from the file system,
think about what is the interface.
You can just write to the blog,
so or read from the, sorry,
you write through the file and read from the file.
If you write from the file,
if you write a in a in a place where already contains data,
you override the data,
you're writing an already existing block.
Right?
And if you're right at the end of the file,
then when if you don't have,
if you run out of existing at the block at the end of the file,
you are going to add a new block.
You are going to expand the fact.
The question,
how to quick format a disk,
you can mark all the fat entries to free.
And this can be easily implemented.
The main.here is, again,
is like you can actually,
there are two ways to format it and again,
formal meanings in it.
Just you want to have the disk that's new.
Now,
if you just remove all the information in the fact,
without doing anything without these blocks,
that this block still remains,
you don't zero there.
Then from the point of view of the operating of the file system,
the disk is free.
You can allocate everything because you removed your reform.
You just as mark all is a fat and is being free.
Right?
You are going to allocate from the previous blocks which are written
for a different file suggest of rights.
No problem.
Now, obviously, this is not a hard format,
because it maintains the information from the previous files.
And typically,
when people format,
they also want to relate this information for security reasons.
So you need to be careful about what kind of format is going to happen
on your format disc.
If you care about the information from your previous files,
do not be visible.
Again, for instance, your hand down,
you hand back your computer to your employee or something like that.
The fact that fat directory is a fat directory.
It's again it's like in a director,
you have to remember you have these and doubles.
One is a file name,
the first part is a file name,
the second one is a file number.
Here is a factory also of have.
It's a linguist, right?
This like we know all is the directory,
what you see in a directory,
which is basically a list of names.
What happens here?
You are going to have each of these,
what you've seen entering this directory is going to be linked all of them,
a a in a linguist.
If you remove a file,
then you are going to update the pointers so that you are going to step
over that file,
which was over that entry, which was deleted.
Okay?
That's how you have here.
So it's very simple.
One.
So one, there are a few things about the fad directory,
which is worth mention.
It's where do you have a the attributes for a file is
like protection and permission attributes who has access to the file,
to read it, to write it,
to execute that file is if it's a binary file.
In the fact,
these attributes are maintained here in the director,
like we'll see in other file systems,
these attributes are associated with the fire itself.
The other question, which, in general is,
it's an important collision for all the file systems.
Where do you find that?
Where do you start from?
To get the route?
If I give you a file name,
you need to go and get the route directory and then goes to the past names
in that end the directory to find the particular a file name,
and then I number for the file.
And typically this route or what it's a well defined place on the disk.
Right?
For instance, a case of fat is blocked.
What else here?
Obviously,
because this is maintaining a linguist and in order to read a directory
and display the content of directory,
you need to go over this linguist.
You need also to go what which is commonly defined,
because when you do a display like all the entries in our directories,
you are want to display all the files in the directory.
But when you want to find a fire in a directory,
you still need to have to go over this linked list,
which can be expensive.
Any questions?
He had a few questions.
Suppose you start with a file number.
The file number is everyone like in our previous.
Here you see also is yellow is you have a file too.
Let's tell me,
let's see.
What is the time to find a blog?
What do you need to find a block?
You take this is you already,
it's our friend or any the number of blocks.
I say, in this case, you say route,
then reverse the desired number.
Here you already have the file number, the third one.
You don't need to do the directory traversal,
but this is correct.
And gilbert, so basically,
in this particular case,
you need it's a linear search, right?
You need to find a particular block.
You need to follow the pointers in the linguist,
and everyone knows at english to find something in a linguist is linear.
So near that,
what is a block layout for files?
It was a previous question,
but they need to be contiguous.
Not.
Yes.
It's correct.
Actually, they don't need to be going to go.
They can be random,
because then we are going to have our linguist in the fat table to maintain
the logical order of the loss,
which provides you a lot of flexibility about where to allocate the blocks.
And which is what sequential access.
What do you think about?
Sequential access is a fast,
slow.
Yes,
the director is out of link lists also are presented in the fat in the and
there are also linguists,
but with directories is a linguist between the entries in the directories.
Here for the files themselves,
you have the linked list,
basically between the blocks of that file.
Now, the answer to the question,
sequential access can be somewhat slow,
because need to linear is gone for every access.
Because we do not have a guaranteed order is correct.
So the sequential access can be slow,
because if you look about at how block01,
and3 are located here,
block zero, and one are consecutive right?
Because they are consecutive.
You do not need to incur a sick latency or a patient latency.
What if to go from block zero to block one?
But now to go from block one to block two,
you have to incur a sick latency, rotational agency.
This is huge overhead.
You have a lot of flexibility.
You have to put the blocks on the disk.
But if you are not careful and you put them around on me,
then is going to hurt your access to
how is random access.
Yes, it's even slower.
Since you have to encourage us,
you need to sequentially search for the block,
which contains the data you want to read.
It's quite slow.
Fragmentation.
How is fragmentation?
Fragmentation is pretty good,
is not much fragmentation because remember,
you can put the blocks anywhere.
See, if you have just some three blocks,
you are going to get it.
No problem.
It's okay, it's going to help your performance.
But you can have your fragmentation will be very low.
Small files.
Is this sufficient for small files?
Remember what if
so?
It's,
yes, if the file fits in on,
block is very efficient.
Right?
It's very good.
If a file fits only in one block, like why?
Because you all in the file number,
it's indexed into the block.
The first block,
you find it immediately.
Right?
As you have more blocks in the file,
then it becomes more inefficient.
For the reason I mentioned, rightly mentioned.
And for the big files,
it's even more inefficient.
It's again, because the blocks can be loud.
They are loud on the disk,
can not end up being random.
And then you pay a lot of sick time rotation latency to read and write
from the file.
This is fact like very simple and very influential.
Like this was for many years.
For decades, this was a file system or personal computers.
Because obviously90%of the personal computers were running microsoft
operating system.
Now, let's switch the gears and talk about unique file systems.
And the next file system,
this is berkeley standard distribution.
4.1is what we are looking.
Now.
This is a part of your heritage.
And the similar in the linux today has very similar file structure.
It's again, a hugely influential,
a file system,
the file number or I numbered.
As again, it's an index into an array of eye notes.
I notes corresponds to a file, right?
I notes contains the indexes to the blocks on the disk.
And in this case, it also contains other meta data associated with a file.
It's pretty good for both little and large files.
All the assume that still all the blocks are the same size.
The trees, what you are going to see is estimate because you are,
he's here is how it looks like.
You have an, I not array.
The file number is the index in this area,
the iron ore in this area,
it's is basically, this is,
I know, data structure.
The first part, there are a bunch of attributes,
for instance, 99basic control bits.
You have typically owner or users,
group, and others.
So it's basically,
it was at the owner of the file.
And for each of them,
you have three beats,
read, write, execute.
So for owner of the file,
for the group and for others, right?
Basically, for everyone else.
And typically, obviously,
the owner has the most rights,
then the group,
and then every others you have,
and also you have a few other beats,
which basically you can executed only at the owner permission
rather than users and to execute at groups permission.
Again,
it's pretty classic.
The more interesting part is after this,
but remember this permission,
bits,
and information.
It's associated with the iron ore, with a file.
In this case, in the case of fat or fat,
it does this information on maintaining the director.
And then you have13 other entries in this idle structure.
Each entry points to a block.
The first ten entries are called on each of them.
They are pointing to one block.
The 11th entry point is called indirect pointer,
and points to a block,
which each element is a block.
It's a pointer to a real block.
Then you have double indirection pointers where this points to a block,
which is full of pointers, or each pointer,
points to another block,
which is full of pointers to, finally, two blocks.
And then you have triple in direction,
pointers, which is, again,
going three levels.
In this case,
if you have four kilobytes blocks,
is a feature you have,
you have.
Here you have.
Yeah, sorry, I said the first they did.
Direct number of direct pointers was then it's actually, sorry, it is12.
Life is12.
And then you have three other ones,
one for india, indirect.
Doubly direct and triple indirect.
So you have to12.
And if you have 12point, that is,
this means that if you have four k blocks,
you can start using only direct pointers.
You can start 48 kilobytes files.
And if you remember, from last time,
when you are looking at these results from this paper,
which are looking at the statistics of the length of the file system of size,
of the file systems,
there in that paper, in the plots,
we presented lifetime,
we are seeing that most of the files are small files.
Therefore,
for most of the files,
you are using only the direct pointers.
Then for the bigger files,
you are going to use the indirect pointer,
establishing direct pointers, entry, playing direct mode.
Just to give you a sense,
you can get for doubling direct pointers,
you can get to 4megabytes.
Why?
Because in this particular case,
it's again of this pointer.
Here, the 13pointer.
It points you to one block.
A block has four kilobytes.
Each pointer, in this case,
is4bytes.
Therefore, in a block,
you have 1,024pointers.
Each of these pointers points to a physic, to a block.
A block four has four kilobytes.
Now I have,
then1,024×4.
You have four kilobytes,
you have 4megabytes.
This is level two.
It's a 111 in direction.
The doubling direction is going to add another layer.
And it's basically you have four gigabytes.
And then for that hour,
and then for if you have the triple indirect.,
that is you have four terabytes.
So it's a lot of storage.
Now, there is advantage for these ones.
What is the disadvantage with the going with the that with indirect,
doubly indirect and triple indirect loss?
What is the disadvantage here?
Yes.
Longer access times.
Because right now,
I if I am going to to go to this the first level pointers,
i'm going to get the I node.
Then from I node, I get the pointers,
all the pointers to the block.
I have another access to get to the data.
11x axis.
If I am going to have triple indirect in order to get to these data blocks,
I have to get one other access to get the first level block,
which contains pointers at the first level,
then another pointer,
another I need to access another.
They get another block at the second level to contains against pointers,
another block at the third level of container game pointers.
And finally,
I am going to get the data to the real block.
But also here I have for each of these levels,
I have an extra axis.
Okay?
On the other hand, it's pretty cool designed, right?
Because for the small blocks,
it's pretty efficient.
Small block less than 48kilobytes.
All these pointers here are to data blocks.
At the same time,
you can store huge files like up to four terabytes in this design.
It's a question here.
This seems really similar to page tables.
Do file systems have the equivalent of super pages or huge pages?
Is very similar to the files is similar to the base table in some respects,
right?
Is one is that the unit of allocation a it's a it's a blog, it's a page.
It's also they are connected, right?
Because the reason for which you have pages in when we do demand beijing
is why?
Because these pages needs to be stored.
Eventually when on the disk when they are evicted, right?
They need to be read from the disk.
And the unit, again,
it has to be the same unit.
It's a block, right?
Block.
And the pages are basically the same unit.
Otherwise, to make things much more complicated,
you'll see towards the end of the lecture,
hopefully can get there where you see the similarity,
but more because they are going to talk about memory maps.
So then you are going to map the files into memory.
And then you'll see one more of the similarity in terms of file system,
having the equivalent of super pages of huge pages,
you do have that not in unique,
but you don't have that in the windows,
the more and more than windows file system,
microsoft file system.
And in that case, you have what is called extent.
What we are going to learn later in this lecture in visa blocks can have
variable sites.
Great questions?
Let's take an example here,
I right now.
And that's why I was a little in this particular a it's a different example.
And he here assume that each block is one kilobyte.
We assume that there are ten direct pointers.
And in indirect blog,
the standard pointer.
So directly you can access only 1 kilo one,
1kilowatt, one kilobyte,
ten ten×10kilobytes files.
Then because you have only one kilobyte.
If each entry,
each point there is 4bytes,
then you have only20 56indirect blocks at the first level.
Then you have twenty five two hundred,
56power to doubling the right box and 256 for three people in the right box.
That's kind of the layout in this case.
And now the question is that how many access is you need?
How many access is to get to the block23?
Assume the file is everything it's open.
Now, i'm just to add one process, block the industry.
How many answers
Is this 23 in a direct pointers?
But it's not right,
because I have only done in this stuff.
It's A
23 will be in the single indirect block.
So you need to ask this,
right?
We need the first access to get to the root of the first level indirect locks.
And then from here,
once you get there,
you are going to read the data block.
What about block five?
Block five is in the first stand.
So you are going to have only one access.
It is a data block.
Number five,
block service, three hundred fourth.
That's 340 hits in the first level,
the indirect loss.
Does it feel?
How many you have that?
You have twenty five fifty six last time,
which are direct is only indirect blocks or direct.
Therefore,
you need it has to be in doubling direct.
So then you are going to have how many axis?
Again,
one axis per level, each level.
So you have double for each level,
you need one access or two,
and the third one for access to the right.
Some announcement.
So again, many congress for finishing the second meet them.
We are making progress here.
Omar five has been released.
It will be due on monday,
november, 22nd.
The project too.
Obviously, now is due on sunday.
Hopefully everyone here,
it's in a good state with that project.
If not, please feel free to ask any questions we are here to help you.
That was the initial file system in unix,
4.1.
Now,
people, obviously,
after they used it for a while,
they figure out there are some limitations and they try to address these limitations.
And the address is limitation in what is called berkeley fast file system,
ffs which is bsd.4.2.
This was at least 84.
So still a long time ago,
it's very similar with 4.1.
The differences are that while in 4.1,
typical is a block size with one kilobyte in 4.21~4 kilobytes.
Why?
Because obviously, the discovery are increasing size.
It's a very good paper.
I recommend you to read.
It's in the reading material.
If not, you can search on the web and you can get it,
but it's very interesting.
And there are a bunch of optimization.
We are going to go briefly through these optimization and comparison with 4.1.
So let me go.
So I am not going to go now through this list.
I'm going while I am going to explain this optimization.
But the media thinks about, first of all,
let's talk about what are the motivation?
What are the problems with the file systems in unix,
bsd 4.10 k
the one thing is that the fire system is a fat table,
and all of these,
I note data structures, right?
They were in a fixed disk,
in the fixed place on the disk.
Okay?
And the problem,
or is that if you have all these I notes on the disk in on place,
then it's very likely that
they are going to be far from most of the data blocks.
The data blocks are all over, obviously.
And the eye notes are only at the age.
In order to access the data blocks,
you need the information from the inode of that particular file.
Right?
So you need to read on I note,
and you are almost guaranteed that I know the place where I know the store
on that is is far away from where the data is located on this.
It's sick time.
You are going to pay for the 6th time.
The other thing is reliability.
If somehow the outer edges tracks of the disk are destroyed,
because sometimes when some of the failures happen,
is that when you have a power outage and the discourse are rotating,
and sometimes the heads were kind of scratching the disk
in that particular case.
Then if you lose this kind of the inode information, you lost everything.
So that's a problem.
The other think it was,
it's hard to allocate for performance,
because in unix,
most rights in many rights are by append.
It's again when you write either your right to existing block,
because what is the existing data?
Is that you override the data.
But if you append,
in many cases, you just append to file,
then you are going to add new blocks.
And the problem here is that you want to allocate, in some sense,
obviously, on to allocate blocks which are contiguous, right?
But that's kind of was difficult.
In the case of4.1,
you need to be 84.1.
You have a linguist for the three blocks,
like in the fact table.
And then the way you allocate,
you go through this list,
and you allocate always the first block, which is available.
But the going through the list of the three blocks,
all these blocks can be all over the place.
So are they done?
So here is what they done.
Basically, they define this kind of block groups.
So the tracks which are nearby are in the same block.
And correspondingly, also,
they define the cylinder group,
like all the blocks which are fall under block groups,
which are falling under the
the drive head heads on all the bladders,
are in the same cylinder.
You imagine a cylinder which are going to contain all these data blocks,
which are overlay one over another.
So right now,
then instead of having these I nodes,
and only at the edge,
start at the age of that is you are associating these eye notes,
right?
To the files,
the eye notes with which for the files,
which are who was that I stored in the same block,
are also in the same block.
Seriously, this is, I know,
the information for the files which are stored in blog group one.
And these are the eye notes.
The information now for the files with data is in block group two.
Furthermore,
instead of maintaining the are available three blocks in,
at least you have a bit back.
And i'll tell you,
i'll show you next time you can do if you have a bit back.
Right?
But this is what it is now.
In terms of performance,
if you have this kind of layout,
now, because I nodes are in the same blog groups
with the corresponding files,
what do I gain here?
What do I save here?
In terms of performance?
What is a big deal about this?
Again, for a file to access a file,
I need to get its eye node.
And then I need to access these data.
Because once I get there,
I know I have the information or the blocks of the file are located.
I'm going to read or write.
That is a big deal about this layout.
If the iron ore is near the file blocks,
then it will be much faster,
but it especially for small files.
This is good.
The sick time it's exactly listeners and it's
basically the sick time would be smaller,
which will be much lower.
Right?
Because the sick time,
it's about how far there are two tracks on from each other.
This is a sick time it is given by.
And now the blocks are on tracks which are closer together.
Right?
So this is what it is.
It's not only that I read the I note,
and i'm going to this file, separate these files,
but also all the fire,
all the blocks are in each all the blocks of the file are in a blog group.
If they are in a blog groups and going from one block to another.
Even if they are not contiguous,
the sick time is going to be loved.
Also, here,
one thing which I didn't mention is that the I note for for files,
and the pattern is the entire directories with the files.
They the file system tries to put them on the same cylinder.
Right?
So on different corresponding blocks on different bladders of that is right.
It's, again, to minimize a sick time, in this case,
going to do analysis from directory.
You all the information is within the same cylinder.
I will discuss about this data block metadata and free space are
within each block.
A voice huge, 6 time between user data and system structures.
You also put the directory, like I mentioned,
and these files in the common logo.
Basically,
you try to preserve some locality between the meta data of the files
and the data blocks of the files
on by being careful how you store them on the disk.
But I try to be close to each other.
Like I mentioned,
the least the free block allocation.
Here we use bit map that before we used least by using bit map,
you can actually avoid some fragmentation.
One important things,
which is true,
both for the file systems in unix,
bsd 4.1 and 4.2,
is that you need to keep some 10%,
20% of free space, always,
because this, too.
But because if you don't have any kind of free space,
really, you have no freedom about where to allocate the new blocks.
They are going to become pretty, very random.
The performance of the disk will will slow down to a crowd.
Right?
But i'll say a few more words about that.
But now let's see what is a big difference?
And what is the advantage of maintaining a big map for the three blocks?
Instead of linguists?
Here is a difference.
We'll go over the summary here.
So here is the difference.
So here is a bit much.
Okay?
The dark shades,
each rectangle,
it's a correspondence to block,
a square correspondence to block,
the shy shaded, one represent blocks,
which are in yours,
and the white one cities and three blocks.
So a here,
a it's a very nice characteristic.
Let's say that I I I am starting to add to expand the a file,
and i'm going to allocate new blocks, right?
I have to allocate new blocks.
Okay?
What i'm going to do here,
i'm going to go through this speed map.
I'm going to start reading from the beginning.
Whenever i'm going to see a free blog,
i'm going to allocate it.
So this one,
the blue ones are the one which have been allocated.
So far.
So good.
Again, it's like i'm going to allocate what I seek encounter.
First.
These blocks, actually,
in terms of the location,
can be quite random if they are not one near each other.
However,
when I am going to start allocating the more I allocate or file,
the more i'm going to start,
looking for bigger gaps,
right?
For more contiguous regions.
Okay?
I think that's basically the key.
So initially, I am allocating,
as I find,
these blocks available, empty.
But then after a while,
when I start to allocate more and more new blocks to file,
I am starting to look more and more for contiguous blocks.
Right?
Because I have a bit map.
It's much easier to look for continuous blocks,
because I know I just look at the bit map.
In the case of the linguist is much harder because I need to pop
up from to go from one to another entry with a linguist.
With a linguist, really,
I am going to in the order in which I am going to see to find
in the linguist the three blocks.
Does it make sense?
Then the pldr here is that a a with a if I have a big map,
then it's much easier for me to identify contiguous regions of three blocks.
It's a simple that more efficient.
Then as I have of larger and larger files,
which advocate more and more blocks,
I am going to start using and allocate more of these contiguous blocks.
It's a bit map.
The question here.
The blocks here are in an area rather than a linguist.
Yes, again, it's a a bit map is by definition and others,
but it's very efficient, right?
A pointer.
How many beats you have?
Right?
For a point that you have beats 4 bytes, right?
32 beats, at least.
Here you have for one block, you have 1 bit.
Right?
Now let's go back.
A summary for these fast file systems are now layout.
If you have a small directory,
you can fit all the data of the files in the directory,
in the same cylinder.
There is no very little six.
Right?
So If the file had that is are smaller than the whole blocks,
you can obviously fetch many of those at the same time.
The last one, remember that one of the disadvantage of 4.1,
it was big reliability,
because all the eye notes are in one place.
If that place is corrupted,
you lost all the information from the entire risk.
Right here, it's basically,
if some part is corrupted,
maybe you lose some eye nodes,
the information about some files.
You can never access those files,
but many other files,
they are still going to be accessible,
because that I knows are going to be intact because they are stored
on different places on the disk.
Okay.
Here is another very interesting aspect is a rotation like this.
We talk about the sick.
The group block groups are intended to reduce the overhead for the sick time.
What about rotation letters?
Here is a one interesting thing.
Initially, with the unix,
a lot of these blocks,
the block is a lot of functionality of the file system was implemented
in the operating system.
The controllers of the drive,
this drive was very simple.
Now, the operating system was getting a block,
right?
Say, and then needs to transfer the data from the block.
But while transferring the data from the block,
the head was on top of the next sector.
And then you don't know, right?
And then you are going to miss reading the data from the next sector.
Right?
Basically, think about this.
I am want to do.
Ii want to transfer the data from sectors one by one.
Assume that the data is on contiguous sectors.
It's great.
Right?
But now the problem is that I read the data from a sector.
And while i'm transferring the data from the sector to read it,
the head is on the next sector.
Right?
And then I missed that I miss the beginning of the next sector,
right?
Then I need to wait for the entire rotation of the disk to get the next sector.
So one original techniques to address this problem,
it was is when I I am writing data on sectors,
is to intervene,
do not write data downs on subsequent sectors,
but skip one sector.
So that when I read the data,
then i'm reading the data on a sector.
And while i'm transferring the data from that sector to the operating system,
I I am not going to the next sector is fine if i'm skipping it,
because it doesn't contain the data from the file.
By the time the head,
it's over the next sector,
which contains the data from the file,
I am ready to read it to read.
Make sense?
So basically, here you overlap the transfer time,
right?
With a rotation,
it is pretty cool.
It turns out that actually,
the other solution was you just read ahead.
I read a sector.
While i'm transferring it after that,
i'm not sure whether I need the data from the next sector or not.
But it's okay.
I'm just assuming that i'm needing it.
So i'm going to read ahead.
And if I don't need it,
i'm going to discuss it.
I'm just going to buffer it.
I just need a buffer to push more data.
So that's that's another solution.
It's more flexible solution.
And this is actually what they it's used.
And this is implemented mostly in the controllers of the disk.
The disk has a ram has a buffer, if you remember.
So you read in that buffer,
and then you transfer to the operating system.
Any questions about this?
The first solution is implementing your rewriting,
while the second one is implementing your reading is a question.
No, not really.
In both cases, you can think about this optimization for reading.
It's, again, the problem here is that you read a sector,
and then I I am going to send the request for reading the next sector
and the next sector and the next.
I'm reading this sector.
And then I need to transfer the data from the sectors.
And by the time,
I am going to issue the request for it in the next sector.
The head, it's already over the next sector,
on the list.
Right?
I'm reading this sector,
and then I am,
by the time I am going to issue the request for reading the next sector
from the file.
The next i'm already over the next sector, i'm going.
So if it happened,
that is actually the sector.
I want to read it just after the sector I am reading,
then I am going to miss it,
because I don't get in time the comment to read the next sector.
Therefore,
I I have to wait all the way for the destroyed once to read the next sector.
What this first optimization says that I am reading a sector,
all I am transferring and give you some time before I get the next comment.
And if I get the next comment,
then I am going to know i'm going to be close to this next sector after I
skipped one.
Okay?
If I want to continuously in this mode to have maximized performance,
I need to interleave the sectors.
I when I write them,
so when I read them,
I am going to read ones and while i'm transferring and be getting command
for it,
reading the next sector,
I have enough time.
So I am ready to read the next section.
This makes sense.
How big does a track buffer usually needs to be to store the entire track?
That's a very good question.
So candida had the entire track.
Ii don't know on top of my mind of my head,
what is how much?
Yeah,
i'll try to get back to you,
but I assume a few tens of megabytes,
depending on the disk.
But so gilbert did answer your question.
So it's again,
remember that the disks and this controller do a lot of things under the foot,
right?
Like,
remember,
we did last time we learned about c scan and other scheduling algorithms,
three orders, a request.
So therefore, you reduce a 6 time and rotation letters,
the price of 4.2,
you have official storage for both small and large files.
And this is because you have this direct blocks,
indirect block pointers,
and doubling direct and triple indirect.
You can accommodate both small files and large files.
You have locality for boston,
small and large files to try to do that,
because they try to store them within the same block group or cylinder group.
And you also try to,
you have the locality between the meta data and data,
because the meta data that is I nodes.
We try to store them on the same block group,
whether the files themselves are stored.
We didn't talk about this when they say, no,
the fragmentation is necessary.
Not a fragmentation in the study here because you have the big map in what
happens to is that with and
I remember that when I use it long time ago,
when use fat,
when you or this30 microsoft operating systems,
the file systems,
what you have from time to time, you need to dance,
the fragment, the disk,
the fragments of this.
What meant is these to rewrite the information from the distribute.
So the files are more contiguously stored,
right?
Because the discourse fragmented as you believe disks,
as you delete files and you write more files,
is more and more fragmented,
meaning that the date of the files is stored more and more randomly.
The blocks are more and more randomly from time to time you do the fragmentation.
So you are going to try again to this to ready to rewrite the files,
so to move the blocks around so to speak,
so that the files are stored on contiguous blocks,
and the performance will be much better.
Okay?
Here is not really necessary because I told you about these holistics
in which you try to find large,
a a large bunch of three blocks for large files to store the data.
The course, it's efficient,
inefficient for tiny files.
It's a little bit unfair because it's still fundamentally the block
to store the unit of storage.
It's a block.
So even if you have1 byte,
you still are going to read or write an entire blog,
which is four kilobytes.
In additional, you need an eye note for this data block,
most of the file systems will have the advantage and inefficient encoding
on file is mostly contiguous on the list.
This basically says that you are going to have this bid map to tell you
where the blocks are.
And if you have 1 bit a for each block,
but for instance,
if the file is continuously a stored on the list,
then you need only 2 pieces of information.
What is the beginning the point that to the first block as a point
up to the last block?
Because everything in between is continuous,
this what means it's inefficient?
Encoding one files is mostly contiguous on the disk.
And still,
in order to avoid the fragmentation,
you need to have this kind of space on the disk.
So you cannot allocate the entire 100% of the disk space.
You need to leave around 10,
20% linux.
It's pretty similar.
You have12 direct pointers,
like in our previous examples.
If you remember,
when I was a little bit confused between 12 and 10,
you can have, in this case, you have 12.
The other thing you can configure the says the size of the blocks
to be different sizes.
Right?
You can have one kilobyte to kilobytes, four kilobytes, a kilobytes,
and so forth.
It's again,
you don't have in the same system,
lots of different sizes.
But when you configure the system,
start with, you can choose different block sites.
These x two and x three,
there are different versions of linux.
In terms of particular of this cloud.
We also have journaling.
We are going to talk about journal ink later,
but it's a particular way to start the files provide for tolerance.
And we'll talk more about that.
And other than that,
is the same kind of organization here.
You have,
these are the pointers in the group descriptor table.
You have pointer to the blocks in each blocks.
You are going to have.
You have, I know tables.
And then the I know tables are going to go to directory.
This is how the directories are organized in ex two three,
sending them hard, at least.
Sorry.
So here,
we remember last time we look through this directory structure
and the directory structure.
It's an analogy.
Okay.
What you have, typically,
what you can do in unix,
you can have a different,
you can have another hard link is called harding,
another link to the same file.
Right?
You can have the same file,
which is basically you can have two names for that files,
and these names can appear in different directors.
When do you want to do that?
Obviously, when I want to share a fart from different directors,
right?
I want to appear to be locked up to that directory.
Right?
It's like, for instance,
library fire.
So it seems like that.
Right?
And in this case, again,
I i'm going to have point that is the same two different file names
are going to point to the same file.
And in the I node is i'm going to maintain a reference count why I need that?
Because we're all only when all the references I know
to the same underlying file are removed.
I carry on the file.
In addition,
I have also soft links.
The soft links provide the same kind of behavior.
It's again,
they are used to create another entry in my current directory profile,
which exists in a different directory.
But this is symbolic link,
is our softening.
In this case,
it's actually a symbolic link is another entering the directory,
which basically about it has a file name,
is the new file name,
and then it's linked to the destination of file name.
You think in bowling and into just something you write in your directory,
which basically links the file name,
the new file name with the destination finding the one which I want to link.
Right?
In this particular case,
or if the destination file name is removed,
the opening the file using the symbolic link name,
it can fail,
right?
Because there is no one under the hood to keep the reference counting.
How many as a fine name out of pointing to the same file.
But this is easier to implement.
This is what it is.
You can create boss command line,
the symbolic links,
also hard links,
but also you can have a system called to dramatically manipulate
this involving links.
Let's look here as an example,
and rather than close to the end of the lecture,
about what happens under the hood,
let's say we want to access this file,
a stopped or text,
and the last name is Holmes last years on c two,
and then is the name of the file, stubborn text.
Right?
First of all, we need to start from the route.
So you need to have the I number of the route and say,
that's the position to.
And this one is going,
obviously, it are going to have here.
And I know,
right?
The inode is going to contain a pointer to the data.
And this data, in this case,
contains the directory data, right?
Directory entries.
Remember, the directory entry maps a to a file number.
Let's assume that the file number is 8086.
Now, this is what you have in memory,
what you have here down.
It's in memory.
Now,
you read the block 8086,
right?
What do you get there?
You are going to get the I number of the file.
You have the I number and the I number for this,
the subdirectory,
CS 162.
And you are going to get from that I number.
You are going to get data in that directory.
And daytime the directory is going to maintain the entry and mapping
between csrc two.
And it's I number,
let's say, 7th, 32.
You go to 732.
Now is the eye number.
You are going now finally to get all the Information which is in CS
as in the directory,
which is also you have file Starbucks next year.
And one,
once you read the data in the directory,
you are going to find the mapping between stuff dot text.
I the number now is ninety nine zero nine.
Finally, I have ninety nine zero nine,
which is a nine number of stop dot x now I can start reading the data
from several text.
This may require to read additional blocks before I get to the data blocks.
If this file is large,
and we need to have single indirected or doubling
direct or triple indirect data blocks.
Okay?
This is pretty much what happens.
And this is a beside of the files,
the data blocks from the file.
And that's pretty much it.
So let's stop here and will continue next time.
So here,
the question is that what is that was also file in slash dot com called CS 062?
I'm going to answer this question.
So basically, if it was in home,
another file CS,
that will be CS 162 dot text.
But I also have a different extension.
So the file system will differentiate.
You have a if as a file system would have exactly the same name
as a directory that cannot happen.
You cannot have a file name and the directory of the same name in the same directory.
You can try it.
You are going, you cannot create it, you don't get another.
Okay?
With this.
Thank you.
And i'll see you next time.