Hello, everyone.
Welcome.
Today we are going to continue our discussion on file systems.
If you remember, last time we are discussing about,
we ended our lecture with the discussion of the first file systems.
And we chose the version of the next version of the file
system in unique bsd after original version.
And this has a lot of quite a few innovations.
And we went over a few last time,
mostly the innovation or about improving the performance,
like different block sizes,
basically improving the rotational latency.
A few more features are going to improve the performance.
The one thing we didn't go over is the organization of the directories.
So what is the problem here?
So assume that you have a very large directory with many entries.
Now, if you remember the early file systems,
organized directories as lists, this was,
in the case of a fact,
the microsoft dose of first file system or arrays
of entries or an entry is a file name and the I node
corresponding to that file name.
I know, if you remember,
it contains the entire information about where which are the blocks
of that particular file,
as well as other information about that file,
like access rights and things like that.
The time was on last updated and other information.
The challenge with that is that say,
I want to locate 15, right?
And whenever you are going to and is a command line,
or you are going to write a file names to say,
caesar contact to open,
you need to find that file name because in the directory,
because the entry in the directory of that file name,
because that entry will give you the I node.
And the I node will tell you where are the data blocks on the disk of that file.
But if the directory is organized like a list or an array of entries,
then the only way to locate that file is linear search.
If the director is very large,
it is linear search, it's expensive.
Even more,
you may need your meaning.
You may need to read the entire directory just to find a file.
Again,
if the directory is large,
you may have to load all the blocks which are storing this large directory.
Again, just to find the fire.
What is a solution?
The solution is to find a better structure than a list of one and an array.
If you want to search water of some better structure to search
than at least an ordinary,
you learn about many of those.
Can you give an example?
What would you do?
If you had to design a directory data structure,
which is much more efficient in terms of search?
It's a binary tree, right?
Yeah, that's pretty good.
And it's even better.
Here.
We can have ab tree.
And when you have a tree, a surgery,
the depth of the tree is what gives you the complexity of locating
that the particular,
in our case, file,
which is a leaf in that tree.
This is for you, just aab tree.
It's a more sophisticated search tree.
If you remember,
this is just aa reminder for to refresh your memory.
Here, a node is pointing out at a lower level,
a on to an array.
And that array contains values,
which are smaller than the value of the paranoid.
In this case, 100 points to this array of values.
And all these values, 48, 50,
79 are less than 100.
Also, the following.
Now, the sibling node of 100, 1,
55 now is going to point to a set of values,
to an array of values,
which are lower than itself,
but higher than its sibling on the left right and on.
So these are numbers between 120, 8and 140,
and so forth.
Eventually, you need to get the leaves,
and let's see how to find a value of the lead at the leaf.
So let's see how this is used in the context of directories,
in the context of directories.
How do we get?
A the number is easy to get?
You just hash is the name of the file.
Now we get a number.
And hopefully the hash is good enough.
The probability of collisions is very small.
But this is what it is.
It's exactly, it's a binary search tree.
Sorry, it's a big tree.
It is a values in the beatrice,
are the hash is of the file makes.
And you can see here on the leaves,
you are going to see to have the entries in the directory,
which again, is the name of the file, a name,
and the file number.
Or I note any questions?
I
so in this particular case,
you see that the hash two out two,
it's c 194.
And you are looking through the beatles.
First of all, you are going to look at the values,
which are you are looking to the values to the consecutive values says
that the value on the left is lower,
the value on the right,
it's higher,
then c one, 94.
And then you are going to pick the node corresponding to that,
which is for the range.
Then you are going to go on level down.
For instance, in this case,
c 194 is smaller than the first value.
At the first level,
you are going to go take and go to the arrays pointed out by that value.
Note eighty one one zero two o k because remember,
eighty one zero one one zero two,
which is a last left mosque.
Now here,
at the top level,
is going to.only to values which are lower than itself.
You are going to go to the next level at the next level.
The second level, again,
you are going to look at the numbers of values at that node.
The values are going to go from the smallest battery, c 19,
c 195.
It's against c 195 is greater than c 194.
You are going to go again to the next level is going to be allowed,
which is pointed out by the first I corresponding to the leftmost value.
And finally, here,
you are just going to see that you are going to have to find ac 194,
so you'll find a match.
And that match will take you to the entry in the file directory,
which is the name of the file and the file number.
Michael, here has a great question.
Why do we want to hash the file names?
Wouldn't using the file name themselves in lexicographical order?
Have the benefit that is easy to enumerate files in lexicographical order.
Anyone wants to answer this question?
The file names can have arbitrary length.
It's going to make the implementation a little bit harder.
Someone says also perhaps to distribute the hydrogen.
For me, that's a great.,
actually, as well.
You get the more balanced three.
You if you have a hash with hash,
is going to give you pseudo random numbers.
So you are going to easily get a balance three whiles you once you build it.
But the other thing is that if use of finance, it's their strings.
So comparing to strings is much more expensive.
Then comparing to numbers again, remember,
we are doing building big trees because we want to improve the performance.
Hash is give you values,
which are at the end of the day can be our integers,
can be.
And just comparing integers,
it's much easier.
It's much faster,
and also much easier to build data structures where the fields have a union
with the same land.
Do different file systems,
use different between types,
or it's some standard like 234.
That's a great question.
Actually, I do not know the answer to that question.
I should look around.
That's a good question.
I would assume that there are some a rule of thumb
here about whether the good numbers for this application.
While directory can be large,
probably it doesn't compare with a number of rows.
You can have a in a table,
as you probably know,
be trees are coming from database field to index the rows in a table.
I guess you can have hundreds of millions or even billions of rows in a table.
I don't as well as a number of files can be large,
is not going to reach that barrier.
But that's a good question.
So now we switch gears and we are going to look
at another file system and file system,
its windows and dfs what in distance for new technology?
Right?
So it's called new technology file system.
It's an interesting name, right?
Because it's always going to be called new technology,
but now this is like3020,
30 years old,
so cannot be that.
So new technology,
this is still the default on modern window systems.
And if you are using the windows machine,
most likely you are using an ndfs file system.
Let me just tell you what is the main idea here.
The main idea here,
one of the main ideas is that instead of fixed blocks,
will we have valuable length blocks?
These variable line blocks are called extents.
And then instead of the fact or I not array,
we are having here what is called a master file paper.
And the master file table is almost like a database.
And it's in the database because it's it has attribute value pairs.
And these attributes and the values can be different things.
Each of these entries,
which is attribute value,
can have one kilobyte size.
So it's more general than the name finding pairs,
which are finding in traditional file systems.
Like we learned so far.
Let me show you a little bit how this is organized.
But the point is that the reason it's more complex,
but this complexity buys your efficiency and performance.
And you'll see how one is.
If you can find enough room on the disk,
and you can have an extent,
let's say, of 100 kilobytes larger than any block.
Right?
100 kilobytes extend or even higher,
and that's contiguous.
Right?
So it's very fast to read that block.
There is no signal that extent.
There is no sick time.
You have only one sick time.
You need to waste in order to get to that extent.
But then you read 100 kilobytes with blocks.
It's again, it's like they may not be contiguous.
So you are going to have more sick times.
And this kind of, it's more complex.
And not only that,
but as you'll see, like, for instance,
if you have a smaller file which is more than one kilobyte,
you can actually put in this master file table,
because one of these entries, remember,
it can be a up to one kilobyte.
Okay.
Let's look, this is a master file table,
and then you have a bunch of records.
And these records are content depends on how large is a fire.
You also are going to learn next lecture about journaling,
which is a way to provide file reliability for the facts.
This is a very small,
it's a small file,
tiny file.
So the file is less than one kilobyte.
One of these centuries is one kilobyte.
So what do you have here?
You have in one of these entries in the master file table for these small files.
You have standard information,
which is the usual when the file was created or the modified the last time,
if you wanna access the last time,
owner id some security specify as flags,
whether is read only hidden,
whether you can see, like,
if you do like a user alice,
whether he sees a file or not,
or it's a system file and things like that.
Right?
So this is what you have in the standard information.
Then you have the file name in the file table, master file table.
You have the file and remember that.
In the case of I node fa you do not have,
you have only I know the I node,
which is a file number.
The file name is in the directory only.
Then like we discuss if the data is a fairly small,
you may be able to put the entire data in this entry,
right?
And then it's free.
And you are going to just read on one of all this record.
In one goal,
you always want this access.
You can read everything about the file, including the data.
It's as fast as you can get.
Right.
Now, what happens if the file is a little bit larger?
If the file is larger than instead of having the data here,
right?
You have A bunch of pointers, attribute values.
Remember, the same attribute values you are going to have.
And each of those is going to point out to a data extent.
Again.
Remember, data extend.
It's a variable size block.
In order to refer to a variable size, block, or extend.
You are going to for to have a a start,
aa starting pointer and the length of the extent.
Right?
That's enough.
This is what you have.
Now, if you have a are there even larger files?
Then what you have,
you can have pointers to there,
to other extent.
Remember to the other mmpf records.
Remember, at the end of the day, extend,
it's a contiguous region on the disk, right?
So these are this leaf.
No, so to speak in this hierarchy are where the data are,
the data extents.
In this particular case,
the attribute list is going to.to have to.to different entries
in the master file table.
And this is what a huge file of.
It's again, you are going to have a lot of more mmfd records.
Here we go.
Right?
So basically,
at one level, to summarize,
if the fire is very small,
the entire file can feed into an mfs mfd record.
If the file is a little bit larger,
then you still have on one of the mfd record.
But in the instead of data,
you have a bunch of pointers.
They die extent.
So it's one level of indirection.
Right?
The extents are referred by the start and the leg.
If the file is even larger,
then you are going to have multiple mfd records.
And if the file is even larger,
you're going to have more fmf direction.
Directories are implemented as betrays.
Like we learn the file numbers,
identify its entry in mft it is similar with the I note table or ra and
mfd entry always has a file name attribute.
Right?
To remember here, right?
You can check it.
It's human readable as well.
How do you implement hard link?
Very simple.
The way you are going to implement a hard link,
that will be another entry in the mfd table,
which is going to.to the same data extents,
or is going to point to another mft which represents a file.
Its attribute, least part of the data.
This was a question.
Very good.
I assume that where it's at the good list,
I think it's nice.
Let me just the attribute list, its, again,
is part of the mft record.
I'm not sure what you mean,
what the question means about asking about whether it's part of the data is
part of or from afd record for the file.
And it's, again,
you have this attribute list if you cannot fit everything in a simple m
in the single mfd record,
where instead of data,
you are going to have pointers to the data extent.
You cannot have this one here in the data part.
You do not have enough the room to have to start the pointer,
stall extents.
That's great.
It's a question here from actually,
what are the pros and cons of this of an assume and dfs over berkeley?
Fast file system?
The list of extensive,
similar to the list of direct and direct pointers stood in the eye note.
The data part is replaced with an attribute list of larger facts.
Yeah, do you want to,
anyone would like to answer?
So gilbert, you mentioned about the data,
but is replaced with the attribute list of four large files.
I'm not sure is that an answer to a shake question?
Anyway,
who would like to try to answer this actually question?
What are the pros and cons between ndfs and ffs
one thing is about,
remember,
what is the difference between extend and blocks reviews enough of us.
So with extends,
you can have any size blocks.
What ffs gives you is the ability to configure the file system
with different block sizes.
But once you configure the block size,
it will still be the same size.
All the blocks are going to be the same size.
And with a data extent,
with arbitrary size,
you are going to be guaranteed that in order to retrieve and to read
all the data,
from one extent,
you are going to have need only one seek to get access to that data.
The blocks are going to be, in general,
smaller than one extent.
You are going to have multiple blocks.
And multiple blocks means that you may have to,
if they are not contiguous,
and you are not guaranteed to be contiguous.
If they are blocks,
you may have to pay multiple access times to read the same amount of it.
Nfs is also better for small files, exactly.
Michael.
And this be,
because like you see here,
for if the file is very small,
it's less than one kilobyte,
then it fits in one mfd record.
While in the previous case,
you need to have multiple access to loud,
a small file, at least.
You need to go to read from I node.
You need to go to read the data blog, which is separate.
Like this is a cumulant.
Like the data itself will be part of the eye not.
Right?
But with ffs is not,
you need to read the I node which is access.
And then even have very tiny file,
you still need to need read another blog where the data is located.
Excellent.
Now, let's move and do something even more interesting.
Memory mapped files.
Let's what are the memory map files?
You see, and why do we need those?
You see,
when you access a file and what we learned,
things are getting quite complicated,
and the data is replicated multiple places from that file.
You need to.
The operating system has to have a buffer.
We are going to learn more about the buffer a little bit later to store
the data in that buffer.
And then there is another buffer to put that data at the application level.
You have multiple copies of the data plus system costs.
But what if we could map an entire file directly with our memory?
Right?
And when you are going to read something from that file,
it just is like you read from that region of memory.
When you have to write it,
you're writing like in memory.
And eventually,
the operating system will take care to write back your changes to the list.
By the way,
the executable files are treated this way when we are executing a process.
So now to see the differences,
let's refresh our memory about what happens on a page.
47 instruction.
The instruction provides a virtual address.
The virtual address goes through an mmu and you are going to get
the physical page number.
Then you are going to the figure the page number,
the physical page number is going to index into a base table.
Right?
And the base table is going to give you the frame number.
The frame number is going to be,
depending whether you are going to have paging or segmentation,
you are going to concatenate a frame number is the offset,
and you are going to get the address of the physical number.
You go virtual address,
you get the page number from the virtual address is going to point
in the page table,
is going to give you the frame number.
And then you are going to get the offset of the visual address.
And you are going to get a frame and offset congratulating.
You're going to give you the address in the physical memory.
Now, if you are going to have aa baseball,
baseball means that they do not find the entry
corresponding to the page number is a page type.
What we are going to do is there is an exception which
is going to be handled by the operating system,
in particular by the baseball handler.
And that is going to look gate on the disk what the page
and is going to load it in memory.
Maybe for loading that page,
you need to evict an existing page,
because maybe the memory is full.
And then you are going to update the page table to. to the page,
which you just loaded in memory.
And then you return from the page fault.
And the operators operating system will reschedule that process,
which causes a baseball to execute the same instruction.
And when you execute the same instruction,
now you do have page table is correct.
So you are going to be able to read the page from the physical memory.
So we did that in the past.
This is just a refresher.
Now, what happens is a memory map as well, very simple.
It's exactly what you expect.
Here it's a file on the disk.
You are going just to map the file in the memory,
and you are going to map to initialize the base that we
are going to allocate base table entries for each page of the file.
When you have, in this case, a baseball,
basically,
when you are going that the page is not in memory which represent a file,
which is part of the file,
then you are going to load directly the file,
the portion of the file into the page.
And now you are just going to read files when you access it,
when you access a physical memory,
you basically access the content of the file.
So this is a i'll give you an example.
So hopefully that will clarify things.
This is a system call to create a memory map file.
This basically,
you provide the file descriptor of the file and the offset from where you
want to get to map the data from the file.
For instance, if offset it's 100,
this means that I want to map of starting with a byte,
100 from the file into memory.
These are some flags and protection.
The other very important fields are the address and of the length is
how much from the file you want to map in memory.
And the address,
you can even give an address.
And if you give an address,
then the file system is going to try to map the file that the address is given.
But if it cannot,
then it may find another place in the physical memory,
which enough space to map the file,
which basically is a contiguous region of lang claire.
In either way,
the function returns the address in the memory where you map the file.
In most of the cases,
this can be all you can use also this memory map,
also to communicate between processes.
We'll talk briefly about that later.
But here is a pro, it.
Here is an example of a program.
We just give you a sense and what memory map files means.
And what is that?
In effect,
here is a simple program.
And just for the sake of it,
we are going to type three addresses to bring three addresses.
One is something is the address of something is variable something.
And that are something is when a it's a data segment,
then we are going to allocate something and everything which is allocated.
It's on the hip.
This is address for the result of ma log is residing the hip.
The last one is to have this my file here variable,
which is a local variable.
We know that the local variables of the functions are put on the stack.
This address depends on is an address in the stack sector.
Then you open a file,
and this is a file.
We want to map in the memory.
And now we map the file in the memory.
Basically, we are taking this file description.
It's file descriptor are going to pass to a map,
the file descriptor of rfd zero,
meaning that I want to start mapping from the first bite in the file.
Here there are again, some flags about read, write,
and this is about whether this can be shared between different processes.
The other important thing is that I am the first address or to map.
This program passes sets as being zero system,
the operating system.
You are free to choose a region of memory in the memory where to map this file.
Most of the cases is what you are going to give.
This argument will be zero, right?
Because you don't know better than the operating system where you
should put this file,
or you should put this file in memory.
My file is a return,
the starting address allocated for that file to be mapped,
where the map where the file is mapped to.
So now,
and then you print the file,  Right?
You pass a file.
This is the argument is an argument of this program, and you print it.
And then you write something at the address of the file in memory+10.
Let's write over it.
Let's see what happens.
First of all, when I print it,
this is when you print the file.
Let's say this is a question.
This is the content of the file.
Right?
So it's my bad.
So the first three lines,
so i'm invoking this program with argument tests.
The first three lines are the printers I talk about printing addresses
in the data segment,
heap or stack and stack.
And then the last the next five lines are written by the spring types,
and is basically the content of the test file.
So the content of the test files that are four lines.
This is line one, line two, line three, and line four.
Here, i'm now this file,
every content the content is mapped in memory.
And now in memory,
I like I mentioned,
I am writing at the address+20.
Let's write over it.
And then I close a file.
I want to see what is inspire after I close it.
I look at the test,
and this is what I find.
This is line one.
And then you can see,
let's write over it.
Because this means that obviously I wrote starting from
the The 21st character in the file,
I wrote the string let's write over,
which is exact, and then I close a file.
And obviously,
everything was saved,
including the changes in this fact.
Does it make sense?
It's pretty cool.
You guys should drive.
It's like I mentioned,
you can share the files between two different processes.
Here I have the same file and I have two virtual addresses from two processes.
You can share,
you can map the file in memory and can be shared this file
between these two processes is exactly like a the
file on the disk can be shared between different processes.
Also, you can use this a map to as to share the data,
or is it to share memory and use a memory to share the data
between the parent and the children and your four kids children?
You can also create an mf file, its anonymous file,
because there is not a real file.
And you can share it to the children.
And then you can use it to pass data between the children and the parents
with this memory map,
file anonymous memory.
My fact,
this is not backed by the disk.
The question here is a file printed by the printer or the puts
here is printed by the printer,
this file.
But I it puts this a special case of printer.
Free sprinter fits is formatting, right?
You can bring different values,
right?
In the same instruction.
Here you can see,
as a first argument,
you are going to print because you are painting the map address.
And the second argument,
you are printing what is as the address of, i'm fine.
There what you have?
A bunch of you basically have aaa bunch of characters.
You have a string,
and you print everything what you find that.
Okay.
So announcements of project three,
design document, remember,
is due saturday,
this saturday,
and the homework five,
homework five is due on monday.
Basically,
almost what2 weeks from now.
Any questions about memory map files?
The next thing we are going to go over is a buffer cache.
Remember, we discussed that when you read from a file,
you will create different copies.
One of these copies is in the buffer cache.
It's in the operating system can maintain a cache of the data from the file.
In this case,
you can put the data,
you can put I nodes,
directory,
directories, and so forth.
And some of these pages which are cashed,
can be dirty, obviously.
And then the operating system has to take care that to write
back eventually the dirty pages to the disk.
And really, what you want, the key idea,
why do you want to cache the disc data into memory?
Again, this is an operating system memory.
It's not in the user space memory, like memory,
my files you copied directly in the user space.
For this is in the operating system to get this data,
even if it's in the memory of the operating system,
you still need to make a fund,
a system called to get that data.
And you,
obviously, you cash it to exploit the locality.
Right?
There are more, many access is to the same blocks.
If you have them in memory is much faster than accessing the disk.
You need to do this translation between a bass name of the file and the I nodes.
And then from the block address to the misconduct, right?
The logical block addresses,
let's see how the buffer cache is worked,
and here is settings up.
So this is on the right hand side, you have the disk.
This is like ffs layout on the disk.
And now this is a buffer cache,
and the buffer cash has a bunch of blocks.
The blocks typically are the same size as pages memory, bates.
Then you are going to catch the blocks and you can have data blocks.
Like I mentioned, they can be I nodes.
They can be directory innovation.
You have a free also,
you can have the free bit map.
Remember, you do have the free map on the disk to maintain data about
what are the available blocks,
free of available three blocks.
This is what you have.
This is a block side is the cache is organized as an array of blocks.
The color represents different kinds of types of information.
Here you have a state whether,
in this case, it's free or dirty or things like that or what happens,
whether you read or write a blog.
Then let's see what happens.
Let's say I am reading an I node,
sorry, I am reading a a data block.
I'm reading a data block,
a new data block from the disk.
I am going to find an available block in the cache.
Then I am going to write,
now you see the state is read.
This means that now I am reading the data from the block on the disk
into this available space.
Then once you did you once you read it,
you are going to mark that it's no longer free.
If you write it, you have to market that is a dirty.
Because now this is modified.
It's no longer the same content as the sale as a page on the disk.
Now you say you are going to read a directory,
right?
Is the same thing.
You are, okay?
You find an available block and you read it there.
Right?
And you say what it is.
I know,
if you do it, the data is the same thing.
But if you write it, now you say dirty,
the data is dirty.
This is what if you write in the block?
If you write to a block, you first,
if the block is not in the cache,
you bring the block in the cache,
and you write on the block in the block, on the cache, in memory.
And your market.
Is that any questions?
So discussion?
So the buffer cache is entirely implemented in the operating system.
Right?
It's in the software.
There is no dlb the blocks goes through transitional
state between 3 and years being greeted from the disk,
being written to the disk,
and so forth.
And blocks contains all this variable where variety of information,
like I mentioned,
I nodes and data and directories and the free math.
And the os it is going to maintain the manners them to maintain the pointer
into them.
It's also the os is going to manage this buffer cash when the process exits,
when writes reads.
For instance, on the process exits,
you are going to flush to write back all the modified data
from the buffer cache to the list.
Now this is a cache, it can fill up.
So what happens when you fill up?
There is a replacement policy,
like we know, like the man beijing, if you remember,
deployments policy, what can you do?
You can do a radio.
It worked pretty well for demand bailing,
so I wanna do something like this.
This works well.
And if the memory is big enough,
especially if can accommodate the working set of the particular
applications or consent in terms of the data which is accessed from the file.
Now, the disadvantage is that is for some access patterns,
you is not good.
For instance,
if i'm just going to scam the file,
i'm just going to read and to read to it.
I'm going to read a blog only once.
So with alu that block is going to displace another block in the buffer cache.
But then the block we just was loaded into the cache.
I am no longer to access again,
because I got it later.
I'm just doing a scan.
So that's a problem.
Right?
What is a solution here?
It's a smart solution.
The solution here is that the operating system allow application
to request other policies.
The application knows more best.
What is the access pattern?
If the application knows that it's only going to scan the file,
it can specify as a replacement policy use once.
This means that the file system can discard the block as soon as they are used.
They don't need to operating system,
doesn't need to maintain that block in the buffer cash.
Now, the cache is obviously stored in the memory.
One question is that how much memory you should give
to the operating system for the buffer cache versus
the memory for to map the processes virtual address space.
If you give too much memory to the file system cache,
the access can be fast,
but you may not have enough room left for the applications.
If you give too little memory,
you are going to have a lot of access to the disk,
because you cannot cash the blocks which are going to be used.
Frequently.
The solution here in the operating system adjust dynamically is a boundary
between the os cash,
the application memory,
so that the amount of the rate of beijing in are roughly the same.
Any questions about
another things about is the file systems.
You see, a lot is pre fetching,
refreshing, you remember is read ahead.
And we discuss that also in the case of demand beijing and demand beijing
is to avoid compulsory misses.
Right?
If the access is sequential,
that if you have your one of your access, one block,
then you are going to very likely these are data from the next block.
So why not bring both blocks right away in memory?
Right?
And avoid to have another access to the disk,
which is very expensive.
You have aggression here.
How many how much you are going to read ahead?
How many blocks are you going to prefect?
If you do too many,
then it's fine,
but you are going to be wasteful.
Right?
And if you are going to do too little,
then you are going to have a lot of more access.
So not these two things off.
One is be fetching is easy if the blocks are sequentially arrange on the group,
arrange on the disk.
Right?
Because it's one sick time,
and you just read multiple blocks.
The other thing,
it's if you are going,
even if the blocks are not sequential,
then you are going to provide the disk controller,
a bunch of blocks you want to read.
And you remember the elevator algorithm.
Two lectures ago,
the elevator algorithms reorder the requests.
If he gets more requests at the same time,
so that he uses the sick time,
it puts them in the order in the order along the direction that the head
is moving.
Excuse me,
the head it doesn't go back and forth.
It's just going in one direction,
and is going to get small sick times to the next request,
minimizing the sick time.
So the more privileges you do,
the more requests are going to give the disk,
the more potential to for the elevator algorithms to be efficient at the
minimize the sick time.
So how much to prefect you just discussed?
Too much.
It's going to be wasteful boss because delays,
because it takes maybe a little bit more time to refresh multiple blocks,
but also because they are going to bring this data in in the buffer cache.
And maybe you are not going to use it.
And this data, the blocks you are not going to use it,
May be replaced some blocks you are going,
which are used frequently too little pre fetching,
many, more six, right?
If you at the limit,
you prefer the only one.
You prepare nothing, right?
You just then you are going to have a sick for each new block.
You are accessing.
This was about reading multiple blocks.
The same you can do also about the rights is called delayed rights.
So delay writes basically means that it's, again,
when you write the data,
you modify the data is modified only in memory in the buffer cache.
So it is not written immediately on the disk.
So therefore, the rights are very fast out of the memory,
the rise to the file, a rise to memory.
If the block is in the buffer cache,
the read is going to first go to the buffer cash to see why there is
a block they want to read,
which is a buffer cash.
And if it is in,
is going to get the most up to date value.
Even if that block was not written yet on the disk,
is still the up.
The right.
Previous right update is a block in the memory.
So we have to find here.
So when does the right,
the changes made by a right to reach the list?
There are a few cases.
One is operating system is flashing it periodically.
I think, like, say, 30 seconds,
every 30 seconds,
you go and scan the buffer cache,
and you look at the blocks which are dirty and ride them on the disk.
Or obviously, when the cash is full,
then you may want to flush them to write on the disk.
So what are the delay rights advantages?
Why don't you tell me here?
What do you think?
Are the delayed right advantages compared with you right back every time
you want to modify a block?
Yes, you do not have to go all the way to the disk for changing every time.
That's very good.
Can you think about anything else?
So honest, again, if you don't need to go to the disk,
you are going to have a performance advantage, obviously, because you like,
I said,
you just write a memory to write to the disk.
Right?
It's also,
you can accumulate multiple rights, right?
You can write to the same block multiple times before you is,
before you are going to write the block to the disk,
you have only ones right to the disk,
corresponding to many updates of that block.
The other thing is like for the reads,
if you are going to write multiple pages that discuss the same time,
you understand all these requests to the disk and the disks,
the elevator algorithms on the disk,
again, reorder these requests,
so that there is going to write close together,
blocks one after another,
and again, minimize the sector.
Another thing is that for delay rights,
you may want to allocate multiple blocks at the same time.
For a files to keep them contiguous.
You can make a room when you write,
you write multiple contiguous files.
Right?
What i'm trying to say here is that when you are going to write data and I
have multiple blocks that are modified from or the new blocks,
right?
Because you can create new blocks,
which I remember they are not on the disk.
If you expand the file, right?
If you're right at the end of the file on the disk is smaller, right?
But now you are going to write,
you are going to allocate more data in the buffer cache,
that now the filing memory is larger than the file of the disk.
Now you find out they worth of ten blocks in memory,
then if I delay to write these ten blocks to the disk,
when I write them the disk,
now are these ten blocks?
I'm telling that from the same file,
so maybe you can find a contiguous place to one that needs to place
all these ten blocks,
one after another,
which again, is convenient when you read the data from these blocks,
because there's one after another,
says particular region on the risk.
Again, you avoid, in that case,
the boys are sick that we are going to avoid the second rotation like this.
Here is a fun thing.
If you have some files,
you open a file during we need your application.
And you close it,
you just use from some to have a file to create a file to share some data
between two applications.
If that file, it's very short duration,
you may never make on the disk, right?
Because it's going to be removed and it's going to be deleted before closed,
right?
And delete it before.
You have the operating system,
have a chance to write it on the disk.
Okay, so here I have a question for you.
So with the man beijing,
we remember we demand beijing,
we have an aluria and the same kind of algorithms,
but we are very paranoid then about the performance of the allergy.
And we implement some approximation like clock algorithms and things like that.
Second chance algorithm with buffer caching,
it turns out that people do not implement exact area in the operating system.
So people are not as concerned about the performance of alu cashing
for buffer for allah,
you for buffer cashing versus demand beijing.
Why do you think is that?
Why do you think that in the case of the buffer catching is
fine to implement the exact area?
Where is the context of demand?
Paging is not that we need to implement up or smash.
It's in softer,
so not that much of a performer skit painting is also in softer.
So demand painting is implemented in software as well.
Anyone?
I think it's a subtle question and it's okay.
If you do not the answer to this question,
one reason is about think about the foreign thing,
demand paging,
the expectation of the application you are going to read and write from memoir.
This is what you are against.
You are against the latency provided by sort of memory,
because as the expectation of the application,
it acts as his memory,
you need to be very fast.
In contrast,
when you access a file,
you don't have a expectation to be that fast.
Buffer cash is improving the latency,
but the baseline is accessing the disk, which is slow.
And sometimes you have to access the disk because it's a buffer
that the data is not in memory and so forth.
So the fire,
so that's kind of one reason, right?
Because expectation on you,
when you when you access a disk,
is not to have the fastest operations.
Right?
So therefore, it's okay.
If you had ability to be slower,
and actually,
with being a little bit slower,
you can manage a cash even better,
but it's no longer an approximation algorithm.
Eviction palette policy demands beijing.
Remember, is you have big not recently used pages when memory is slow,
close to full.
With buffer cash is different if you write back dirty blocks periodically,
even if you recently.
Why is that?
The reason for that is, again,
different expectations.
When I read and write to memory,
I don't have any expectation about your ability of the data.
Right?
You do expect that the computer crashes or even the program crashes,
you lose your data in memory, right?
But if you're right on the disk,
if you think that you're right in a file,
you do assume that what you wrote is persistent.
Right?
So now,
we'll talk about this quite a bit for the reminding of this lecture
and the next lecture.
You need the operating system needs to try pretty hard to provide that persistence.
Savannah is doing it is by periodically writing the updated,
modified blocks from the buffer cash is a risk.
The marginal difference between al a real and on a normal area.
Isn't that big in this context since this baseline,
since the baseline is at these corporations,
which takes super long?
Anyways,
this is a comment by gilbert.
That's exactly correct, right?
So in the case of the buffer cash,
the baseline is a disk.
In the case of demand beijing,
the baseline is a memo.
So like,
like we mentioned in order to improve the persistency,
the operating system rise data to the disk from the buffer cash periodically.
So it flashes it,
like in the case of being on 70, 30 seconds.
However, obviously,
this is not bulletproof,
right?
I what if the operator, the operating system,
or you have a failure as a machine fails,
and you have dirty blocks into the buffer cache.
Obviously, this information is lost.
Right now, you have the case.
You have from your application.
You wrote,
something is a file you owe,
it was open.
And now, machine file fails after you wrote.
And what you wrote is not in the fact.
Although as a programmer,
you may believe that I wrote in a file,
the file is persistent.
It must be in a file,
because it happened before the failure.
Right?
And this can be pretty ugly.
If you, for instance, you want to modify a directory.
If you don't modify,
then you may lose entire files because they are you lost.
They are dangling fans.
There.
We have no presence in the directory or there are many others.
Okay?
You may lose, I know, and so forth.
So the file system needs some mechanism to ensure the persistence,
including some recovery mechanisms to recover kind of inconsistent state.
There are three important properties of a system when it comes to
its to speak,
performance availability and so forth of a system and the file system,
in particular.
So there are three things.
One is availability and availability really tells you percentage of time
while the
system can accept and serve your requests.
So three lines, meaning,
in this case,
meaning that the probability you send a request to the file system and you
don't get a reply or it is not resolved,
is 0.1%.
Then in durability,
the durability means is that if the data is on the disk,
then is durable,
meaning that if this fails,
there is still a way to recover the data,
availability and durability.
They are not the same,
because availability means that the data is somewhere,
but doesn't mean necessary that it's accessible.
And then is a reliability is usually the strongest one is the ability
of a system to better form is required functions as it is defined.
Its application level definition,
what that means to perform the function and is
typically stronger than because it implies availability.
If it's not available,
the the system cannot perform its functions and also includes durability,
because the data has to be any purses and data.
I should be able to get access to it.
First, we are going to look about how to make this system,
the file system durable.
How do you make a file system beautiful?
What I said that what I want to ensure here is that if I wrote the data
on a disk in a file,
I want to get to be able to read that data at a later time,
no matter what kind of failures were happening.
Right?
Say, the one classic failure is that I this failure.
Ii wrote that on the disk,
it made it from the buffer cash to the disk.
But then that's this failed.
I lost the data.
How do you avoid that?
Redundancy?
You back up?
Absolutely, is what you are doing for you,
sure you should do for your only the most important data you have,
right to more than one,
this totally.
And there are many ways to do it.
And we'll see you can do it,
rich solomon.
They are correcting codes.
There are other things you can do.
It is like,
you can have battery backgrounds or non volatile ground.
See that doesn't necessarily need to be on the disk.
But you can also write it in ram as long as it's powered as in its own battery,
its own battery,
and the machine fails.
The ram is not wiped out,
but to clearly to have the data surviving more a lot of more long term,
we need to replicate it.
And again, when you replicate it,
you need to be very clear about the assumptions,
failure assumption you are making.
Because if you have to these stripes and both are on the same machine,
if the machine fails,
then you lost both copies to avoid that.
You need to put copies on different machines.
But if the machines are in the same rack,
and the rack fails,
or the data center experience a catastrophic failure,
you lost access to those of copies.
Now you can put the copies on several different continents.
You are going to be safer than You see that, right?
Because typically,
many of you assume that when they back up their data,
where do you back up the data?
Do you back on the same machine?
Now?
Where do you back it up?
Actually, I'm curious anyone backs up the data
cloud,
many people being the other one clone the cloud.
Right?
Yeah, and this is Michael has a good point,
maybe also the medium you want to write on different media to protect
against some catastrophic failure,
which are going to engage to involve only on media or degradation over time.
Good.
But many people to write to the cloud, right?
And the cloud actually can replicate the data across different regions
in different continents.
But now getting back and this was like many years back and this was people
are developed.
First,
the technology called grade actually was developed at Berkeley by David Patterson,
Randy cards, and their student god Gibson was faculty of Kennedy mellow.
Now it's at Toronto.
Is that Toronto you just have a replica of each disk and one you call
the recovery group.
You double the capacity you need and your new rights.
A write is done only if you write both as the primary and the replica
of or recovery group.
That's it.
Right.
Now the problem here is that the rights can be quite expensive,
because each right in it needs to go to tourists.
And you remember when you write,
you have but a rotation,
a disk latency,
you had going now to finish,
and you are going to wait for the slowest time to finish disk.
For as long as this to finish,
that was a performance.
It's worse for rights.
You can synchronize the disks.
Right?
So then all both of them finish at the same time.
But that's very hard.
What about the reads?
It turns out that with these, you are better, right?
Because with reads,
actually,
you can have twice a boundaries because you can read for any replicas,
right?
Or you can send the same read to both replicas,
and you get the one which is arrived first.
So it's good for reads.
Both in terms of latency and the support is bad for rights.
And also we need to double the capacity.
What happens on the recovery?
When a disk fails,
you need to buy a new disk.
Then you are going to copy the data to the new disk,
all data to the new disk.
Now you have a game to Africa's.
Now, that was, again, pretty expensive.
And that was the right one.
Again, right,
is means redundant arrays of inexpensive disks,
as opposed to much more expensive,
presumably more reliable beasts.
Here you have cheap,
less reliable this,
but because you do this kind of replication or you'll see a major coding,
you are going to achieve a much higher level,
given a much higher reliability than the expense of these.
There are different, again, level levels of rare rage.
And you can look in the textbook.
They five and more what they do.
They basically,
they stripe the data across multiple disks,
and they add also a paradise,
a a parody law.
So basically say, in this case,
in this figure,
that each DD one, d two, d three,
these are disks, and these are the blocks.
D zero, d one, d two, d three.
Sorry.
These are the blocks, the name of the blocks, d zero, d one, d two, d three.
Then to this one,
you are going to add a parity block is zero.
The one you can do it.
The p zero is the x or of the values of the data blocks.
Therefore, you have four data blocks.
You are going to add another one,
which is a paradigm.
The overhead here is 25%,
not doubled.
What happens here?
You can,
if one this goes away,
you can still reconstruct the data.
How do you do it?
You reconstruct the data of the lost block by simple x sorry,
all the remaining blocks,
the three remaining blocks,
plaza, parity block.
It's as simple as that.
You can also spread the Information,
not only across multiple disks in the same server or in the same data center.
You can also do it across the internet.
You can use the same technique.
I'm going to stop here.
We are going to talk a little bit more about this,
how to make this durable.
And next time,
thank you.
And this Thursday,
it's Veterans Day.
I hope that you are going to enjoy a well deserved lighter day.
You can get some rest.
I'll see you next week.
Bye.