Hello, everyone.
So today we are going to continue our discussion on a file system,
reliability.
And we are going to talk a little bit about transactions and start talking
about networking.
If you remember, from last time,
these are the three notions which are characterizing a system ability to function.
One is availability and refers to the system ability to respond to the
request process and response to the requests.
Durability refers to the fact that is reflected the storage means it means that
if you successfully start a piece of data,
you are going to be able to later retrieve the piece of data,
that piece of data.
He's not going to disappear or is going to be lost
despite maybe some the storage device failures,
and then reliability.
It's puts the two together,
both availability and your ability,
and basically the ability of the system to perform the required function,
according to some specification during the space.
For instance, if you are going to send the request,
you are going to get a response within a specified time period.
And obviously, that should be correct.
Last time, we discussed little about a durability.
Let's go again back.
And we discuss about this is basically a summary of the last few slides
from the last lecture.
I know you could provide your ability.
It's again, the ability that once you start a piece of data,
you can later retrieve that piece of data.
It's basically replicating the data.
Right?
And if you replicate the data,
then it provides you the ability to survive to one this failure.
Because if one this failed,
you still have the other these storing the epitope of the data.
The data is not lost.
We also discuss.
So what are the characteristics of this system of this red one where you
replicate any piece of data on two different disks?
One is that when you write a date, a piece of data,
you need to write on both disks.
Therefore, you sacrifice the bandwidth of the right,
because each right now becomes two rights to different disks.
It's also, you need to wait for the slower,
slow as this to do the right.
If you want to really optimize of how long this right latency,
you probably want to synchronize a disk.
So therefore, both rise,
take the same amount of time, more or less.
On the other hand,
for real things are a little bit different and are better.
Because now you have two replicas, and you need, when you read,
you need us to get a piece of data.
So you can get from either disk.
So actually, you can improve or can even double the throughput.
In this case,
finally, if you remember,
when it is fair,
is what you are going to do.
You are going to buy another one,
and then you are going to copy all the data from the primary
now from primary disk to the secondary,
to the new disk.
And now you have a game to a rebel class.
Now,
this assumes that while you're doing these recoveries
of primary disk doesn't fail.
And that's something to keep in mind.
And actually, this is a problem, in general,
because this is if you do this right one,
and you do you build the right one and your application,
presumably, what you want this to be from different batches of production.
Because if you and this,
you need to be careful, right?
Because when you buy this,
you buy all the disk at the same time to build this system.
But then if this guy from the same batches batch of production,
they tend to have the same failures and the same kind of failure pattern.
And then when one this fails is pretty likely than other,
is also from the same bachelor fail.
So you don't want to do that,
because you want to reduce apps as a minimum,
the risk that during the recovery,
another disposal.
So that's how you use different product batches or you receive and may be
different disk manufacturers.
The problem with red wine is very expensive and so far so high overhead.
We discuss about this straight, right?
Five and more your stripes, the data.
So you have a parity block.
In this case,
you take the blocks out of,
you start successively, in this case,
for blocks on four disks.
And then on the five disk here,
you are going to have computer parity block,
the parity block.
One way to compute its excellent,
like we discussed last time,
d zero here is d zero,
x or d one, x or d two x or d three.
Here is an example.
If you want,
if one biscuits it's destroyed,
you can still recover.
This is an example.
Here is an example.
Here.
Each block is 1 bit,
let's say, d zero, it's zero,
then d one 1, d 20,
d 31.
If you do the x or here,
you are going to get zero.
This is a parity on the content of the parity block.
Now, suppose this to fail.
If you do this to fail,
then what you do,
you are going to do the x or everything,
which is, including the parity block.
And then you are going to get the content of the lost block.
So in this case, we do was zero.
You get deal with the zero,
x or v one,
x or b three, x or p zero, the parity block.
And you get zero, you recover.
It's a great question.
Why do we start parody staggered?
Gilbert, he says,
answer that if they are in the same row columns and we
might have to trouble recovering if that specific route column got lost.
So basically, it's about load balancing the load when you have failures.
Right?
For instance, if the parity block fails,
then both the readers,
the disposal parity block fails.
At least the reels will not be affected,
because all the blocks are there, right?
The data blocks in the background,
you are going to reconstruct the parity block.
So that's 111 reason.
Right?
It's a game.
It's like, if you put all the parity blocks on a disk,
then if any other disks goes away,
then all the reads have to reconstruct using the parity block.
So it's expensive.
All there is for the data, from the failures.
If the parity blocks are staggered,
then again,
when the disk is a parity,
when you access the data whose parity block was on a failed disk,
you don't need to do anything because the data is available.
This is I the same solution,
in principle, is going to recover.
Also.
What is the internet?
Right?
It's like, not there.
It doesn't need to be in the same data center or in the same rack.
And then it's, again,
this straight five.
It's provides your ability in the presence of one this failure.
What if you want to have more these failures?
There are, as a version of ride back,
ride x instead of parity blocks,
there is your asian code.
For instance,
rate six allowed to disk and replicate to fail in the replication,
strive to fail.
Many of these are the three solomon codes of the radio codes.
In this case, you have m data fragments.
You can think about blocks,
and you generate n minus m extra fragments.
Now, to start m blocks of m fragments of data or blocks of data,
you are going to need and blocks out of which n minus rm
are newly generated blocks.
This can generate n minus m failures.
So basically, you can,
if, as long as you have,
m in, the m disks are still up,
then you can reconstruct nemd scout of n are up.
You can reconstruct all the pieces of it, right?
It's again.
So like, for instance,
if you want really to have extremely,
something extremely resilient,
extremely durable, you can have, like, in this example,
you can have m is for fragments or blocks and in 16.
So then you are going,
the overhead is quite high.
And by this system will be extremely durable.
And like mentioning,
you can have the device.
All the disk drives in the same a room,
or you can have them across the internet.
And obviously, when they are across the internet,
you are going to have a much more durable system because the correlation
of failure is lower,
right?
If all the discard in the same room,
if you have an earthquake or you have a fire,
or that this may be destroyed.
Here a a it's a very interesting aspect.
And at the high level,
so one is so say you want to do,
you are prepared to pay an overhead here.
In this example,
you say an overhead of forex.
So for each piece of data,
I am not going to require 4 time storage.
Like if I start one gigabyte of data,
I am going to use four gigabytes of storage.
And one thing is to have for a wise replication,
each piece of data,
I am going to replicate on four different pieces.
And then you compute here,
this is fraction block loss per year.
This is on the y axis,
the x axis,
the repair time of algorithm,
or but then in your computer probably is that you lose all the data, right?
This means all 4 days start going to fail before you have a chance to rebel.
Now, the other way you can do it is the following thing.
And that's why it's called fragments.
I'm saying,
i'm taking a block and instead of replicating four time for on four beasts,
I am going to take assume that I have,
say, 64 disk,
smaller disks that are the total story is the same.
But then i'm taking a block,
and i'm going to divide it into 6, 16 fragments.
And for each fragment, I am going.
And then for the 16 fragments,
and i'm going to compute using gradient codes.
Another 64-16,
48 fragment, right?
The overhead is the same.
But now I have a lot of more fuel,
a lot of more fragments.
And in this particular case,
this will be a much more durable system.
Let me say a little bit about this plot.
Now, on the x axis,
you have repair time on the y axis.
Here you are going to have probability of block failure period.
This basically says that, as you expect,
and different lines are for the number of fragments,
for 8, 16, 72,
64 for four fragments.
Is basically you have a replication on,
basically, on for,
as you can see this way on for the or for devices.
Obviously, you can expect that the repair time increases,
then the probability of failure will increase,
right?
Because if it takes one day to repair,
that is a chance that other bees will fail within one day,
is much smaller than if the repair takes 6 months.
Then now you have seen 6 months have already, obviously,
the point that is to fail is much higher.
But this, basically,
again, this is simple probability.
This basically tells you that the probability to have,
say, in this case to have for this,
so for this to fail,
so you lose all the copies is much higher.
Then they probably to have all for this to fail to have.
In this case, 49 of these of 64,
these two facts.
Michael asked this question in practice, are error codes.
I the parity codes ever used instead of eraser codes.
If you have only to tolerate a failure,
I think you are still going to use the priority codes.
It's just easier,
or you are going to use replication.
The other one.
But in general, you do is erasure codes and erasure codes.
Actually, they are using all these distributed file systems,
also like how to distribute file systems that are version,
which are using erasal codes.
They actually exactly to improve reliability.
But I will ask a question,
what does it mean to repair for 6 months?
So think about this is depends of how difficult is to repair,
but in the past,
you have the discounts,
and you lost some disks.
So now you need to order those disks.
The delivery,
it may take 3 months, right?
Because in your order to be approved,
if you are at a company and all of these things, right?
And then your disk have to be shipped.
Maybe you have all the disk and your similar disk,
so it just takes time.
The time is a mean,
repair time is a time it takes.
If you lost some cop,
you lost some copies to recover these copies.
Because and for that,
you may need to buy additional hardware to replace the one which has failed.
Make sense?
Here it's an example about using and studying the fragments over over the internet.
So again,
just wanted to make sure here to go back that what we are saying here is
when you do that application,
again, you have one block,
so say one block is one kilobyte.
You replicate.
You have4 copies, one kilobyte,
only on different amounts.
When you lose a fragmentation, here,
you take one kilobyte,
and the divide is out blocked divided in 16 fragments.
For 16 fragments, you are going to have what?
It's to power.
It's one kilobyte divided by 16,
right?
And I believe it's what 128,
something like that bytes.
Now you have this kind of.
It's now you have,
sorry, you have 64, right?
16×64.
Yep.
So divided one kilobyte is 16 fragments.
And then you are going to each fragment now is going to have 64 bytes.
Now you are going to generate another 48 fragments.
Each of them are 64 bytes using greater products.
Now, in order to read the data,
you need to read 16 fragments.
Any of these 64 drag,
any 16 fragments out of 64 fragments will do it.
And you can construct and construct the original block.
Make sense?
I need to make sure we are on the same page.
This is about your ability.
But this is not enough the fact that the disk,
the data is still on the disk.
It doesn't mean that you can access it.
Also, it doesn't mean that you are also able to write the data on
the disk in the first place.
Right?
So that's why we care about reliability.
Reality is looking at the end to end.
It is not doesn't care only what the data is on the disk,
but whether you can put the data on the disk and you can retrieve the data
from the disk.
So next we are going to talk about reliability,
but let's talk about what can go wrong, right?
Which is orthogonal to durability.
So say a disk loses power or you have a software crash.
Now you have a read operation or write operation.
What happens is that route operation, which is in progress,
maybe can be lost, right?
Or maybe it's interrupted in the middle.
You just wrote half a block, not the entire block.
So raid doesn't protect against any of such failures, right?
Raid basically says,
if you are successful to write data and you have so many replicas,
if you once you've done that,
I guarantee that you find the data.
When you come next time,
it'll be store.
Right?
So, yes,
you need your ability.
But this is not the entire story.
So this is what we are going to talk next.
Right?
Why is this a bigger problem?
This is a bigger problem,
because when you write data on a disk,
when you write a block of data in a disk,
it's not only that piece of data.
You need maybe to,
you need to update the I note data, right?
Because you have a new block.
Now,
maybe it's an indirect block.
The.up to the indirect block,
the indirect indirection pointer.
You need to update the bid map of the which files are now available,
sorry, which blocks are available.
Availability bit, mark, right?
If you write in a blog on a block,
that block is no longer available.
So I need to update a bit much.
So for each of these riots,
you need actually to touch and multiple.
You need to touch multiple pieces of information from the risk.
And if some of them made to the disk,
but some of them do not make the disk.
You are going to leave the disk in an inconsistent state.
So that's a problem, right?
How do you do that?
Not only when you have this kind of multiple operations,
which means all to succeed in order for the right to succeed.
And by the so that's kind of the problem.
Right?
And you also there are other complication because if you want a concurrency
for improving throughput,
so you want to to perform this operation in parallel and sing
in sensing like that.
Make sure it makes sense.
Any questions?
What are the stress to threats to reliability?
Like we discuss its interrupted operation?
Crash of software crashes,
power failures.
And when this happens,
then you can get into trouble.
This is a classical canonical example about the bank transfer.
You transfer from one bank to another,
to from one account to another.
What happens if you have a failures after you withdraw the sum of money?
But before you have a chance to deposit the sum of money,
a in a different account,
then you lost that those fun if you are not careful.
It's also this one failure of nonvolatile storage, right?
Storage media may cause previous store data to disappear or be corrupted,
like we are going to see.
Any questions about what problems you are trying to solve here?
You're trying to solve here.
The biggest problem is that when you are going to write the data on the disk,
the biggest problem you do not want in the presence of failures to leave
the data on the disk
in an inconsistent state.
That's a problem.
There are two ways to do it.
Two general ways.
One,
you are just careful in you carefully are ordered your
operations such that if you have failures,
when you restart,
you can clean up the mess and leaves a disk in a consistent state.
That's why the other one is copy and write.
The copy on write.
You can think about the data you wrote is immutable.
When you try to modify some piece of data,
you basically create another copy,
and you modify the copies,
you don't modify the original so original.
It's always there.
When you are done, you are pointing to the modified copy,
and maybe you can garbage for like the original.
Okay?
This is what it is.
So the left hand side,
the careful ordering of recovery is used, by fact,
and fast file system, the unix,
this is file system check.
It's a command iran.
When you reboot the system,
this command runs to clean up the disk.
If there are problems,
inconsistent data.
Really,
you are carefully about the order in which are doing these operations,
right?
Like for instance,
you create a new file is you need to update the directory.
You need to update the 3 bit map,
the updates, I know to update the data book.
So this is a careful ordering couple.
So at the high level is, again,
problem I want to solve.
A failure shouldn't result in the data that this being inconsistent.
The solution you need to order carefully,
all the rise to the disk,
which are needed to store that.
But the piece of data such that when you are going to restart,
you have enough information.
So you can clean up the disk from any partial and wrong.
Information is also used at the application level,
say, editors like or emails.
So let me ask you this question,
because this is the court to understand this technique.
I assume you need to store a piece of data and the directory entry point
to the data or the pointer to the data,
and assume that each of this operation is atomic,
but there are two different rights,
one to update to put the data on the disk.
And the other one is to put to update the director.
Tell me now this a question is the following.
Which one you should write?
First?
The data of the point
data,
why that's very good.
Why is the data?
It's exact.
You don't want the pointer.
The point is about the state.
I don't want dangling pointers.
Excellent.
Right?
And then say this is correct.
First, you write the data,
and then you write the pointer.
Now say you have a failure.
You are successful to write the data, but not the pointer.
What do you do?
When you restart the system?
Because now you have inconsistent state,
you need to garbage collection collect somehow.
Basically, you look at all the data on the disk,
all the blocks.
And you see whether there is a pointer,
there is a directory entry,
in this case for them.
If it's not, you are garbage collecting it.
This will appear like the right has failed in the first place didn't happen,
which is okay.
If we write beta,
but no pointer,
michael is asking if we write data,
but no pointer isn't that the same as writing mask at all?
It is.
But now that space may be used,
so you need to garbage collect.
Yeah, this assume that it's very good..
It's assume that you also update the three maps.
That's why iiii make I simplify the example.
In general, you need to obey the three map.
You need to obey the I node, like,
what's your next?
Right?
But in this case, I assume that when you write a piece of data that block,
it's our already allocated.
So therefore, you need to garbage fund.
So now it's very easy for you to understand.
Here are the normal operations for berkeley,
for fast file system.
You allocate a data block,
you write a data block,
you allocate and I node,
your ici node, which is pointing to that data block.
You update the big map of three blocks and I nodes,
and update the directory with a file name,
pointing to the I note number.
And then you update modified time for directory.
And what do you update the modified time for the director?
It's like,
right?
You start from the data and you go backwards all the way to the directory.
What do you do on recovery?
Like we discussed the scans, I know, table.
And there is any only files,
not in any directory.
You delete it,
right?
Or maybe you put in lost and found directory.
If you have one,
then you compare the free block bit map against I naughty and to see
whether they are consistent.
Right?
It's again, we just can't elect or they are missing from the big map.
They are not reflected in the free map to garbage collector.
Then you scan directory for missing updated access.
Now, you do all of these things.
Again, a it's a mode involving procedure,
because you are here,
you have to write more pieces of data which are associated or linked
with a data block when you write a data block.
But fundamentally,
the same idea like we discussed earlier on when you have only data block
and a pointer to the data.
Obviously, the problem with this, and if you want to do it,
is the time is proportional to the disk size,
because you need to look at all blocks.
Any questions?
This was the first solution.
How do you recover a failed recovery?
For the failure?
That's a great question.
For a failed recovery.
You make sure that when you are going to take the actions,
you are taking the same action that when you recover next,
you can still clear clean up everything.
Okay?
That's what it is.
You apply recursive with the same idea.
The second one is copy on the right.
This is also called cow.
And you fundamentally create a new version of the file.
This is a simple version.
The simple the simple implementation of this is that if i'm going to update
a piece of beta,
if I want to update a piece of beta,
I don't update in place.
I create a copy, and I update the copy.
And later I can believe the origin.
It seems expensive,
but the updates can be back.
If you have multiple updates,
you can do at the same time.
Which, so you remember,
if you send a batch of rice to the beast,
the disk can be smart.
This controller can be smart to reorder them.
So to minimize the c latency and even the rotation latency,
this is a method.
This a is approach,
copy and write is taken by a few other systems.
Zfs is oracle.
Now,
There is also an open dfs and that appliance has its right anywhere file
layout or waffle.
They use the same this technique.
And here how it is assume that you have the file is represented as a three
of blocks.
Right?
You are just updating.
What is called here is a fringe block.
The block at the end, you started all you,
and you are adding more blocks to this file structure.
Now, assume that you update these blocks on the right hand side,
the one, which is,
it's half blue.
Right?
What you do, actually,
in this particular case,
you write in a new block,
a copy.
That's all you write.
You took this block,
you replicate it,
and your updates are bigger.
The regional block remains untouched.
So now what you do, you just basically generate a new bunch of pointers,
a sub three.
And then you are going to connect these new notes in the new
version of the tree to the corresponding existing tree
notes.
Right?
Now,
if you are successful in updating all these pointers,
after you updated the data,
then the version of the tree and of the file moved from the old version
to the new version.
Once you do that, you can do garbage,
collect the rest.
You see all the blocks,
data blocks from the all version of the file,
as well as interior nodes in the tree,
again, which are not pointed by the new version.
They've been garbage for that.
Any block,
any interior node,
to which there is no black arrow pointing.
This can be garbage collective.
And now you have a new version.
This, again,
is like you are going to move from all version to the new version
only in the last moment.
Once you update all the interior nouns of the tree,
and obviously the day you created the new, you update is a blog.
After you copy it.
If you are not successful,
if you fail during this process, it's okay.
You have the old version.
The old version is still consistent.
It only reflects a new update.
But again, that's okay.
The main problem we try to solve here is to not leave the storage system
in inconsistency.
Any questions?
Is this better or worse on ssd it seems like we are writing a lot more,
but don't have to erase as often.
Well, yeah, it's worse for us at this,
because you are going to wear is this small.
And but again,
we have other solutions like we'll see.
But in general, this is worse.
You still need to erase because you need to garbage for like,
garbage collection means you later.
But a great question.
This is,
like I mentioned to you,
the fs of the fs is variable size blocks.
It's a symmetric tree.
Basically, the tree you are building is symmetric of a certain depth.
So basically,
it because you might be dislike how large or small is.
If the depths of the tree and what leave the need for you are at,
you can estimate that side of the triplet they are, correct.
If it's balanced, right?
If it is symmetric,
if it's not symmetric, then you cannot do that.
You store the version number in the pointers.
The pointer to inspiration number belongs to,
like we saw before,
you can create a new version by adding new blocks and new pointers.
As a tree expand,
you are going to garbage for like,
the all day does all pointers to make room for the new date.
In this case, is you try to batch everything,
you try to batch the rights,
you try to batch the updates to the free space and so forth.
Now, let's talk about more a general solutions,
one solution, which are going to talk also next time.
Now it's just briefly,
is transaction.
Fundamentally,
what do you want here is remember,
we want to avoid to have to remain in an inconsistent state
and the remaining an inconsistent state,
because they have multiple related updates.
If only part of the updates happen,
then you have in western state.
So we had this problem before.
If you remember,
and we talk about critical section,
we talk about that when I talk about atoms.
Right?
With atomic operation,
we want all of the operation to happen or none of sort.
The same idea is this transaction for the storage system.
This is called in some transactions.
There are more than atomic operation because they also required durability
and other properties.
But the idea is the same a transaction contained multiple operations,
and the semantics should be,
these are all the operation in a transaction are going to happen to be successful,
or none of them will happen.
If you're a failure in the middle of the transaction,
then it looks like none of the updates is the transaction ever happened.
The entire transaction failed.
Okay?
We discuss about this and it's again,
closely related to its critical section and with the concept
of atomic update for member.
In some sense,
the file for fast file system,
the witch approach to carefully ordering the sequence of updates,
and then recover from inconsistent state.
When you restart a it's a primitive form of implementing this idea.
Again, we discussed that just to draw home the.,
a transaction is a bunch of operations,
which state a system from a consistent state to another consistent state.
And therefore,
we want all the operation in the transaction to happen,
or none of them to happen.
If none of them will happen,
you remain in the previous state, which is consistent, by definition,
if all will happen,
you are going to move to a new state,
which is, again, will be consistent.
So in one way,
transaction extends the concept of atomic updates
to multiple data structures for a
memory to persistent storage.
What is the typical structure of the transaction?
You have a begin transaction,
you have a for me,
transaction or end of the transaction.
And then you do a bunch of operations.
If you fail during these operations,
you are going to roll back to undo the effect of the operation have succeeded.
So this way, you are guaranteed that if you fail during a transaction,
then all the operation will be undued.
From an external observer.
It appears that the transaction,
nothing from the transaction happened.
Okay?
These are examples in which are going to transfer $100 from alice account
to bob accounts.
There are a bunch of operations here to update the account of alice and bob
went to account the branch,
how many money,
how much monies are in the branch?
Assuming that alice and bob are in different,
their accounts are in different branches of the same bank.
There are four operations.
All of them should happen in a transaction to be able.
This is what you do.
You have these operations here is on the exercises at that time.
This is how it appears.
And then there are these operations that can be interleaved this operation
from other transactions.
So there are transaction, actually,
like we are going to see next time,
can overlap.
And then you have starter transaction and commit
transaction.
Any questions?
Let's see how transactions are used for file systems.
You can see a little bit about how they could be used.
Basically, the chain changes are treated as transactions.
And there are 2 kinds of file systems here,
2 types of file system,
log structure and journal.
In a log structure,
the data stays in the log.
And locks are updated using transactions.
In a journal file system.
Log is used only for recovery.
The data is still in the traditional data format on the disk.
We are going to look to journal file system in the next couple of slides.
It's the same idea.
A little bit always like is that you don't modify data structure on the disk,
direct this idea,
you will put them on the changes on the log.
And only after you are done,
we saw to speak, the transaction is all the changes.
You push the changes to the risk.
It turns out that as long as long as along is persistent,
even if you have failures,
you can always recover.
We'll see how to say that on the show of amygdav.
Okay.
This is exactly what I said.
You're right.
The updates of the as a transaction,
the related updates as a transaction in the law.
Once the transaction is committed in the log,
you can now start applying those operation in the transaction on the storage.
If you, if you fail in between, it's okay,
because when you come back,
you have enough information to continue to update the disk.
The data on the disk.
Once along all the operate,
all the updates in a transaction are successfully applied to the disk.
You are going to remove the log.
So this is linux use journal file system,
and basically took of ffs like file system and apply jam.
There are many systems.
There is a journaling file system.
Okay.
So let's it before to see to get a sense about how journaling is working.
Let's look, again,
what are the typical updates you need to do when you are going to write
data on the disk.
For now, there is no journal.
So you need to do what you need to find a free block.
The yellow block, there is a free block.
Good.
You need to find a free entry.
I know the entry.
You need to find where you are going to insert.
And the in the file directory where you are going to insert the entry,
which associate the file with the I node,
file language, I know.
And then once you're update,
you find all these free available spaces.
You start to write,
you write the in the free map space.
You say you mark that you allocate the data, you're right.
And I note entry to point is a block you're out and derive
that the director directory entry to point to the item.
This article.
Right?
And remember, if something happens, wrong happens,
it can leave the disk in the inconsistent state.
Now, let's see how we address this problem in journal.
A german is locked.
So instead or when,
instead of writing directly to the disk,
you start you write to the lock.
It's not volatile.
It's on flash or on the disk.
What do you find the free data block?
Again, like these are the operations, right?
Find free data block, find 39 or 90,
find a directory and insertion pointing directory for adding the directory
entry to map the file name to the island.
It's what you do.
You start the transaction,
and you write this operation.
Now,
you don't write directly to update the free space map.
You put the operation to the updates,
a free space map in the law.
You don't write the you don't update the iron ore table to point
to the new block.
You write that operation in the lock,
the same.
The operation to update the directory entry,
you are going to write in the log.
Now, you're committed.
So all updates,
all operation to update information on the disks are in the lock.
Nothing happened so far on the disk.
And then once you are done,
you are going to go through all the operations, the logs.
And you are going to update now,
the data or the information on the disk.
So you copy all the changes,
you advance a tale of the log.
And now,
when the tail goes over the commit or executed, all you,
after you execute all the operations,
apply all the operation from the log on the file system.
You can discard that log,
that transaction in the log.
Let's say that I was only successful to write to the logs,
only this
do the operation to get to the free space,
to modify the bit map,
to the space bit map,
and the pointer to the item.
In this case,
if I am coming back,
and I assume that after these operations are written in the law,
but before the transaction ended, I have a failure.
At this point, in this case,
if I come back,
like the only thing I need to do is to remove this operation to remove
from the lock,
because it spines point still nothing has been applied on the disk.
You apply the changes on the disk,
only after the transaction is succeeded on the lock.
After the committee,
there are two questions here.
Can you have a fail when while writing the log?
Absolutely.
But then everything will be clean up.
Like, in this case, you can fail while you're writing on the log.
When you come back,
you look at the incompetent transaction,
you clean them up,
Because that nothing from the transaction which has not finished for me,
did,
has been all applied to the disk.
What's a big difference between writing directly?
The big difference from writing,
between writing directly and writing is along is very simple,
right?
Is basically because I have a log and I have done,
then I can easy reconstruct the state to make it consistent in the file system.
Otherwise is more difficult.
Remember,
like with a files check for the fast file system,
in order to make the state consistent,
you need to go and to sequential look over the entire distance
is extremely slow.
It's again here.
In the log,
we assume that we know that we know that arrive has been completed.
Assume that we know that the disk eventually will tell you.
If the disk doesn't tell you,
then you assume that it doesn't.
Yeah.
So the question here is that basically see how to ensure the sequentially?
Well,
you make sure that a controller for the log is not going to reorder the rights.
Faces an excellent question.
That is a very good question.
So resources how this happened,
if you and now,
we saw that what happened if you just a log was partially written.
When you come back, you just remove the entries from the partial logs.
You are done.
But now let's assume that let's see what
happens like what now we are.
We committed the log the transaction.
Now we need to apply all the operation.
In the log, we need to apply them to the risk.
What do you start from?
That matching commit?
And then what you are going to do here,
it basically is against every of this operation is either important,
meaning that if you apply it multiple times,
you are going to get the same result,
because it just right, one, right?
Is particularly identical that if you write the same value
at the same location over and over again,
you are still going to get the same value.
No matter how many times throughout,
here is what happens,
here is about, again,
if you are going to successfully apply all the operations to the disk,
you are done.
You can garbage for it like you've seen.
But now assume that you have a failure in the middle or you're applying
the operation from the law to that is.
So what do you do?
Simple.
When you come back?
Again,
you go from the beginning and you applies all the operations
because the operation are right important.
It doesn't matter how many times supplies eventually are going to finish.
Right?
And then you are going to garbage for like the transaction.
The question,
how does discard the log work again when the machine started writing
the log disk that it's already updated?
Partially?
How do we undo the only part that is not permitted?
So maybe I was not, it's a great question.
And we are not clear.
There is nothing you are going to update on the disk unless the transaction
is being committed.
Nothing.
You see this operation?
Let me just very clear.
What's these green things?
They are not modified.
I just found this entries.
Right?
Nothing has been modified on the disk.
You start only modifying,
once you wrote, the transaction has permitted,
now you can start to go back.
You apply all the changes in the transaction on the disk.
Only now you update the data on the disk.
Not before.
Did answer your question?
I owe you answer.
Another question,
can we even tell which portion of a committee log is finished?
It's again,
if you don't need to know, right?
If you don't know to know it is finished,
because you are going to repeat from the beginning every time.
When you go back,
when you restart,
you are going to redo all the operation from the lock.
It doesn't matter whether I already done.
Previously.
I've done a few.
So I have three operation in the blog,
in the log to apply 1 to 3,
I applied its operation one, and two.
Then I failed.
When I come back, i'm starting again with 12, and 3.
And then hopefully I am successful to apply three, and then i'm done.
I can apply one and two again,
because one and two are rights.
They are immutable.
They are going to write to,
i'm going to write the same value.
It's okay.
Why go through all this trouble?
Because it makes it easy to reason and be quite efficient to make
sure that the state on the disk is persistent.
It's consistent in the presence of failure.
Isn't it expensive?
From one perspective, it's expensive,
because you are going to write twice,
you may write the data,
you are going to write on the blog on the log.
And then you are going to write data on the list.
However,
the modern file system is for about this to mention,
they have different optimization to do it.
So you can have different optimization.
Like, for instance, eventually,
the data you can write it directly.
And if you fail,
then you eventually recovered at the light of time.
But there is one, actually,
I want to ask you,
can you see one reason actually journaling file systems generally can be
good for performance.
If I tell you that journaling can also help with the performance,
why do you think that would be the case?
How is the log
organized sequentially?
Correct?
We know the sequential rise are fast,
so all the rise in the longer sequential,
so they are very fast.
And then later,
you can actually batch the updates from the logs to the disk.
So you can do them as efficient as you can.
That's the reason.
So it's not all bad when it comes to performance.
Announcements projects three,
design reviews this week.
This is the last round of the dining bills.
We are close to the end of the class.
Hormone five is due monday,
next monday.
And we have
mid term grades were released.
I think you did congratulations, you did very well.
The first exams,
aminos around%50%.
Now it's almost 60%.
So great job.
Now we have another a little bit more than 12 minutes,
and we are going to swiss gears.
So we are done with file system reliability, and it's file system.
In general.
We are going to start talking about distributing systems.
So we are talking about distributed systems,
because they are everywhere,
because we need to scale all these workloads.
And they require a lot of machines,
lot of resources,
which many separate systems.
Because any application today are using almost it has a backend,
which is some somewhere in the cloud connecting europe,
the front end of your application.
You can answer your device with a back end is another disability system.
So you have everybody in your car.
There are5,100 microprocessors that are connected by a bus.
That's also a distribution system.
There are 2 kind of disability systems.
One is centralized.
And if you have a coordinator, a server,
for instance,
all the machines are connected to one particular server is follows.
A plan set up a model is on the left hand side,
the right hand side is peer to peer model.
The peer model is more.
Everyone can every other now can communicate with every other.
Now,
the communication in moscow is less structured,
is more general.
The kind of client server is also implemented by some
of the distributed systems for framework,
like hard look spark.
This is,
and like I mentioned,
disability systems can be on the same car in the same you can have.
And the context can be widely different.
You can have a distributed system in your car,
in a room,
in your home,
in your building data center or across the globe.
There are many reasons, again,
for being distributed systems,
some of them because the applications, the users,
you want to connect the users.
And the users are different locations.
Some of them,
because like I mentioned,
one server cannot do is not powerful enough to support all the workload
to perform all the workload.
But there are also other reasons.
Sometimes it's cheaper.
And this was a truth like it used to be that if you aren't very powerful computers,
you build supercomputers,
you can still be able to play supercomputers.
These are very expensive,
takes year to build, to deliver.
And then with the rise of the internet,
in particular, google drove the charge,
and that was based on some research which has done it directly network
of all stations.
People started to replace supercomputers with a bunch of servers,
commodity servers,
by service, you can buy right?
Online or whatever, right?
And then you connect the servers.
And now we have a much more powerful intelligence software on top,
that on the aggregate,
they can provide you a lot of power,
computation, power, and storage space.
What is the promise of the security systems?
One problem is higher availability.
If one machine goes down, use another one,
right?
Despite some failures, actually,
all the services in the cloud are pretty reliable.
Your facebook, google and so forth.
They are pretty reliable,
more reliable than your laptop.
Better your ability.
You can store like you saw the data in multiple location across the globe.
And also, in principle,
modern security,
because we have multiple pieces.
You split your application, multiple pieces.
And now you need to protect only 1 piece in a I only 1 piece at a time
and securing 1 piece.
Presumably, it's easier than securing the entire system.
However,
you need to be very careful,
and it's not easy to deliver on that promise.
In general,
there have been many systems beyond distributed systems which provides
worse of everything,
worse availability,
worse reliability, or security,
worse availability.
This is leslie lambert.
During our winner,
you'll hear more about him before the class ends,
but you are saving the healthiest quote.
A it's like a funny coat.
A distributed system is one in with a failure of a computer.
You didn't even now existed,
can render your own computer that you unusable.
You can think about if you have your email and email server, right?
If your email client works on your computer,
but the email server is down,
your computer is pretty useless for email.
What is reliability?
If the data you are not careful of the data,
and you don't know where the data is.
If the day if the computer crashes of starting the data crashes,
then you lost the data.
What security?
Because if you compromise a component,
maybe you can compromise the entire system.
Also, coordination is more difficult.
But I remember we have all these challenges to coordinate
on the same machine between different threads.
Critical section deadlocks.
Remember that now this is much more complicated because
not even on a single machine,
it's across the network.
And you remember,
to address these challenges,
we have this kind of very convenient primitives,
like test and set or pmb well,
these are atomic operation implement based on atomic operations,
implemented in hardware.
How you are going to implement this in a distributed system.
When machines can be thousands of miles away.
And fundamentally,
the security is a trust.
It's more difficult,
because you need to be careful that even if a component of the system is compromised,
then other parts of the system are not compromised.
This is corollary to lump code.
A disability system is one where you can do it,
because some computer you didn't even now existed,
is successfully coordinating an attack on my system, right?
It's again, in compromise part of the system.
You can bring that down the entire system.
If you are not careful in designing these systems.
Now, when you design a distributed system,
what are your goals?
What are the requirements?
And simply the requirements you want to have is to be as transparent as possible.
It's to be almost maybe like your lap more or less.
Right?
You don't want to be aware about.
There are so many machines.
You get this transparency, like, for instance,
when you use your facebook application,
do you know how many machines are involved in answering some
of your requests in sending the news,
feed or messages, chat, widows.
No, you don't.
That's transparency, good transparency.
The transparency, as you can imagine,
has multiple dimension location.
You don't know what your servers and servers handling your facebook account
up located migration.
Sometimes you need to move the data from one place to another to scale
up the system that should be also transparent.
You are not aware about the replication.
You don't know in how many places your data is replicated.
Concurrency, you yourself.
You cannot say you cannot tell how many other Facebook users
at the same time on the system.
Still,
your experience is the same whether there are 1,000 or 5,000 or 51 billion.
That means that is Paris.
You also want to be paralyzed.
I if you want to have a big job,
you want the system to somehow transparently split it, ideally,
and then execute multiple pieces if possible in parallel and different machines.
So it is running fast and falter as for sure,
like we discuss.
If there are failures,
you absolutely do not want.
There's also to see these failures.
So any of these things requires the nodes,
do some computers to communicate between themselves.
And this is what protocol exchanges.
Okay?
The protocol.
It's an agreement about how to communicate.
It has a syntax.
We describe the comments,
the syntax of the send message, for instance, receive message.
What are the type of fields?
Name of the common as any semantics?
When you send some packets?
What really matter, what really happened,
what actions are taken?
In general, this is description of a state machine,
a protocol.
You receive a message.
You are in a way state to wait for a message,
to receive a message,
and you go into a state to process a message and seem like that.
We are on the Top of the hour.
So to stop here,
we are going to continue next time.
And next time.
It's going to be an exciting lecture.
We are going to talk about protocols.
You are going to talk the byzantine general problem, consensus problem,
and also going to talk about now about real transactions and to see
how they are implemented under the quote.
Thank you and see you on Monday.
Good luck with everything else.