Hello, everyone.
So today we are going to talk about a few things.
I think all very interesting topics.
In particular, you are going to talk about transactions how in general,
how do different computers can agree with each other?
And then we are going to talk quite a bit about networking.
Let's start, if you remember,
from last time,
we discussed about we touch on the protocols and protocol is
a fundamental concept when
two parties are communicating,
because you need a protocol to see how everyone is going to perform
the communication and how is going to interpret the communication.
And like we discussed last time,
there are two parts of a protocol is a syntax.
And the syntax is basically describe the structure,
the comments of the communication protocol.
Then there is a semantics which describe the meaning of,
say, the messages of the meaning of the comments.
And these are typically implemented by state machines.
You send a message.
What is the same machine means here?
Is that you are going in initial state and from initial state,
you are going to send a message.
And then you made transition in a state,
and you are waiting for a reply.
Right?
That's a different state.
If you wait for the reply,
the reply doesn't come,
then you may have experience a time out,
and you are going to go into another state.
And maybe you are going to,
he sent the original message,
right?
Just to give you a sense.
And also, if you want to the protocol to be for tolerant,
one way to do it is to start its state,
the current state of the protocol.
So that when you are going,
when you come back up after the failures where you left,
here is a very simple class example.
This is about,
for instance,
when you talk with someone with telephone or by telephone by phone,
you pick up the phone,
but I do open it and listen for dial tone today on the cell phones that are
no longer dial phones.
But if you used one of these older phones that it's a dial phone,
dial down and dial down meanings that the phone it's available,
you can dial in the number.
If it's busy signals and you cannot, well, you can,
but if nothing will happen,
so you dial a phone is aa number,
and then you hear the ringing.
Right?
This means that the other person,
the founding store,
the other person,
and then colleagues and is going to answer hello.
And then you are going to start a conversation.
Then typically,
there is some kind of the protocol, right?
What is this is, again,
describes a protocol.
Then typically, when you wait for an answer, what do you do?
You pause, right?
You don't continue speaking.
You ask a question,
and then you are opposing what you want to give the other party a chance to
talk.
And then when the conversation ends,
you say something like buy or see you soon,
then you hang up, right?
This is an example of protocol, right?
And we are going to talk about some of the most important protocols
networking next lecture.
In particular, we are going to talk about dcb transfer control protocol.
Any questions?
Okay.
Again,
these are red lines represent the basically the communication exchange
of the information between the two parts.
To part of this.
The first group of adults exchange represent setting up the connection,
setting up the call,
right?
If you ring.
And then the other party answers that from that point you can start communicating.
Then the second group of arrows represent the communication.
Once the after the connection has been established,
the last group, it's obviously closing the connection.
Last two arrows.
So now,
so fundamentally,
now we are having an adult and we are having different machines.
Like we discussed last time,
many of the applications are running on different machines.
All of these your client,
facebook client.
And back end of facebook is the same application.
The back end of face facebook or google consist of many machines,
but I don't know serena queries that are a large number of machines which
are going to contribute to provide you with the answer.
This machine somehow needs to communicate and needs to synchronize among themselves.
And the biggest challenge here is that it's, again,
it's like you need to on a single machines,
we have the same problem to synchronize multiple threads in the case
of a single machine.
We've done that at the end of the day by using this kind of harder primitives,
like test and set,
which are atomic slide,
checking a value and setting a value.
And that operation is atomic.
If you remember, it's all very,
very helpful to build also the higher level, communicate,
synchronization, primitives,
like pnb and things like that.
Or locks and summer force.
The problem a a a in a distributed system.
That's the only way to,
but to application process is running on different machines,
can communicate is through sending a receiving message.
That's the only say thing you have and sending and receiving
a message is atomic in the sense that typically the receiver gets
the entire message you send by,
the sender don't send,
you don't get half a message,
but not you don't have more than that.
Right?
Anyway,
if you can think about what the abstraction looks like to
exchange information between two processes running on different machines,
sending and receiving message.
Abstraction is like a mailbox, right?
A you send a letter,
the recipient gets a letter and send you back.
Right?
You have a send primitive and receive primitive.
That's pretty much what you have.
So now,
let's think about how we are going to use these primitives to build
higher level primitives.
One of the most basic primitives.
It's about consensus.
So basically, what consensus about is that you want multiple nodes,
multiple parties to agree on a value.
This is what consensus means to agree on something,
right?
To pick one choice from multiple choices.
You need to do this in an environment,
in which different notes may fail,
a stop responding and messages can be lost.
And also, the message,
how long it takes a message to be delivered,
can be unbounded.
So this is a problem,
right?
And just to simplify the problem, actually,
you just think about that are two parties which wants to choose
between train force.
Right?
And if they choose have the same choice,
they commit, otherwise they are boss.
And,
again, need to do that in a globally scalable system.
And the decision shouldn't be forgotten,
especially when there is a failure.
Right?
You need to have some sort of durability.
Here is the example,
is this general paradox.
This is us one formulation of the problem to just illustrated the point.
So he has assumed that you have two generals who want to attack,
who must attack the enemy.
In this case, the red enemy,
the red castle in the middle.
Now,
if boss of these armies on his side,
attack at the same time,
they are going to win.
If the attack had different times that going to lose,
because the enemy will be is powerful,
is more powerful than a single army,
but it's less powerful than two army put together.
As such in this case,
the two armies need and the generals of the two armies need to agree,
went to attack.
Now, the biggest problem and obviously,
here think about all times we need to send messengers,
but the messenger can be intercepted by the enemy,
because the enemy is in the valley.
So say, in this case,
between the two arms,
this is it was aaa real similar situation like this custard in
in the history of the united states.
That was about a little big horn when she arrived earlier,
and he engaged earlier,
and I believe he died.
But it's a problem.
There's a power.
What we need to do here is to develop a solution in which
the two generals are going to agree on the time when to attack.
That's a problem.
Can you develop a such a protocol in an environment in which the messages
can be lost?
Can be arbitrarily related?
It turns out that is the answer is no.
Fundamentally, it's again,
say one general,
say I want to attack at 11:00 am the other ones say11:00 am works.
But then the second one,
who said that how he knows that the third general got his message,
the confirmation.
Because if he didn't,
right?
If he didn't get the confirmation,
then it's not going to attack.
Right?
And the second general attack alone,
right?
And so forth.
I told you that there is already no solution.
Now, I just want you to think a little bit.
Here is an example about an instance, right?
But can you think about,
and can you argue convincingly,
there is no protocol such that under these conditions,
the messages can be lost and can be arbitrary delayed.
The two generals can agree on the time to attack.
Why don't you take a few seconds,
maybe half a minute to think about this problem.
During this time, i'll get some
other.
Any idea?
Yes, there is always a final message required.
Allison said there is always a final message required to terminate the protocol.
And if that message is delayed or does not arrive the or cannot terminate,
this is pretty good answer.
Anyone wants to charming?
The more formal proof is the following.
Assume that the protocol,
a protocol exist,
and assume that the protocol has m messages.
Right?
Any protocol a has to terminate.
He has must have a finite number of messages.
Otherwise, if he never terminates,
the general, by definition, will never agree.
But now think about the last message.
I i'm sending the last message to you.
So you want to agree.
So I send the message,
but that's the last message.
I have no idea whether that message was received by you or it
wasn't received by you.
So from my perspective,
that message it's useless,
and it shouldn't be needed for the agreement.
Then this means that the protocol doesn't have a messages.
Is the protocol is a-1 messages,
is going to be good enough.
But then if it's you go so that the protocol has a minus on messages,
right?
You cannot go recursive,
because now a-1,
the last message doesn't have any value for you.
It should be n minus the messages.
That's kind of the way to think about it.
But it's allison,
it's correct.
It's about thinking about the last message.
Right?
All is the last message for the person who is going to send it.
It's useless because they don't know whether it was received
or not by the other party.
Now, this is a hard problem, right?
It's really hard problem.
In real life, you can use other things.
But how do we get out of it?
Right?
Because we still need different parties to agree to build any useful applications.
And this is where it comes.
The two face commit protocol,
because they cannot solve this general problem or general paradox.
We solve a related problem.
Before going here.
Any questions so far?
About the general paradox,
the general problem?
So the way to do so is that you to get around the problem
is that now the challenges of the general paradox is that you still have
the same problem,
oh you have more than one parties agree on something,
but you remove that is a time during which they must agree.
So you basically say there are no constraints on time.
They just eventually will happen,
eventually will agree.
Right?
That's kind of the big deal.
This is a two phase coming protocol.
It was developed by jim dray,
who has huge influences.
He was the first berkeley,
phd student computer science,
phd in 69,
and has a huge impact on databases.
And many important database breakthrough are going back to gym.
Unfortunately, he disappeared several years back while sailing.
So what is that to face coming?
Protocol is very simple.
First of all, you do have a persistent storage,
so you can save the state.
And then you have two phases,
prepare face and commit face.
Also, not all members are equal.
You have a coordinator,
You have a bunch of workers.
And the coordinator executes a protocol.
It basically sends to every worker,
a message basically asking to agree with something or not,
or whether it or not agree.
If every worker response that is,
they agreed,
you are the coordinator is going to tell to tell in the commit phase,
all the workers to commit.
If at least one worker says abort,
then all the workers will abort.
And that entire operation is about it.
Again, to take a step back here,
we want here that another way to think about it's all workers.
They must execute an operation.
These are all of them, the executive operation,
for none of them execute the operation.
In the case of databases that operation is a transaction.
So either all of them,
do you know exactly transaction or none of them?
Okay.
If all of them are ready at a big degree,
the transaction say we are ready,
we then coordinators they sent,
that to coordinators,
a coordinator will send back on it,
so everyone will commit the transaction.
Otherwise,
the coordinator will send aboard and everyone will abort the transaction.
Make sense?
And like you still, now,
you'll see the locks will be fundamental to guarantee that this protocol
is going to a correctly,
which means that either all workers commit or abort the transaction.
Again, you have one coordinator, in summary,
you have n workers.
The high level algorithms is the following.
The coordinator ask all workers,
if they can commit,
if all workers reply,
yes, we can commit,
then the coordinator broadcast to everyone commit.
Otherwise, a coordinator broadcast abort,
because there is at least one worker you cannot commit.
And the worker just obey these global messages where there is committee
and abort.
That's it.
We use persistent log in order to make sure that the protocol
or correctly when machines fail.
Now, here we assume that the machine fails is going to eventually come up,
look at the log and continue the protocol.
But again,
we don't put any bound in terms of the time that this protocol it takes to finish.
It's again,
there are only two possible votes a worker can make and can do commit and abort.
Committees are not.
It only happens if anonymously.
Everyone says for me,
in the preparing phase, you remember,
the preparing phase is a phase in which you the coordinator ask every worker,
whether they can commit or they need,
or they are going to, they can commit.
If a worker says that it can commit,
then it means it makes,
it means it needs.
It can do that only if it's sure they can accept the transaction.
And this assurance,
this vote is must be recorded in the stable lock.
If the worker votes abroad,
it must guarantee that will never accept the transaction.
This also is going to be a recorded in the lock and finishing.
It's all the machines have agreed to commit.
Then if all the machines have agreed to commit,
you record the decisions the committee in the local log.
And this is for the coordinator,
and then the coordinator inform everybody to commit.
Otherwise,
the coordinator logs,
the decision to abort and send that is abort to every work.
The machine remembered the workers from the previous life.
They cannot take back its decision.
Right?
So we are guaranteed that exactly one of this will happen.
So basically, if if a worker says I can commit this transaction,
you cannot later say I cannot accept the transaction.
The other way, if the worker says I bought this transaction,
he cannot later say,
I changed my mind, I am committing this feather.
Here is another way to look at the algorithms.
You have coordinator on the left,
work on the light.
The coordinator sends fold request to all the workers.
The workers are waiting for this vote request message.
If they are ready,
they are going to send to vote, commit to coordinator.
So this means that they can commit.
Otherwise, they send both aboard and are going to abort.
The coordinator collects all the boats.
If all the votes are commit,
they send it sends a global commit.
If at least a vote is aboard,
then the coordinator sends a board to every other worker.
Okay?
If the worker then become,
receives global commits and commits.
Otherwise, therefore,
any questions here?
Pretty simple, probable, right?
Okay.
Now, although despite the fact that this protocol is simple,
it's two questions.
Alice on question is that so it's okay.
If the algorithm thanks forever.
In theory,
theoretically, it can hang,
it can take forever.
I'll show you how later.
Actually, let me give you an example,
one example in which you can hang forever is that a machine fails
before getting the global commit.
It says commit everything,
everyone for votes for commit.
The coordinator is going to send everyone for me,
but that machine or the coordinator,
the coordinator gets,
let's do this example.
The coordinator collects all the votes,
but before and write the result of the vote.
But before going replying global with a global message or sending
a global message to every worker,
it fails.
Now we come back.
We're looking at the global storage in the log that it has as a result
of the vote says from it.
But before again,
ken a has a chance to send a global commit fails again.
This can come and can happen indefinitely,
right?
For the coordinator.
Come up, see the results of the vote,
but before has a chance to broadcast the global message to everyone.
Once again.
Now,
this is unlikely to happen.
So in life,
everything is probabilistic, right?
So the probability for this to happen every time, it's extremely low,
unless there is some persistent bug,
in the program.
Since messages are unreliable, does the work?
Is the next question from michael?
Since messages are unreliable,
does a worker keep sending his vote until it gets a global decision?
Yes, the workers can do that.
But if the messages are unreliable,
the coordinator like,
we'll see next.
If he, if the coordinator didn't hear from the worker for some time,
the time out,
then it can declare that worker or is not able to accept the
transaction and is going to log the result of the boat as being aboard.
And as everyone else to aboard,
that protocol is still caught.
What about when the worker doesn't hear from the coordinator?
So in that particular case,
it you eat the workers has to wait for the protocol to be correct,
because the worker doesn't know as that,
especially for a worker.
I hear you are talking about a worker who can who said that it can commit it.
We cannot finish the protocol until it gets a message from the coordinator,
because it doesn't know what to do.
It doesn't know whether the vote is committed above.
So in this case,
you have to ask to retransmit the court guaranteed for to retransmit
the global commit or global.
But it's, again,
the probability is to happen is very low.
In practice, is working.
It's a very good protocol.
It will go through a little bit of these questions.
Next is here is a failure for examples.
This is a timeline on the horizontal axis.
You have one coordinator, three workers,
the coordinators and vote requests,
then say every workers and vote commit,
and then the coordinator sends global commit.
Very simple.
Now failures easy.
Remember, you are discussing these protocols,
you have a state machines.
This is a coordinator state machines.
You are in any state.
When you receive start,
the next thing we are going to do a coordinator what it is.
You send the vote request when you send the vote request,
you go to a different state because you need to wait for the votes
from the workers.
Okay?
So you receive all about commits or right.
And if you receive all about commits,
now you go and you are going to go into different.
You are going to record.
Now, this is the result of about this commit.
You send the global commitment now you go to the commit is a committee state.
Right?
Otherwise,
you allow the results of the boat as being abort and go send a global abort
and go into the abort state.
While you are in the state,
if the worker blows a message,
like we discussed earlier,
and wants to get sends a a request for
for the coordinator to resend the decision.
The coordinator knows exactly what to send,
because based on where it was, they did this.
It's committed about.
The workers is similar.
They diagram, they machine.
It's again, it says in it, I am in it.
And i'm starting and they need,
I am waiting for receiving the vote request.
And from here from the vote request,
I can do two things.
I can say I want to abort case in which i'm going
directly into the abort state and i'm sending both abort,
or i'm going to go to commit.
And then i'm going to vote to commit.
Then i'm going to go to the door in a ready state.
I'm ready to commit.
And here i'm going to wait for what?
To receive either global abort or global commit.
I'm going to receive global abort.
I'm going to go to a birthday.
I'm going to receive a global committee.
I'm going to go to the committee state.
Let's see dealing first to his oracle failures.
When I can be affected,
if I am the coordinator,
when can I be affected about a failure?
It's really only when I am waiting for something with a waste it.
Because for in need,
i'm just sending about request and for commit and abort.
I just sent transition to the transition to go to these states.
It's by sending a message.
So here I when as a coordinator,
i'm going to be impacted when i'm in the way state.
In a way, if it doesn't receive any votes,
like I mentioned,
you can time out the coordinator of time out and send global awards.
This will work perfectly fine.
It'll be correct.
Here is what the examples,
coordinators and vote requests.
But somehow worker three didn't send welcoming to where it the message was lost.
So coordinator waits for some time to get the commit,
the vote from workers three.
But if it doesn't get it,
when the timeout expires,
it sends global award to all workers.
And that's ended.
Now let's look at the coordinator failure,
the coordinator failures.
When you can be impacted as a worker.
It's again,
you are impacted by the failures when you are waiting for something
from the party which can fail,
you are waiting as a worker from coordinators for two messages,
vote request.
This is in any state and global commuter global abort.
So here where you can be affected.
So here you need to look at.
Right?
Now,
this is the answer I gave to the question of what happens on coordinator fail,
fails.
So if coordinator fails,
worker must block waiting for the coordinator to recover and sends
a global message.
Right?
Like we discussed before,
the worker has no choice,
but to wait for coordinator.
Anyway, let's see the as a failure happening in it,
the coordinators somehow doesn't send about requests,
because it fails before the vote request is sent out.
The workers will time out.
They can now send both of us.
They can time out and send both of us.
Now you are in the ready in the registered worker ways for the global messages,
vote request.
And somehow you have all required for commit,
but now the coordinator failed.
Now, the worker, in this case,
have to wait for the coordinator to restart and to send the global abort of,
in this case.
And in this example,
and only and then they can finish.
But it's again,
the reason for the worker that while the worker needs to wait for the coordinator,
again,
it's very simple because if the worker decided to say that I can commit it,
doesn't know what to do,
because the boss choices are valid.
Geezer has to abort or he has to commit.
He must know exactly what has to be done has to do.
Because he has to be consistent.
The season has to be the same decision as all the other workers.
Obviously, you need to keep the lock in a stable storage.
You need to provide your ability and the coordinator or saying, say,
is going to restart,
is going to find the the accurate state in the stable story.
That's basically what it is.
And open recovery,
you have this set of rules.
The coordinators, if they cover supports, if it's in,
the you need weight or abort state.
The coordinator committee,
this is a committee state.
Right?
So they are right as a worker aborts.
If it's any need and a border state and committee in the committee state,
If it's a coordinator is a worker, it's in ready.
So it's asking for which is exactly the question we had before.
If the coworker is in the ready state,
when it fails and it comes back and see how you it was in the ready state,
it has the way it has to ask again,
the coordinator whether to commit or trouble.
Any questions?
Miles,
ask the following question.
If only one global commit message from the coordinator to worker fails
will be in trouble.
Yeah, so let's see what happens.
So assume that the water cutter,
so it's the coordinator said again,
in the previous example is that we had three workers.
So assume that two messages get through,
but one global message,
global community message doesn't get through.
They said the worker didn't get it.
What will happen in that case?
Why do you think it should happen?
If you design the protocol, implement the protocol?
What do you do?
What do you think we should do?
Sell the car blocks for how long
a certain amount of time and that amount of time expires what you
are going to do
if you have to implement it.
So what is the natural thing to do?
Maybe it wasn't in the previous diagrams,
but that is the natural things to do.
I don't know how the coordinator decided what i'm going to do.
Don't do anything.
You are block that.
But what else can you do?
That?
Certainly you can do that.
No, don't, I think a a it's a valid option.
Another thing you can do is ask against a coordinator what?
That's good.
Actually,
you can ask, again, the coordinator, what you decide.
That's correct.
That's what you'll do if you implement this product.
So let's go for have this short discussion.
So why do you need dcbc decision making?
Well, you need it because you aren't in four different programs,
you want different parts of the program which run on different machines to agree.
A a very simple example is that you want to replicate the state
for your ability on different machines.
Right?
So you need, for instance,
to the that's one example.
By the way,
a group of machines can come to a decision if any one or more of them fail
during the process.
Right?
In that particular case,
if some process fails,
the other can still come to a decision.
Right?
Because they are okay to record, say,
to commit the transaction.
So if the third worker fails to can still commit to commit the transaction.
And maybe the other one, the third worker,
and when it fails,
it comes back.
And as a coordinator,
and accordingly safe to commit,
and it's going eventually also to commit the transaction.
We said we discussed that just to emphasize why do pc is working
in generals paradox doesn't is because to
bc relaxes the problem in that it
doesn't require the notes to agree by a certain time.
They only say that eventually,
there will be agreement.
And it also allows us that's why to reboot and continue
announcements.
Homework five is due on monday.
Midterm three grades will close on sunday by the end of the day.
Any more questions about consensus,
general paradox and the two bc protocol?
If not, we are really going to switch gears.
Now.
We are going to talk about networking is obviously a fundamental part
of the operating system,
especially today where everything is connected,
like we discussed so many times.
So here are the main concepts need to keep in mind.
First is a network interfaces.
Each of your machines,
the machines you are watching now,
as a network cards,
i'm a network or another cheap.
Right?
And that's a cheap which communicates the outside world,
sending physical signals,
radio signals,
and so forth,
or signals through the wire.
Okay?
These are the network cards.
One computer can have multiple network cards,
because a computer can communicate multiple ways.
Can you give examples about a few ways the computer can communicate?
How can you have a computer communicate with some other computer?
Lan, wireless, optical, copper.
This is good.
Right?
Wireless wifi, right?
Sounds good.
That's a good one.
Bluetooth is another one,
bluetooth wifi and so forth, right?
Ethernet.
You may have heard.
So therefore it again,
one machine can have multiple cards.
Remember that there's no talk.
Okay?
Typically, it's not a card is associated to addresses.
One,
it's a media access control,
address or mac address.
This is a physical address.
And this is burned into the cart by
the company which produces these cards when a card was produced.
It comes with among others.
Like we'll see it's 48 beats.
And then there is an ip address,
the internet protocol address.
This is the address to which when we send a packet operating system,
send a packet,
is going to send to one of these ip addresses,
not to the mac address.
We learn more about how they map to each other.
This is what you have.
My address, like I mentioned,
is 48 bit unique identifier.
It's assigned by the current vendor.
Ip address,
used to be 32 bits.
It's assigned by the network administrator or who is dynamically in connect
to the network.
Typically, today, almost everyone is dynamically connected.
Your laptop,
your phone.
When you get an ip address that's dynamically allocated to you.
Right?
When you connect to wifi that in a wifi network,
someone is there is a process by which you are going to get an ip address
without an ip address you cannot communicate.
Right now is ipv six.
You have 128 bits.
That's the length of the others.
Then you have a connection.
The connection happens between two processes.
Now, on one process, on one machine,
you can have multiple processes.
One machine,
you can identify it remotely by this ip address or a mac address.
But how you are going to identify when you send a message that you
want to send a particular process out of men is running on the
same machine that is done using a poor numbers.
A poor number is a 16 bit identifier.
It has local scope to that operating machine or to an operating system
to them on with the process is running
local scope to the machine.
Therefore, a connection is identified by two end points.
Each endpoint is identified by aip address and a partner.
And this is how to processes communicate.
This is how your application communicates.
So you have mac addresses,
which comes with each card.
Is that assigned?
And they cannot be changed.
They're assigned by the vendor car vendor.
You have ip addresses,
which in general are assigned dynamical.
Then you have four numbers which are assigned by the operating system
to the process.
Now,
in order to identify to send a package to one process,
you need to specify both the ip address of the node on which the process runs.
And the port numbers are all the process.
The poor numbers are, again,
used to differentiate between different processes on the same machine.
What is the main natural functionality?
The main natural function,
it is delivery of a packet from between two hosts across the globe.
That's a problem.
It as a service with implement,
what do you need to look for?
What are some properties of such service function id?
You certainly may want to be reliable.
The packet may be lost,
maybe loss for different reasons.
Can you think about actually some reasons why packets can be lost
in the network?
If it's on wifi,
but I do interference and disturbance very good.
Someone turned on the microwave.
That's definitely can happen.
Corridor was none plug.
I they will all see in the packet.
They can, even in the wire metals,
they can be still lost.
If, for instance,
there are too many packets arriving at the routers more than the router
can handle.
Therefore,
the buffer, the router is full,
then you have to drop packets.
So that's one.
Now, this is what we are talking about is another thing is a flow control.
The flow control is avoid overflowing the receiver buffer.
Say you have a cell phone or whatever,
which is our cell phone,
which you can get data only at one,
say, one megabit per second.
And I am a big server.
I can send you back as I can blast you to 100 megabits per second,
100 times faster than you can receive.
What you are going to do.
There is no way you can get at that rate.
Many packets will be lost.
So therefore,
what you have to do,
you need to push back on the sender and tell the sender don't send that fast.
Jason say, at one megabit per second,
this is what you need to do.
This is flow control.
The receiver pushing back to the server do not send to fast.
There is a congestion control.
The congestion control is avoid overflowing.
The buffering, the routers that ii we discuss that.
If the buffer in a router overflows,
you lose back as a packets are dropped.
Congestion control is making sure that the sender doesn't send
too much data so
that the router is overwhelmed,
these buffers are overflowing.
So packets are lost.
So flow control is slowing down,
because the sale receiver congestion control is slowing down,
because the routers is another.
There's a difference.
Now,
we have to have right now.
Today we have different notes communicating between themselves.
Each of them executing the protocol.
It has a the syntax will describe what is a packet format?
Packet types,
right?
And the syntax would specify.
I get this packet, what i'm going to do is it what action I should take?
This means that the two parties,
they have to speak the same language,
have to understand and execute the same probable.
So we need to standardize if you want to come here with someone,
they have to run the same protocol.
Right?
I if you want to speak with someone else that person should speak english
or maybe another language,
both of okay.
So how does the standardization happen?
There are multiple ways.
One is there is a standard out there and every software
developers follow the standard when it writes the application.
Of course, the other one is basically have only one person,
only one or only company producing the entire software,
but I think the entire software is not desirable and is not realistic.
So that's why internally have the standard bodies.
For the internet.
The standard bodies is iatf internet engineering task force.
And typically the standardization happens for a new protocol.
Someone's write a document.
We specify the protocol,
syntax and semantics and send to the other members of the task force
requesting for comments
is called request for comments.
After multiple rounds,
that can become us can be approved to a become a standard in idea if you
don't need consensus.
Right?
It's not like to bc to face from it.
The majority has to agree.
But one thing that always required an idea is to have running code
to demonstrate which demonstrate that the protocol is feasible.
And typically, you are asked for two implementation,
different implementation of the same product.
There are also other ways to have de facto standards when some software
becomes so popular.
It becomes the factor standard.
And as I will follow after it like linux,
there is no standard body for linux,
but it's an effect of standard.
So everyone follows that standard or writing the application.
One thing about and this is the title of this networking section.
We are learning during this class during this lecture.
Is larry.
What about larry?
What is a problem?
The layering is a problem here,
is that think about.
You're right.
You want to send a message from your application,
from one process to another.
And that is what you like some instructions.
High level language may be sent, received.
That will be compiled down in machine code and will be executed by the processor.
And now you send it, but then you send it.
Eventually, that information you send,
it needs to go all the way to the wire,
or all the way to be transformed in a physical signal.
So there are many kind of steps from a sent to all the way
to that information to be sent on a wire,
on radio,
and then to be received the signal to be received on the other side
and to measure its way back to the receiving process,
which invokes probably I receive comment and ultimately get the date.
The problem here also is like we discussed.
There is not only a one way to send a signal.
There are many ways you can send the signals.
You can use blue stars, radio signals, wifi,
you can use optical networks,
you can optical signals.
You can use electrical signals like in wire networks.
You have many of these things.
So you need to organize all of these carrier pigeon.
That's a very good one.
You can do that as well.
You can send the information,
right?
This is a problem just thinking about application and transmission media,
how we are going to do it like one way to do it.
It's basically for your application,
your ideal application so that it's able your converters or adapters
to send to use every communication media,
wired fiber, optic,
wifi, bluetooth name it.
That's one way to do it.
What is the problem with
this kind of a lot of work?
That's correct.
Because you have a new application or you need to implement
this application or over all these communication media.
If you add a new transmission media,
it's even worse every application.
Now, if you want to support it,
you need to update the application to work on this one
over this communication radio,
over this new communication,
over this new transmission media.
A lot of work.
So what is the solution?
Encapsulations,
almost, but encapsulation assumes something else encapsulate in what
layer protocols you are talking about layers.
That's absolutely correct.
Here is a solution.
You add an intermediate layer.
There is a a famous quote,
basically saying that any problem in computer science can be solved by
adding another level of indirection.
This is in direction at work.
You have an intermediate layer as an intermediate layer,
provides only one interface to the application.
And all these applications are going to be written again, the same,
api the same interface.
And then if I am going to add, so basically,
this is really easy.
Right?
I am going to a new application.
I need to only be worried about only one interface to work with.
If you are going to add to and to add another transmission media,
you just need to provide the same interface of the intermediate layer.
Then everything will work.
If a new application,
if a new application is developed,
no need to touch the transmission media part.
If a new transmission media is added,
no need to touch existing applications.
Pretty cool, right?
And this has to do a software system modularity,
right?
And the modularity, whatever,
is going to provide these abstractions,
differentiate between the interface and the implementation,
high, the implementation details.
Thus, when it develops a code,
you are going to write functions.
The function provides signatures as the interface of the function.
Typically, the implementation shouldn't matter.
You write a function to do sort.
The sorting, if the interface looks the same,
you provide us, you provide a list,
and you get out the least orders,
ascending or descending order.
How the implementation,
how that is done doesn't matter.
Bubble sort.
Quick start.
Keep sort whatever this kind of modularity.
And also it's related with encapsulation and encapsulate the functionality.
It's widely used as a method in computer science,
right?
To simplify,
complex, sinks modularized.
Right?
Now,
fundamentally,
you a there is one disadvantage of modularity is great,
because again, I can send the can change the implementation,
can be a lot of lines of code without anything else.
Is the application to be changed?
However,
these interfaces also high information.
Some information can be very useful.
And without this information,
the performance can be impaired.
Let me give you a classic example.
I send a packet to another,
and the packet doesn't make it.
It's not acknowledge, I expect an acknowledge.
I don't get acknowledge what I should do,
resend it again, right?
But how aggressively i'm going to resend it?
And after how long it will depend on how the packet was lost,
it was because the interference,
like we discussed, I want to resend it immediately.
If it is because the congestion is a matter,
then I want to slow down.
Because if I send it the same, right?
I probably the man,
the packet was lost because I was sending too fast.
If i'm just descending and rescinding and rescinding that more packets
are going to be lost.
In that case, I want to slow down.
If the interface doesn't allow me to expose this information,
and today doesn't,
I don't know exactly what to do.
The performance will suffer.
Network is like system modularity,
but that another modularity is like system modularity,
but is simplified.
He simplified because they have layers.
Modules can be connected in any ways.
Layering.
It's connected in only one way is basically one layer on top of the other.
One layer can use only the functionality of the layer beneath which is
which is beneath it.
Right?
Only the two nearby layers are going to interact with each other.
Now you have a bunch of layers.
The next question it's about,
you have a bunch of functions you need to implement reliability, flow,
control, congestion.
And we discuss about that which layer is going to implement them.
We are going to learn next time about entering principle which provide
a guiding is a guiding principle of where to implement
certain functionality.
And then is a question about where the state is shared.
It's stopped when you have a failure,
right?
Then you can lose a piece of state,
then you need to recover it.
This kind of stuff how you are going to think about the state shared state
in the distributed as a in a distributed system.
And we are going to address all of those.
So we have ten more minutes.
Let's dive in now in netherlands.
I said the layering,
it's this partition of the system or a lawyer,
a layer relies only on the services from the layer below it
and provide services only to the layers above it.
And the interfaces between layers abstracts away the implementation of a layer,
which provides that interface from the layer using that interface,
there can be changed in isolation without in a transparent manner
to the layers above it.
There are several concepts which are associated with this letter and we
care to answer service,
what a layer does,
what functionality provides,
service interface,
how to access a service?
How do you access the service?
What is the api what is the interface?
And then is a protocol.
The protocol like we discussed in the past is how the peers to peers
communicate with each other.
What is a packet format sent us?
What do I do when I receive a packet?
When I don't receive a packet,
when I have a timeout?
There's a semantic he said to be service interface and protocol.
This is a network learning.
Initially,
as it was a standard body,
open system interconnection that declares that there should be seven layers,
physical data link,
network transport session, presentation, and application.
However, the internet protocol,
this standard,
it was unsuccessful, india.
It was overtaken by internet protocol,
which was initially initially grew as a de facto standard.
And only later, it was the idea was only it was created later.
I think nine ten years later after ip was design ip and the tcpip protocol.
Remember, it was a software.
It was a protocol which has implemented in unique bsd better places in distribution.
You should be very proud about that.
Okay.
With these layers that are with this probably the internet protocol,
you have only five layers.
The presentation and session layers are included in the application layer.
So these are going to learn about what each layer is doing.
Let's start bottom up,
physical layer service,
move the information between two systems connected by a physically,
the physical link can be wired,
optical, or through the air.
The interface specifies how to send and receive bits.
What are the levels of voltages?
How you encode one or the ones?
How do you encode zeros?
Right?
And the protocol represent actually the coding scheme.
So it's like the interfere is basically here.
I'm saying about a what is a bit is like transition from low to high voltage,
or transition from a lot of hybrid from high to low voltage?
What is the duration of a bit for how long it sent?
These are the examples of sparsely archival optical fiberly,
intense of us.
The next is detailing layer.
So by the way,
the physical layer is between two machines which are directly connected.
The data link layer is the same.
But here there are multiple machines which are connected
to the same communication media.
Typically like for instance,
the same local area network.
What is called all the machines on a wifi network, right?
If you are connected with the wifi with the same base stations,
you are on the same level.
In this case,
you need to arbitrate the access because you have multiple machines sending
on the same communication media.
They can send at the same time,
so they can have collisions.
So you need to think about that.
But this is a service laid out in layer provides.
It can also provide reliable transmission and flow control.
Remember, flow control is what?
Not overflowing.
The receiver slowing down to not overflow the receiver.
The interface is sent framed.
So here are the packets initially with physical areas and bits.
Here you aggregate the beats into frames,
and you send frames.
Each frame has a header,
right?
And the head that will have this mac added, this is your seat.
Finally, you have the protocols.
It is media access protocol to arbitrate access.
There are many implementation we are going to briefly talk about that.
Here is what you have,
right?
A you have a frame header.
The frame header has a mac,
a destination and source service.
Then they are converted as a lower level in bits which are sent on the wire.
You see,
okay, you see that you have the counterpoint,
you have the instantiation of the layers at boss by boss,
beers at both end points.
Right?
So now,
actually, you can look about your on your machines.
And if you are curious about this physical address or the mac address,
you can easily find those as well as the ip addresses.
But this is what if you do if config in linux or ip configure orientals machine,
then you are going to get these physical addresses
or internet adapter and so forth.
These are the mac addresses.
So like I mentioned,
a group of machines which are on the same communication media,
they are called form a lab,
local area network.
And these are the examples computers in your home,
starbucks, wireless, starbucks, and starbucks,
and so forth.
But the most important things here is that when you send a frame on a line
that can reach any
other machine on the same line.
So it's a general, it's a broadcast media.
It's like we are in a room or on this web.
I'm saying something everyone else from here.
Now, you know,
how does it know?
Because everyone will get the same phrase for a frame.
How does the now the recipient they intend the recipient of the frame
to get the frame and other others not get the frame?
It's because of mac address.
When the sender sends a frame in the frame header,
it puts the mac address of the recipient,
in this case is b now the frame is going to be forward to everyone,
but only b is going to look at the header and is outgoing to see
that its address to itself.
It's going to pass the frame to the next layer,
the second,
the sea,
the other,
if that if a computer looks at the frame and it doesn't recognize its mac address,
it drops it.
Now things are more complicated.
Even for a land,
there are switches and so forth.
This is what we are going to continue to discuss next lecture.
And with that,
stopping here, please, if you have any other questions,
let me know and be asa or send an email.
I'll see you all on next tuesday.
Good luck with the homework.