Hello, everyone.
So today we have quite a bit to cover.
In particular, we are going to finish layering another king.
What we started last time.
Then we are going to talk about end to end argument,
and we are going to then start the discussion on flow control.
So larry, so if you remember,
she just recap from the last time,
there are a few layers in the network has another king stack,
has a few layers.
In the internet, you have five layers.
The first layer at the bottom is physical layer.
And the role of the physical layer is to send the signal between two machines,
which are connected to the same transmission medium.
And the service is to move the information from one machine to another.
The interface is about how to send and receive bids.
The protocol is about how these beats are encoding.
It's like based on the voltage duration of each bit frequency.
It's again, depending whether we are using the across your cable,
optical fiber,
the wifi,
and so forth.
The second layer is data link layer.
Also, we discussed a little bit about it last time.
The data link layer enables the host,
which are on the same physical connected,
the same physical network to exchange messages or atomic messages.
Basically, the physical layer sends beats zero.
And once here,
we send packets.
We send messages.
Also, they are called frames.
And what are the services here?
It's one it's about because you can have here multiple machines,
which are connected,
may be on the cell physical line,
or in the same wireless or the same wireless link.
There are multiple machines which can send data at the same time.
So somehow you need to arbitrate to make sure that multiple senders
do not call you.
This is very much like in a room in which everyone talk and talk with everyone.
There has to be some kind of protocol so that not everyone stuck
at the same time.
So people can understand each others.
The interface is about how to send the frames to as over from one machine
to one horse to another horse.
And they also includes each frame includes an address,
because this is how i'm going to indicate that I am going to send
a particular frame to a particular host is a list by destination address.
These addresses are the mac address,
is a media access or so called addresses or data link addresses.
And these are the ones, if you remember,
from last time,
there are 48 beats,
and they are chosen by is a network card vendor.
So on that card,
it's you create another card or you
also associate address to it.
And the protocol it's about like we discussed about how you
are going to arbitrate the access like to this shared communication
media.
Okay?
Each frame contains a source and a destination address.
Each of them, again, is 48 bits.
And obviously,
this beats,
this addresses are unique.
Every network has a unique address.
You can also see these addresses,
like we discussed last time.
If you do ip configuring windows or if configuring linux,
here you can see these physical addresses is called,
and this has 48 bits.
You see.
123456.
And each of these groups has it in hexa.
You have two digits,
and you have four beats for each digit.
You have,
in total, you have 48 weeks.
Remember that the machine can have multiple network cards.
So in this case, that's how you are going to see.
In two physical addresses.
In this case, one for the internet,
for the wire network, and one for the wireless network.
Any questions?
So when I said that these hosts are connected with the same communication media,
typically as a data link layer, this kind of metal,
the sharon at or two is a hostile connect again or communicate
with each other is called land local area.
Network.
And it's again examples are in a wireless network.
It's all laptops in a starbucks affair,
all for instance,
devices in your home or in your office.
But this is a the key is that on all the devices connected with the same line,
can communicate with each other.
So you can think about this as a broadcast channel, a shared channel.
This also means that when you send a packet or a frame,
that frame is going to be delivered to everyone.
It's again like in the room,
when you say something loud enough,
everyone can hear.
Okay?
But now the obvious question is that if I want to send a frame
to one particular post,
then how do I do it?
And obviously,
the answer here is that by indicating the destination address
of the recipient in the frame,
in this example,
if I am going to send,
I want to send to ba wants to send a frame to b is going to put the address
or to be in the frame as a destination address.
Now, because this is a broadcast,
the line is a broadcast channel.
This packet will be delivered to every host in the network.
However,
each host can check whether the data frames are intended to itself by checking
its own mac address against the destination address in the frame.
If they are the same,
then it accepts a packet,
otherwise it drops back.
Any questions?
It's like in our examples.
If you are going to speak loudly and everyone can hear,
if you want to,
say, address to your friend,
john, you basically say, hey, john,
and then you are going to say whatever you have to say.
Right?
And by that,
this means that journal pay attention,
and maybe the other people do not pay attention because that message is
not intelligent.
Now, the land can be larger,
can include multiple hundreds of machines.
When includes hundreds of machines or a large number of larger number of machines,
typically they are connected by switches.
Switches are a little more intelligent.
And so basically,
switches are doing some pruning of the messages.
So if I switch,
get some message is it's and that is the horse is not behind.
One of its connections is not going to send that frame on that connection.
In this particular case, for instance,
when b arrives at the switch,
the switch will directly send to be is not going to deliver to bnc it's a feature.
It's more efficient.
But I can that's why the switches are.
In general when you have a lot of machines,
what is very inefficient for that frame to be sent to add to reach everyone?
Questions?
How can we ensure mac addresses are unique?
This is excellent question.
Typically, every network vendor,
it's assigned a block of mac addresses.
And he that vendor can only associate the mac
addresses in his blog to all the network,
to all the network cards it produces.
That's ha.
No news.
So another great question is this where security concerns come in?
Can a horse who has a packet is not addressed to still read the message?
Yes.
It's an opec.
That's why you are told that when you are going to be in,
a starter started by scofield,
what you are going to be, you are told, right?
You need to use encryption.
Why do you want to use encryption?
Because you don't want just someone to snoop on your own snoopy
on your packets and read everything what you send or receive.
Great questions.
Michael, here is another great question.
How does the switch now that mac address of b does a device declare
its address open connecting to a new media?
There is a special protocol by which the devices connect,
and then they advertise their address, the switch.
Excellent questions.
Please keep them coming.
Now, one of our problem is, again,
now let's think about, again,
these broadcast media,
because even with a switch,
with a switch here,
we are simplifying it,
but behind each of this output of the switch,
there are many hosts.
It's not only one host still there.
You still have in by this,
that almost by definition,
in a land,
you have multiple hosts being able to send and receive packets at the same time.
And when you have multiple people, say,
sorry, multiple hosts sending being able to send back at the same time,
you need to somehow make sure they don't collide.
Right?
And there are three solutions,
a channel partition, taking turns,
and random access.
Channel partition is basically think about you have different frequencies.
This is 11 typical example.
What you do is frequency division multiplex.
You have a band of frequency,
and you are going to split that band in different kinds of frequencies.
And then you allocate one of these frequency to a different host.
And each host can only send on that frequency.
And you can listen for multiple frequencies,
so you can get the packers from on any frequency.
Right?
Now, what are the advantage of that?
Is simple.
It's pretty clear.
It provides also some isolation.
You have your own frequency.
You don't care about the other people you can send on your own frequency.
You don't care about other costs.
It's a pretty efficient.
One is very high load.
When the load is small,
then it's very inefficient.
Because from if all, for instance,
you have only one host sending to another host, right?
Out of 100 hostels there.
Then you can use only one,
1% of the entire frequency range,
the ones that frequency,
which is allocated with that particular host itself,
while the other one are not yours.
Ideally,
what you would like is that of the only two machine to host or communicate
with each other,
you should and none of the others send data.
You should these two holes should be able to use the entire frequency range.
The other one is pretty similar,
but this is resource,
but instead of dividing the frequencies,
it divides a time.
So basically, here,
it's you have imagine that you have a talk.
A talking is a special budget.
And the stock on is going.
And again,
you can think about that hosts are organized in a logical drink.
For instance, okay,
then this stock and goes from horse to horse around the ring.
Now, you can send data only while when you have the top,
if you have data to send,
but you don't have the token.
You need to wait to receive the token.
So again, because it's only one post has a token at a given time.
You are sure you are ensuring that there is no collision,
because only one horse can send up a given time.
Again, you have the same kind of a little bit issues.
When everyone has things to send is working great,
because you get a token,
you already have,
you send data, you have to send data.
If only two hosts,
one host has to send data to another host,
then it's more problematic,
because you need to wait for every other host around the ring to get.
There is and send out the token before you can send the next packet.
It's kind of an overhead,
just waiting for this token,
to go around,
just for each host to pass it,
who doesn't have anything to send just to pass it to another,
the next force.
They just pure overhead,
which reduces the efficiency of this protocol.
And finally,
it's random axis.
It's also its carrier sense.
Collision detection is called csma this is infinite.
If you heard, this is probably the most popular data link layer technology.
Right?
And a form of this is also you have for wireless.
But here this is exactly to better understand it.
Imagine, again,
there is a room full of people and they are talking right.
Now, imagine that again,
everyone hears everyone.
So the room is small enough.
So what do you do?
Right?
First of all,
before you speak,
you listen a little bit, right?
This is scarier sense.
You listen that it's a pause.
No one else is talking.
Right?
You also don't interrupt, right?
Someone.
So if someone is though is talking,
you wait for that person to finish before you start that.
This is for life.
This is scary of sense, right?
Someone is the medium.
It's busy because there are some packets being sent out.
Then you wait for a pause for the media to be idol.
Before it.
You said this is not enough to avoid the collisions,
because more many people may have like in our analogy,
As a room analogy.
Multiple people may wait for the current speaker to finish to say something,
sometimes happens that people can start to people to start talking
at the same time.
Now, that's a collision the same here.
When the media is either to horse,
are going to send back at the same time,
these factors are going to collide.
Right?
What do you do that?
It's again, assuming that you are polite,
you are most people who like start talking at the same time.
This when they stop,
right?
They stopped for a while and then try again.
Right?
Sometimes again,
it's like,
as you probably,
i'm sure you witness that two people start at the same time stop and then again,
start at the same time.
So we want to avoid that here in the design of this protocol.
And how do you design it?
Each of the parties, each of the hosts,
if there is a collision,
waits for a random amount of time.
If you wait for a random amount of time,
the probability of collision, again, colliding again,
is lower.
This is pretty much it.
Right?
And it's very simple.
It decentralized.
It works pretty well.
In practice,
it's beautiful protocol.
Any questions?
It's again the token you can assume this is again like this protocol,
the cmic csmacd it's like think about always like the protocol,
people who use polite people who used in a room or speaking with each other.
This token protocol,
I will discuss in the previous slide,
the taking turns.
You can imagine it's like only people who have the mic are going to talk.
Right?
When you ask questions like a conference and so forth.
When you ask questions, there is a mic.
If there is only one mic,
only someone is going to hand the mic is a person who has who can tell who
wants to ask a question,
but only the person who has a mic.
And as a question.
So there are no apologies.
So let's see.
Why would I want allison has this question?
Why would I want my computer to play fair?
Can I configure my computer to just shoot over everyone?
So then it will be faster.
I think that's a good point.
The problem, though,
is that if everyone is doing the same or even,
other people don't do exactly the same,
you are going to have collisions.
And if you have collisions, you have garbage, you cannot be hurt.
That's a problem.
Right?
You cannot, in some sense,
you cannot increase the intensity of your signal.
So probably in this case,
you don't have the ability to increase that kind of intensity.
Like in practice,
maybe you are going to yell.
Your voice will be stronger than anyone else,
but here everyone is on the level playing field.
The same you can send only beats the same visa services against the same voltage,
the same density,
if two people, if 2 horses,
and at the same time,
these are going to be interference.
And your message is not going to be delivered to the destination.
Simon,
how does random access guarantee a node ever get a chance to speak?
What if in the random someone is always speaking when I try to speak?
Could that cause a starvation?
That's a great question.
And it's probabilistic.
It's like,
you,
there is a the probability that you are going to be able to speak is non zero.
Now, it turns out that this random access protocols,
they work very well.
You remember this as a token that the token protocol and the one and with
a frequency division multiplexing,
they are working very well.
When the system is very utilized,
this is highly utilized when everyone copies everyone.
But it doesn't have such a high efficiency when the system is now utilized,
because that say,
if you have only to host talking to each other,
they cannot use the entire frequency range,
or they have to wait for the token to get around only for and all the other
was not doing anything with the doctor.
This is a reverse,
is working extremely well on another piece is lightly utilized,
because there are no collisions.
But when these heavily utilized,
there are many collisions,
then the efficiency is going down.
So there is a problem with that.
And but again,
so this is probably the intuition behind your question,
simon.
But in theory,
you are going to get your thought.
It's like,
think about the one.
It's like here is another analogy.
You are coming from a secondary road.
You are in the main road and you don't have a priority and you want to take
the right or less.
Right?
Like you go from,
say, for you whatever you exit, right?
So you need to wait for a gap to get to enter the traffic.
And in theory,
you may never get that bad that gap.
But in practice,
you don't know you did not need to wait too much.
So probabilistic really is not salvation.
The next is a network layer.
I don't know, I so need to update this figure.
On the right hand side.
We are talking about the network layer.
The network layer is actually the most important.
In some sense.
When you talk about internet,
internet is the main layer in the internet is the internet protocol.
Or ip you heard about the ip right?
Ip is the internet proposal is another class.
The network player had its own address.
They are called ip addresses.
And every host a as a unique ip address.
And this is global,
it says the level of the entire planet.
So nathara blair is basically going to be able to ensure the main service
is going to ensure its connectivity.
You can deliver a packet,
specifying the network address or the ip address across the globe.
From new york, tokyo,
from a network in europe,
from a host in san francisco to a host in tokyo.
This will be across multiple data link layer methods,
because you cannot have just a data link layer network over the entire globe.
There are possible other services,
like scheduling priorities,
or some packets are more important than the other.
You can think about.
Video packets are going to have higher priorities,
and data packets seem like that.
You need also to handle the buffer management.
The packets, along the way,
are going to be buffer.
The interface is very simple.
You send a packet to a specify not address this image,
and you receive that packet,
which is intended to you.
The protocol includes defining these network addresses which are
globally unique and also constructed the router what are called
forwarding tables.
So a router which connects a router,
connects different and locality and adults.
It receives a packet.
It looks at the destination address and decides where to send it out.
This is the metal player.
And you see the metal player packet.
It has a payload and the head they are encapsulated in a data frame.
Encapsulation means that you take a packet from the metal player and you
add the head of the frame.
This becomes a frame.
The other header contains the ip destination address and the ip source others.
And as I mentioned to you,
these are routed by the routers,
connect different data link that data layer methods.
And all this aggregation of local area matters is called a wide area network.
So now what is the difference between the switch and the router?
It's simple.
The router, it's only it recognizes and routes based on the ip addresses.
A switch,
it's only in a local area network and only recognize mac addresses,
sort out the function like I mentioned,
his father, it's to get the packets,
look at their heads and decide on which output link to send them.
This is how the router works.
You have a bunch of incoming links,
you get pakistan,
and out outgoing links.
It's like a huge intersection.
Right?
And basically, what router implements a mechanics,
which is called store and forward store and forward means the packets
are received first are stored.
And after a store,
the router inspects the header.
And based on the destination of the others decides where the forwards
and they are stored because you
don't want to drop the package if the router cannot process them fast enough.
Does it be?
Again,
the forwarding table is a mapping between ip addresses and the output.
Right here is an example about the packet going from host a to host each
other or decide to watch output goes to forward the packet based on its ip address.
And based on the information is a forwarding paper.
So now this life is very important,
because it's obvious question.
Now.
I have mac addresses,
and you told me that they are unique.
Now you tell me also about ip addresses which are also unique.
Why do I need to kind of others?
Why not using a single type of others?
In particular, why shouldn't I use as a mac address for output?
I already have this.
Why do I need another address?
The answer is that remember how the mac addresses are allocated?
I am a network card vendor.
I get a block of macolysis.
And i'm going to use this address is in the block to assign to my net of cards.
It's not.
Okay.
And then these network cards are in computers which are all over the globe.
So there is no aggregation is very much like social security number.
Now I am asking you,
i'm giving you a social security number,
right?
Let's say they are not private.
They are not confidential.
And i'm telling you, hey,
deliver this letter message to this social security number,
123456, whatever.
How easy is that?
Or how hard is it?
It's pretty hard because there is now they are random across the globe.
Now, to compare that,
if I am going to give you a message or a letter to deliver,
i'm telling you what is the home address of the recipient.
It's much easier because the others are structured.
Right?
The only thing, for instance,
say,
i'm going to send the address to this17th street and northwest washington,
dc and so forth.
If i'm sending it from california,
only the first thing I need to know is that is going to washington,
dc so I put it on a plane to go to washington,
dc that's the only thing it's very easy.
Right?
The amount of state I can use in san francisco to say i'm going to send
the packet.
The letter is very small, right?
Only the cities or the states or the country.
If I am sending international letter,
once the letter is coming, going to washington,
dc remains in the washington dc area.
And then I know i'm going to look at the street,
and then i'm looking at the others for this.
So you can have this theoretical structure and routing of the letter
from the sender to the recipient.
This is what the ip address gives you this structure who is much will make
it much easier.
I and then if i'm sending from that on to someone from california,
from berkeley, it's again,
just look at the berkeley first sent to berkeley to or someone
close to back san francisco,
auckland,
a on a plane to auckland.
And from there is going to be delivered to you.
Any question?
So fundamentally, it's, again,
the ip addresses have structured geographic structure,
the political structure.
And therefore,
they can be aggregated aggravated.
Therefore, the following tables in the routers can be much smaller.
Right?
While for mac addresses,
there is no aggregation,
we need to keep a following table,
which is equally the number of mechanisms,
existing market analysis,
which is huge casing..
Assume that you want to send a packet from
new york to a particular ip address to a particular host in uzbek.
Then they use it.
Berkeley.
Actually, all ip addresses are starting with this.
The first are 2 bytes,
are all common, a 95.
So the router in new york,
it needs to keep only one entry for all hosts,
which are in you associated with this directly.
If you don't have that and you use mike addresses,
then the new router has to keep an entry for every host,
which is much harder and much harder to update,
maintain, and things like that.
Does it make sense?
Any questions?
So to summarize here,
ssn mac address like ssn and an ip address is like an address,
although it's not readable.
Right?
So therefore, it's much easier to build a system like a male system.
In our case,
to deliver the letter to a particular address, which has structured,
then to some identifier,
Which has no structure.
Any questions?
Like I mentioned, this is the internet protocol,
the international player,
and the internet protocol is the internet senator player.
The service it provides.
It's got its connectivity and back at delivery.
But its best effort means that you are not guaranteed that your packet
is going to make the destination.
It may be dropped, it may be corrupted.
And also,
it doesn't guarantee that the package will send two packets on out of one
after another.
They are going to arrive at the same time in the same order,
because they may follow different routes.
It's like,
you cannot guarantee that two cars which started san francisco and arrive
to and are driving to la they are going to get that delay the same work.
It's very simple.
Now,
on top of the metal layer,
you have transport layer and the transport layer provide.
It's one level up.
The net of layer deliver a packet from one horse to an ass.
But the hosts do not consume the packet.
Application consumes the packet.
And the application is a process.
On a machine have multiple processes.
You need to specify to which packet to each process on a particular machine.
The packet needs to be delivered.
The ip address of the recipient is not enough.
Read another thing to differentiate between multiple processes running
on the same action on the same course.
This is a port.
Now.
I could see.
So the transfer layer,
multiplex and the multiplex packets,
which arrive on the same post,
that as other services can provide the reliability,
right?
Adaptation, like we discussed last time, flow control, congestion control,
and timing properties.
Maybe they are going to.
You've got a guarantee that the packet will be delivered within 100 millisecond.
It's important, say, for voice communication,
the interface is the same message to a specific process of a given estimation.
And the local process receives a message sent to it.
The protocol includes the poor numbers.
We used to differentiate between different processes.
It may implement reliability,
flow control,
and packet is asian because of my sense bigger,
depending on the interface,
you may send streams.
Like if you remember,
we have this kind of interface to the network.
You have blocked and stream interface from the stream interface.
Somehow you need to chop these streams into packets and send these packets.
That is a higher level.
You have the transfer layer,
you have a transfer header.
The transport header is a protocol number as the for port numbers.
And you have also like, for instance, 80,
it's identifies for the port is reallocated the port for hpv server.
There are two important transport protocols in the internet using udp
user data ground protocol.
And this provides only multiplexing and multiplexing among processes.
This is the best effort.
Backers can be lost, can get out of order.
There is no flow control, nothing.
The application is to take care of.
Then it's pcp which is a transport control protocol.
This obviously still provides multiplexing and in multiplexing around processes.
But in addition, has a notion of connection.
You set up the connection and tear down the connection.
If there are packets which are corrupted or corrupted, you discard them.
There is a check sum.
You check.
If the check sum is violated,
you discuss the packet.
It transmits a lost packet.
A self provides reliability to the application,
and it's also provides flow control and condition control.
Remember, flow control is about not overwhelming.
The receiver.
The congestion control is not overwhelming.
The method,
the services are not typically available.
Any bandwidth or delay guarantees.
In internet, you cannot specify that.
You cannot say I want 10 megabytes per second.
You cannot say,
I want these packets need to believe delivery 100 millisecond.
What I mentioned to you,
I mentioned earlier that, in general,
the transfer protocol,
the transport layer can provide that.
But I am telling you now is that transport protocols in the internet
do not provide this kind of
then that be like our boundaries guarantees.
Also if a session with a connection,
if you try to migrate an application from one or to another,
they using yummy migration or something like that,
the connection is not preserved.
We have another question.
The questions are reports used to differentiate which packet to send
to different processes on the house.
Yes.
Exactly.
For that.
Different processes will have different ports numbers when they open a production.
That is the application layer.
Is here any service provided to the end users.
This application is like the interface depends on the application,
protocol depends on the application.
In the osi architecture,
there are also a was a transport,
sorry, was a session on the presentation layer.
They are not existent in the internet protocol.
So be happy.
We only need to learn about five really four layers instead of seven.
This father, their function,
it is absorbed by the application layer data.
This is a better step.
You see, kind of the waterfall.
A packet at one level,
becomes a payload as a set as the next level,
as you go down the stack.
And when you are going to go up the stack,
you are going to strip headers after header until you get to generate
the first layers,
physical layer data link layer network layer are implemented by the host
and by the roots.
The switch is not shown here by the switch implement the physical layer
and italic layer.
The host implement transport and application layer is throughout the broad implement.
And the protocol is between two ps at the same time.
Some announcements discussion will be recorded because of the thanksgiving.
The office hours for wednesday, thursday,
friday are going to be canceled against because of the thanksgiving.
The middle three reviewer session is coming next monday.
The time is to be determined.
Please stay focused.
You are going to announce it on piazza.
The medium three is next wednesday between 7:00 and 9:00 pm and homeworks
is released.
And is it has been released and is due on friday.
December 3rd are layers,
five and six used explicitly in other systems,
or are they obsolete everywhere?
They were used by other network protocol and network stacks.
In the past, there are many of them,
but all of them are obsolete.
Eventually the internet protocol took over and everyone knows provide
the internet protocol.
So the answer to your question today are obsolete.
Previous recording letter will be applauded,
recording, recorded letter.
It should be.
We'll make sure that it's upload it.
Sorry about that.
Now let's switch the gears.
And this is a very interesting aspect of the internet.
It's called end to end argument.
If you look about this another way to look at the internet protocol stack,
its shape is what is called our glass.
What this means that the internet protocol is and is a waste of the howard glass.
And that's why internet probable is so important.
And the sorry,
internet in ip layer is so important in the internet network stuff,
because it's kind of unique.
So everyone has to implement the internet protocol interface.
But under the internet protocol,
player and above it,
there is a large variety of different protocols at different layers.
You can answer it under the internet protocol.
You can have different data link layers.
You can have different physical layers about above.
You can have different transport protocols,
this pngdp about you have different application protocols.
Right?
This is beautiful.
The reason is beautiful because it decouple the evolution of the layers
of the layers under
the underneath and of the layer above.
Remember it when he discussed the level of indirection.
Last,
this is it.
But I do remember the couple the evolution above from the evolution of the last.
Therefore, if i'm going to add a new data link layer,
as long as i'm providing on top of it,
ip interface,
then all the other application,
all of the other layers above ip should work without any check.
The same.
If i'm going to invent a new transport protocol or a new application protocol,
I can do that.
And as long as i'm going to write against the ip interface,
none of the layers below the ip should care that.
Now there is a new application protocol or a new transport protocol.
This is why the ip layer is so fundamental.
This is what we discussed.
So a single internet module player allows arbitrary networks to operate,
allows application to functions on all networks.
And therefore,
because the players below and the layers above can evolved separately,
this is how you also involve the innovation.
It enables innovation.
However,
changing ip itself is very hard,
because it's only one layer of a proof point.
The transition from ipv four to ibv six was very painful,
probably don't like 20 years.
Now,
the layers,
it's a very nice construction, very logical, very clear.
I provide a lot of isolation because one layer can only use a service
of the layer below it.
At the same time, he has some drawbacks,
because the layer may need some same functionality like false tolerance
of no reliability.
Some players are going to replicate this function of it.
The layering can also hurt the performance because one layer can hide
information from the above layer.
Like I mentioned to you,
it's one classic example is that the data link layer hides,
wire packet was lost.
The ip layer hides while the packet was lost.
The transfer layer which provides for recent bcp which is provide reliability,
and it needs to do the transmission of the packets.
It cannot make the right the best decision,
because it doesn't know where there is a packet, for instance, was lost,
because it was dropping the matter because of congestion.
So therefore, I need to slow down when I send a new packet,
but I retransmit the loss packet,
or the packet may have been lost,
because interference case in which I don't need to slow down.
But without having this information,
I need to make a decision the decision today to slow down,
which is not optimal, for instance, for wireless networks.
Some of the layers are not always clearly separate.
The other thing is that you had, as you remember,
like for each layer at its own head,
you have a lot of head ups and that overhead,
because it's not really data you want to send in some cases ahead.
That is much harder than the actual data you want to send.
So now,
again,
you have all these layers and you want to implement some functionality.
The one question is,
at once layer, you are implementing that function.
And the end to end arguments is a principle which tries to answer that question.
Some people say is a sacred text of the internet.
And like any sacred text,
there are endless disputes about what exactly means.
Right?
And everyone cites the supporting their position that it's a little bit a
like the bible,
but still, it's very important.
But let's consider this, for instance,
some function into like reliability or security.
It's obviously, where do you implement the italian man,
ib land and the metal layer,
transport layer where and why?
And our application can implement that.
And the main point here is that like,
we'll see in the next example,
is that because a network,
even if they want at a lower level of the network,
cannot implement,
and to end and end,
function will be corrected.
The application may anyway have to implement.
Let's take a following example,
but I it's okay.
It's an example.
Say you want to transfer a lively a file from one host on us
how this will look like.
If you want to build an application,
where is the data from the file?
Then you send it over the network from hostile to hostile.
The horse bees and the application from horse b is going to write it
on the disk,
be this is how you copy a file.
Now, if I want to have a reliable transfer, what you are going to do,
there are the solutions.
I make each of these thread steps reliable.
And now I can catalyze them.
I have here are five reliable steps,
entrance that must be reliable.
The second one,
I don't know any of those that seems.
But after I get all,
what I am told is a file,
i'm going to computer checks out,
and i'm going to send to to match against the jackson,
sent by the host by the sender.
So basically hosting,
when he sends a file, it computes also a check stop.
He sends out the file to horse, be,
the horse be takes against a file, save the file.
And also, after it saves the file,
its entire file,
it computes a check sum and our computer check sum of the, say,
file with the check sum sent by the whole state.
If they are the same success,
If they are not the same, send the file again,
which of the solutions are going to be?
If it were for you and one
edison say solution one because solution three is bad for large files,
through solution three is bad for large files.
Assignment.
I like solution to anyone else.
Simon, why do you like some shampoo?
Because I don't know whether between each steps is my break.
That's correct.
Great answer.
So that you see the point is that here,
if I concatenate five reliable steps,
it doesn't mean that end to end.
Everything is reliable.
Right?
This is the grain is a solution, though.
It's checking the checks out.
The solution is incomplete,
because what happens?
For instance, when I copy the data from the disk to the application memory,
and the application memory is corrupted,
but luck fundamentally,
because I cannot guarantee that the end the solution one,
it's is correct.
I need any way to do a check sum and verify
the main point here that the application,
anyway, has to implement the functionality to verify the checks out,
even if you solution one.
So therefore,
the full functionality of reliability can be implemented as the application
level.
The network doesn't going to do anything.
Now,
for correctness reasons,
right?
It's a game.
It's enough to implement the application.
The network doesn't do anything.
Still,
we are just talking that the network also implement reliability and not
the natural transformation,
reliability.
So why would sales and effort implement reliably?
They are reliable for a reliable product?
It's not necessary for correctness.
We just conclude that,
but still,
you may want another to implement elaborate.
Why is that to avoid very expensive collection?
Alexander?
So if you think about,
right?
It's in the second solution,
if you have ten gigabytes size five,
if one bite 1 bit,
not on bite, 1 bit is corrupted.
You need to resend the entire ten gigabytes.
However,
if you have,
the network is reliable.
And the
that's perfect.
So the question is that should I implement this function
at the lower levels or not?
The question is the answer here.
It depends,
right?
Because in and and the reason this is a
question is that if you implement the function,
it is a lower layer.
This function, I it doesn't reduce the application complexity,
because you anyway,
into implement there and increase another complexity.
Worse yet,
it can increase,
it can add overhead to application which do not read that functional.
Like, for instance, if you have a voice over ip telephony over the internet,
in that particular case,
reliability is not helpful,
because you need to satisfy,
you need to the latency is more important than getting every every packet.
Correct?
Like if the sound is a little bit distorted,
it's probably it's okay.
But if we need to wait for a second to return in the packet,
that's probably not.
Okay.
Yeah,
it was glitch.
So I don't know what will happen also is recording because on my side,
it said a little bit recording is in progress.
I hope that it's just a glitch.
So that didn't mean anything for the recording.
That is a the great timing while we are discussing about entrant reliability.
Anyway,
so basically,
you can implement a net of function is at a lower level stack.
If we can improve performance.
Now there are different interpretation of the end to end argument.
And one extreme implementation, he says,
even if you can improve efficiency,
don't bother if you cannot simplify the application or the cost software,
don't buy to implement as another player.
This is very conservative.
I have the moderating term in interpretation.
So the moderate interpretation is kind of it's it basically says you
can implement the function.
It is a network, but be careful about that.
Think twice.
In particular,
you can implement the function id at a lower layer,
if and only if doesn't impose a burden on applications that do not require
that functionality.
And it provides a significant, improving platform.
So the benefits are out waiting the complexity of the implementation.
And by the way,
you shouldn't be a burden for the applications who do not need that function.
So if the application doesn't need for reliability,
you shouldn't suffer.
For instance, should that experience?
Have you like latency and relatives and you say interpretation we are using?
Okay?
Any questions?
So again, you have a functionality like reliability,
which you must for being to be absolute,
to be correct to ensure correctness.
You have to implement the application level at the end.
Hosts the question.
Should we also implement the liability of the lower layers?
Is another layers.
The answer here,
according to the moderate interpretation of the entrant argument,
but the bad for that is pretty high.
You can implement the liability another team.
Only if you get significant increase improvement in the performance,
you are not going to hurt the application.
We do not need that function.
Any questions?
Now we are going to start one of the last topics of the course.
This is flow control.
So the flow control,
remember,
assures that a fast sender does not overwhelm a slow receiver.
And we already seen some mechanics,
like producer, consumers is bounded buffers.
So remember, in this case,
you cannot overpower the consumer,
overwhelmed the consumer.
Because if the buffer is full,
the producer can no longer put packets in the buffer.
The buffer is naturally pushing back on the producer.
One is full, accepts no new items.
Therefore, if the consumer is slower,
the producer is going to adapt to the consumer speed
because of the bounded buffer.
So that's the idea.
In the case of the tcp and this is a talk about this, be flow control.
Things are more complicated because they are not on the same machine.
We are on different machines.
And with an unreliable network can be doing dcp choosing what is
called a sliding window protocol as a byte and not packet level.
And there are 22 types go back and is this a bit a hole
near and selectively be disappeared?
The star hall,
new reno and sack,
are the different types of pc ps.
We are going to talk about more about them,
a little next lecture,
go back and meeting.
Here is a difference.
We explain the packet level.
Before it's easier.
I sent them packets.
And the 5/5 packet was lost.
The receiver gets the first four packets,
and then the last five packets,
1234, and 6789, 10.
Please go back.
And you are going to go back and resent from back at 5:00.
So i'm going to pretend five,
and 6789, 10,
despite the fact the 6798, 10,
we have already received by the receipt by the spiders, by the recipient.
So you miss something,
you restart from that missing packet,
all the way selective repeat like the name implies.
If you lose a packet in our previous examples, a packet five,
we send only back at five.
Why doesn't everyone implement selective repeat,
which seems much easier,
much in a much more efficient?
Because it's more complex.
Go back and is my simple thing for all the less efficient.
Now is the dcp flow control.
The receiver tells us that how many more buys it can receive
without overflowing this buffer.
I'm going to tell you I can receive 1 kilowatt.
And in some way,
this tells you that you can send me one kilobyte of data before you hear
from me whether I receive anything.
Right?
Because you're now based on what I told you that I can get one kilobyte,
but because you cannot send me more to be before you hear from me that
like you can send more.
This is advertising.
Now, like I mentioned,
for the pcp the protocol is not at the packet level as a byte level.
The acknowledgment as a recipient, i'm telling you,
i'm acknowledgment, contain the sequence number of a byte of the next byte.
The receiver expects.
This means that i'm telling you that acknowledgment contains a number,
the sequence number 100.
This means that I received,
i'm telling you implicitly that I received all the bytes up to 99.
There is no gap.
All of them up to a 99.
And the sequence number is start to count.
It's like, is from the fast first byte.
So the first byte, which will send up to the connection of that.
Right?
This is a very simple diagram showing the sending process,
the receiving process.
And the buffer are the receiver.
The dcpip is implemented in the kernel.
Remember,
what you discussed is about bsd unix bsd we said that
the dcpip is part of that was first implemented
in the bsdi think,
4.3 version.
And it's part of your legacy is one of the biggest achievements
in the open source software,
because that's internet.
Why do you do that?
Also?
That is because you cannot do context switching.
You cannot do it application level again,
performance at one garbage per second.
Typically, the packers have been 1,500 bytes,
the ip packets.
This takes to send, like one garbage per second is 12 set of micro seconds.
And if it's 100 bytes packets,
it's lesson on my one microsecond.
And by the way, one gap is per second is slow.
Today we are talking about ten cabbies per second,
40 cabbies per second,
100 cabbies per second connection.
There is no way you can do context.
Switching starts that fast to send every packet,
the application to send every packet.
And actually,
there is not only one buffer.
There are multiple buffers.
There is a buffer, which is between the process and in process.
The piano.
Again, you cannot have contact switching on every packet.
Then it's between the receiving operating system that the operating system
on the receiving force and the receiving process.
And then you have a buffer actually,
between the two hosts as atcpiip level, the transport level.
There is a buffer that operating system on the recipient cost is maintaining,
you get the packets from the sending post.
So here it's in more details how things that happen.
You have this buffer here,
and you have this buffer here.
You see me at the end,
host and whispering host.
And but I tell you,
so you have the state buyers to produce our consumers sending process,
sending pcb sending dcp receiving pcb receiving dcp receiving process.
Let's take up of these examples.
They say the maximal ip packet size is 100 bytes.
The size of the receiving buffer is the receiving buffer,
is 300 by bytes.
Recall, the acknowledgment indicates the next expected byte in sequence,
not the last recite received byte.
We assume that these are circular buffers.
What is a circular buffer?
A buffer has a size of n you may have an infinite sequence of bytes
and a bite.
We sequence number k is stored in a location with the index k mod and+1 in
the buffer.
This is a for example,
these are sequence numbers of hello world.
So say, age is a sequence number 27.
And l the last l is sequence number 76.
And the buffer has only ten entries.
Right?
Then this is how you map it.
27 is 27 mod n it's seven,
because any stand and+1, it's eight.
So n plus,
was it so sorry?
This is age.
We are looking at e which is sequence number 28,
sequence number twenty eight twenty eight, more ten,
+1 is mine.
This is how this data is a buffer data from e to r the blue,
which is in blue, shown in blue,
is a buffer in the simpler buffer.
Initially,
we are going to have a bunch of variables which. two different
things in the buffer,
three on the sending part,
three on the receiving part.
You have last bite to be done,
which is the last byte written by sending process.
Last by scent is a last byte,
send by sender to the receiver.
Last byte act is a last act byte by the receiver is a sender.
Last byte received now is on the receiving side.
Is the last bite received by the receiver from sender.
Next bite expected is the last in sequence byte expected by receiver.
And the last byte read is the last bite read by the receiving process.
Actually, for the next byte expected,
this should be the next in sequence by the expected by the cigarette,
not last.
Okay.
Now the advertised window is a number of bytes like we decide the disappear
receiver can receive.
So what is this one?
Let's say with blue here,
a is a bite which are already in the receiving the receiver buffer.
The advertising window is a maximum receive buffer.
It's a maximum buffer size minus the last bite
received this one,
and the difference between the last byte received and last by thread.
Right?
So basically, this is,
You need to subtract from the maximum received buffer.
So from the buffer size of the receiver,
how many bytes are still in the buffer,
which are not yet read by the receiving process?
On the sending process side is similar to you have a sender window,
which is a number of buys atcp sender can send.
And the center window is advertised window minus last by cent,
minus last by act.
Intuitively,
this means that I can send as a sender.
I can send a number of bytes,
which is by subtracting what you told me that you can receive,
what I always send,
I haven't heard from it.
And I'm finishing with this example.
Say you told me the advertising window is one kilobyte.
And since you told me that the advertising window is one kilobyte,
I send you 100 bytes.
How many more bytes I can send you without hearing from the answer?
It's 900.
Right?
So that's basically what the center window tries to capture.
Is this.
I'm going to stop here.
And this materials we've done in this lecture,
you'll be part of the midterm.
And again, best of luck with everything and happy sensitive area.