Hello, everyone.
Welcome to the next to last lecture of this semester,
the one to the next to the last week of classes.
Today we are going to have a very interesting lecture,
and that will be on the dcp flow control and actually congestion control.
Remember,
here we are talking about the transfer layer.
This is about the networking stock,
the internet stock.
And as you can see the transport layer and if you remember sits on top
of the network layer,
the transport layer it's implemented actually is the first layer if you go
from bottom up,
which is only implemented by n hosts is not implemented by the network.
Okay.
And one of the key services that the transport layer is providing,
if you remember,
it's multiplexing and multiplexing connections on the same machines,
between the processes on the same machines.
Right?
The internet as another player doesn't differentiate between processes.
The letter blair addresses only machines,
only and hosts.
So nato clare is going to get take a packet and send it to another
and host whose address is in the packet header as destination address.
But once the packet gets to the end to that end host,
it needs to be delivered to a particular process to particular application
to being processed.
The way you differentiate between these different processes is using poor numbers.
The transporter is the one who uses four numbers to the multiplex of packet
when it arrives of an host and deliver it
to the proper process.
Okay?
As you again, if you remember,
in the internet as a transport layer,
we have two protocols,
udp and dcp the user data ground protocol and transport control protocol.
The udp doesn't do much more besides multiplexing and many multiplexing of packets
from and to processes.
So we are not going to talk more about that.
Now, the transfer control protocol,
which is the one we are going to talk most.
Mostly in this lecture is providing two additional services flow control.
We talk a little bit at the end of the last lecture,
but I am a to start again talking about it.
We have more time during this lecture,
and it's a very important topic.
And congestion control.
The difference between the two is that the flow control.
The goal of the flow control is not overflow.
The receiver, a slower receiver,
the congestion control is to the north of our flows and network.
Overflowing means that the sender sends more data than the receiver
or the network can hand.
During this lecture, we are going to talk about flow control and condition.
Any questions?
Again, from the last lecture and from many lectures ago,
if you remember this producer consumer is a bounded buffer,
meaning that it has,
we can accept only a finer set of items in the buffer.
This is improvised implements a natural a form of flow control,
because if the consumer cannot consume as fast as a producer percents that
I died into the buffer,
inserts item into the buffer,
the buffer will get feel.
And when they get when the gap buffer is full,
the producer can no longer add new items in the buffer.
So the producer has to stop.
It's going to slow down over time to match the speed that with a consumer
can read the data from the buffer.
That makes sense.
So that's pretty much you.
So obviously,
the one problem you have with this one and we are going to discuss more
about it is that
if producer and consumer as a buffer on a single machine,
things are easy,
but here the producer and consumers are on different machines.
How do you now produce a being on one machine?
How does it now is a buffer on?
The consumer side is full?
He needs to somehow wait for some acknowledgment from the consumer that
it's okay to send more data.
The simplest version of that is called stop and wait,
and is as simple as you can think of.
We are going to use a lot of this kind of diagram,
and you see you have sender and the receiver on both sides.
And then the time goes down.
The oldest time is at the top,
the newest time it is about.
So stop and why it is very simple.
You send a packet,
you wait for an acknowledgment,
and only after extent you got the acknowledgment, you send another pack.
Okay.
Now, there are several important aspects in our metrics here.
So it is this d which is a delay or one way delay.
How long it takes a packet to get to the receiver from the center?
Right?
It takes some time.
There are different overheads and at all,
on top of that, obviously,
there is a speed of light.
So across the continent, I think, is what?
Maybe than 20 millisecond in us something like that.
And now you need to wait for acknowledgment.
So acknowledgment, it might take another,
the same amount of time,
assuming that asymmetric capacity metrics,
it's not necessary for the past to be symmetrics.
Because as the packet from the sender to the receiver,
can go on a different path from the sender to the back from the receiver
to the sender.
Even if they go to on the same path,
there can be different level of congestion in the network is,
for instance, at a given time, in the day,
is not taking you the same time to go from auckland to san jose,
as to go from san jose 2o'clock.
Right?
Different level of congestion.
But anyway, for simplicity,
assuming assume that you have the same one way latency,
as this, assume no congestion.
So if there are no congestion,
so it does take the same amount of time.
And now,
but then you need to wait for two times d in the best case scenario to get
the acknowledgment back.
And these 2 times this round trip time,
it's called round trip time.
Round trip time is how long it takes a packet to travel from sender
to receiver and back.
Okay.
Now, what is this throughput?
How many packets you can send?
Let's say,
let me give you some numbers.
So say, is that one way latency?
It's 1 million seconds using this protocol,
assuming that everything is symmetric,
all the one way latency are the same for all packets.
How many packets I can send in 1second?
I know latency is 1millisecond.
And I am asking you how many packets I can send in 1second?
500.
That's correct, simon.
Indeed, that's the correct answer.
And it's very simple, right?
It's like we can send only one packet per round trip time,
because you need to wait for the acknowledgment before you send another packet.
The round trip time is twice the one way delay.
Latency is too many seconds.
So 1second over 2 million seconds.
It's1,000 million seconds over two is500.
Good.
Sounds good.
So how fast can you send data?
You answer that question?
Again, the little law applies on this case as a number of packets.
It's be how many packets you have in the system times the round trip time.
And b will be the number of packets you have in the system.
Sorry, you the number of packets you have in the system.
It's only one pack.
Right?
So you have one packet priority,
like we discuss.
Now,
let's do a little bit more complicated here.
Now you have,
in this particular case,
you'll have what is the throughput in terms of the number of bytes,
not in the number of packers?
Like I mentioned, I ask you a little bit earlier.
If you have the round trip time of 100millisecond.
So one way the latency is 50millisecond,
a packet has100,
1,500bytes that what is a throughput in terms of bits per second?
It's very simple, right?
You can send one packet means1,500×8beats in0.1seconds.
So it's 120 kilobits per second.
Okay.
The main.here, though,
is that as you can see,
this is very simple protocol.
You can implement it right away.
So it's at the advantage of this protocol.
It's simplicity.
On the other hand, is very inefficient.
You see,
he's taking, you cannot send more than at 120 kilobits per second.
No matter how fast than a turkey is,
because because in this case,
a throughput is governed only,
by the one way letters.
The one way latency will not depend in moscow cases.
If you think about its mostly speed of light,
it will not depend if there's a speed of light component of the latency
of how fast is a network.
How fast is the link?
If you have 100 megabytes per second or one gigabytes per second bit
or ten gigabytes per second,
you can still only send at 120 kilobits per second.
So how can you send more?
How would you modify this protocol to send more
batch acknowledgement?
So if you bat, it's true.
But if you bat the acknowledgment,
this means that you have to send a packet before you receive
the acknowledgment for that pack,
your intuition is correct.
But as you'll see,
and that's big part of the solution.
But as you see, things will not be as easy.
It's exactly simon and allison.
It's the same.
You don't need to get block on act,
because if you get block on a knack,
then it's no longer you can send packets.
Right?
But the problem is the following.
Okay, you don't draw it's, they do it.
Your intuition is absolutely correct.
The main problem here is that I need to wait for an acknowledgment
from the previous packet before I can send the next packet.
And the solution is, okay,
don't wait for that.
Right?
Send more packets as a problem.
And if you don't have losses,
that will be great.
But if the packets are lost,
then here the acknowledgment serves to proposes one to slow you down,
to slow the sender down, right?
To block the sender.
But the other one is also to say,
there's a packet has been successfully receipt.
So let's talk about losses.
So in the internet,
you are going to have losses like we discussed last time.
Right?
And actually,
dcp transfer control protocol is going also to provide reliability
besides flow control and congestion control.
Right?
But as another player,
you are going to have losses be because many reasons,
it's like we discussed in the past.
We have your microwave can corrupt your wireless link,
even in optical network, in optical networks,
abyss can be corrupted.
The wire can be bad,
not very well connected.
And many reasons.
Or like we will see the buffers in the routers are going to overflow,
and you are going to draw packets.
Now,
we,
when you with a packet,
you have associated,
basically,
as we'll see,
there are two way,
two,
or two ways to lose a packet here.
First of all, the packet doesn't get to the destination at all,
is lost.
The second one, the packet is corrupted.
You get the packet,
but some bits are flipped.
Okay?
On the receiver side,
you need to know that you need to make sure that you get all the packets,
the package you got are not corrupted.
And by the way,
you also want to make sure that you get each package exactly once delivered
to the application.
So this acknowledgment,
like we see by soft earlier on,
they also serve as an acknowledgement that the packet was delivered to the destination.
So basically, if I am the receiver,
I get the packet.
I check the packet.
Whether is correct?
How do I check the package that is correct?
They have the correct information.
How you do it?
You are the designer.
That's you do have a check sum,
like the check sound like parity,
be something more sophisticated than that.
But that's the idea.
The packet has a data and has a check sound.
You take the data and you could compute the checks,
are using the same algorithm.
You compare that the computed checks out is the same as the jackson in the back.
If they are the same,
you say this packet,
the data is correct.
Otherwise, you drop the back.
Now, if a packet is dropped,
like in our previous case,
right?
The question is that i'm sending a packet.
The packet is lost,
for instance,
or it gets a packet is get to the destination this job.
What i'm going to do,
so what i'm going to do because i'm going through it indefinitely,
because i'm going to wait for a knack which will never come.
So what you do here is basically very simple solution.
Basically, you wait for a timeout is like you in real life.
You are waiting for your friend to call.
And he doesn't call at When it was the time you expected.
What do you do?
After a while, you are calling your friend,
right?
Or you go to meet someone.
And that person doesn't show up.
What do you wait for a while?
And then you leave.
All right.
So now, obviously,
again, it's like,
it's very important to notice here,
by the way, that if you don't get the acknowledgment,
it doesn't mean that the receiver that it didn't give the original message.
Now, right?
Can you give me an example in noisy receiver?
I didn't hear about the acknowledgment by the receiver got the packet,
and the packet is correct.
I send you the packet.
I I don't hear from you back.
Yes.
The acknowledgment is lost.
The acknowledgment is also packet that can be lost as far.
Right?
So basically,
you may send a packet.
Me maybe sends a packet,
because they don't get the acknowledgment on the timeout.
Now, the receiver gets an application of the packet.
That's why the receiver has to have a way also to differentiate
between duplicate as the original packet.
Because if the original packet was already delivered to the destination
to the process,
you need to drop that the duplicate.
So this is an example.
When the ark is lost,
you resend the packet.
And now the receiver gets to packets right.
Now,
it's one of the challenge here is how you are going to pick the time out.
If the timeout is short,
you may get lots of applicants.
So why is that?
Right?
Remember that this,
like in our simple examples,
we assume that the one way latency is constant.
It's like in real life.
It's like, once a highway,
like we discussed, the latency is not going to be the same.
You are too trigger happy with the timeout and to resend the packet.
I wait just for that time out,
the minimal time out, right?
That sort of the new as a minimum round trip time.
Then if I send,
I may send too early,
because I didn't give enough time to the packet to make the destination
and the acknowledgment to come back.
Obviously, if it's a wait,
it was too long than the performance offers.
For instance, around 3 times,
it's 100 millisecond and the timeout.
It's 1.
Second, right?
This means that if there is a timeout,
I lost the opportunity to send another line packets,
right?
Or ten depends how you count how you deal with the application.
Basically, you have somehow to put some sequence number in the packets.
And these sequence numbers are unique.
And the acknowledgment will be for a particular sequence number.
Right?
And the sender, when you send,
you keep the packets which are not acknowledged,
right?
About you still have the packets.
If they are lost,
if a packet is acknowledged,
the sender can remove that packet from his buffer.
And on the receiver side,
I also keep a track of the sql numbers of the packets.
I got.
If I get the duplicate the packet with the application number,
I can drop it.
You want to simplify it by having only one message at a time.
Again, and you just don't move until the message has been sent,
has been received by the sender, by the receiver.
Okay?
And this is exactly what we are talking about in our example.
The problem, obviously,
that is slow and better perform us.
So now,
let's go back to solve our problem.
And our problem was that how we are going to improve the throughput
over stop and write.
Right?
We said that in order to improve this report is quite easy.
Is basically don't we send packets without waiting for the acknowledgment?
And we saw that doing that won't be that easy,
because the acknowledgment also acknowledged whether the packet was
received or not and leave the packets or lost.
Things get complicated.
Right?
But this being said,
this is a solution, right?
For improving the performance.
You send a lot of packets without waiting for the acknowledgment.
So we pipeline the sending,
right?
That's very simple.
Now,
if you have this one,
the natural way to implement this and to implement this protocol,
is to call to have what is called a window.
A window is how many packets or how many bytes you can
send without hearing for an acknowledgment.
If the window size,
let's think about in terms of packets,
and we say without missing in terms of bytes,
if a window size is ten packets,
this means that I can send ten packets.
Before I hear,
ii get back the acknowledgment from the first packet.
I said,
okay,
now, in a round trip time,
I can send a window worth of packets,
right?
Because this is how many packets I can send without hearing for an average.
Right?
So therefore,
in the number of packets which are in flight,
are going to be without meaning in flight,
from packets, which are in flight.
I haven't heard an acknowledgment for this package.
It yet is a window size over the packet size.
How long do you, does the sender need to seen packets around?
What is your answer?
How many packets that the sender needs to skip around?
If the packets are lost?
Can still fix the loss.
Alison, this is good.
You need to keep at least a number of packets,
which is equally the window size.
How long does the receiver have to keep the packet data?
Remember, the receiver needs to keep the log back as date hour,
and these are a sequence number in order to avoid applications.
Until the packet in the window that is time out.
Let's think about forget about the protocol.
When can you remove a packet?
Think about your receiver packet?
When can you remove the information about that packet?
Again,
the main reason you are going to keep that information around is not going up.
So I send your packet.
When do you know that I am not going to send you again that packet?
When I send the next packet depends on the protocol, right?
Is the next sequence number.
It's a little more complicated, but than that,
I think we are close.
But fundamentally,
the answer to my question is that that you can remove the packet
when I know that you got the packet,
once I know that I you got the packet,
i'm no longer going to send you the packet.
We'll see a little bit is how that is done.
It's not that easy,
but because you see if i'm getting user packet is an sequence number,
it's not necessarily the case, right?
Because like here,
if you look at this in this figure,
a packet will be lost.
But back at the set packet is lost.
I get the next packet.
Actually, in some cases,
you cannot return,
you cannot remove the packet one or two.
Because in some protocols,
the sender is going to start from the beginning to send all the packets.
Actually, in pcp and most version of this piece soon happen,
what if the sender is sending back as faster than the receiver can process
the data?
In this case, it's quite simple.
You slow down the accomplishments.
If you cannot get more buffer about more packets,
you slow down.
Now,
we are going to talk about these are some good questions and to keep
in mind and see how they are.
So in particular, the last one,
how long does the receiver have to keep the packets data?
What if the standard is sending back as faster
than the receiving receiver campus is a rate,
which is about exactly the flow control?
Now, the pcp again,
I mentioned that last time,
but it was very quickly has a slide the window protocol at the bite,
not back at level.
So far we talk about packets.
It was easier to visualize.
And he has two ways to recover, go back.
And is that if I miss some packets,
right?
I'm going to go back,
and i'm going to send the packets from the one in chinese
and also the subsequent packets,
whether you receive them or not.
Selective repeat, you only send on the packets is called discipline sack.
You only send all the only the packers which are lost,
all the bytes which are lost.
Qa the main way of this tcp implements,
the flow control is by the receiver,
telling the sender how many more bytes it can receive.
And this is called advertisement.
And the acknowledgment contains a sequence number,
and of the next by the receiver expects.
This means that the receiver has received all bytes in sequence up to
and including n minus one.
If there is a gap,
I received the first 100 bytes,
then there is a gap of 50 bytes.
And then I received the buys from 150, 250.
As a receiver.
I'm still going to send to the sender,
101,
which is the next byte in sequence.
I'm expecting.
So next we are going to go through a bunch of definitions about some variables.
There are six of them.
And then we are going to take an example,
a simple example.
So hopefully the examples will clarify things.
But it's please beer with me.
This is a bounding.
If i'm taking this bounding buffer example,
like I showed you earlier in the lecture,
I tried to map it on to hosts sender and the receiver.
This is one I will, or I I I can show I can do it.
I can have a buffer on the receiving process.
That's a bounding buffer.
And the sending was going to send it to.
And these packets are going to be and curing in that buff
and then delivered to the receiving process.
However, like I mentioned to you like we discussed last time,
this is not going to work well in practice,
because this means that for each packet,
the sender process sends,
you need to have a course, a contact switching,
because your operating system is going to be involved in the act of sending
the packet,
because the tcpip is a network stack,
is implemented in the operating system.
If you do a context switching on sending every packet, like, for instance,
in the case of the internet,
the packet size is typically 1,500 bytes.
Then in order to sustain the stroke of a one garbage per second
or one garbage per second link,
you need to send a packet every 12 to 12 microsecond.
If the packet is small, smaller,
like 100 bytes in less than one microsecond.
And this is too little for the contact switch.
Right?
Therefore, how you solve the problem,
you have other buffers.
In general,
you have one buffer on the sender side and one buffer on the receiver side.
This is what operating system maintains and the processes themselves.
They can have other buffers, right?
Actually,
the process of sending from one process towards another has three steps.
The sending process sends the data to the operating system or is buffered
in the discipline.
The operating system is using the ip layer to send.
We chop the data,
you send the sender into packets and send it to the receiver operating system.
The receiver operating system will put the data it receives in a buffer.
And then from this buffer is going to deliver the data to the receiving process.
By the way,
the fact you see is I have a buffer allows me for something else.
The sending process can have a stream oriented protocol like we learned.
So I can send a stream of bytes,
1,000 bytes,
four kilobytes,
whatever.
Then the operating system, this buffer,
I put all these data into the buffer,
and the operating system can then take the data and chop it in packets,
because that ip layer is not a streaming protocol.
You have to send packets.
I need to put take some piece of daytime,
putting the headers,
poor numbers for a source and destination ipip addresses.
Then at the lower level,
you put the mac addresses and things like that.
So now,
let's assume that the maximum ip packet size,
for this example,
is 100 bytes.
Again, in general, in practice,
is 1,500 bytes.
In the size of the receiving buffer is 300 bytes,
the receiver, and this is a buffer.
300 bytes also recalls as the acknowledgment indicates,
the next expected biting sequence,
knows the last three seat bikes.
Like as we discussed last time, we circular buffers.
Right?
If you remember,
basically, a circular buffer is like, you see,
here is basically goes around,
and you keep the head and the tail of the buffer.
So now, with all of these,
let's see how things are working.
Like I mentioned,
we are going to decide to define six variables.
Last byte written.
This is a sequence of the last byte written by the sending process
into the operating system buffer.
Last byte Send is the last by sent by the sender to the receiver.
Last by act is a last act,
received by sender from the receiver.
Last by the received is the last by the received by receiver from the sender.
Next byte expected is a lasting sequence byte expected by the receiver.
Is it a convention to start a circular buffer at one index?
It depends what language you are going to use if you see is probably zero.
Yeah.
Now let's take the examples and sorry the last by dread is the last
by dread by this receiving process.
Okay.
So this basically says that you have in this blue area,
in the receiving buffer is how many bytes you have in the buffer
in the receiving buffer.
You consumed from one end.
This is the start.
The last by dread is the start of the buffer of the data in the buffer.
Last byte received is the last byte in this data of the data in the buffer.
Next byte expected in this case,
is the last by the receipt+1,
because that's the one you expect.
Okay.
Now, the advertised window is, by definition, again,
how many bytes,
the receiver,
the sender can send me without me overflowing?
Basically,
if i'm the receiver and my buffer size is 300 bytes,
the buffer is empty.
I tell you you can send me 300 bytes.
If my buffer,
I already have 100 by source of data in the buffer,
I tell you you can send me only $200.
This formula is computing exactly what I told you.
It's a massive zeta buffer minus how much data I have
in this contiguous region in the buffer,
which is last by the received minus last by the red.
The same in the same thing.
It's on the sending side of similarities.
Right?
Here I have last bike act.
Here, if I get an acknowledgment in this protocol,
if i'm going to get an acknowledgment for a byte,
this means that the receiving process receives a byte.
I know I no longer need to keep it in the buffer.
As a sender,
cried everything before after before last byte act can be dropped.
And then you have last by set.
What is last by act?
What is these things between us by act and last by cent?
This green area,
this is green area represents the data that the sending process send it
without being acknowledged.
That's it.
So let me see.
It's exactly simon, yeah.
The package we send that have not received an axe so they are not acknowledged.
So now think about sender window.
And this again, you have the formula you can look at the formula,
but let's take an example.
Now let's think about from the receipt,
from the center perspective,
say the receiver,
you are the sender.
The receiver tells you my advertising window is 300 bytes.
And since I learned this information,
I already send you 100 bytes.
How many more bikes can I send you before i'm hearing back from?
So that I am absolutely certain.
I'm not going to overflow you, right?
It's again, the receiver tells you,
you can send me 300 bytes.
Since you heard that, then you heard that you send 100 bytes,
still, nothing from the receiver.
How many more bytes you can send before you hear from the receiver?
It's, in my example, was 200,
right?
Receiver told you, you can send me 300 bytes,
you send 100 bytes.
You haven't heard yet.
You can send another 200 bytes.
So then you send in total 300 by rights.
Before you hear back, you cannot send more.
This is exactly this next formula.
The sender window is how many more bytes you can send without overflowing
the receiver.
It's advertise window minus my number of bytes you send out without being acknowledged.
Is that radar?
It's still true.
There is a very important aspect.
This is still true if you miss the data,
these formulas,
because if you miss that data here on the receiver side,
the next byte expected, by the way,
you see here, the next byte expected is the one which is in sequence.
Right?
Because you have a gap, the gap doesn't matter for the next bikes expected,
but for the last by the receive, it matters.
So remember that these are the same formulas if you miss the data in the middle.
Now let's take a simple example.
Let's say the sending application since 350 bytes,
we assume the ip only accept package no larger than 100 bytes.
And let's say the max receives advertised window.
Mac receiving buffer is 300 bytes,
and advertising in the initial is one hundred three hundred bytes,
send the first send buffers packet,
how much we get the first packet?
100 bytes.
Because as a maximum size of the package,
we grain, I show the packet which are sand without being acknowledged.
Here on his side,
i'm saying one one hundred between these square brackets is a by which had been sent.
I am starting from one.
So eventually,
the last by sent, when I am doing, when I am sending,
initially the last by that,
it's is zero.
I no, nothing was active.
As the last by cent.
It's 100,
because I send 100 bytes.
And I eventually this packet is delivered to the destination.
Last byte receives.
It's 100.
Next spike is expected.
It's 101.
Right?
Everything is good.
Now,
the sad receiver send back acknowledgment 101.
Advertising, don't know, is 200.
Right?
Because I it was 300, I got 100.
Now you can send me only 200.
Okay?
Before receiving this acknowledgment,
because the window advertising,
there is 300 bytes and I sent only 100 bytes.
I went to send the next packet me being the sender.
The bytes are between a one on one and 200.
Right?
Again, sorry, here I am saying all the packets which are being sent,
all the bytes which have been sent.
Now I sent from the center between 1 and 200.
This packet is going to,
now the last by cent is 200.
It's going to get to the receiver and the receiver.
You have lost by the receipt 200,
next by the expected 201.
I'm going to now201.
Now assume that next thing is what happened,
the receiving process.
There is some data, let's say it is 100 bytes,
the first 100 bytes.
So now, in the receiving window,
in the receiving buffer,
I only have 100 bytes,
because 100 bytes already were required processed by the receiver,
were already delivered to the receiver process.
And i'm going to send back an acknowledgment.
I'm going to include the next sequence,
the next flight expected,
which is 201.
And then advertising window,
it's again 200.
Because in the buffer,
I have only 100 bytes.
The buffer is 300 bytes.
Now,
the sender is, again,
I still have,
I know that I ii send only 200 bytes.
The receiver told me initially that I can send 300 bytes.
I still can send 100 buy.
So let me send the next pack.
But let's assume now to make things more interesting that this packet
has been lost.
Okay?
That's fine.
In the meantime,
as I have and the last by set sent as on the understanding on the standard
to 300,
in the meantime,
and the sending window now is zero.
I can no longer send you see the sending window magically now is zero
because I sent 300 bytes.
I knew that the advertising noise, 300 bytes,
I haven't heard anything from the receiver.
So that for I have to stop sending.
Now, in the meantime,
I get the first acknowledgment back.
The fact that nourishment back is telling me,
I have 101 the economy is 1, 01,
and advertising window is 200.
Right?
The first packet was acknowledged,
right?
Because the first packet was acknowledge,
it was acknowledged and also indicates an expected to send.
So the receiver no longer needs the first 100 bytes.
So i'm going to remove these from the receiver,
but from the sender buffer.
Because the receiver told me that it got the first 100 bytes.
Okay?
I am going to ask advance last byte act 100,
but the sender window is still zero.
Right?
Because I I ii send said,
iii send 300 bytes.
Now the sender told me I got 100 bytes,
but I can receive only 200 bytes,
2 or 200 more bytes.
I I removed the 100 bytes at sanders and told that the receiver told me
that they receive.
But still, I have 200 bytes which are not acknowledged.
And the receiver told me that it can only send receive bytes without being acknowledged.
So I cannot send anything.
But finally, now I get the second acknowledgment.
And their second acknowledgment tells me,
tells the receiver that the get us to the sender that the receiver got
the first 200 bytes.
The next expected byte is 201,
and the advertising window is 200.
Now you're on your computer advertise window.
You get 100 because it's 200 advertiser window.
Now I have in flight,
only 100 bytes,
so I can send another 100 bytes.
I don't have 100 bytes to send.
I only have 50,
right?
Because I I wanted to send 350 bytes.
I'm going to send this By few the last 50 bytes.
And then they are going to be received by the receiver.
But now I have a gap, and the gap is a third packet which is lost.
You see it?
Now, next byte expected is still 201,
right?
The last byte receive now is 350.
Now I sent back to the receiver and say,
I got the next bite.
I am expecting these 201,
but the advertiser on one window is 50.
If the advertiser window is 50,
what is the sending process going to do?
Right?
Yes.
You can send, in this case,
you can send the packet.
We just lost.
Why you can send this packet.
We'll do more about this in a while is still in the green region.
It's exact
by the sending window is less,
it's good by the sending leno is less than zero.
Is very good observation.
But the point here that I can descend the packet,
because I already sent that packet, it doesn't count.
I can all always,
he sent aa lost a packet which had previously ii previously sent,
right?
Because in the worst case, it should be the duplicate.
In the best case,
in the worst case will be duplicate.
In the best case, it's going to repair the loss.
You see, the receiver by this gap already accounted for the loss packet.
That's a key.
You see, it's already accounted.
The next expected byte is 350.
Therefore, if i'm going to send a packet,
that's not going to change the window on anything,
it's again, either is going to repair a loss,
what is going to be dedicated.
So that's why I can send the packet and why i'm going to send now.
In this particular circle is aaaa particular case.
I am going to send it because you see,
is the second time,
I get acknowledgment sender.
The receiver told me that the acknowledgment is the next sequence number,
it's expecting is 201.
Basically, if and we'll see this next,
this is a way to detect a failure.
I can't aa packet loss.
One way to detect a packet loss is that if the receiver tells me multiple times,
I am waiting for this sequence number, next sequence number,
because this means that it gets the reason in the receiver.
Can you tell me that it twice for the same sequence number over and over again,
is that I sent him a next pack, another packet,
but it's a gap is not in sequence.
Because if it's in sequence,
the next sequence number,
the receiver will tell me will advance as well.
Anyway,
now, if you have,
if finally you get the next packet,
the loss packet,
the receiver gets a loss packet.
Everything gets got up to 350.
Is going that acknowledgment or contains 351 with the next sequence number
is going to wait for.
Advertising window is still 50.
And now,
and the receiver,
the sender gets acknowledgment,
351.
It can remove every everything from its buffer,
because all the data I sent was acknowledged.
Now we are done.
Any questions?
So please,
you can go through.
This example is very revealing,
but you need to go a few times to really feel it,
understand it.
So let's have a short discussion before remove.
Yes.
Almost everything we talked,
it goes to back and selective repeat.
The only difference is like it was said,
someone said, for instance,
the difference here,
This was mostly I shown you about selective acknowledgment.
So i'm telling you what is a difference.
So we go back.
And that is the sender is going to send everything up from 2001,
including the last 50 bytes which are already received by the receiver.
You only already go from the first sequence number,
which was expected by of the missing packet.
Okay?
In the case of selective acknowledgment,
the recess sender is like, in this case,
is going only to send out the missing packets.
The missing
information would last bite read calls a bottleneck on how is the question
from my assignment?
Would last by read,
brad, cause a bottleneck on how fast we can clear the buffer.
If we are not spending enough cycles to man copy from buffer from to process,
we cannot advance last by dread as fast so that limits our advertising know.
Absolutely and that exactly the proposal the goal of his having
this last bite read.
The goal is basically he had the ultimate receiver is a perceiving process.
So the receiving process, for some reason,
cannot consume data with the sender shouldn't send faster.
So let's move on.
Let's go.
So why not have a huge buffer at the receiver memory ship?
After all?
A huge buffer is a receiver,
also means a huge buffer is a sender.
Right?
We'll see that huge buffer actually,
also in the network organization control,
means as a latency is going to increase significantly.
Because the latency is going to increase significantly,
because it's going to take more to send to clear the buffer.
It's like a large transmissions that the round trip time,
the transmission time is going to grow up a lot.
Ascending window also depend on at a congestion is that are going to go
to do next.
There are a lot of details about,
if you are interesting about networking takes cs on 3.68.
By the way,
we talk about a few buffer to buffers here in the operating systems.
For the sender and the receiver side.
In practice, there are more buffers.
There are network artist buffers,
buffering the network and everything.
Let's announcements.
Meters three is tomorrow.
What they've done over today in the lecture is not for next,
for is not included in the material.
For the exam,
for the last meter on sunday,
we are going this project three party between 10:00 and 2:00
pm the discussions will be converted in
office hours to help you with the projects last project.
With the exam, if you have, well,
is it will be after the exam.
So it don't help you as much.
The office hours also will continue into that week again to help you
with the projects.
How much c six is due friday and next friday and project.
No, this friday.
So next friday.
And the project through three,
it's due as you now on december 8.
Now we have another 15 minutes.
Let me tell you a little bit about the congestion control.
Flow control,
don't overflow,
the receiver congestion control,
don't overflow the network.
The network has routers has buffers in between.
So now the question is,
how you are going to detect the congestion is an adult.
And remember the congestion i'm going to detect as a transfer level.
Player.
There is no transfer layer in the network.
It's only between two and host.
So I can only observe the network.
There are a few ways to detect the congestions.
One, a packet is dropped.
You interpret this to be a sign of congestion,
because you assume there's the reason a packet has been dropped is
that because a buffer of the router was overflow,
filled in the router can no longer cannot send packets as fast as you get
the buffer fields in packers at all.
There is a modified version,
early congestion amplification.
So when the buffer is a router,
increases of over some threshold,
the router set up a bit is called easy and bit in the packet.
And then the receiver sends back to the sender saying, hey,
don't send a slowdown,
because this router it's about to be is congested.
The other one is the light packets.
When the buffer grows,
the late entrance latency growth is like on the highway.
If I see that the delay has increased,
maybe I need to slow down.
The simplest one.
It's drop packets.
And this is what we are going to assume,
is the most use sign of congestion today.
Like we discussed, there are two ways what to detect these drawbacks.
Again, the question is,
how do you detect a drawback?
Right?
Congestion means the router buffer is full,
and then because it's full, the bakery is dropped.
But now,
if i'm the sender,
how i'm going to know that's a packet of stock,
how i'm going to decide a packet of stock.
One way is like we discussed earlier on timeout.
I wait for some time,
which is significantly larger than round 3 time.
I don't get an acknowledgment.
I assume the packet is lost,
even if it was.
So I resent it.
And the other one I just alluded to you earlier on.
It's when I received the same acknowledgment,
the same sequence number in the acknowledgment, the next sequence number,
expected sequence number over and over again.
Because again, in this case,
i'm going to send yourself, in this case,
I send you the packet200,
right?
From 100 to 200.
So you tell me the next sequence number i'm going to,
I ii am expecting from you is 201.
Now.
I'm sending you the next packet with a bias 200 to 300.
You lost.
You don't tell me anything.
Now i'm sending the next packet 300 to 400.
You give me the acknowledgment for that packet,
but is the sequence number.
Next sequence, expected sequence number is still to 100,
because you are telling me about the in sequence,
next expected in sequencing number.
Now, you told me 2 times 206,
the next sequence.
In sequence number,
you expect this 201.
I'm sending you another packet.
Now between 400 and $500.
Again, you tell me the next bike in sequence,
i'm expecting is 201.
Again, an acknowledgment which is duplicate.
This is what they called applicant acknowledgment,
because you tell me repeatedly over and over, I call you,
don't they told me over and over again.
Beyond the next equal number,
i'm expecting is 201.
So after a few of those,
I decide that packet was lost.
And i'm going to resent this is the applicant acknowledge.
Make sense?
Congestion control.
The key idea is a standard increase to increase ascending rate
if the network until congestion,
if the network is not congested,
individuals ascending ratings and turkeys congest,
how does the sender control sending rate?
Send their it's called window size, the sending window size,
which is called right now in this context,
congestion and window size.
Here is a great question from allison.
About the previous case.
What I mentioned to you,
the question from allison is the following.
Can you not conclude it was lost?
The packet was lost after the first duplicate act?
Tell me why you wouldn't do that.
You could do that, but why you wouldn't do it.
May be out of order.
It's exactly out of order arrivals.
You see,
look at this figure and assume that these packets which is lost
instead of being lost.
It travels on a different passenger network and arrives
actually as a destination after the packet,
the force packet,
the one, which right after the last packet, right?
Which was sent by the sender.
The third packet is lost in this example,
but assume is not lost,
but it arrives after the force packet.
If that's the case,
the sender will see the same things.
It cannot differentiate between the two.
So waiting for more duplicate acknowledgments,
it's a way to make it more sure that the packet was really lost.
It's not because the packets are ordered,
and the packets are reordered,
because every packet can take a different route in the network,
which means also is through a dialogue that street applicant acknowledgment missing a city that became $1 million
are not necessarily always guarantee a back at has been lost.
It's correct.
It just increase the probability that a session to be correct.
Okay.
How does the sender control sending?
Right?
It's as easy in account as again, a window.
It's called congestion window size and congestion window size.
It's going to take the minimum between the sending window size
and this congestion window site,
which is computed in the network.
And obviously, it might be less than the receiver advertising, though,
and increase the size of the windows and until congestion and reduce
the size of the window if congestion.
Right?
Because the window size,
it tells me how many packets,
how many buys I can send without being acknowledged.
Right?
Bigger window means higher throughput.
I can send more data before being acknowledged smaller window size.
I can send, if it's unpack it,
I can it's stop and wait.
So finally,
let me tell you, i'm going to spend a few minutes on this plot.
And this is just to give you a taste about how is the tcp
it's working and congestion control.
What is working?
This is one, right?
First of all,
I don't know how much when I am starting to send data as a receiver as a sender,
sorry, as a sender.
I know how much the receiver can handle,
because the receiver there is a initially,
when I established a connection and a three way handshake protocol,
and the receiver tell me about the advertisement.
It's advertising.
So I I know how much to send result of applying this.
That is very simple.
But they don't know about how much I can send without overflowing is
a network that what i'm sending,
i'm going to send a start with a congestion window of one.
Let's again,
think about our congestion window,
one packet to simplify the discussion.
I'm moving from one from window measuring and bytes into packs to pack us again.
I'm sending one packet and i'm waiting for acknowledgment.
So i'm sending only one packet.
So it's like stop.
And now,
when i'm getting the first acknowledgment,
I saw I sent a packet.
It went through.
Let me be more aggressive.
Now.
I'm going to increase the congestion window when I get the acknowledgment
by one.
Now i'm going to send two packets.
And each acknowledgment I get,
I add another one to the congestion window.
Now, this is called slow start.
Slow start is a terrible name,
because actually,
if you think about in the slow start by cw is a congestion window here,
if you increase a congestion window,
every time you get a knock by one,
you double the congestion into every rounded time.
In the first round of time,
I sent one packet.
I got one acknowledgment.
Now.
In the second round of time,
I sent two packets.
I get two acknowledgment for each acknowledgment I get
in the second round trip time.
I'm going to increase the window size by one from two is going to go to four.
Now, in the third condition,
in a round of time,
i'm going to send four packets.
For each acknowledgment, i'm going to increase the condition by one,
so i'm going to have eight.
This is what you see.
The congestion window side is on the vertical.
It's going from small a double every time.
And at some point,
I am going probably to lose a packet,
because I sent too much.
This is when the packet is lost.
So what i'm going to do when that happened,
you need to be very aggressive,
because it turns out that if you are not very aggressive,
and this is it's a queuing theory properly.
We don't have time to go into it.
But if you don't reduce a sending rate very fast,
you cannot be relieved the congestion.
Right?
So in this case, you are very dramatic.
They are going to go in the congestion window all the way to one reduce it.
And then you go, again, slow start,
the gain, exponential increase.
But now you go through until to this threshold.
And this threshold is the last a is a congestion window.
In the previous slow start,
you are still successful.
All the packers made it.
Right?
Congestion window.
It was eight.
I sent eight packets.
I got eight acknowledgment.
Then and then when I conditional increase to 16,
I got I lost by I lost packets.
I'm going the next time.
I am only going to stop this slow start.
What aggressive start?
2~8.
Because I know that kind of a successful last time.
And then i'm going to be much more timidly explore how increase and explore
the capacity of the network.
Right?
So i'm going to increase now with one i'm going only to increase is that I
was talking about.
And now i'm going to increase only the condition we know by one
by round trip time.
So this means that in now,
when i'm going to get an acknowledgment,
i'm going to increase a congestion window by one over n where n Is
a current congestion window size.
If I have the congestion window site is stand,
and every acknowledgment I'm going to increase,
the window sized by 1/10.
Now, in one round of time,
I'm going to increase a condition from 10 to 11.
You get this one.
This is additive increase.
It's called additive increase.
Right?
Then I get the loss here.
If I lost here, maybe I is because cw get acknowledgment.
Now I'm going back.
If it's really double, we get acknowledgment.
I'm going to get back to the threshold.
Right?
And then I go, I grow again and things like that.
So that's basically what it is.
So there is an early stage,
you grow very fast to explore the limits of the network.
Then after that,
you get into this regime, which is,
at the end,
you additive increase,
then the window size, and you get a loss,
you multiply to be decrease.
This is called multiplying degrees.
Basically, you're cutting to half.
In general,
you grow linearly,
you cut it to half, you grow linearly, you cut it to half.
That's pretty much.
Again.
It's fascinating.
Algorithm is very simple, but in dynamics,
the dynamics are fascinating.
I'm going to stop here,
and we talk about the network.
The networking summary we will talk about at least we talk about networking.
We have a few lecture on that.
Remember the internet has five layers, physical layer, data link,
layer network layer,
transporter application layer.
We talk about and to end argument and to our argument is saying
that if higher layers can implement functionally correctly,
you should implement the functionality as a lower layer only if it improves
the performance significantly for applications that needs a function ID
and it does not impose burden on applications that do not require this functionality.
We discuss flow control,
which is whose goal is not overflows.
The receiver buffer.
Congestion control is the main goal,
is to not overflowing it.
Thank you.
And next lecture,
I'm going to do its special topics.
I'm going to tell you a little bit about some of the research which we
have been doing at rice lab and envelope.
Okay, see you all.
I'm going to stop here.
And there is a question I'm going to take.