Hello, everyone.
Today we are going to talk about one of the main concepts
of the operating system that is threats.
As you remember,
from last time,
we went over three.
That's the 4th fundamental operating system concept.
Thread,
which is a unit of execution,
which encapsulates execution state,
program counter, register,
stack, execution flag.
Then we have the outer space which represent this the set of addresses
in the memory,
in which is the program executes the process,
which is an instance of the execution program.
So therefore,
has consist of one more and more of more threads and the other space
where these threads are executing.
And finally,
we talk briefly about this dual mode operation and protections,
which enables a system to access certain resources and manage the processes.
While the same time being protected from the user processes,
changing the operating system.
Today,
we are going to start to finish as the discussion
about this dual mode operation and protection from the last lecture.
And then we are going to continue to focus on the main topics of this lecture,
which are the threads.
Okay?
Again, like always,
please ask your questions on the q and a I will stop periodically and answer
these questions.
So again,
about protection,
what we want is to protect the operating system and the harder by being
out from being accessed by the user programs.
User programs changing the state of the operating system
and even eventually crashing the system,
or getting and having the system leaking private information
about the other users and application sharing the same thing.
If we think about the protection,
you think about what are the resources which are shared
between these application and processes?
And how do we need to protect these resources?
One of the key resources,
it obviously is a memory, the other space,
right?
Which is shared by the threading the same processes in the same process,
but it's not necessarily shared by different processes.
This is a unit of protection at the same time, the address space.
Also remember that what we want here is that we want to decouple
the physical memory,
then from what the virtual memory,
which is what the process sees.
Okay?
And the virtual memory is supposed to provide the process,
the illusion that the process owns the entire address space.
On the physical machine,
you have multiple processes.
You have to multiplex the physical memory across different processes.
How you are going to make sure that while you are multiplexing the memory,
you provide boss protection and you provide the illusion to each process
that has access to the entire machine to the entire others.
Okay?
One simple solution is to have this base and bound.
On the left hand side, here,
you have the layout in the virtual memory of the
code and the data of a particular,
basically a thread and process.
Okay.
On the right hand side,
you have how this virtual memory,
this region in the virtual memory are mapped to the physical memory.
Now,
if you think a little bit,
if you have multiple processes and each process,
it has its own view and independent view of its own virtual memory.
Both all of them, they are going to see the same addresses.
Right?
They started from zero.
The code will start from other zero.
Right?
Now, when you are going to bring the physical memory,
go to map all to map to the physical memory.
Obviously not.
Both processes can start from other zero.
You need to map and to translate the addresses
from the virtual memory addresses to the physical memory
of different processes.
This is exactly what happens here.
A base a is by how much you are going to translate the virtual the
regions in the virtual memory seen by the process to the physical memory.
In this case,
it's like 1000 is based.
So this means that what you are going to do,
you are going to add to each others in the virtual memory of the process,
these base, others,
right?
And then the base and the bound represent the region of the physical memory,
which is owned by the process.
So that's kind of the main idea.
Now, when you are going to execute,
when the process is going to execute this code,
or is going to access its data,
the address is a process is going to see are the virtual addresses,
right?
But now, obviously,
the day towers instructions are in the physical address.
That's what they are actually stopped.
So in order to access those,
they just need to translate all these addresses,
which are accessed from the virtual memory by adding that address to the base.
And now you are going to obtain the corresponding physical memory.
Where is a code or the data it's are stored?
This is exactly what happens here.
You take the virtual address,
you are the base.
And then you are also going to compare with the bound.
So why you are going to compare with the bound now?
Because remember,
this process, which is the memory,
mutual memory of this process are yellow,
is mapped in this region in the physical memory between 1 and 1000,
and 11000.
Therefore,
you are going to compare the bound to make sure that the address and it's
within this the basin.
The bound falls in this region.
And if you do so,
you also make sure that this process cannot access a any memory
locations outside the base and the bound.
Okay?
So outside this region,
and that's basically what it is.
This is what also is called, obviously,
address translation,
because you are going to translate an address from the physical memory,
from the official memory to the physical memory.
The question is that now it's very clear, right?
I am going to split the physical memory in different regions.
Each region has going to have a basin bound,
which says, what is the minimum and the maximum address of the region?
And then you are going to make sure that each you are going to translate
the virtual memory of every
process within to one of these virtual one of these regions in the physical
memory.
And then you make sure that you translate whenever you are going to access
any or on a process,
access any man, any.
It's virtual memory.
You translate that address to the physical memory.
And you also make sure that the process cannot address a location of the memory
in or of the physical memory outside this region.
How do you do that?
One way to do it is to do it when you load the program,
you compile the program.
So everything in the program is the code of the program refers
to the virtual memory addresses.
But then when the operating system loads,
the program in the physical memory is doing translation.
At the low time it's overwrite,
the address is in the code with the translated values.
This is one way to do it, right?
It's still going to protect the operating system and isolate the program.
And there is requires no support from the operator,
no support from the hardware,
and even the support from the operator or the operating system.
Because these are enforced on your loads of program.
You make sure that all the address is folded a in a particular range.
And that's it.
So is there a question,
if you have 100 physical address space?
Is it possible to get 1,000 virtual address spaces?
If so, could you go over how that works again?
This is a great question.
I'm going to give a quick answer.
Now.
We are going to have an entire lecture about our even more than our lecture
about how to do this.
The answer is you can have virtual address space can be,
and it is much higher than the other can be
much higher than the physical address space.
For instance,
if you have a 64 bits computer,
the address space,
it's two power, 64,
right?
And you are not going to have a machine with so much memory.
Right?
In this, because what other mean?
I think it's four gigabytes is probably 16 terabyte or something
like that or more of them of memory.
And then you need to figure out how you are going to do it.
The way is that you do it is that you are going to have,
first of all, the application,
i'm not going to use the entire other space logically are going to have
these 2.2.2 to power 64 address strain in space.
But you are not going to use it.
And then what you are going to have,
you are going to have pages,
and you are going to instantiate in the physical memory,
only the pages which are corresponding to the virtual memory,
which are used by the program.
If you exceed the capacity of the physical memories,
and you are going to take some pages which are not used,
and you are going to put them on the disk.
That's kind of in and pages it.
Again, it's a chunk of physical memory,
and also a chunk of the challenge like for kilobytes or 16 kilobytes.
So a question here is,
what do we need to relocate as a louder?
It's again,
I what I mean by this is that when you start an application in this case,
and this is a more theoretical,
not many systems are doing this today,
you're facing, right?
It's in theory of how you can do it.
So if you think about here,
again, it's like when I the code,
when it's generated by the compiler,
has a virtual address.
Right?
It's using the virtual addresses,
because the code, when the compiler generates a code,
doesn't know anything about the physical memory.
And he shouldn't.
But now, when you are going to allow to load that code in the memory,
you need to make sure that code and the data associated
with the application are only going to be constrained
in a particular region,
in the physical memory,
because you want to protect other processes and the operating system
from the application,
or we are just starting to run.
Right?
So now,
basically,
when the louder is that the code and everything and in the physical memory,
so you make sure that the code and everything,
which is going to be accessed by the application,
which is in this region,
defined by the basin bound.
And the operating system will decide which region is that.
Right?
But now, for instance,
if the program say it was jumped to 00 to a particular virtual address.
Now, when I load it in the physical memory,
that address has to be changed.
Right?
Like in this case, right?
Because the address,
for instance, 000here,
I when one is going to be loaded in the memory of the physical memory,
should be issues.
It should become 1000.
That's what means.
It means that you want to have to override the addresses in the code,
the program executable,
so that you make sure that these addresses are going to be
within this region allocated by the operating system to the application.
How if can you constrain low stores?
What if a program asked too much to a pointer at run time?
That's a great point.
So basically saying what if the program being something at the run time,
which I cannot predict, because it's happening as a run time.
So that's how you do exactly this.
It's the way you do it.
It's like when the program is going to,
you add something to your pointer, to your address,
you are going to have to look to have an address here.
If the others is bigger than this, the bound,
then you are going to preclude that instruction from executing.
You can be, depending on the operating system, this can be a segment.
You can get a segmentation for there.
Right?
Again, these checks may be written.
It's again, you can have like cuisines and future.
You can be harder support to make this check.
But if not, the actually program the loader,
when you load the program,
you can add these instructions when you have an address which is computed
at the run time.
To check,
you can have additional code to check whether the address is going to be
greater than the bound.
Hopefully answer your question.
Yeah, so is the law.
There is a one checking that the address reference is followed
in the base and bound.
If you have no harder support.
The loader, like I said,
is going to add a canada additional code to check for that.
But if you have harder support or the operating,
then that like we say,
we'll see in the next Slide,
it can work in the next few slides.
I think it will be handled by the harder.
This is a very simple.
This is a baseline, right?
So I think we should move on because this is something for you to know
that it's possible,
but it's not really how it's implemented today in the operating system.
What do you have in the operating system?
Is that you have what translation happened as a run time.
You have a virtual address, you have like,
if you think about the processor has a built,
you are going to run on the processor,
you got going to give a virtual address.
And then magically,
the translation will happen between when before you access a memoir.
Right?
But this is so the address is translating on the fly.
And in this particular case,
typically, you have to have harder support.
So now think about that in law,
in instead of doing that,
the law that is doing it,
when you are going, it's allowed that is not doing anything.
You're still loud.
The data in the memory is the code and the data in the memory.
But now,
when the code is still contains a virtual address,
but now when the code start to execute the ability to refer to a virtual address,
the virtual address is automatically it's on the flight translated
by the harder to a virtual address,
to,
sorry, the physical address.
So base address,
it's every time when you are going to refer to the physical memory
from the processor,
you get the virtual memory,
because this is what is in the code.
But before you asked the physical memory,
then you are going the harder is going to add to the mutual address,
the base address this.
And now you are going to access the correct physical address instead of memory.
And also the harder can also check for the bound.
I'm looking again on the question.
So he's allowed us on to,
no, this is how does.
So he's allowed us on checking that the address references followed in.
Yeah, ii think I asked the question.
The answer is, how does a lottery sizes are based on the boundary,
particularly or in whatever scheme we used to keep the protection between processes?
How do we size up the expected size of physical memory?
A process should be allocated?
These are great questions to ensure the operating system should provide you
what it is a basin,
the bound for each process.
How much you are going to allocate?
This can be,
it's a typical, it's a default.
You can actually ask also configure it.
For the operating system,
you are going to say,
you can say how much.
But today,
these hard questions are addressed by visualizing the memory.
We are going to learn about that more.
But these are,
if you don't have that flexibility of the real digital memory,
these are the hard questions.
And you need to pick some numbers like each,
say, share process.
You're going to get exactly a regional for gigabytes.
So it is the os that relocates the louder.
So though the os in this particular case, again,
you are going to provide the base and the bound.
And the louder it is a utility which comes with the operating system.
And then once of loaders you give,
the loaders are based,
and the loader cells are based on the bound.
Like I discussed, it's going to override.
The address is in the code before it loads it,
physical memory.
But ii really want to emphasize and re emphasize that what actually things
happen today is that it's not the louder relocating the code.
Is what happens today is like in this slide,
where their visualization and the translation of the address is happens
at run time any harder.
Let's move on.
We have a lot of to cover.
Okay.
It's, again, can the program, in this case,
touch os can you touch other programs?
Why don't you start to?
What do you think?
You can maybe give your answers on on chat or the q and a
add on very good now.
And I see a lot of notes.
It's absolutely correct because if you cannot fundamentally,
if you look at these schemes,
the program cannot access a physical address
between outside the base address and the bounds.
As simple as that you cannot.
Right?
Because the address, by definition,
is higher than the base,
because you are the current address,
the virtual address, which is greater or equal to zero, right?
To obey the address,
you have to get something greater than the base address.
And before you are going to refer the physical memory,
you also compare this address with a bound.
And if it's larger,
you are not going to let the program add as a physical memory.
So by construction,
you cannot access the memory outside the base address in the bound.
Very good.
You cannot touch other programs,
you cannot touch the operating system.
Okay?
Now,
let's see about how things happen here when you have in a little bit more detail.
In this particular case.
Remember that for the protection and the dual mode operation,
you have this kind of bit.
You mentioned that is say it's a one when you system mode and one is zero,
and it's a user mode.
And this beat this girl when you are in the system,
or you are going to be able to add to have to access more resources
and also access even
the data and of the processes.
Here you have like n processes and you have the operating system.
On the left hand side, on the right hand side,
here is the layout in the physical memory.
With gray is the operating system.
So it's at the top.
And then with yellow and green,
you have the physical memory,
which is allocated to these two for us to put the process one and process
to respect.
Right?
Initially, let's assume that the physical the operating system executes.
You can see here,
these are registers.
You have the cis mode is set one.
You have a base and a bound for the operating system.
You have the this is a user program counter.
We are going to see how this is used,
and you have the program counter.
This is a counter of the current instruction,
which is now run by the operator,
executed by the operating system,
and you have a bunch of registers.
Right?
Now,
what we want is basically say,
we are going to move to,
we are going to to give the control to,
and we are going to give us a control to to a process,
in this case, to the yellow process.
So how we are going to give the contract?
Well,
to give the control to this process,
first of all, we are going to set up in the upc the user program counter.
You are going to say the current program counter for the yellow process,
a process to we are going to set up all the registers for the processor.
What are these registers?
All this information is contained?
This information is contained in the thread control block.
Right?
It each process has at least one threat, remember,
and or were,
in particular, this data,
it's the threat control block,
which associated with the thread is it's managed and it's maintained
by the operating system itself.
Okay?
The operating system wants to run the process to, in this case,
is going to the threat control block of process, too,
and take the information and popularize the registers.
Right?
So now,
you is a privilege instruction, privilege, instruction, or instruction,
which can be executed only by the operating system.
Then you return by return here in this rtu is the return to user.
It's a special instruction which basically now gives once you populate
the registers with all the
information relevant state information of the corresponding process,
then you are going to give control to the process.
And as you can see,
then what happens in the return instruction?
You copy the in the program counter,
user program counter.
Now it becomes the main program counter,
because now you have to start executing the code of the process to.
And now you execute the code of the process to which will only everything
will be constrained between the base and about that.
So this is how you switch between in between the operating system and the process.
Right?
Kernel a is a core part of the operating system,
which always resides in a memory, always.
It's always so to speak around.
Right?
So how do you now switch between one process to another process?
How do you switch from process two to process one?
The way you do it is that who is going to do the switch operating system.
So therefore,
you first need to switch from process to to promote the operating system
in front or the kernel and from that kernel to the processor.
What do you need to do?
First of all, you need to say,
when you switch from a process like index this process to,
you need to save the entire running state in that control blocks,
which means the current program counter,
the point of the stack,
point of the hip and everything.
So,
and then basically,
you are going to return to the system.
The system is going to decide,
which is the next process to run.
And then is going to restore the state for the process it wants to run
by populating the registers,
and then is going to give control to the next process like process one.
Right now,
there are many ways to,
there are a few ways to return to the actually,
to return the control to the kernel.
Right?
One, it's about a system called,
okay,
a system call.
There are many system calls.
Every service which is provided by the operating system to the application.
You remember about this kind of glue, right?
The operating system can be seen as a glue,
providing common services to the applications and also providing services
for the application,
trying to communicate with each other.
But for invoking any of these setting of services provided
by the operating system,
you are going to have,
typically you have a system call, right?
And again, the services can be file systems,
meta communications and much more.
Okay.
This is invoking is like a function invoking,
a functionality provided by the operating system,
open a file.
The way you do it, each distant call has aa particular identifier.
Therefore, what you do as an application,
the application code is set is putting in some register.
This I can identify and some other registered the argument of the system call.
And from there on,
it lets the operating system greed,
this identifier of the system call.
So in our system quality to execute its argument from the other registers,
and then goes to executive system call.
Another way you're the operating system,
the kernel get control is basically through interacts.
These typically are external interrupts.
This can be our devices.
Stripe is like when you move the mouse that same in interrupt
because the system is to respond to your action.
It can be when you get a packet, right?
Just another interrupt, you need to get the packet, right?
You need to start the packet as if the packet is lost, right?
It can be a timer.
Right?
Others.
In general,
there are io the interrupts are generated by the io devices.
All right.
This can be independent again from the user process of user,
the process which is actually running,
but it may not refrigerate.
The final one is strap or exception.
This is happening when something bad happens.
So I just like think about divided division by zero,
by zero or protection violation.
It's like we discussed early on.
It's like a process somehow asked to address.
It's going to be outside the base and the bound other addresses
in the physical memory.
Right?
The system will have,
you are going to get a violation.
In most of these cases.
The program is terminated that these are kind of what are called kind of un
programmed control transfers.
Because in many of these,
they are not programmed by the user.
This is what we mean by that.
Now,
how do you get the system target address of the young program control?
So basically, the question here is like I alluded earlier on,
is how does the system know what code to execute when some of these events happen?
Right?
That's what it is.
I already alluded, and I told you how this is happening for the ccc call.
This is a little bit.
Now this is how you do it for the internet.
Right?
For the interact,
you can have internet number.
Like for instance, when you,
for instance, when you click a key on your keyboard,
it can be interrupt like interrupt one.
When you except from the mouse, they interrupt two.
When you get from the network interrupts three.
Okay?
For each a kind of input devices,
you have an interrupt number.
And this is qualified and configured in hardware.
So automatically, when you get an interrupt from a keyboard,
they interrupt one and then an interrupt one.
Basically, you are going to point to a particular address,
which is put in the physical memory.
And that address,
you have the address of the handle of that interact of the code,
which runs when that interrupt have.
This is what you do.
Where do you see this kind of dispatch patterns?
This is a dispatch pattern, right?
You have the internet,
you have a in summary, the memory,
a physical memory, which is actually managed by the operating system.
You are going to have set of addresses each other's corresponds
to different interrupt and each other's points you
to the handler corresponding to that interrupt.
Any answer on this one?
What else do you see this dispatch pattern?
And then I will answer the questions.
Yeah, try and catch a that's a very good one.
Right?
So in that case,
you are going to have for when the general you have different exceptions,
you are going to want to invoke different code past.
There are many even in cisco,
when you do the cisco is very similar as I explained a little bit earlier.
Let me see a lot of fashions.
Let's see.
It is the os that it locates the louder.
I think I answer that it's any of its set,
a particular piece of hard harbor that hard that handle translation.
There is aa particular piece of hand harder that which handles
a translation and not only
it is typically called memory management unit.
Dubai tables contain the base and the bound,
not really because the page address the page has an implicit base,
but it doesn't need to contain the bound,
because all the pages are fixed size.
So that is implicit.
The bound.
If all the addresses are four kilobytes,
all these babies have four kilobytes,
you need only to know the starting address.
Once the starting address,
also the bound others.
So basically,
under permission,
can this be a when touching operating system or other programs like malawi
or other remote control application?
Or is as harder to be unknown?
No hardware to be no.
Under permission.
Can this be a when
i'm afraid I don't know what it's can this be a maybe you can add
the some clarifications that I don't know
what can this be a yes.
I don't know what history first,
or maybe you want to reformulate that address.
Is that question?
As a very beginning,
why is a bound?
Not 100?
Why is it?
Fff
I think I am.
So you shouldn't take,
I don't remember exactly what was in the slide and what are the values.
But you shouldn't take this,
the base and the bound number.
These are just examples.
The base and the bound can be any numbers.
Again, these are decided by the operating system.
Rpo return to users.
This stands for the question on what is rto stands for?
How many control blocks that exist?
So each process,
and we are going to learn more about that.
In the next lecture,
has a process control block.
We have all the information pertaining to the process.
Then each thread is in the process has a thread control block,
which is the state pertaining to the thread,
which is basically the running state.
Is there thread control block the same thing that cannot stack?
Now, the state control block is basically refers to the state
execution state to running state of a particular threat.
Typically, it's a user set.
The kernel stack is a stack of the operating system,
but obviously,
operating systems you can think about it has also its own threats,
right?
And if you have operating systems,
say it's only one thread,
then the kernel stack will be the stack of that kernel thread.
Hopefully, it will be more clear.
We are going to have some examples later in this lecture.
Does the existence of interrupt imply that there are context switching
back to the system to run?
Absolutely to checks?
Yes?
When this is what I was saying,
this is one way,
one in which the operating system gets a control.
Three interrupts.
When interrupts a curse,
you switch from the user process to the kernel for the kernel to treat
that interrupt,
to handle that interrupt.
How is the interpret eyes handled?
That's a great question.
This is a complex answer here.
Actually,
some of them are cured,
but in a simpler instantiation,
in different interrupts have different priorities.
Like some of it like maybe in interrupt from the printer,
it's not as important as they interrupt from the keyboard.
What happens here?
If it's a less priority,
it's a lower priority interrupt happens while a higher priority interrupt
is executed,
the lower priority interrupt weights.
If it's the other way around and you have higher priority interrupt,
when a lower priority interrupt is executed,
the higher priority interrupt can interrupt the lower priority interrupt.
I execute a so I interrupt from the printer.
Now I have an internet which is higher probability come from the keyboard.
I'm going to stop executing the lower priority internet from the printer.
I'm going to start in gripping the interrupt from the keyboard.
Once i'm finishing,
I am returning to finish,
treating or handling the lower interrupt from the lower level.
Lower probably interrupt from the printer.
Why do we tend to have a full vector with instruction inside the vector
rather than just a jump table?
I think this is actually very similar with a jump table,
because it's a jump table.
You still need to have when you,
sorry,
so just to make sure I this is a number,
okay?
Because it is this number, right?
We can have intervals 1234.
Then say this vector of interrupt hand within that handlers,
then it can start, for instance, from other zero.
Then the way you are going to happen,
you automatically when you have this is a 4 byte computer,
70 bits computer,
then basically,
you are going to have the first interrupt or the interrupt zero.
If you have, it depends how you index it.
If you start from zero,
then you from the first 4 bytes in the memory that are handled
for the first interrupt,
the next four buys for the second interrupt, and so forth.
So when you get an interrupt,
say I then you multiply I by four,
and then you are going to get to the address which contains
the interrupt handle for that interrupt.
This is what exactly happens here.
So hopefully that indirectly answer your question,
i'm having trouble distinguishing between operating system and kernel.
What is the difference?
Great question.
The operating the canon is part of the operating system,
which is always resident in the memory.
The operating system has many things.
It can have a file system.
It can have a part which is window system,
which controls the screen and some of these
not all of these functionality which are provided by the operatives,
them need to be loaded in memory at all times.
Like, for instance, if you run an application in the background,
which doesn't require the window system for you to interact with the computer.
That window system doesn't need to be in the memory.
Right?
You don't want to,
in order to use a physical memory more efficiently.
You do not want to allowed every single operating.
All the function is operating system can do in the memory.
But at the same time,
you do want to have a kernel,
you want to have a minimalist set of the functionality implemented
by the operating system,
like handling the interrupts,
or can't handling the contact switching between the user processes and the kernel
being a resident at all times in the morning.
Could you give you an example of what an interrupt handle function could do?
Say, for a keyboard input?
I can do it.
We are very late,
but I can do it.
So for instance, when you are going to have the handler for a keyboard,
then the keyboard that handler is going to read.
And this depends of how it depends on the hardware and the operating system.
But for instance, it can read,
you can associate a special address in the memory as representing
the content of the key we just clicked.
And therefore,
that when that handle for the keyboard is going to look
at the special address and read the key,
the code of the queue which was clicked by the user,
and is going to take that one and is going to give it to display it on the screen,
or give it to an application which can display it on the screen.
Okay?
Or the question above under permission refers cancel program,
touched os can you touch other programs?
Now it's, again,
the main idea here about the protection is that the process
for an application cannot touch
other processes or the operating system,
because the protection ensures that whatever the process is doing,
its remaining between the its the bounds,
but the base and the bound in that region of the physical memory,
which is allocated to that process.
By the operating system, you cannot get out of that.
So therefore, because you cannot get out of that,
you cannot access the memory of other processes or of the operating system.
Let's move on.
We are there.
Now,
let's see how the context switching start happens
between process two and process one.
Like I mentioned now,
you want to switch from process two to process one.
You are going,
sorry, so in this particular,
no, sorry.
This is an example in which it shows what happens when you get an interrupt.
Okay.
Here you are running the code of process one, process two,
the yellow process.
Now you are going to get an interrupt when you are going to get an interrupt,
you are going to put in the program counter,
the handler of that particular interaction interrupt the vector of I
and you are going to save,
you are going to say,
you have to put the program counter of the process tool in the user program
counter.
Now you need to save the registers of associated with the state
of the process tool.
But I still need to now this state,
because you need to know for the next time when you are going to run the process,
too.
Here you see how you are going to save the state of
all the state,
all the register of process on.
And now,
which charity is green.
Now,
in that particular interrupt,
let me be in a more clear error.
What in this example is,
I interrupt is a timer interrupt.
And the timer interrupt,
in this particular case,
three girls, the switch between process two and process one.
If you remember how the different processes,
how different processes,
how do you visualize one process?
Right?
To multiple processes?
We visualize it by dividing the time in time slices.
We give each time slice for to one process to a different process.
Now, how do we know how to do the switch?
The way we know how to do the switch is that we have a timer for to tell us
when a time slice is done.
So every 10 millisecond,
you have a timer triggering and say this life size is done.
This is what we are describing here that causes an interrupt.
And now that interrupt,
in this particular case,
is going to cause a handler is going to switch from process to the processor.
This is what happens.
Now, you want to switch it to switch.
You're safe again.
Sorry.
You save all this information,
the operating system, save it.
And this is done by the handler of the time I interrupt.
And now you load the registers for process one from the thread block
corresponding to process one.
Now,
with that is a program counter for the operating system for the kernel,
while still executing the handler of the timer.
And now you are going to give control,
do the process.
But before you give the control to process one,
you are going to put the address,
the program counter of the process one.
From the upc from the user process,
come from the upc registered to the program counter.
Now you can start run,
we can start executing process one.
Let's see.
What are the more question?
How does the os now which process was waiting for an interrupt?
For example,
in this particular case,
which knows?
The question is,
how does the operating system now switch process was waiting for an interrupt?
For example, if process one is waiting on keyboard input,
how does the operating system know to give control to process one
instead of process?
So this is going to happen from the system through the system calls,
because the process one is going to tell the operating system that I
am waiting for the keyboard inputs.
This is what is going to happen.
Again, we'll talk more about that in the future.
At a given time,
only the process which is in the so to speak foreground,
can get to the keyboard inputs.
If there are multiple processes,
the choice for the keyboard,
only one is going to get the input,
and the one which is kind of in foreground.
Let's hurry up.
It's a lot of so now this is done is the ground give you a sense about the production.
What we've done so far,
we've shown how the operating system or the
louder can protect,
can provide memory protection.
And then we also shown how the operating system can manage
different processes to switch
between processes or how it manages to switch between the
running a user program to running the operating system code.
Now, next, we are going to focus on threat.
The motivation for thread is very simple.
Why do we have multiple threads?
Because in many cases,
there are multiple things happen at the same place at the same time.
Right?
It's a acronym here.
We use mplmpal and you run the code.
You're on your application,
but like we discussed,
you can have some interrupts from the keyboard, from the network.
So you need to handle all of these at the same time.
Then you can also have multiple,
you can have parallel programs in order to better you to use the resources
of a single machine,
many processors now have multiple course.
You can have a parallel program which runs different.
You choose this,
which has multiple threads,
which is thread can run on its own core.
And then this communicated each other of, obviously, one of the menu.
This is the user to have a computer which is responsive to the user actions.
One of the other things is very important.
We have multiple threads is to increase the efficiency
of the increasing utilization by
hiding the latency of the io operations,
where there is network and risk.
We'll do that will show you up in a bit.
Now there are two things you need to differentiate.
The is that the concurrency and parallelism.
So the thread that you need of concurrency, right?
What is concurrency means is that when you have different things which are running,
not necessarily at the same time,
but which access the same resource,
right?
To have a concurrent access to the same resources.
So then it's a problem you need to solve,
because you don't run different.
So to speak entities,
which have asked the same resource where entity here is a thread,
a step on each other, those.
And the concurrency and the parallel is they are related also is multi process,
the concept of multiprocessing.
And multi programming.
Right?
Let's see.
What is the difference between that?
By multiprocessing,
we mean that we have things running at the same time,
right?
On the harder.
And one example,
like I mentioned earlier,
you can have multiple as you can have multiple cores.
And on each core,
you are going to run a different,
a different application.
Multiprogramming is related,
but it's different from the user perspective.
They are similar multiprogramming and multiprocessing.
Because at the same time,
you are going to see visually.
It can be similar, because at the same time,
you can see is the illusion is that application can run at the same time.
You can see here in this example for multi programming,
that now you have one core,
so you cannot fundamentally run all applications at the same time.
But you are going to divide this core,
the time in time slices.
And you are going to alternate between the,
in this case, between this thread abc that is going to happen fast enough.
So the illusion you provide the user is that everything happens
at the same time.
All the processes of all the threats,
abc run at the same time.
So from that perspective,
and from the user perspective,
multiprocessing and multiprogramming can be indistinguishable.
Now,
the more multi programming.
It's a more general notion, though,
even from the user perspective,
because also includes a case in which you have applications running one
at a time,
and you still have multiple applications and running on the same computer,
but they are not running at the same time.
One application starts only after the previous one finishes.
This is shown by the first example in the multi programming example,
where a goes to go,
runs a you run a up to its end,
add up, and it finishes,
then you run b and up to when it finishes and run c right?
That ldr here for a multi programming,
think about you have multiple activities,
multiple threads,
which shares the same course.
So you cannot fundamentally around physically around each thread.
Multiple threads at the same time.
While multiprocessing,
you think about,
you have multiple cores,
you can run multiple threads at the same time.
Physical.
So the concurrency is about hardening multiple things at the same time.
And parallelism is about doing multiple things simultaneous.
This is what it is.
The concurrency you have.
In the case,
going back here,
the concurrency is more associated.
It's associated.
You can have concurrency both in the case of multiprogramming and
also in the case of multiprocessing while multi processing while parallel
is imply multi processing ok so to stretch on a
single core execute concurrently,
right?
Because you still need to protect,
they can still share the same resources.
When each of them runs.
We need to be careful there,
but they are not running in parallel.
Another way to think about each thread handles or manages
as separate things or tasks.
But those tasks are not necessarily executing simultaneously on the hard.
Although, again, from the user perspective,
because they can switch so fast on.
And this is what happens today.
They can switch so fast.
The cpu can switch,
the kennel can switch from between them so fast.
Then the illusion from the user is that really,
they are also running at the same time.
So to drive home,
as an example here is one a simple example.
It's about threats.
So imagine the following program.
You have a compute pie and you write the value of pie and pie dot text.
Then you want to do bring class list.
What is the behavior here?
You shouldn't look at the slides.
So why don't you tell me?
And why do you think of the behavior here?
Yes.
Simon,
you are correct.
You'll never get to print the class list.
Why is that?
Because compute pi will take forever and it will take forever,
because it has an infinite number of decimals.
Right?
Great answer.
So now,
how you can solve this problem,
you can solve it by we thread.
Now we have two activities compute by and print class list.
They are going to happen.
So to speak at the same time,
even if you're going to have a core,
you are going the kernel switch between them,
largely between them,
and each of them will make progress.
Right?
That's what it is.
So from the user perspective,
this is behaved like two things running at the same time.
Each of these things like compute pie and print plus list,
like having its own.
Let me chase some announcements.
And you should be starting working on homework zero already is because
it's due tomorrow.
And I hope that everything you have yet have account,
everything is taken care of.
You are already familiar with the cs on seafood tools,
like submit out a greater we are given and see like that.
If not,
you please do that as soon as possible.
Also, it should be working on project zero already,
because it's going is due next saturday.
And this is the first project,
which this is the only project you need to do on your own.
It's like a homework.
All the other projects are going to be done in a timor for sleep days.
So we have,
you have plenty of sleep days.
So I think it's like we have seven sleep days for homeworks.
Seven sleep day spot project.
Seal is still try to manage them.
I wouldn't spend them at the beginning,
actually facing towards the end of the class.
Things are going to get harder because you have projects not only for this class,
but also project you for other classes.
Try to manage them.
You are going to not get no credit when late after your line of sleep base.
One thing to keep in mind about the projects the days.
They don't apply to design reviews and to project zero, the first one.
And finally,
please remember that friday is a drop early drop day.
Please, if you are not serious about making the class drop it,
so then other people can get into the class from the waiting list.
And the group creation forum is due sunday,
this sunday.
So let's go back to threats.
One of the use cases of threads is to mask the aisle agency.
So what does it mean?
So it is something very simple, right?
We also need,
now we are introducing the state just that can be.
So a threat can be running,
can be ready to run or blocked.
As you can imagine, in general,
you have a list of thread.
You while you are running a thread,
you have a list of other thread charity to run,
then you may have a list of study chart blocks.
When you switch to another thread,
you always speak a thread which is ready to run.
So the point is that if you have a thread,
you wait for an input output operation to finish,
that thread is going to be blocked,
because it's waiting for that operation to finish.
And that operation may be executed by the operating system.
So the thread, right,
has nothing to do.
What is an example?
The thread is going to wait,
for instance,
for an even from the keyboard,
a thread is going to wait to receive some data from the network.
What I said will wait for some or some, for instance,
to open a file or to write some data to the disk.
The.and once is of these events happen,
the far the data has been written to the disk.
You got a network event,
you some network data on the network.
You get a keyboard event if you're waiting for it.
Now the thread becomes ready.
Right now.
If you don't have any ioe events,
you have something like that like we discussed, right?
Your ultimate between both as in this case,
boss saying you have two threads.
Each of them has its own virtual superiors,
and both of them are always ready.
Like, and then you execute,
you alternate between them.
Right?
Now,
let's see what will happen if you have an eye operation.
If you have an eye operation,
say the thread one corresponding to vcp one has an eye operation.
Say, right to the disk,
and tell to the operating system,
write these data to the disk.
And then it waits until the data is written to the disk.
They're doing during this time.
The operator, the thread one is going to be blocked,
right?
When he's blocked, it has no reason to hold the cpu right?
It's ineligible to run and the operating system.
While the thread one waits for the opio operation to complete it can run.
I do when the operation of the first,
if you order of the first step ends,
then you are going to the thread one becomes eligible,
and the operating system is going to schedule it to that.
Right?
Let's go example again to the previous example when you have two threads.
Now, for our example,
to write pie and sorry, in this example,
and it is similar with what we have,
but it's more realistic.
At the second thread,
it's in the first.
So here we have two threads.
The first one is reading a large file,
and the second one is waiting, is rendering.
They use the interface, right?
It's going to say to show you what happens and on the screen,
okay?
To your actions.
Right?
And this is happens all over all in many cases.
Then you say you have a background,
you have a task which is doing something expensive.
Like in this case again,
reading from a large file.
And obviously, during this time,
you do not want your computer to be a responsive,
right?
You want your computer to still respond to the user,
you to the user input.
This is how this is,
where threads are going to help you.
Right?
Okay?
Because in this particular case,
when an event occurs right on the keyboard mouse and things like that,
then grander user interface thread will be scheduled,
then is going to handle your input.
And therefore,
from your users perspective,
is going in the computer is going to be responsive despite the fact
that in the background is processing this large file.
So when you compile ac program,
you run the executable.
A process is created.
And each process has at least one thread.
But this is not visible to you.
You wrote probably many c programs.
You never said,
have an api who say,
to manage the threats.
But this is the particular case.
In general, you can have, in the same process, multiple threads,
but you have multiple thread, you have to manage them,
and to manage them,
you need to have an api and we are going to learn a little bit
about that api right?
What that api has to do,
it is to allow you to create threats.
It's a system call,
the system call is to the operating system.
Remember that we discuss about how the operating system exposes a function
into the application.
One of the function it is to create and manage this thread.
Here is a soft stack,
and all the system call interface is between the operating system and the libraries.
Right?
Because and the libraries are the portable operating system libraries.
These are the libraries that when you include different libraries in
your c program,
the system libraries,
they are giving you access to the function of the operating system
and these libraries.
At the lower level,
there is a system called interface to call in the operating system.
So far,
we used so left the top left picture to show you multiple processes running
on the operating system.
On the right hand side, is that a little bit more accurate description?
And in this description,
you are going to see that actually,
these processes use the functionally provided the operating system
through these os libraries.
And for instance,
lipsea ok so what are the ipi what are the ap is of this libraries?
In this case, you for be thread,
you have a library for be thread.
This library for ap thread offers you this kind of functions.
One is to create a function.
This is to create a function.
You give what is important here.
You start routine.
This is a function.
You want the federal execute.
This is the last argument.
Is this call is the argument of the function.
The attributes typically is now.
But one example to attribute,
you can set up the stack size and peace thread is the returning parameter.
Here.
You are going to get so to speak the identifier to the thread.
And you use this identifier to the thread to call other functions on this thread.
What are the other functions?
One other function is exit.
Right?
When the thread finishes,
you are going to exit from the thread and join.
Right?
This piece that exit you are going to call from the current thread.
Piece that join is called from another thread.
Therefore,
you can need to pass the threat you are referring was piece that joins.
It's waiting for the thread.
Past here is the first argument to finish.
Right?
Nbp thread is not the pp thread join is not the best name,
may be p thread to wait or have been a better name.
But this is what happens.
Let's look.
And we will have more examples.
Then hopefully this will be more clear and clear over the next 5 minutes.
But this is what happens under the hood and help be threat is implemented,
be threat, create.
It do some work to get the argument process, the argument.
Then it's running, it's calling the operating system,
how it's calling the operating system using the cisco.
Okay?
How you do it?
You put in a sum is eixebx is a registers.
These are registers for intel processor.
You put the cisco code,
which is create thread,
which is one code, which is known by the library.
And it's by the operating system.
You put in this register,
and then you put the arguments to all the arguments of the p thread call
in other registers.
And then you a special graph function,
which go and gives control to the operating system.
The or the kernel,
the kernel, when you get this graph function,
what is going to do is going to read the argument from ex the from argument
from ex is basically telling it what cisco is called.
It's going to invoke the handler for that cisco,
and that handler is going,
which is dispatched the system function.
And that hander is going to read the arguments of the cisco from the other registers,
ebx and so forth.
You return the value also in the x and then you passed the control
now to the user code,
which executes this piece that create the line in the library.
And this,
you use that code,
but it is a return of value from the x is doing some kind
of more bookkeeping and then return the value to the problem.
Right?
It's again here with blue.
There are things it executed in the user mode.
By the piece read library, we said,
are the instruction executed by the kernel?
I'm going to ask to answer all the questions after we are done.
Stay for a few more minutes to answer these questions.
Now,
fork and joint pattern,
this is a fork and joint pattern.
The fork is like create basically,
the red here is the main thread of the process.
And then you can create a bunch of threads,
and then typically,
thread is going to exit.
When it's done, you say, exit.
And then the main thread is going to join to.
This thread is going to wait for all threads to finish.
After itself finishes.
This is a very simple example.
Here, you have,
what do we have here?
So we have here this thread functions at the top,
which is basically takes a thread identifier and write something about the thread,
about the stack.
And also it's increment in a common variable.
It's a common, it's a global variable, which is implemented.
Right?
Remember that all the threads in the same process have access
to all the data of that process.
All of the threads are going to have access to the common variable.
In the main,
you are going to create a bunch of threads here.
And then you are going to join to the threats you are going to create,
let the idea left,
let the join the separate execute,
and then wait for them to finish.
Okay?
How many threads you create?
The number of threads here is, by default, two.
And you create two threads.
And then,
but if you passed the argument,
then you can create a different number of sets.
This I did.
And by the way, notice a straight function.
It's end with peace, thread,
exit.
So how many threads are?
I'm going?
We are going to talk more about this next lecture.
But how many threads are here in this program?
Obviously, is a number of threads.
It's an thread there.
And and does the main thread join with a thread in the same order that they
are created?
Right?
They are created in the same the same order.
And do the thread exit is the same order they were created?
Probably now,
because they can take different amounts of time.
If we run the program again,
there is a change is a very important question,
and we are not going to get out to it.
But it's, again, like,
let's again,
summarize what happens in this code.
Here where the thread is created.
You allocate a space for all the threads.
And here are you create the threads?
Right?
You create any threads,
right?
And then once the thread is created,
you start executing the thread.
When the thread finishes,
you call pizza bed exit.
And this is what you are going to get.
Okay?
What you see here, I call it be thread with argument four,
so there will be four threads.
It's and then different threads.
And they finish a different time.
So there is not that time and not in the order they were created.
Thread zero finishes last,
although skated first.
And then, as you can see, also,
is thread is basically increment in the common value.
And therefore, this common value,
it changes.
You see that the order in which is as increment,
it is the same as the order in which these threads were created.
Right?
The last the thread we just created first said zero is going
to increment come on.
That is going to be the second thread,
not the first thread to increment karma.
Okay?
This gives you a sense about this kind of concurrency.
And this are going to talk a lot about it as we go on,
because the thread introduced non determinism.
And this will be a challenge we will need to address.
I'm going to stop here.
And instead,
i'm going to spend few more minutes to answer all the questions.
So people who are interested to hear the answer to the question can stick
around for a few minutes.
And then we'll conclude the lecture.
So,
so the question this library is,
does os typically only provide c libraries for unix is written in
c or lenos.
Actually, these libraries tend to be written in c so the answer here,
typically, the operating system you are working with,
also including marcos,
provide the system libraries are written in c and provide ac interface,
although you can easily write a schiller on top of that to provide
other interfaces for the sea libraries.
Like, and you do it,
you every language is actually providing its own libraries,
which are on top of the sea library.
System.
Library is provided by operating system.
Like, for instance, if you do python,
you can still write data from the input.
Under the hood.
This is going to call a system call.
And that probably is going to happen from one of the sea library.
So these libraries are very specific.
They are always specific.
How does the sequel talk to the registers?
The sea code.
How does it talk to the registers?
Actually, you can inline assembly language in the sea code.
That's why the signal is so powerful.
So you are going to have,
you can accommodate special instructions in which you can operate on the registers.
What is the trap instruction?
The trap instruction here,
it's voluntarily assist aaa user,
a process,
relinquishing the control to the operating system, basically, say,
trap now is an operating system.
The operating system should run and to to execute the system.
Call, right?
It's again, I want to call that let me take a step back.
The goal here is that I want to call a system call,
like to execute a system call.
I'm going to put the album,
the identifier of system call in one register,
and I'm going to use other registers to put the argument of the system.
Now I want the operating system,
execute the system call.
How do I do that?
I do that,
invoking this strap instruction and the strap special instruction,
now is giving the control to the kernel,
which is and look at these registers and execute corresponding system call.
Could you go over again why we passed thread fund into the pastry create?
Well,
it's, again, like the threads are about executing,
executing some piece of code.
You need to specify to the thread,
what piece of code to execute.
The way you do that is by defining the function with the thread you
want to execute.
Okay?
That's basically the answer.
So you need,
that's how you call a thread,
your call you you create a thread.
Sorry, that's where you create a thread, you create a thread,
bring the crystal code,
how you are going to save our code.
It is.
When we very easy to do a natural way to do it, it's like a function,
right?
To put that out in the function,
then you are going to pass the pointer of that function to the thread.
The thread can create when you create the thread.
The thread is going to create to run that function.
Are we supposed to freeze this restructure?
So let's see if you are talking about these peace threats,
such as if you are going to.
Yeah, you are locating the program,
you can be allocate, sorry.
In this particular case,
we don't read because the entire program ends.
And when the program ends, the process ends,
the operating system is going to de allocate all of the resources,
including the memory allocated to the process.
So there is no need to Free.
But in general,
if you want to say the pattern is to allocate to start ten threads,
and then I start another thing, independent threads.
You want to Free the once the first and threads are finished,
and because you join on the first and threads, all of them finished,
you may want to Free that thread a data structure.
In general, the answer,
in this particular case,
you don't need to because the problem terminates.
And the operating system is going to clear all the resources allocated
to the operating system,
including the memory.
This is the piece thread struct you allocate is not freed
by the peaceful exit necessary.
So there is some point chat.
Okay.
Thank you, everyone.
And i'll see you next Tuesday until then have a great Labor Day weekend.
Bye, everyone.