Hello,
hope everyone had a great, long weekend.
We'll start today is the first lecture of the glass.
During this lecture,
we are going to finish our discussion on threads and processes from last time.
And then we are going to start the discussion on file systems.
In particular, we are going to go over a high level file,
io and streams.
As always, please.
If you have questions asking the q and a I will stop
periodically during the lecture to answer these questions.
So is that being said, let's start.
So we discussed quite a bit of about threads.
And by now,
the threads are the execution entity which run
some code within an address context and or
within a process.
So this threads in the same address space in the same process,
share the content of the memory.
This means global variables, heap,
as well as other resources, like file,
descriptors and other connections.
And their state are the same time.
A thread has each thread has private state,
and that state capture the execution of a particular and this
information is stored in what they called thread control block.
Like we discussed in the past,
it contains the cpu registers,
including the program counters and the execution stack.
Now next, we are going to talk a little bit more about the execution stack.
What does it contain?
Why is it part of the thread privacy?
At the high level, the execution stack stores?
The parameters arguments passed only call a function and the return address
from that function.
Here is a very simple example.
On the left hand side,
you have three functions,
ab and c and on the left,
we have some labels.
And they think about this label like addresses for the particular line
in the code.
And the red rectangle illustrates the code,
the line we are currently executing.
So let's start by invoking function a with argument one.
Now, you see, on the right hand side, you see the stack.
What happens here?
We push the argument of a on the stack, the value.
It's what?
One.
And then we also pushed the return address after a it's executed.
The return address here is exit and you can see the exit.
It's the address in memory right after a one is okay,
because stamp is one on execute a then we take this branch and execute b
when he called b now there is no argument passed to be.
So on the start, we are only going to push the address.
We need to go back after executing b this is a plus two,
b call c again,
no argument is passed here to see.
We just wish the return are the return address after the executive.
See.
See, it's calling a again with argument two.
Now we put the argument on the stack,
and the return others is you+1 after a of two executed.
And now an aids executive stamp with the argument of two,
we are going to run the final,
the others.
We are going to run print f we are going to skip calling b
the output right now,
because stamp is through the printer.
Here, you also can see on the bottom,
right out,
the outputs being printed.
We are going to bring to.
Now a finishes be a finish is being executed.
Now, we look at that stack where you need to return.
So we need to return to c poisson,
because that was then the next thing,
the next line after a two was invoked.
Okay?
Now see it terminates.
So again, we look at the stack where we need to go.
So we need to go to be+1.
And now we terminate b so we need to go back to the instruction of right
after bill was invoked.
And now this is sprint f but now the tempest one,
because this is from the first invocation of a you can look also this
at this on the stack.
Now we are done.
The output is going to be two and one.
Okay?
The stack is extremely important.
It holds not only variables,
and the arguments are returned.
The return address after we exit the function.
But in this way,
it also allows for recursive writing your recursive programs.
Really, this is the key of all modern languages.
One thing to note, though,
is that the stack grows down.
You start from means you start from high addresses.
Then as we push on the stack,
the address is going to go down will decrease.
Okay?
If we look here as a memory layout for to spread which running
the same processes in the same process,
you see that, again,
here, the two threads,
they share the code,
the global data, the heap,
but they don't stare the stack,
because the stack contains the execution state of that thread.
We have to set off stacks.
But now obviously, one question is that when you start these stacks,
where do you put that?
Right?
Because you need to put them such a way that has enough room to grow.
Okay?
So you need to make sure that you need to live in a room to grow.
Also,
you need to make sure that one stack will not right over another stack so far.
In this case, you should make sure the stack one,
as it grows,
is not going to go and overwrite stack, too.
So how may two questions here?
What happens if the threads violates this?
You can answer that on the question and answers thread.
No answer.
So what happened?
That corruption, second fault.
Right?
Why?
Because if you override a on the start, what happens?
Right?
If you override,
you can override the return address of a function involved by a particular thread.
Now you are going to have garbage there,
and then you are going to go back.
You are going to execute some random code.
We can even try to executing the round of the code
of a different process or operating system.
And in case in which are going to get segmentation for,
how might you catch
violations?
Got pages that's quite sophisticated stack canary.
So you need, if you can.
Yeah, user is very good.
We can use if there are different mechanics.
But fundamentally, you want to make sure that we can use bounds,
like we discussed in the past,
each stack is confined to a particular region of memory,
so that you make sure that and you make sure that region,
its own only by one thread by that particular stack.
Right?
Then you cannot go out,
therefore, you cannot step over as a stock
that will add overhead,
because now you need to check.
It also had some memory protection for the stack.
We are going to talk more about that,
and there is a trade off there,
but most your questions,
your answer to start out of the other corner.
So now,
we are going to touch on a very important aspect,
and we are going to talk about this a lot of times.
And it's not only important.
It's also painful.
And this is it happens because
we want to provide this kind of great abstractions to the programmer
in which each thread,
its own cpu and you want to provide, on one hand,
this obstruction like act like illusionist.
And on the other hand,
in reality,
you don't have as many core as a threat you have in order to provide that obstruction,
the way you do it,
like we discuss in the past,
is to interleave the threads on a limited number.
Okay?
Now the problem, what is the problem?
The problem is that if you are interleave the threads,
this means that you need to stop to suspend a thread to run another thread.
And seeing the tooth in the threads you are running can share
the same address space.
Then they can modify the same location in the memory.
As a result, they can step on each other toes.
And because you don't know exactly when the threats
are going to be interrupted at what instructions to be suspended,
this kind of interaction is also unpredictable,
non deterministic.
So that's the idea.
For instance, this is a piece with us.
You have three instructions here.
Now, this is in a thread which at some point will be suspended.
One possible execution is to go through the completion and all these instructions.
But another possible execution is after execute the first instruction,
which is x equals x plus one.
The study suspending and as a strategy to run instead,
or this thread can be suspended after the first instruction
are going to be executed.
You can have a myriad of way in the stress italy,
right?
Like you see here, see,
you can also, in some cases,
the stress can each of them go through completion,
because they are very short.
Or if you have enough course,
then they are not interleaving,
because israel is going to run on score.
Right?
But the interesting part is see when they are going to italy.
And again,
the point here is that as a programmer,
you do not know when the study suspended,
because operating system, in particular,
the scheduler has no idea about the semantics of your program,
so you cannot do anything.
So from operating system,
point of view is a bunch of instructions.
And at any given time,
it can,
in theory, it can interrupt you.
It can suspend your thread and run another thread instead on the same core.
Okay?
So now,
there are 2 kinds of threats you can think in this world.
There are threads which modifies different variables so that the variables
they modify,
they are to be joined that independence.
And they are going to provide determine these things us,
because it doesn't matter when they are suspended.
They are not going to use the same variables.
So they are not going to interfere with each other.
And then there are cooperating threats.
And these are the interesting ones and the difficult ones.
We share state.
We share the state.
Now, the goal is how to design a program,
which is correct.
No matter when a cooperating threads are suspended,
you are going to get a predictable,
a correct result.
Let's let's take a aaa few simple examples to illustrate the point.
And by the way,
when two threads,
interleave and modify the same variables.
Many times we refer to that as race condition,
because one thread races against the other thread.
Now, in this first example,
is to have two threads,
a and b and these threads modify a different variable,
study modify x that be y this is an example of independent threads here,
because again, they write,
they modify and they read different variables.
For instance,
no matter how the scheduler interleaved these threads,
the output for thread a will be always fun.
But now let me ask you,
in this example, what is the output?
So you have again to threads.
But now they share one variable,
which is why.
Okay?
Both of them read and more,
but thread b reads and modify y and a reads.
Why?
Let's assume initially that x is zero and y zero.
The question, in this case,
for these cooperative threads,
what are the possible values of x why don't you take of
23 minutes and think and please write down the
values?
You believe x can get?
Yes, that's correct.
135.
That's perfect.
Thank you, right?
So because if the first,
if thread a executes first and the first instruction is executed to completion,
then y was zero,
x would be up.
But there are other possible executions.
For instance, the first instruction of strategy can execute.
Y is equal to.
And then the instruction of a can execute.
Now, x is y which are set by thread b to choose x will be three.
Or thread b can execute all boston instruction first,
and then thread a and if thread big one or execute all instruction first,
then y will be four.
So x instead a that is y value of 4 plus 1 is 5,
x is five.
Now, you can see that even in this simple example,
means you are going,
things are getting complicated when they said share the same value.
Now you can imagine that for a more realistic program,
this is even much more complex.
If there is a question here,
how do threads share a variable?
If a thread is the unit of execution?
Wouldn't local variable be local to be thread?
This is a good question,
but i'm going to go back here To answer this question.
The answer is here.
As you can see, it's, again,
all threading the same process,
share the code the data,
go on the file descriptors.
Why they don't share are the registers.
They don't share the stack,
but the stack only contains the temporary variables,
the argument which are passed to the functions and the return parameters.
It does.
A stack does not contain.
The global variables are in the data segment here.
In this example,
I just gave one.
This we are talking about x and y are global variables.
All the global variables are shared by all the thread in the process.
Going farther.
Let me just go in.
There is another question.
Let me take this as a do thread share the skip as well,
the thread share the heap as well.
So if one thread allocate something on the heap,
it can give the pointer to another thread which can read the data,
allocated from the heap,
from the day of agree the data allocated by the first threat.
How do different processes communicate?
We are going to learn about that.
They can communicate by reading and writing on the file system.
They can communicate with sockets, pipes.
There are many ways they can communicate,
and there is actually also mechanics to provide shared memory between processes.
We'll talk more about that.
Thanks for your questions.
Now, if you write a program which you have multiple threads,
we share the same the same data,
then you need somehow to coordinate among them to make sure that you get
the same results,
no matter how the threats are intermittent.
Right?
So what means you need to synchronize?
One to a woman,
a threat should access what?
Right?
And aa particular way to think to synchronize that is
that to make sure that only
one thread is doing one thing at a time.
This is mutual exclusion,
will have examples.
Another important concept is critical section.
You can define a section in the code,
which it's a critical section,
which this means that section can be only executed by one thread at a time.
You cannot have the two threads executing instruction
from the critical section at a different time at the same time.
Another way to think about is that from the programmer.of view,
all the instruction is the critical section.
They are executed sequentially.
Okay?
No one else will modify the variables of which are in the critical section
from the stripe executing it.
And then how do you in for these critical sections?
And again,
critical section and mutual exclusion out of the two sides of the same coin,
you in order to have a critical section,
need to implement a critical section,
you need to have mutual exclusion beginnings that whilst thread execute
the critical section,
another thread cannot execute the instruction that could become a section.
And then how at the lower level,
how you implement a mutual exclusion.
And therefore, because section is choosing blocks.
Basically,
the concept is that when you are going to enter a critical section,
you are going to acquire a lock.
Now,
and everyone who has to enter the critical session has to acquire the law
before entering it.
If you have the lock,
no one else can under.
When you x is a critical section, you release a lock.
Okay?
This locks,
operation, like typically,
it's not acquire and released,
are atomic,
but meaning that something is atomic is that you cannot,
you cannot be the sad with executing blocker.
Choir cannot be suspended in the middle of executing clock,
acquire the same about local release.
And we are going to learn how we are going to implement these logs later.
For the p threads, libraries,
you do have the lock primitive.
You have a piece of mutex in when you are going to create a me lock,
and then you can acquire the lock.
And by piece thread, mutex lock,
and piece thread mutex unlock,
you release a lock.
Okay?
You are going to do this in homework on here.
It's a simple example.
This is a piece of code from the code I shown last time,
in which we apply that we have the critical section here.
For my common is common plus,
common plus, common.
Sorry, it's a global variable, if you remember.
So now you may ask yourself,
why do we have?
It's in that?
It's just a single line.
Why do you need to protect by locks as these are single line of code?
The reason,
again, we are going to discuss more about this in the future.
This is just a preview.
Is that this line,
my common is equal,
my is common plus,
is basically composed by multiple instructions.
Processor instructions.
Therefore,
you can be interrupted in the middle of executing this instruction,
is this line of code.
And that can lead to inaccurate results.
Like, for instance, this line,
what may do is going to access common from the main memory,
bring it in a register.
I'd want to that value,
and then store the value back in the memory.
If you are interrupted,
after you brought the value in of the memory of the common in register,
right?
And someone else read and write it.
When you are going to be resume execution,
you are going to execute the old value,
which is the registers.
And then write it back.
You can override the value of a different thread.
Another way to another primitive besides lock.
And again, don't tell you are going to talk more about.
This is just to give you a sense.
And also because you are going to use in you have to deal with this
in homework one.
Another way to implement locks is similar force.
Think about the generalized locks.
This was defined by diaspora.
One of the parents of computer science,
all the way in 60s, yours.
This is also amazing organization primitive using original unix and windows.
Okay?
The way to think about this,
you have these two primitives,
b and b they be comes from program to test,
and we were hogan to increment from dutch dash that I was a dutch,
was dutch.
Basically, the way they are working is that p thought
tries to decrement.
And if the value of the semaphore is zero, then it blocks.
It's waiting for that value for the center,
for to be increment.
And if one is increment,
it's unlocked.
And is the great and the value is determined.
And we it's increment is the value of the semaphore.
And if there is any p waiting b is going to signal to it,
so it can decrement and continue.
Here is a piece of code which shows you how thread join is implemented.
You remember,
for the third join means that I am waiting for a thread to finish.
In this case,
basically, the thread join is implementing are doing some of four down.
The similar for it seem it's set one.
And this is the critical circle section, right?
Is like in something like your summer fall down.
What does that mean here?
Some are for down.
Here is going to decline the summer for one.
From 1 to 0, you are going to have zero.
You are going to enter the critical section.
Notice that, again, this part,
the mutual exclusion part is implemented by all the threats,
right?
And only one thread can enter the critical section.
Right?
Because one, it wants one system once thread entered this critical section.
Everyone?
Sorry about that.
I got disconnected.
Please add the questions,
and let me try to answer the questions.
Again, sorry about that them up.
Okay.
So please,
I there are a few questions I haven't answered and I no longer see
them after reconnecting.
So please ask them again.
So let's move on.
Okay?
Basically, here,
if we want to implement the signaling for the strategy join,
like I mentioned earlier,
you can use a semi force.
When a straight finishes,
he just bring the summer for up.
Therefore,
okay, so sorry, thank you taking your step back.
In this particular.
So initially,
what we saw is a previous example.
I don't know how much you lost from what I said.
We are implementing a critical section.
This is the first example about using similar force to implement
the critical section where only once thread at a time can execute
in the critical section.
The second example is implement on the thread join,
and with the thread join,
the way we implemented it is like, first of all,
the semaphore now it's initialize to zero, not one.
And when a threat finish,
it is is going to increment the semaphore right?
The main thread which created the other threads and ways for the stress to finish,
is going only to call some up or down.
And initially,
if the threat no threat has finished,
the sum of four is zero and remains zero,
the same the main thread calling thread join is blocked.
When I started finishes,
then this is decrement it,
which is exactly the behavior you want.
So there is one connection,
one question.
Some of us don't have an owner like locks,
do I this is depends on the implementation,
is nothing fundamental about blocks,
also enough for us to have an owner.
The one,
the only important things,
even for locks,
is to make sure that only one thread can get a lock at a given time.
In our context, the next question, in our context,
you can potentially have infinitely many threads, right?
Then was the difference between our concept of threat
and the limited harder threats.
Like acpu has 12 courts or 24 threats.
It's, again, the thread is the programming construct,
right?
And you can have infinitely an infinite number,
not an infinite,
nothing can be infinite here.
But you can have a very large number of threats, let's say, 1,000.
But at the same time, you have four cores and four and one core,
say it can execute only one side at a time.
Right?
So basically,
the difference here is that, again,
the thread is a programming construct,
is what you create in a program.
And a core.
It's what you have physically, right?
And you need to deal with our constraints.
You can run at a given time, for example, only for a stretch.
That's how you need to design their living to map all these 1,000 threads.
You have at the application level as a programmer level to this four course.
And the way to do it, like I mentioned many times by interleaving,
by running a thread for a little bit and running another thread and so forth.
Maybe there's a question here.
It's also related with what the concept of hypothetic.
Okay?
Now hyper threading we haven't talked,
and we are not going to talk during the class by hyper threading.
It is a harder concept.
And this allows accord to execute a certain time,
but it doesn't modify the fact that the number of threads that the harbor
can run
at a given time is limited.
It will only say that instead of running,
I I have four cores instead of running 4/3 of the time.
Now I can run 1/3 of the time.
So there is no fundamental difference.
Let's move on.
We are the so now we talk about threads.
Now let's look a little bit step back and talk more about our processes.
The process is an environment in which you execute your code and have
the restricted rights.
So process, remember,
contains one or more threads,
because a stress as a unit of execution and a single other space,
the other space is protected from other spaces,
owned by other processes.
It also owns a file process,
also own the resources like file descriptors,
network connection.
Okay?
When you run a program,
the program execute within a process.
And an application like we're discussing the past,
can iran on more than one processes can have more than on processes?
Right?
Remember, is an example about trivial example is facebook.
It's one application,
but there are many processes that are not even running
onto the same machine that running on different measures.
Right?
In all of them and in operating systems,
today's operating systems,
everything which turns out outside the kernel,
it's a process.
The kernel, if you remember, is a part of the operating system,
which is based always a resident in the memory.
Now,
the processes have a similar mechanism to create other processes.
You also have for processes,
fork in command to create another process.
But what is the fundamental difference between forking a process
or forking or creating a new threat?
The fundamental difference is that when you create a new thread that thread,
like we just discussed,
share the code and the global variables and other resources
with the other thread in the same process,
the thread which created it.
But in the case of a process,
if a process creates another process,
the new processes and new address that are
different other space and share nothing with the process which created it
in order to go around this limitation,
while the fork is doing it,
copies the everything the current process of the parent process had
to the child process.
It copies a crowd,
it copies the resources with the process who created another process is
a new process.
Okay?
If a process one,
crisis process two,
using fork,
the for corporation will copy the code and the access to the resources
that process one has to process two.
Therefore, the process to execute the same code.
And now, when you call fork,
it returns immediately.
And it's,
depending the value it returns,
depends on whether the fork it's in the child process or is a parent process.
If it's a parent processor for returns the process identifier of the child.
If it's in the child process,
it returns zero.
If it's a rise and zero,
then it's an error.
Now, let's look at this simple example.
So you basically called fork here,
and it returns cpid and if cpid is zero,
you do something and bbc cpid equals zero,
you do something else again when you call fork.
And you in this process,
this runs into a process.
A new process is created,
and that new process is going to run the same code,
because the code will be copied in the new process.
Is the first process,
which is apparent process.
The cpid will be the identifier of a child process.
It'll be greater than zero.
This is what you are going to be to happen in the parent process.
The alice branch,
the cpid zero happen and will be run.
This instruction will be run in the child process.
What you are going to get here,
right?
What is the output you are going to see?
You are going to get from this card I
need,
but you should try it.
So very likely,
what will happen here?
You are going to see the first process of parents say you can see the
parent will see parent 1234,
top to ten.
And then from,
ii see that there are some answers better and 10 times.
And not the.
Now the parent will do it 10 times,
and the child will do 10 times.
And this is what you are going to get.
The parent to do then and then tell trans something like.
And however,
if you are asleep will something
change.
That's a great question.
So it was a question.
When is a child code executive?
When is the child called executive?
The child is a different process with the difference which is on stress.
That's a good question.
The answer is on the operating system is titled execute.
The side of the other process is a schedule of deciding it.
That's exactly what the question tries to say.
But try to illustrate.
If you just print one after another,
then the code is green code.
Can run fast enough.
So it's not the process is not suspended.
That's I likely what you are going to see,
you are going to see the parent consecutively printing from 1 to 10
and then the child from 1 to 10
or the other around.
However, if you could sleep,
then that's enough time for the parent to be suspended as a child running
and the other way around.
So we are going to see an interleave interleaving,
the printer from the parent and the child.
We are going to see them into living.
It's another view.
This is a view.
It's executing as an exact will talk a little bit about the exact.
But for this purpose,
it's again, you say, see, here is a parent execute.
Now, look at the if function is reversed,
if checks first,
whether the pid return from there is the return from the fork is zero.
We know if the return is zero,
the code is executed by the child.
This is exact.
Lcpid different than zero,
hopefully is greater than zero than you, the parent.
It's a like, you think, white in this case.
And we are going to what exact is doing.
And we'll learn we'll talk more about it briefly.
Exact.
It's running a program that program will replace the code of the child
with the program itself.
Think about right now,
the fork replicated,
duplicated the code of the parent to the child now is the exact we are
just some sense of conceptually
we override the child code with a code of the program we want to execute.
And this is what happens when you implement the shell.
And you are going to do you do that in your homework?
Right?
What happened is a shell is a path, the shell,
or you type in the comments.
And you type your comment.
Right?
What happens?
The shell process,
forks, another process,
and the 4th process is going to use exact to run the program you want to run.
Okay?
This weight is similar with a join that join like its way it's waiting
for the child to finish.
Make sense?
I'll answer the questions immediately.
So where it wait for process to finish,
these are some other ap is exit,
your terminates approach,
the process you have also exit for these threads.
Then you have this command which is killed.
I can kill a particular process.
If I send this kind of signal,
like, for instance, the operating system,
this is how it kills a process.
For one reason or another sends a kill signatory.
And then if you are a process,
you get aa aa signal,
then you can actually sometimes can do something about the signal.
We'll talk more about it.
But this, again,
a simple program in which,
again, for acpid call zero everything within that branch.
It's executed by the child,
so the child executive and gets it by apiid princess pid and then exit
with a42,
which is a a it's a return code.
Whatever you want to pick,
the code executed by the parent.
It's waiting for the child breaks.
This is a wait.
And now, like I mentioned,
when you get an action as aaa signal,
as a process,
you can do something about it.
How you can do about it,
you intercept.
For instance, you get this is a sink interrupt.
You can also send from a user process to another user process that can send
this signal.
And in basically,
you can associate,
you can say that when you get this thing interrupt,
you are going to execute a piece of code.
You write a function which execute this piece of code,
then use a secret action to pass the address of that function,
to be invoked when I seeking it's when you receive using the process
to receive the seeking that.
Okay?
If you don't have registered for a seeking,
this call back to handle it,
the processors die.
Right?
As otherwise,
you may want to keep the process around and do something about it.
There are many signals I told seeking seeking is also,
it's when you do ctrl c when you have a program and runs into controversy
that generate ac int,
the program, if you don't do anything, it will be killed.
But if you do something,
c control c you intercept it.
You doesn't need to kill the process.
Six step,
its control z you stop the process.
When you seek term is when you have a shell command and you want to kill it,
there are secure and six stop to terminate the process.
You cannot cannot intercept the cigar by cigar action.
So this will terminate your process.
These are, in general,
what is used by the operating system to terminate the process a process.
Let me just talk briefly here and see what are the questions.
Rp set, mutex lock,
and the unlocking implement with a semi force is, again,
is dependent on the operating system.
We are going to learn different implementation for lock and unlock.
How do you know the scheduler one switch in the middle of the parents?
For look, you do not know.
And that's exactly the point.
I said what I mentioned in the previous example that if you don't have
the sleep with a high probability,
what you are going to see is that the parent output from the parent,
the follow up, the printing that ten values,
and then from the child.
But there is a very small probability that you can also be interrupted.
During that.
Look,
the point is that you insert the slips,
then now the entire loop will take you 10 seconds.
Therefore,
you are guaranteed to be interrupted by the child, the parent by the child,
and the child by the parent,
the child.
So does the child always has apid zero?
Remember, the child is a process.
The process has appeared as an identifier.
What we have is here, what we are on earth.
See, talking here about the pid is a return of the fork function.
Basically, the return for functions in the child process doesn't return.
The child process.
Id return is zero.
It doesn't mean the process id is zero.
In return, it mean, we are only saying that the fork, let me repeat.
The fork is a child code returns when executed, return is zero.
When executing fork is apparent,
return,
child process identifier.
How does a parent on calling wait?
And now who to wait?
Who to wait for?
Ii believe if I remember correctly,
the you can specify that in white.
We'll see that.
Let me continue a little,
and i'll stop for more questions.
The a shell a it's a job control system that it's what you're getting a terminal.
You have the prompt that the shell from there,
you can execute other programs and or other comments.
You are going to build your own shell in homework, too.
And you are going to use a fork and exec to create new processes to create
programs like we mentioned earlier on,
right?
Your shell will fork a child,
which will use exact to execute the program ok
so this process versus threads.
One question here is why have four can exact system,
colorful processes,
but just a piece thread create function for a thread.
The answer is here, but again, to summarize,
the main reason for that is that with threads,
if one thread create another thread,
the new thread share the circle and share the global variables and the heap,
which with a sandwich created it right?
While in the case,
in the and then also the p thread,
you give the crowd to execute,
right?
You give a new greater thread,
you give the curve,
the function to be executed by the thread.
In the case of fork,
when you create a new process,
because the new there is no sharing between two processes.
They have different other spaces.
You are going to duplicate the code and the resources from the parent
to the child.
But now,
the parent and child execute the same code.
So to execute a different kind of code for a program, you need,
you are going to call exact.
Right?
We speak.
There is no need for such that such thing.
Because first of all,
there is no need for function id because they shared the threads share
the same address space.
And then it's also,
when you create a thread,
you.out to the few give also the address of the function,
the state should execute,
by the way, and as a note, in windows,
instead of what we have create process.
Here is a question for you.
If we have two tasks to run concurrently,
do iran them in separate threads of iranians?
In separate process?
Again, I shouldn't have the head the answer here,
but it depends.
Is how much isolation you want to have.
The threads are lighter weight.
Why is that lighter weight?
Because they don't share all because they don't have a lot of state
associated with them.
So when you switch them,
When the skipper switch from one side to another doesn't need to save
all the context.
Essentially, the process, it's just a teeny bit of context,
especially the thread.
It's much faster.
On the other hand,
the process that is much stronger isolated.
Again, each process lives in its own other space.
Let me just see a few more questions
since let's share other spaces,
but nor stack,
do the stack start a different offset, absolutely.
The stack.
They do that a different processes.
And if you remember from here, right?
From this figure,
something is very slow.
Here you have two stacks,
a the different.
They start a different they have different stack pointers,
start a different addresses.
Okay?
So let me see that I think there are some question about on the chat.
Yes, the new stack frames,
the new stacks out in the same address space,
but start at different points and different addresses.
What happens to the stack when you make a new thread?
When you create a new thread,
you create a new stack for that thread.
We should not interfere with the stack of the current strategy.
I think it's pretty much it if I didn't answer any questions because that
is connect and everything else.
Let me know some announcements.
The project zero is the project zero is due this thursday.
Today from now,
it's again, it needs to be done on your own like homework.
Is the only one you need to do on your own.
All the other projects are group projects.
Group assignments will be released by end of day this wednesday.
A discussion,
a section attendance is mandatory and with cameras on if you are remarked
and start already planning with your group how to best collaborate on the project,
especially if you are remote,
virtual coffee hours with a camera,
regular brainstorm meeting,
and try to meet multiple times a week.
Most of the problems between from our experience with the groups happens
because communication.
It turns out that not everyone in the group is on the same page,
not everyone understood the same thing like what everyone has to do and buy
what and what to do.
So over communicate over community,
there is nothing like too much communication for your group to be successful
for the rest of this lecture,
we are starting to talk about.
We are diving into file systems, file abstraction.
In particular,
we are only going to talk about high level file io and these are streams.
We are going to talk more about files next lecture on saturday.
So now,
basically,
we are a lot of concepts we are going to work on are inherited
from original unix.
And indeed, why not linux is unique?
Like we discussed ios or out mac os it's on top.
It's a unique system of the call and even windows.
It's now more and more similar to you to unix.
Then it was 20 years ago.
The main.about the unix,
and this is brilliant idea at this day,
is to provide as much as possible a homogeneous abstraction across
different io devices.
And that concept is about a five,
which is a stream of bytes.
This is not only the files on your disk,
but also the way you operate.
And the api when you send messages or receive messages,
or you send data up to the send a file to the printer to be printed,
or you get input from the terminal.
All of these,
you interact with all of these different devices in a very similar way.
You can think, again,
at a high level that everything is a file and you interact with them,
the base system calls then are open,
read, write, and close.
It's open, file, clothes, file,
read from file, write a file,
some of the devices, so not have some of these operations.
Like for instance, for a printer,
you have open,
call close and write, not read.
For the input terminal, you have read, but not write.
Okay.
And then you have also this kind of cached all apiiocepl
for to customary configured different devices.
Right?
It's again for people who are interested in a little bit of history.
And actually to get given is very useful given for this class to get
come context about how things evolved and why you can read this unique,
the unix time sharing system,
which is very old book that is almost 50 years,
very old paper.
But it's extremely influential paper.
And it's quite amazing.
It's again, we are still using the same concept,
fundamentally like this paper described,
again, almost 50 years ago.
If you have1 hour,
this is a fantastic paper of it.
You'll hear more about politics.
What is politics is portable operating system?
Interface, excuse me, for unix.
It defines kind of a standard.
It's an effort of standardizing.
It was an effort to standardize different unix flavors.
27 or 25 years ago,
there are a lot of unique flavors,
different companies.
They have their own unique version.
Politics was the effort to standardize a subset of ap is across this.
Unix is okay.
So the file of file system abstraction.
So it's a name collection of data in a file system.
And the posits file data is a sequence of bikes.
Could be text binary.
You can have a serialized objects, almost anything.
In addition to the file data,
you have meta data.
And the meta data associated with a file,
contain things like the size of the file.
When was the last time modified?
Who is our owner?
Security information who has access control and so forth.
The files are stored in folders,
right?
The folder contains farthest and directory.
A director is a special kind of fire,
and the directories are organized in an article fashion,
as you very well know.
Okay.
There are also concepts of links and volumes,
hard links of links.
We are going to learn about those later.
Now,
every process has its own current working directory.
Okay?
When you start aaa program from a current directory,
that typically is a current working directory of that program.
So if you just read and write without providing a path.
Then you read and write on the current director.
Now,
you can also refer like you very well known to a file using the absolute directory.
In that case, the current direct working directory it's ignored.
Again,
the current talking director you can see thinking
about like an environment variable,
right?
Which is set when the program is started.
And you can have relative specify relative paths to the current directory.
But I dot slash means you go one level up
and deal.
That means home directory and so forth.
And the storage,
it's actually a has a pretty complex architecture.
It goes all the way from io drivers,
and this is controlled all these devices.
Then you have the file system which is implemented,
functionally implementing the operating system.
That is called,
this is the interface provided by the operating system through which
the user level programs can invoke
file system operations.
Then you have the low level io and high level io in provide
different levels of abstractions of the file system to the application.
So here we are going to start from a high level io right?
And again,
a stream is a sequence of bytes.
That's it.
Right?
And how you open a file for in the stream format for this a with a stream
api you use f open,
you include sto this represents containers contains the api
the file related file stream file ap is f open,
obviously, is part of sdo dot h and as the of open take,
several arguments,
one is a file name,
right?
Which is the name of the file.
And here you can, especially if you don't specify the pass.
Again, you are referring to a file in the current directory.
If you specify an absolute path,
then is a current directory ignore.
And you have also a mode,
right?
The mode, it tells,
basically,
what is this?
What you can do is this file.
Right?
You can,
what kind of file is this one?
You can have text files or binary files, right?
With the text files,
the code is interpreted as being a character with a binary file is a bike.
Sorry, that it's not interpreter.
It's not interpreted when you print it,
when you try to print it.
In addition from the type of that is of the fibers that is text or binary,
what is the kind of operation which are allowed on the fire?
R is for it,
right?
Is for obviously modifying,
append.
It's for writing only at the end of the file.
Then you can write,
you can also open a file boss for read and write.
You can also take into account what happens if I open a file,
but the file doesn't take this.
You can get an error file not found, or you can.
I have a use another option to say if it file doesn't exist created
and as an amplifier.
Right?
So when you open the file, what you are,
you are going to get a pointer to the file data structure.
Also, you are going to get a pointer, right?
You represent the state of the file.
Open file is represented by the pointer and it to the current byte
in the file that you are going to read or write.
There are also several specialized files,
standard being standard doubt, standard error.
Okay?
Standard beam is,
obviously from input,
from the terminal sound out.
It's also when you write out to the terminal standard error when you write
and is error.
And again,
the important point to now here,
it's again, is treated all this input from your keyboard output,
the terminal.
They are all treated as fires.
And this standard being a standard out enable composition in unix.
Because everything is a file.
Therefore, you can pipe.
You can create a pipeline of commands,
because in general,
each command is going to read from a file and write to a file.
For instance, here you have cat, hello text, grab word.
What does it mean?
Cat, hello text is basically is going to,
if you just execute that is going to write on the terminal the content
of the file,
hello dot x but because determine the content,
what hello the standard out where the file is written,
it's also a file.
You can pipe in the grip world,
which take as the input of a file to look for the occurrences of the world.
Exclamation.,
exclamation mark.
A a little bit more.
The api is a little bit richer.
Once you open it,
you can do aaa lot of things with the data in that file,
f for c right?
It puts a character.
It's writes a character as a current location in the file.
Right?
Remember, this fp is returned by f open,
this pointer to the file data structures.
F put s an entire string,
a set of characters, which end with a zero.
In the file from the current position,
f get c and f get s goods are reversing,
read from the current position in the file,
or read from the current position for a set,
for for a given set of characters.
So greece,
a given set of characters from the given position and put them in a string.
When you are going to write global to the current position,
the current position is implemented.
If you are going to that to call for efforts,
multiple times is not going to overwrite.
Write in the same position.
It writes as a subsequent position.
This first set of ap is are character oriented.
Then we have block oriented if you can operate on a bunch of elements.
This is, if you think about is very useful and you have records,
your file is a bunch of records,
right?
She's like poor man database,
but I do have records.
Then you want to read and write a bunch of records of the time.
In this case, you need to give the number of the elements you want,
the number of records you want to read, right?
And also the size of each record.
And then the last A it's of AP is are format it.
But I remember when you do a print f right?
You are going to format the string,
right?
The output string.
And f scan f is, again,
it reads a formatted string.
Okay?
This is an example of having a character by character io this is about reading,
copying from an input to an output.
You get your open input and output files files.
Then you get one character from the input,
and then you write the character to the output.
And then once you are done,
then you close the input and the output.
So that and how do you know is done?
When you run, when you get to the end of the files,
you get a year end of file eof
this is an example,
again, to do blog blog by blog io in this case, again,
you opened again to input and output.
And now you are going to,
right,
in this case,
you write by,
like, I like,
array of bytes or you read array of bytes.
Do you have a buffer size?
And say this is, I don't know, it's 10, 24,
so it's one kilobyte.
You write the size of each record.
It's one character.
Right?
Here, you are going to,
again,
to read and write from a file at the level of a brighter blog granularity,
where a blog granularity, again, a buffer granularity,
which is he had one kilobyte.
It's again,
this is most and I'm going to end up with this.
This is for you to keep in mind when you are going to work on the homework,
when you are going to work on the projects,
be paranoid, try to be defensive,
try to think hard,
and try to capture every error.
Right?
That's why you call us function call when you call on,
or when you open a file and so forth.
Just check for errors.
This will save you a lot of pain,
even if you need to write a few more line of code,
and this will also add you a better grade.
Please check on the return values.
Let's stop here.
We'll just this one.
What we done,
what we learned here is we learn about the threads are the os unit
of concurrency and abstract a
virtual CPU and the threat contains all the state related to its executions.
And the processes contain over more threads and another space.
And all assets, all the threads in the same process.
They share the same code and the same variables,
global variables, all the global variables,
and the politics tidy.
Everything is a file.
Thank you.
Let's see.
So I see no new questions.
So with this will end up and see you all on Saturday.
Thank you.