Hello, everyone.
Welcome to the 5th lecture of cs 162.
Today, we are going to continue with the exciting topic of files.
We are going to start another topic,
which is on communications between processes or ipc inter process,
communication,
techniques and mechanics.
As always, if you have any questions ask on the q and a let's start.
Not yesterday 2 days ago,
we discussed about the streams,
which is a highest level api for the file systems.
Today, we are going to talk a little bit of a lower level file io api
which is centered around file descriptors.
Then we are going to talk what is the difference between the high level
and low level?
Ap is, why do we have to kind of ap is about somehow is a state is
managed across processes,
especially when you create another process using fork.
What happens with the file descriptors in the parent and the child?
And finally,
two or three common pitfalls,
you may want to avoid in your projects or homeworks.
In general, when you are going to write a program,
using this,
ap is for the file systems.
First, remember, what we discussed last time is that one unique thing about
unique is that it uses a file systems of a generic abstractions,
not only to deals or files,
or on a storage device like a describe,
but also to deal with different devices,
like keyboard,
terminals,
printer, and so forth.
The second thing is that the abstraction which is provided,
it's by oriented.
So by oriented means that you have what you get and you read or you
read and write to the
devices is basically a bunch of bytes.
And you can think about like a sequence of bytes.
And you can address it by the index of a particular byte.
You can identify the bike in the sequence by its index in that sequence.
The other things we are going to learn more is that when you
are going to do reads and writes,
these reasons rights are not going to come directly to your application.
They are going first to be buffered in the operating system.
As you'll see, also,
with the stream, the high level,
api we talked last time,
there is also a buffer in the application level.
Finally, the pattern is very simple.
You open a file, right?
You have to close it at the end and in between your read and write
from that particular file descriptor.
This is a low level file io api it's quite similar from the one the high level
pilot or api one difference,
though,
it's it's similar in the sense that it has an open,
close,
and in between like your series and rights is differently,
provides slightly different semantics.
And instead of if open,
like for the high level api you have just opened when you open a file,
you pass a file name,
then a bunch of flags,
which basically says,
what are the access rights?
Whether you read, you have the rights to read from the file,
write from the file,
or read write the file.
And then there are also a bit vector a with a permission bits,
which are also who is going to have the rights to access that file.
And you can have users.
The users is a is a user who actually runs a program which invokes this api
to open the file.
Then it's a group.
This is the concept the user belongs to a group.
We learn more about that.
And others means everyone else can access these files.
Then you have the clouds and you have create when your first time when you
create a heart.
Now, the important thing here is that open returns you and an integer.
The integer is also called file descriptor.
The integers are greater than zero.
If it's less than zero,
this means that is error.
It is integer.
It used to identify the meta data associated with a file.
You open in,
and this meta data is stored in the operating system.
So that's why you are going to have.
Why do you have.
Then I integer to identify this kind of this meta data,
which also, again,
this file descriptor.
And why do you have a file descriptor specified as an integer than specify
a as a pointer?
Can anyone answer that question?
It again, open returns an integer,
is a file descriptor,
which identifies the meta data associated with that file in the cattle.
Why not just have a pointer?
Yes, less dangerous.
One is same memory, not exactly.
It does.
That's correct.
Having a point at the canal will allow will mean that will allow the process,
which is a user process, which opens a file to have access to the camera,
actually.
But we know that processes are have their own address space,
which is different from the kernel.
You cannot have a pointer to the address space of the kernel.
Right?
That's why you have an integer,
because an integer is going when you are going to invoke on this one
of this operation on the file systems,
then you are going to pass a file descriptor,
the file descriptor,
it is going to be an index in a table of the file descriptors,
which are open at that given time.
And that index will.out to the meta data are sold or the
state associated with its open file.
So it's a portable way to identify the file state or the meta data
associated with the open file.
Now, there are several default files.
File names is like thunder bean thundered out standard file and this,
sorry,
decided the standard file descriptors.
Okay,
stand up in.
It's when you want to read from the keyboard standard out when you
are going to write to the keyboard.
And the other thing,
it's again, we have high level of the ap is.
Low level ap is,
the high level ap is or stream ap is, if you remember, from last time,
when you do an f open,
you return a file, a pointer.
That pointer is actually a pointer to data structures in the user space.
And in that address,
in that data,
structuring the user space has also contains a file descriptors
associated with that open.
We'll talk more about that,
but therefore,
there is a way to go from the file descriptors.
And that's the pointer which is returned by an of open instructor of open
of system called.
You remember, if you do fo but you get this pointer, file pointer.
And you can from this file pointer,
returned by an f open.
You can get the associated file descriptor by using file.
Now,
correction.
The universe is also true from file descriptor.
You got, when you open a file,
you can go out.
You can get the file pointer to that file by specifying
the file descriptors and the open type.
And now you can use this file descriptors to you to invoke for to invoke
on that file,
the high level ap is the stream level ap is,
low level ap is you have forgained, read and write.
But typically here, when you have read and write,
you are going to read a buffer of a certain size.
You read it into a buffer of a certain size,
or you write a buffer of a certain size, right?
Will read the elements from the files up to the size of the buffer,
which is mark size.
Obviously, when you read, you need to allocate space for the buffer.
The right, it's, again, similar.
You provide the pointer to a buffer,
which of this of a given size.
And that will result taking this buffer and writing it to the device.
In addition,
the other way to look at,
in addition, you have this command,
which is l sick.
Remember,
the abstraction is byte oriented.
If you look at the file,
it's a sequence of bytes.
If you want, now to read or to write in a file at a particular position.
The one, though,
you can use lc basically,
you are going to say,
where do you want to?
Where do you want offset is from the current position?
You want to add an offset,
a to a new location,
or you want to read from or to write.
Let me answer some of the question.
Can we put the powerpoint into presentation mode?
Thank you.
Sorry about that.
Yes, absolutely.
That was an easy one.
What does mode mean on the open code?
Does it apply to just the file descriptor?
Can I share a file descriptor with loser permission?
Then the file in the fs the mode is, again,
referring who has arrived to access the open file using the file descriptor.
And it does apply to a file descriptor.
But a file descriptor,
can I share a file escape tories,
loser permissions,
and the file in the you cannot because
of you if the file the access
rights are,
like in the name implies,
are enforced when you access a file.
If the file, for instance,
when you create it,
it's you can only read.
And again, when you are going to create a file,
you are going to basically say something like with these flags.
All people, for instance,
in my group can access a file.
So now if you share your file descriptor to someone in the same group,
they are going to have our rights to access a file.
If you,
sherry, someone from other,
was as a outside your group,
that person cannot access a file,
because and the operating system is going to look who is going to access a file,
and this logo is not the same group,
then is going to procure the axis.
Why is a buffer?
This next question is why is a buffer of type void?
It's basically saying this signify the fact that in that buffer,
you can have anything,
right?
Is for generality.
But if you put car, for instance,
then he suggests that these are kind of the characters probably in us
for emergency like that.
Void is basically saying it can be also binary representation.
It can be anything.
It's a convention more than anything.
A this is an example of a simple example.
You open an existing file,
you open an existing file,
and you write the output.
Here you is read only.
This is the user is right,
writing, access and writing access for the user.
And then you read it your clothes,
you send the you send the output to standard out by number.
So one question here is about how many bytes these program reads.
So you can see when you read,
this is an important instruction.
You read into a buffer of which you allocated 1,000 bytes.
How many bytes does this program?
It should be easy.
Any answers?
We have some answers here.
Size of buffer without some answers,
$1,000,
at most on salary.
That's correct.
With just a little,
tiny clarification,
you read,
if the size of the file is less than 1,000 bytes,
you read everything, you read the entire file.
If the size of the file is greater than 1,000 bytes,
you read the first 1,000 bytes of the file.
Like I mentioned the design pattern.
It's open.
Before you use a file.
At the end you close it.
And in between and read and write from the file with a low level,
ioapi you basically read and write a bunch of bytes.
That's all you can use lc to reposition in inside a file.
So one important aspect I mentioned earlier on,
you also need to think about the buffers.
When you read something from a file,
that sink doesn't go,
that is not red directly to the operating system to this application.
It reads first.
The information from a file,
the data from the file is first thread,
and is buffered in the kernel.
The same is right.
When you write,
you don't write directly to the device,
you write to a buffering to the camera.
And the camera writes after that to the device.
Okay.
Now can you think about why would you read and write to a buffer
from and probably to and from a buffer?
Is a kernel rather directly from the device to
check for malaysia input?
Faster.
The devices might not be directly, right?
That's good.
It's faster,
and the devices might not be directly ready.
And think about this way, right?
It's also the fact that the devices,
when they transferred data,
they may have a natural granularity, at least a transfer, the date.
So, for instance,
when you read from the disk,
you read kind of ground like these, like blocks, a few kilobytes.
Right?
This is what you get from a describe.
You don't get 1 byte at a time.
You get a block at a time.
Even if you ask for on character, you get a block.
You need to put that block summers.
We are going to put it in,
though this is how we are going to put in.
A is a kernel buffer,
right?
Otherwise means to throw it away.
And then if you read the second character from that block,
you need to bring it again.
The other thing it's about another situation is that when I write,
say, a buffer right to the device,
the device may not be ready.
Right?
Maybe another right is happening on the device.
Or simply, if you have a files,
you have at least the like a disk drive.
You need the disk,
you need to wait for the disk to rotate,
says that the head of the disk to be above this,
the region of the disk,
or you already which is available as you can write new data.
Or in that particular case,
instead of blocking the application,
then for to wait for that event,
then instead,
you are going to write to this kernel buffer,
and the kernel is going to take care of the rest.
The same is another, right?
I I if I want,
if i'm going to write at once a big chunk of data,
and this is larger than what the network can send at once large as are
not one packet.
Then what what will happen in that case that you are going to write
all this kind of chunk of data in the kernel?
The kennel take care to chop how much you want to send in smaller packets
and send packages or each packet at a time.
So hopefully,
this is enough to give you a sense about why you need to buffer the data,
why I need to buffer to have kennel buffers when you read and write.
Then there is another operation.
It's, again, there are differences.
While everything is a file that are different between devices,
like you mentioned last time,
for instance, from a terminal,
you have terminal,
it's only output,
a printer, it's only output,
the keyboard it's only input or the mouse, it's only input.
Like for instance for the yeah,
and then also you may want to configure the other parameters like a printer
to configure the line speed or things like that.
What you are going to do when you have this extra parameters to configure
it for which are particular to a partner to a given device,
then you have this ioctl as a escape batch.
So that allows you to deal with these specialized particular parameters
for different devices.
The other one is a double to duplicate the file descriptors.
And to duplicate you,
a can open a file.
You can get a file descriptors.
And you can, if you want to share that file descriptor to someone else,
right?
Maybe another thread in the same application,
or maybe another process for you to another process to operate on the same file,
then one way to do it is to create another file descriptors to which point
to the same metadata to the same instance of the open file.
We'll show examples of that.
The difference between loop two and loop is that we stop to,
you can actually specify the file descriptors.
You want to point to the same data structure of open file,
right?
With a dupe,
you'll get back the next lowest number available
step in the file descriptor of the file descriptor numbers,
the lowest available by it's like, you'll see,
it's a way to communicate between two processes.
You can think as a cube.
And we are going to talk about memory mapping, files, file locking,
dancing like that.
Now,
an obvious question here is that why do we have high level and low level
like pis why do we have streams?
And why you have file descriptors?
Why do you have fo ones?
And why do you have open?
Right?
First of all, this is how they compare here.
It's high level operation,
which is on streams of bytes.
Here,
it's operation which is on a buffer.
Right?
And the files,
the stream of bioap are preceded by f with f letter.
Obviously,
as a low level,
api they don't have any this prefix letter.
So the middle is the same.
Right?
Remember, this are going to be converted to a system call,
because this operation are implemented by the kernel.
What happens here?
You are going to call invoke the function it in the operating system
by using this kind of trap
and special drop instruction.
And before you do that,
you are going to fill in some registers with the data,
for the operating systems,
for the kernel,
to know which files you are referring.
Right?
And what operation you want to perform on that file.
And for that operation,
what are the arguments?
This is what you put in registers here just before the trap instruction.
And then after it was a stop,
is after the execute the trap instructions,
the kernel will take over,
look at the register.
If you initialize,
is figuring out the file descriptor you are referring to,
figure out what is the operation you want to perform,
figure out the arguments of the operation,
which are in other registers,
perform the operation and then returns back to the users once the operation
is performed.
And if the return values,
it's also make sure that put the return value a in the particular register
like ex the only difference is that,
as you see,
the afraid,
so this is the middle part.
It's identical.
The only difference is that the ways afraid with a high level ap is you do
a lot
of some work before or after.
You invokes the operating system,
you invoke the system call as a user level.
You do some more work.
Right?
That has to do is the fact that,
as you will see,
with the high level ap is,
we have a buffer not only in the kernel,
but also we have a buffer in the user level.
This is exactly to illustrate that point.
Right?
If there are two examples here,
we try to achieve mostly the same thing,
but they have different behavior.
So in the first case,
you are going to,
in both cases, with sprint,
f printer is at the end of the day,
it's a right operation to the terminal.
You give a string,
you bring to the terminal.
This is a high level api right here.
We have the the same kind of operation,
but using the low level ips right?
To standard out to the to the output, to the terminal.
In both cases, what we do,
we write a string,
the first part of a string begin offline.
Then we sleep for 10 seconds.
And then we ride the second part of the string,
but which is hence with character, slasher.
Okay.
What is the difference between that?
What is the difference in behavior?
The difference in behaviour is at the first one.
It brings everything at once souls, although you,
but in beginning of line,
you don't see anything at the terminal before you also print the end
of the string
which finishes which ends with carriage bitter.
In the second case, again,
you spring the same thing.
You are going to see beginning of line printed,
then slip ten.
After 10 seconds,
you are going to see the end what happened under the hood?
And why do you have this behavior?
You have the behavior,
because in the second case,
you have a buffer and that buffer.
It is a cara.
You sent to the colonel,
this kind of the first 18 beats beginning of line.
And then the kernel is going to print on the terminal,
the second one.
And then when you send the last a 16 beats,
the colonel beautifully will print the end, right?
Of the of the sentence.
In contrast,
with a stream level interface,
you have another buffer,
which is in the application level.
You don't directly write in the back kernel buffer.
You write in the application buffer.
And the application buffer is written to the kennel buffer.
Only when you have,
in this particular case,
when you encounter the slash character,
like the end of line character.
In this case, he printed beginning of line.
This is going to do application buffer.
Nothing happens after 10 seconds.
You at end of line in the application buffer.
And then only now because you have this kind of line feet.
So the end of line,
it's the entire application buffer is is written in the kernel buffer.
They cannot will the right on the terminal as the entire centers.
Does it make sense?
That's what happens.
Now, what is it the file disk file of into the file?
Data structure?
Again, this pointer to a file data structure is returned by the high level.
Ap is by f open.
You have the file descriptors.
This is the one which is returned by the low level api which is the side integer.
You have the buffer, like I mentioned,
mister buffer we are talking about,
you have us at the application level.
You also have a lock,
in case there are multiple threads using the file concurrently.
Then you want to lock and you have only one thread accessing the file
at the same time.
Remember about the concurrency discussion,
we had last lecture.
There are many other things in the file data,
in the file data structures,
but this is we are not going to discuss us now.
Right?
So now when you call af right?
Or any kind of high level apia stream,
api what happens to the data you provide is a following you get to write is
a files buffer,
this application buffer.
This is exactly what I mentioned.
And then you have to fly.
And then this application buffer or file buffer is written as a kennel buffer.
Any flushing.
You have a special inter instruction to flush in the particular case
of the print f it is flashed when you get the line fit.
So that's basically what it is.
What does this mean?
When you write code,
you make the weakest possible assumption about how data is flushed
from the file buffer.
We need to make that assumption.
And why is that important?
So your application in your application,
you write yourself, right?
From your point of view,
you may think that all these data already made it onto the disk.
Right?
But that's not the case.
If you have a failure,
just after an f right?
You are not guaranteed as a beta you wrote, is making all the disk.
In order to do that,
you need to make sure that is flushed.
The data is flushed to the kernel, and actually,
and then from,
and then the kernel is going to make sure that it's going to be return
on the risk.
So need to be careful about that.
And this is a reminder for you how use a high level cpi
to in this particular case,
to write and read.
And this is another important aspect to allow you to understand the
subtleties associated with this high level interface.
In this code, what you have,
I have a character c and I am going to write it in a file dot text.
Then i'm going to open the file.
Again,
this is another descriptor here, f two.
And i'm going to read from that file.
Okay?
You write a character in the file,
and you are going to read the character from the same file using different files,
pointers.
What happens in this case?
Right?
That happen?
Sorry,
you initialize x here to c and what you're writing the file is b not c sorry,
ii then the question, what you are going to get,
you are going to get an anatomic behavior.
When you read here,
you can have c or you can have b so why is that?
Can someone say it?
There are two questions here,
so please try to,
yes, that's very good.
So to answer this question,
and then I there is an answer to my question.
The answer to my question is that why you can get deterministic behavior?
Because you don't know any the when the files buffer is flashed to disk.
Right?
So what can happen?
Remember,
when you are going to write b that b is written in the file buffer
in the file buffer,
which is associated with effort.
Now you open f two.
And now this is going to create another file buffer,
which is a social reserve to when you read it,
if this b didn't make it from the file buffer of f one to the kernel buffer
and to the disk,
what you are going, you are not going to read it.
If it made it,
then you are going to really be okay.
Basically, here you write b in a file buffer,
and you are going to read from a different file buffer.
If b didn't make it from this file buffer or have fun to the disk,
then it's available when you are going to open the second the file using
another file descriptor,
you are not going to cb now,
there are two other questions on the second point.
Does it mean that if a file buffer is full,
then the buffer is flushed.
If the file buffer is full, it is flushed.
There are other policies you have no control of.
When with a file buffer can be flushed periodically even before it's full.
After you have data stay too much,
maybe in the file buffer,
or you can do it explicitly.
There is a flash comment like a mesh.
Why do we have to make the weakest possible assumptions on when file is flushed?
It's again because you do not know unless you flash it explicitly,
you do not know when the file buffer is flashed to the kelvin.
Okay?
Let me see.
There are some other questions.
Is there a way to atomic to do atomic file operations?
There is no easy way to do atomic file atomic operation.
You can do that.
And we are going to learn how to do it.
But one of the original designs of decision design decision in unix
was to not support
transaction semantics when you update the fast.
That's where you have database,
but you say you can do it,
but you don't have an operation to do it on an f right?
If the buffer is flushed,
does the input data go into the newly cleaned buffer?
Or does it get written to file as part of the flush?
If it's flashed the flush?
It's you can think,
as an atomic operation,
you flush it, and then you write in the buffer.
Does file buffer have a default size?
Or does it depend on the size of the file being open?
That's a great question.
Ii think i'll check,
but as far as I know,
you have a default size,
which you may be able to recall to configure.
But from what I remember,
it's a default size.
Let's move on.
We have still a lot of things to cover.
So writing the correct code is,
like I mentioned to you,
is basically you have to flash the data.
Now, this is the explicit command.
I mentioned to you ff flush.
Now,
you are going to flush to force the file buffer being flushed
with the flow level appear.
We don't have this problem because you are going to write in the buffer
or in the kernel,
and both the scripters,
when i'm going to open the file of the descriptor for the same file,
they are going to see the same kernel buffer.
Right?
When you have on a right completes,
is going to be visible to secrecy,
subsequent rates.
Now, the key question, which I expected to get and I didn't,
but it's a very natural question.
The key question,
why do you have a buffer in in the user as a user level?
So why do you have the file buffer?
When you already have a kernel buffer?
The answer is one of the answers is performance.
If you write a character at that time,
if you use a stream api you are going to write the character in the file buffer.
This is a user level.
It's just a function call.
If you want to write one character using the low level api that's a system call.
It requires context switching to the kernel and a system called,
because the contact switching to the kernel is
far more expensive than a local function,
right?
Which is 25 times more expensive.
So let me put it this way, and you should try it.
If you write,
say, 1,000 characters,
but it was a 10,000 characters.
If you write it character by character,
using the high level api will be much faster than writing character by
character using the low level api because in the first case,
you are going to have a contact switching only when the buffer file buffer
is flashed.
While in the second case, you have contact switching.
Every time you write a character.
Sorry.
The other thing is that you can implement more sophisticated things
as the user level.
Right?
The second point here about, I guess,
see what I told you about,
but I think it also apply about writing, about reading.
Right?
Because when you read, you can have the entire blog,
which will be transferring the file bar for us.
And then when you do the fgsc on the next character,
then to get the next character,
you are going to be a local call,
because the block is already in the file buffer.
If the block is only on the kernel buffer,
then every time you get the next characters with a low level,
api is going to be a context such.
Hopefully, this is clarify a few things.
Aa system called a system cooperation are less kept are system cooperation,
which is a low level.
Apis are, in general,
less capable.
You can have more functions like formatting, right?
As a high level.
Why it's important is because you want the kernel to be as small as possible.
Right?
You aren't,
because I care anything resident to the always residents in the memory.
And it's not only that if you have less code,
it's less chances to introduce box.
Right?
So that's why this is another reason for it.
You have stream api in high level api and low level system.
Api is because you can add more functionality in the file level,
api without making the kernel more complex process state for file skippers.
Let's move quickly.
Here we are doing,
let's see how the state is maintained in the kernel.
Right?
Recall on a successful code to open,
you have a file descriptor.
It's returned to the user and an open,
open file description.
So the state associated with that file descriptor is created in the cattle.
Right?
When the feature system calls,
the camera looks to the open file description using the file descriptor.
Right?
Okay?
Is a very simple of far code here.
This is a code.
We have two buffers,
buffer on and buffer two,
and we are using the system calls a low level calls to read from food or text.
We want to eat the first 100 bytes in buffalo one,
the second 51 100 bytes in buffer.
Right?
The important.here,
it's about the lock.
The current location in the file is kept by in this file description.
Right?
That's why if you have consecutive calls or read,
you are going first to read the first 100 by the next to read the next 100 bytes.
Here we just a slide showing about files of file description how it looks like.
This is love is a position of the current position in the file.
The structure of, I know we are going to talk later.
It's where the file is located on the disk.
And there are a lot of other information is not important for our discussion,
but it's important for our discussion.
It's about, let's see how things are maintained in the memory.
We have here a process.
And here we have the kernel, right?
Above the dash line,
it has a process.
At the below the dash line,
a a it's a cab.
Right?
In the process, you have the address space,
and then you have a thread,
and you have the thread registers.
Remember, the thread is a unit of execution.
Every process has at least one thread,
right?
Suppose that to execute open food or text,
and the result is three.
The file descriptor,
which is returned by open history,
you have open file descriptions.
You have the file which is opened,
and the position start to be zero.
This is why the file descriptor points.
This is what I wanna.
The open file description is what I mentioned earlier is like the state
of the file for them and the meta data associated with the file.
What is now?
So initially,
you may ask why is three?
Because the standard being standard out and standard error at 01,
and two are already taken.
Remember, this has a default file descriptors.
Next, suppose that you execute read from this file descriptors,
the first 100 bytes in this buffer.
Right?
Remember the previous code?
You read that, and once you read it,
the position, notice in the open file description,
it's a set updated to 100.
Now, suppose that you execute close three,
you execute closely.
The file descriptor is gone as well as a file description.
Right?
So it's simply enough.
But now, instead of closing,
after you read the first 100 bytes, let's say we fork.
Now, if you for, remember,
the entire state in the entire code of the parent process
is going to be copied in the child process.
So this is going also to have what is going to happen is a file descriptors
are going to be copied.
Now, you have to the same open file descriptions.
You have two pointers,
three, both of them are three, obviously,
because that's how you indexing this open file description,
one from parent process,
and one from the child process.
Right?
You are shared the same state,
the shared state in the open file description.
Right?
Now, if you read from buffer 100 or inform process one,
using the file descriptor three,
now the position is advanced to hundred.
Now, if you read,
the process is the charlie process that is from the same file descriptor.
What happens?
The position is updated to 300,
because again,
both the child and the parent operate on of the same open file description.
Now, when you closely is apparent,
the file from the that is closed from the perspective of process one,
but the open file description is not destroyed,
because it's still referred by the client by the child process.
So only when the child process is going to close its own,
the file descriptor three,
only then open file description associated with the file descriptor three
is going to go away.
The cool thing about this.
Now you can have remembered one of the potential,
and we are going to learn more about that.
One of the problems, when you have processes, on one hand,
you have strong isolation because each of them comes with own file system
which own other space.
But you still want to communicate in some cases between the process.
This is one way to communicate.
Right?
You open a file,
you fork a child,
then both the child and the parent have access to the fallacy
with the same fallacy.
You can use file system to exchange the data.
Again,
this is the same repeating it that everything or every device
and its abstraction is a file,
like disks, networking,
and receive some other communication primitives.
This means that they are going to have a high level
at the same high level api open,
read, write clothes.
The same thing happened when you have for the first default descriptor, 01,
and 2,
obviously, they are going to be shared between the child and the parent.
Right?
So if the child and the parent are going to write,
you are going to see interleaved the whatever they are writing on the terminal,
for instance.
Okay.
It's a game.
If one process is concluded standard in,
this means that you can no longer get an input from the keyboard.
Then the process the child is the only one which can receive inputs
from the keyboard.
And that's very important,
because you may want in your program,
only the child process to get the input from The keyboard,
not both across both parents and the child.
So many of the things we talk about and we are going to talk
in the remaining of the lecture are going to be helpful for you in home
or do when you have to write a shout.
Therefore could be very useful for metal king because you can handle
each connection in a different process.
Now there is another way you can share the access to the same file,
and that is using dupe.
Okay?
So what loop is meaning you replicate the file descriptors,
and the file descriptor is going to point to the same open file description.
Here you have is that you like think about on an arias,
but I see if you create it and you open a file,
you got the file descriptor three.
Now, if you can call dope on three,
you are going to get a four.
Now,
both file descriptor three and four point out to the same open file description.
There is another instruction,
which is the tool,
which has a second argument.
The second argument is actually saying,
what is a file descriptor you want to point up to the same open file description,
like the far the first argument in the call, in this case,
file descriptor three.
This is useful.
If, for instance, you have multiple processes of the same application,
you run all of them.
You have a barrier,
you have a constant there,
basically say each of them,
they should open.
They should operate on the files descriptor,
162,
like one process,
create a file open, the files,
then it calls stoop.
And then everyone can operate on that file descriptor.
We are running a little bit late.
So here are some based on what they discussed.
There are some challenges or some things you need to be
careful with when you work with the file systems.
This is particularly very important to for your homework and projects.
First, don't fork in a process that already has multiple threads.
Why?
Because the threads are not for,
right?
You for the state of the process that is copied,
you are going when you copy it a process,
when you duplicate all the state from the parent to the child.
The threats are not copied,
because their executions are ephemeral.
Right?
In the second, in the child,
you have only one process,
one thread.
All the other cells will disappear.
So many member,
only the threat that calls a fog existing the new process.
This is and remember,
when you call exact,
you don't care about it whether there are multiple steps because exact
is basically replace the entire space of the
process who called exec with a program which is going to be executed
in that process.
Okay?
Be very mindful when you mix a low level and high level failures.
It's again, the main reason.
Remember, high level ipoiio has a file pointer and a file buffer.
They have the file buffer.
That,
in this case,
for instance,
when here a it's a subtly subtle problem.
In this case,
you open a file a with a high level api you get file pointer f and then you
get from that file pointer,
you get the file descriptor.
Now you call f read on that file and read on that file.
And the file a file read, you'll get,
you say, I want to read only the first 10 bytes,
and then with a read,
which is a low level api want to read the next 10 bytes.
We started expect when you look at this code,
I say every do will read the file,
the first 10 bytes,
read or read the next 10 bytes.
The problems they may not me,
maybe that might not happen,
because every it returns to the applications of first and bytes.
But from the kernel,
it may get an entire block,
which is going to be stored in the file buffer.
So you may get the first 4,000 bytes from the fire,
which means that in the kernel,
in the associated file description,
the position now will be 4,000.
So when you call the read,
this will go directly to the kernel.
It will read from the current position.
So it may lead the bites from 4,000 to 4,000 before continuing.
Actually, let me answer this question on an f right?
If the buffer is flushed,
does the input data go into the newly clean buffer?
Or does it get written to the farthest?
I answer this question.
Right?
First, you do the flash.
Then you are going to arrive in your data announcements.
The group da assignments have been released.
If you don't know yet.
Take on pizza.
Project zero is due today.
Good luck with a submission.
And project one will be released on friday.
Other than that,
many of you are still online.
Please start planning on how your group will collaborate is
the most effective way.
Virtual coffee hours,
a regular brainstorming meeting.
And again,
try to communicate as much as possible.
Now we switch the gears,
and we are going to talk about how two processes can communicate to each other.
One way to communicate is using the networking.
This is a very general way to communicate between two processes,
because you can do that even when processes run on different measures.
And this is can happen when you have your web browser and what if your browser,
this is how your browser communicate with a web brow,
with a web server.
And under the hood use tcpip protocol.
We are going to learn about it.
For now, we just the suffice to say,
and to take a look about the api the api is very similar.
When you want to send data,
you essentially what is called a socket.
This is, in some sense,
think about the equivalent of the file descriptor and the file description
with the socket.
You are going to write to that socket,
like you write for a file profile descriptor,
but otherwise,
the api is the same right?
Or file descriptors above a certain length.
Then on the receiving side,
when you want to get data,
you are going to have a read.
Again, the same api read from the far less guitar.
This is the socket descriptor in a buffer of a certain size.
Again,
we are going to have an entire lecture about the cpip what is the other way
to communicate between processes?
Another way to communicate between processes?
Like you'll see that are using pipes and using the shared memory.
But,
again, taking her back, a step back,
here, we want fundamentally to punch a hole between the processes,
because otherwise, the process cannot communicate with each other.
That's entire idea about processes to be isolated from each other.
Each of them has its own other space.
They cannot address data from each other's other space.
Here is one example.
This is about shared memory,
but before, let's again, sing again,
recall a guy about how processes are protected from each other.
You have two processes here on the left and the right hand side.
Right program.
One runs in the first process program during the second process.
If then you have each process with its own code,
data segment, heap, and stuck.
Now, both processes share the same physical others,
physical memory.
In the middle, you have the physical memory.
The physical memory is divided into regions.
And this into,
and what happens is the operating system or the kernel map,
the code, the daytime,
the heap from different processes in different regions.
Right?
And these regions are to be joined it.
Okay?
That's why you cannot address the data from another process.
Because in the physical memory,
each process owns a the joint pace of others.
And the reason the way you achieve that it is through translation.
Again, we are going to learn about that.
That's where the magic happens,
and making sure that the processes do not step on each other, those.
So that's what we have despite of this.
And despite this protection and followed by the kernel,
we still want to communicate between processes,
right?
Like we mentioned.
So how do we do that?
And we already shown some example in the sockets.
Another way,
you already know, you can use file system,
right?
A file system can write to a file data,
and sorry,
a process can drive data to a file.
The process can read from the same file,
the data written by the first process using the read and write primitives.
Now,
you can do that.
However, this is quite expensive,
because the right or file,
it's expensive and reading from a file and slow.
And also, in most of the cases,
you don't need a persistence store.
It's an overkill.
Okay?
Like, think about if you want to go from your client to your web browser,
you don't need to start every request and every reply.
Furthermore, this works only on the same machine.
Otherwise, you need a distributed file system.
If the processes are not located on the same machine,
one solution is to have ability to have shared memory.
And the operating system provides that ability.
You can actually create a memory if a process can create a memory and share
and say that
memory can be shared with other processes.
And therefore,
in this case,
both processes one and two,
they are going to.to share the same share space in the physical memory,
which means that within this space,
they can share of it.
Okay?
There is an api there is a way by which you can create shared memory
and a shared memory regions and
share that region between two different processes.
See?
It's a question.
What is the benefit to having memory of the individual processes be deterred?
The benefit of having the memory of individual processes be designed is
to ensure protection.
You do not want a malicious process to access the memory of another process.
What words to access a memory of the cat?
Hopefully answers the question.
What about the other things?
What about if we want to is anything that kernel can provide us
to facilitate the communication between two processes?
By the way,
so the asset it is,
which I only alluded by providing this kind of socket mechanism,
like I when I talk about the cpip right?
But fundamentally, it's, again,
the abstraction you want,
which is useful to provide is like a queue, right?
Because we do not want at least four processes.
We run on the same machine.
We want to kind of in memory queue.
Right?
Again, we don't want to build something on top of the storage file storage.
We said it's too expensive,
too slow.
What is memory?
Cube?
Means is basically the semantic is that a process just push the data
to the cure.
And the other is the producer and the consumer read from the queue.
Right?
And typically, the cues it's in first out,
there are other kinds of cues,
like last in, first out, but typically is,
in first out, what we are going to talk this in this lecture.
One abstraction of such fuel is a pipe, is a unique spike.
So the unique spike,
you are the way you can open a pipe.
And you can, again, it's like a file, a scripture.
You can use read and write when you write
you right at the end of the pipe when you read from the front of the pipe.
Okay?
That's exactly that you sum up.
Now,
these five and you have a buffer of a certain size,
it's not infinite.
If the pipe is full than the right blocks,
you can no longer,
right,
is a bike unless the consumer a process released from the pipe and makes
room for new data to be returned in the pipe.
The same if the pipe is empty and you want to read from the pipe you block
and it looks until someone put some data in the pipe.
When you create a pipe,
what you get to file descriptors,
like you in my imagine,
one file descriptors to,
right?
2 and 15 is still the descriptor to read from.
Right?
So five, you have the that file descriptor is to read from file this zero.
And file descriptor one is the second file descriptor is to write.
And it's implemented, like I mentioned,
as a fixed size two.
Right here is how you can use it.
You can,
you create a file, again,
kind of a pipe.
And then you are going to write to the second file descriptor.
You are going to read from the second file, first file descriptors,
and make sure that when you close both file descriptors,
so piled between the processes,
Again, here a greater pipe,
you get the first file descriptor, three and four,
pointing to read and write from that pipe.
Now you do a fork.
The file descriptors are copied.
And now you also have this file descriptors pointing to the same instance
of the pipe.
Right?
So if you want to write to use that,
despite to communicate between the parent and the child,
then you need also,
this is in one direction.
In this particular case,
I want the parents say,
I want the parent to send data to the child,
right?
I gave the pipe,
which is not shown here.
And then I fork,
remember,
if the result of the fork is not zero,
this means that I I am the parent when I execute the code.
Because the result from the fork is going to be the PIB is
a process identifier of the child.
Then I'm going to write the second descriptor,
and I'm going to close the this is a writer, skipper,
pipe fd of one.
And then to close the read descriptor.
Why?
Because again, in this example,
I I want only the parent to write to comment to send data to the child.
The same for the child.
Right?
I am going to read from the file,
first file descriptors.
And I don't want to write,
so I'm going to close that I described.
So this is what happens closely and close for.
Right.
Now,
the pattern I have is that the pattern process is going to send data
to the child process survive.
If you want to the other way around to get the child to communicate to the parent,
you can do the other way around by closing the other file descriptors.
When do we get end of file on a pipe after the last Friday?
So after the last ride,
descriptor is closed to a bike,
if you continue to read.
So if you continue to read from a pipe,
and there is no right descriptor,
open for that far for that pipe,
you get end of five.
If the grid descriptor is closed,
and you try to write to a file, you get a sick pipe.
This is the interact.
You can ignore it,
but then the right will fail.
All right?
So here,
if you close a ride a scripter,
then and you continue to read from that pipe,
you are going to get on the file.
Now, once you have a communication,
establish a communication,
we need a protocol.
The protocol need about how we are going to communicate between two parties.
Okay?
The protocol will have a syntax,
right?
Which will specify how you need to specify.
You specify the protocol, the format,
the message order or things like that.
How do you send and receive data?
And then the semantics is that what communication means?
Right?
When you make a call to send some data,
what actually happens?
Right?
Okay?
Is the data always guaranteed to get to the destination or may be lost?
Right?
A is a data guarantee to be get is a destination of the receiver guarantee
to get the data in the same order in your send out.
It's also more complicated,
because if you communicate over network,
different computers make you have different data formats,
you need to convert between different formats.
This is also part of the product.
Okay?
This is things and things about,
like you talk about telephone,
right?
You pick up,
you dial the number,
then you talk with your friend.
And then at the end,
you end up, right?
You hang up.
But the protocol here,
part of the protocol is is about what are the part of the
protocols like like pick up the phone and open it?
It's like an open.
Closing the phone is closing the call.
It's like a close.
And then the break in me in the middle you have read and writes.
But what I mean by the protocol here, like, for instance,
the dial is how you are going to contact the other party.
That's part of the protocol.
It's a number,
right?
We need to figure out then is that this kind of part of the total value
where typically you start with the hello.
But I I'm here,
right?
Also, it's used implicitly to recognize because the other party,
if your friend is going to recognize your voice,
or may be recognized because of the number you see she or he sees.
And then before hanging up,
you don't just hang up.
You say, bye.
Right, you also that's implicit protocol here on your boss.
You expect for the other person to talk.
Right?
So things like that.
Okay.
Okay, so the website about it,
this is a very simple example.
You also have a high level protocol,
its application protocol,
which have a request and reply.
That's how you are going.
You see the results from the websites,
from your Facebook account,
or when you do a query on Google.
This is exactly how things are working.
You send a request,
you get a reply which is going to be rendered and shown to you in our process.
So I'm going to stop here.
In the meantime, I'm going to take the last question.
So we are done.
So for people who ask the questions,
I'm going to spend a few more minutes to answer this question.
This has a question.
Actually, I missed recently.
What happens if the new argument in the dot two function
is already being used as another file the skater?
Great question is the old one is overwritten
by www why is file io slow?
The file io is slow is because every operation like read and write leads
to context switching to the kernel.
It has to be implemented by the is going to be executed by the killer.
If you are going to write one character at a time,
the low level file,
what will cause that for every character,
you have a context switch from the user process to the kernel,
for the kernel to write the character,
you write 1,000 characters,
one by one.
Then you have 1,000 context switches.
And the context switch is expensive.
You need to save the state of the process below the state of the operating system.
And then go back.
Like i've shown you from this data is twelve twenty,
no function call,
is at least one or remind you faster than a system called to the operating system.
So why?
So we can buy between any two processes.
You can buy between any two processes on the same machine.
It's a question from miles.
Can a process ever make a Malaysia system call?
Can you assume they're relying on the kernel for IPC secure?
You can assume,
because the operating system is, again, you can,
on the way you ask the operating system to do something,
is to put some data,
the system call,
and the file descriptor,
the argument for the system calls in the registers.
The operating system is going to read the context of the registers.
This is how is going to execute the system call.
And one reading is going to validate the data you put in the registers.
You assume that the validation is done correctly.
And therefore,
by using a system call,
you cannot cause any harm to the operating system.
Let me see whether there are any other questions on the chat.
It's the norm.
Last one.
It looked like the physical memory of a single process was the joint.
I was wondering why not keep the physical memory of each process continuous.
That's an excellent question,
Jasper.
So the reason is you cannot have contiguous,
because you do not know as the beginning of the process of a program,
how much memory you need.
Why a simple reason is, for instance, a stack,
you don't know how much stack will grow.
Another reason is hip.
When you allocate dynamically memories,
a program allocate dynamically memory,
do you know how much a program is going to allocate?
Because of this reason?
And because the address space in the virtual address space about everything
that they the user sees can
be much larger than the physical address space,
then there is no way the you cannot allocate a contiguous region.
Thank you.
Thanks, everyone.
Good luck with first project.
And i'll see you next week.