Hello, everyone.
Let's start the 6th lecture.
Today,
we are going to continue the inter process communication to talk
about the inter process communication primitives.
In particular,
we are going to talk about sockets which allowed to applications
to communicate over the network.
And then we are going to start talking about concurrency.
This will be a pretty long topic which will go over the pure next,
a couple of lectures.
As always, if you have any questions,
please ask in the q and a thread,
or i'll try also to check on the chat.
Let's start.
So,
again, like we discussed earlier in this class,
today, a lot of applications are distributed, right?
They are not only running on a single machine on your laptop,
but most of them, they have a back end.
You need to go over the network in order to implement
almost any functionality of the application.
And the exam, your web browser is a great examples.
Anything you are using today almost like many of the applications like facebook,
twitter,
and google application like google docs.
And obviously google itself as they look this way,
you have a piece of code running on the client side, on your machine,
on your phone,
and a bigger piece of code which runs on the back end,
on a bunch of servers in the data centers.
And typically, all these applications, in general,
looks like that, like this.
The client sends a request,
and it gets a reply back.
The request can be a query and google.
The reply can be the answers to that.
The it can be the reply to your search query.
And for something like that flicks,
the reply will be,
as a request will be your clicks.
Selecting a movie,
the reply can be also recommendation of other movies or the movies
start streaming and things like that.
And typically you have more than one client talking with the same set
about the same machine.
And like, for instance,
have many web clients,
and the many of them are talking with the same web server.
This is a kind of pattern communication pattern we have to implement
under the hood.
So here it's about how also a little bit more and more details
about how client and the server are similar.
And even more importantly,
how they are different.
The client again, sends a request,
like get index html this basically specified to get as a content of the web
page of a site of the first page of a site to render on your machine.
And in order to do that,
you need to contact a server which stores the index dot html,
this fight, the content of the page you want to render on your machine.
One thing obviously need to do is that when we need to know is the address
of that server,
right?
It's like when you make a call,
you need to know the number you are calling.
Okay?
So keep in mind that.
So you need to know the address of the seller from it.
You get the content.
And now the server,
it's typically always on,
it has always to be ready to receive requests and answer this request.
Unlike on the other hand,
obviously is a client.
It's not always on your phone, your computer,
your laptop is not always on most of the time.
It's actually off.
But when it's on, it's going to send his request to a server.
We should be on all the time in order for you to get the reply right away.
And obviously,
the clients initiate the conduct of the server nor the other way around.
The client know doesn't need to know to have a because of that,
the client doesn't need to have a well known address,
but the server has to okay.
And like we said before,
when the server gets a required as aa request,
it's going to answer something back,
hopefully satisfying the reply,
answering the reply according to the user expectations.
Again, we need to call to send data over the network.
And what we do that,
we need to send, we are going to send some bites.
Data consists of bits.
We aggregate each eight beats.
It's a one bike,
typically of majoring bytes,
like memory.
You also typically major in bytes,
or maybe which is a bunch of bytes.
So more than that is not only we have individual bytes,
we have stream of bytes.
Remember, the stream of bytes is the same interface,
the high level interface from the file systems.
Here, we are going to talk more about networking later in the lecture,
but here we are talking about dcp connection.
Tcp stands for transport control protocol.
Do you know what is the other type of protocol?
Common protocol?
Besides dcp udp what does udp stands for?
And icmp acdp is a protocol,
but a a it's at a higher level.
It's on top of the tcp udp it's user data, ground protocol,
not unified user data,
ground protocol.
And http and ftp are also protocols,
but they are the higher levels they are running on top of pcp again,
we are going to learn the network.
Software is organizing stacks a in a bunch of players.
Here we are going to talk about the transport layer and pcp and udp are
at the transport layer.
So thanks for your answers.
So now we need to abstract the connection between two employees and b
the way we are going to do that,
it should be, again, be very natural,
because you are going to send a string of bytes.
You need to abstract like a cube,
write yaq because,
for instance, aa very simple example,
what happened if the client sends faster than the server can receive
or the server,
for some reason,
is doing something else.
And you cannot get the data sent to it right away.
This data is either is lost,
or if you don't want to lose it,
you need to buffer summer.
Right?
So you have to have a cure, right?
You need to have boss on from the client to the servant,
from the server to the client,
because both of them, they are going to send data.
One of them is going to send typically request,
and the other one replies to the request.
Now,
but what is the abstraction?
Right?
This is kind of,
how do we manipulate this kind of connection?
And remember that one of the big things about unix is that everything looks
like a file,
right?
Or it's abstract with very similar abstractions.
The same is true for communication,
like we saw for pipes.
Last time.
Pipes.
Again, it's how you communicate between two processes on the same machine.
Here are sockets about how you come,
how do two processes on different machines communicate with each other.
But they are very similar that the abstraction is very similar,
and is looking like a fire.
And this kind of abstraction for communication is called a socket.
This is how you do it.
Right?
If you want to send some data,
the processor sender is a client call or write system function call,
which passes a descriptor.
This is a soccer descriptor,
a buffer in the length of the buffer.
And the receiver or the server.
It's calling the read operation with a file descriptor and aa
buffer where it can receive the data on the size of the buffer.
To make sure that if it's more data,
the operating system doesn't overflow that buffer.
Right?
The circuits is the endpoint of communication, right?
And the cures are in between here somewhere along.
Actually,
there are many queues in the network that choosing
the operating system queues as the routers along the path
between the sender and the receiver.
It's pretty complicated.
We are going to learn more about that.
But in general,
the things to for you to know that are accused, there are cues,
one of the simplest reasons,
one of simple motivation for cures is to, again,
because the client or the two end points,
they don't have the same speed sending and receiving.
If you receive at a lower speed,
they need to buffer the data or that the receiver at that time,
maybe is doing something else.
And he cannot receive the data right away.
So now,
the circuits you have two sockets connected over the network,
one of the sender,
and on the receiver or one circuit for each endpoint.
Now,
the sockets, you remember,
what do you do with sockets?
Right?
It's like, what is a typical?
What is a pattern?
Programming pattern?
You open, you read,
if you have a file descriptor,
like you open the file, a script,
or you read right from the file, a script,
and then you close the file list.
So we need to learn about how to open and close are also these sockets.
Let me see,
here is a question is a communication between two processes,
actually communication between the threat of the processes.
This is, so anyone wants to answer that question?
The communication it's about is between two processes.
But remember, the process is a container.
Right?
You have the other place,
other space,
and it provides a protection.
But the actual unit of execution or concurrency is a thread.
Each thread, each process is at least one thread.
So it's correct to say that the processes communicate.
But it's also say it's correct to say that always to stress communicate,
because the things which are going to run the code inside this process are
the threads.
Typically, when you have one thread and one process,
you just interchangeable.
You can use process or thread,
but hopefully that answers the question.
Okay?
It is a hidden abstraction for socket io what we are going to talk about here,
it's pretty much,
at least in the next couple of slides about,
actually, is how you are going to use a socket interface.
Right?
So
like we discuss the circuit is an abstraction for on end point of the network.
If you have do you have, in general,
you have two processes to end points communicate with each other.
Each of them is going to have a socket.
And somehow you need to connect these two sockets to each other.
If you want to establish a connection,
it was introduced first in berkeley standard distribution version 4.2.
That is one of the biggest contributions
of actually open source contribution of berkeley,
because has huge impact.
And the story here is that then the runners like during those days,
you distribute these operating systems through tapes.
And the things here is that it's about how you are going to.
Then there are people waiting in line for the tapes to be copied.
Therefore, to take it back to their companies,
to install the new version of unix,
to which with this kind of dcpipa code in it.
A this is a beautiful thing is that this is the local, again,
it's like it's the abstraction for a lot of kind of networks,
not networks type of when I say a lot of kind of networks i'm talking about,
all boss about how how they are physically implemented.
They are over fiber,
they are over satellite cellular networks.
It abstracts away what kind of your application on your iphone.
It doesn't knew, it doesn't know that you are on a solar network, right?
Or you are a wifi, right?
Doesn't know.
That means abstraction in that case.
Or there are also about how packets are rooted in the network
and many other things.
Lower level of the network stack resource,
apple dog and ipx and the great thing about this tcpip it becomes an effect
of standard of how
nodes communicate over the internet.
Right?
This is what enables the internet at the end of the day.
And again, when I say the vector standard,
I say because it doesn't,
it was a piece of gold.
It was not a standard body to create it,
but it's a standard now because everyone is using it.
If you don't use the cpip you cannot talk with other as a noise in the internet.
Okay?
The sockets,
you'll see,
it's a little bit more elaborated interface.
But at the end of the day, you need to open,
you need to create a socket.
You can close a socket in between you read and read and write.
Now,
Everything is a file descriptor,
like we discussed, but loss also, if you remember,
like we discussed,
although you have every everything is file escaped out,
you don't have for each device.
You don't have all the comments,
like you have four file systems, right?
For right?
For five system, you remember you have a sick, right?
You can reposition the pointer from what you read in a particular file.
I can lc and I can read from the 100 bytes in the file, right?
Is still,
the abstraction is still aa stream of bites, right?
But I can reposition.
Here.
You cannot have sick, right?
You send up, have you send the bias and you receive that?
Or in the same order?
It is kind of strange to be out.
I want to read the 100 bytes, right?
Maybe that 100 bytes is not even your computer haven't received it.
So you don't have lc your abstraction is just a cube right?
In.
First out,
you always get the but data in the order.
And if you sent the other thing what happens is
under the hood is abstracted away is that you don't over the network,
you don't send us small bikes, right?
You actually put it in packages in your package it.
You divide the data,
you have to send your package it in a pack.
Each packet will have addresses, right?
Because it depends on this tells another where is the packet should be delivered.
Right?
It's like you put amazon is using trucks and each truck now says an address,
the driver where it should deliver the packages.
Right?
Something like that.
The many need also some kind of like rbc kind of facility to,
for instance,
because the data format,
which is understand by the receiver,
is not as the same as the data format,
which is understood,
understand by the senate.
Right?
And you'll talk about this is big indian,
little indian kind of different formats,
different for different processors.
This is a very simple example echo server.
Hello, world echo mean,
I am sending is a message to the server.
The server is going to send me the message back.
Right?
So here is how things that are happening, right?
You have a client on the seller on the left hand side,
stubborn on the right hand side.
You have with this also the data points at the time here goes from top
to the bottom.
You have this kind of this green rectangles shows about the
life lifetime of socket,
both on the client side and the several side.
Soccer starts with being open and close, right?
Okay?
Once you open and close the socket,
the server should be ready to receive data.
What the server is doing then, well,
is calling a a a read,
the read system command on the corresponding socket descriptor of that
connection and provide a buffer where the operating system should pass
the data it receives.
Okay?
The clients say it do f gets to get from the standard input,
from you can type the message.
And we want to send that message, right?
How you send a message like we discussed, you do your color,
right?
And you pass the socket file descriptors on from the come from the same communication.
And on the center side of the client side,
and you pass a buffer,
you want to send out right now.
And then you want to read back.
Right?
Not is that both the reads are blocking.
In this particular case,
there are variants of fields calls,
which are not blocking.
But here we ask, by default, we assume is blocking.
We need to you block until you get some data.
Right?
The client writes as a message,
and then ways to get some a reply back,
that message may be chopped in different packets.
The packets are sent over the internet.
Actually, each packet can can take a different path.
And the set of the server gets the data.
Maybe rights show it on the screen,
is doing some print types or something like that.
And then you write it back to the socket.
So you want to send it back to as a client.
And the client, as I read,
it's, again, I was writing into it.
A call is going to get the message back and is going to print on the screen.
Again, the same as we are talking here about an echo server.
Right?
Cooperation.
Let me see if there's another question.
Rpc what it stands,
danny asked about,
what does rpc stands for?
Rpc stands for remote procedure call.
This is a higher level.
And again, we'll learn about it.
And we just mentioned a little bit about it in a previous lecture.
But this is about think about you want to call a function.
And that function,
instead of executing locally,
it's executing on a different machine.
And you want to just set the syntax.
And ideally the semantics,
although we learn that's not really possible to be
very similar with invoking a local function call you want,
how you invoke a local function,
aa remote function,
to look very similar with how you invoke a local function.
So rpc tries to bridge that gap and make them very similar.
Okay.
That's we have a bunch of code here.
I'm not going to go through every line of code.
We don't have time.
But we'll try to cover as much as possible,
but i'm saying that if i'm not going,
and maybe you have questions, please ask me.
But it's not my intention to go through each line.
This is about for the previous examples,
how the code look like, right?
This is typically how the code look like, right?
It's like this is the cloud client.
You are in the y loop.
You get some message typed by the user.
You send it to the server,
the server send it back and you print it.
Right?
This is what you do.
You get them as you get,
as a message you write to the socket.
You read it back,
and you write to the you print it out.
Before you read it back,
you clear the buffer so that it's not the message.
You just send it just in the buffer.
You clearly to know that what you have in the buffer is what you receive
from the setup.
The server is very similar.
You read.
Then I think it's a mistake in this code.
They should be if land less than zero.
So this is how much you read.
If land is less than zero,
this means that it's an error.
If land is greater than zero.
So this land actually let me just try to,
okay,
you read it is a server reads data from the socket.
If it's greater less than zero, it's an error.
You return greater than zero.
You print it to the terminal,
and then you send it back to the client.
Right?
You echo what you got from the client.
This is a sand from the client and the corresponding received from the server.
This is a corresponding send from the sender,
from the server as a corresponding received from the client.
Very simple.
So now we are making some assumptions,
which are actually, this is,
in some sense,
the assumption we are making here is about what is the networking field about,
is about how to ensure that these assumptions are true, are standing.
So I know the assumption we make is that the data when you is not lost,
right?
You send it over the network,
and the receiver gets all the data.
There's a scent of sand.
It's like a local pipe, right?
But this is difficult because this is internet is probably the biggest
and the most complex,
a system that humans build in some sense.
And there are many things can go wrong in between.
So making,
providing to the applications and no matter what happens under the hood is
a network.
The data which is sent by some of the client gets to the server
without being lost is not easy fit.
The other thing you have is that it's, again, remember,
this is the abstraction.
It's a stream.
The radar abstraction is a stream.
So this means that the water in which you send the data is the order
in which the receiver gets the rape.
If you write x and write y then this receiver reads first x and then gets five.
Right?
When you ask for a read,
you get what it's ever at that time.
So basically say,
if you write, for instance,
so this is very important.
So if you write,
say, 1,000 bytes,
actually, the receiver can get,
he can get it in a bunch of 100 bytes.
Right?
So if you get every time on hundred bytes,
you need to read10 times to get the entire content.
That if nothing,
it's arrived after is on the connection,
you are blocking like we discussed.
And there's a semantics,
pretty much like pipes.
But now it's over another instead of a single note.
Now, so we had a single getting more interesting.
It's about how do you create these sockets, right?
And basically, it's you need to,
if you think about with files is simple, right?
With files,
you have a name and of the file and the open that the file is
that particular name.
And that's independent of the processes so easy tonight, right?
How do you do in pipes?
Do you remember?
How do you do?
How does, for instance,
when ii guess it's the slide is already saying.
But how do you do it in with pipes against the pipes?
Processes runs on the same machine.
If you are going to communicate between the parent and the child,
then it's easier, right?
Because a child, remember,
inherits all the file descriptors of the parrot.
So already, now,
the file descriptors corresponding to a pie.
So now,
with the sockets,
there are two things, one,
and like a pipe.
If you remember this one way communication with sockets,
you have two way communication.
Right?
You need both the sender and the receiver being able to send data to each other.
You'll see a little bit.
Why is that?
And the processes are separate,
right?
Are on different machines.
So they cannot communicate otherwise.
So how can they agree?
Or how do I know to what other process I need to communicate?
That that's kind of is a crux of the problem.
It's anemic.
How do independent to independent programs know how to talk with each other?
Again, we discuss a little bit about at the beginning of the class.
But in the internet,
the way you are going to name,
it's basically using these dns names, right?
And this is an example.
Again, we are going to have a lecture.
We are going to talk more about that,
but for now is ww dot pcs not very clear,
dot edo you have a domain name medium,
and then it's a top domain,
and then berkeley the institutions.
And it's a department.
And this is a protocol.
This application level protocol.
Again, dcp and ipadcp and udp are transfer level protocols.
But then under the hood,
at the transport level,
this is what application of this is what you can type in the browser,
ww dot google dot com.
Right?
This is what application understands.
The transfer layer,
the tcp doesn't understand this.
What understands are ip addresses.
There is, a way,
is dns name resolution by which is dns names or the horse names
are translated into these ip addresses.
But when we are going to operate at this level,
typically we are going to operate with the ip addresses.
An ip address.
It used to have several beats.
You still have in many parts of the world.
It's still dominant.
And this is ip ip before it's ipeip stands for internet protocol.
V four version four,
32 beats.
This was from the beginning of the internet.
Then we ran out of addresses because ipp four,
you have you have several to be,
so you can have only 4 billion addresses.
Now we have ipv six,
and it took probably 20 or more years to start and to kind of get
up to speed with the transition from ipv four and ipv six.
And ivv six has 128 bits.
A lot of this,
we won't run out of them.
Now, in addition to the addresses,
you have what are called poor numbers.
And I probably there are people here who took networking.
So can anyone answer what why do we need a port number?
What is the port number?
Allison, very good.
So multiple services run on the same cost host.
So it's very simple.
These ip addresses name a host,
name a computer,
name a machine.
But a machine, like, we know,
runs multiple processes.
And your code to receive data runs in one of this process.
So you don't need only to identify a host.
You also need to identify the process to which you are going to send.
And from the network perspective,
that process is identify by a port number is not identified.
It is not by outside as a computer,
is not identified by the process id it's by these four numbers for numbers
as to 16 bits.
The first beats the first 1,023 ports are well known,
meaning that they are well known services.
What does it mean?
80 for 80 is typically for a web web browser.
So if you've got 80s and it's typically a web browser,
listen on the port 80 to get all the packets,
which are coming to that host.
They say they are looking for part eight.
Now,
when you have aa server, right?
And remember what we have this figure early on,
we have multiple clients talking with a server.
Okay.
How does the server can talk with multiple clients?
How does it now which packets come from each client?
That's a problem.
Right?
The way we take care of that is very simple.
The server doesn't communicate with each client.
The server only ways from each client to connect.
And when it connects,
the server creates another process,
which communicates with a client.
Okay?
That's kind of the idea.
We are going to reiterate on this idea,
hopefully will be clear by the end of this lecture.
But that's what happened.
That's about.
So the client created socket and connect the setup request.
But again, it doesn't send just a message, a request.
I have the request, give me a reply.
The client sends a connection request to create a connection first.
And only after he has a connection,
you can send, sorry,
you are going to send the data and your request.
The server listens.
It's in the state of always listen for new connections,
accept the connection.
And now it creates a a new con,
aa new socket.
This socket can be in a different process,
or can be in in a different thread in the same process.
We'll see that.
Now you have a connection socket for this client.
Now you are going to send information about this connection socket,
and you established.
Now, a connection between the client socket and socket on the server side,
which is special for that client.
This is what happens, right?
Each connection, this yellow thing here, right?
Between these two green bubbles,
it's identified by five sinks,
source ip address,
destination ip address, right?
These are the source and the destination.
When you send a packet,
you have the source,
ip address of machine,
the ip address of the machine who a sends a packet,
the destination ip the ip address of the receiver machine,
then you have the poor numbers is a poor numbers of the process who sent
the data
and send the destination port number.
The rest is the port number of the process who receives the data
as a new protocol type.
Now here is a protocol type.
It's tcp in this lecture,
like we discuss, also you can have udp user data ground protocol.
Let me see it's another question.
Ii think probably I missed this.
Actually, as this question,
isn't this also a problem for processes on the same computer?
How will one identify the other pid so basically about how do I identify
the processes?
So,
yes, so depends.
So on the same machine,
the problem is not about only how do I identify,
but how you are sharing the identification.
For instance, on a machine,
you have access to the pid and you can identify everything by pid
on the same machine.
If you want to send to make apid not to let one process
about know about identify another process.
There are many ways to do it.
Right?
One way, simple ways to write that in a file.
Basically, you have like the cuba land of a server on your machine.
You want to now say the pid of that one.
You always when you start that server on that machine,
you write the pid in a file.
So that one, but by the way,
by the way, the one important things to know is that while here,
I am always repeating and repeating and repeating that the sender
and the receivers are on two different or are two different notes,
they can also be on the same machine.
It's going to work.
You can use dcp to run to communicate between two processes on the same machine.
Okay, no problem.
Yes, sir.
Good.
So in order to know the server,
what do you need to know?
Right?
Again, you need to know about its ip address.
And then the port numbers on which this server is listening.
And typically against the well known services,
they have well known ports like port 80.
Send mail is 25 and things like that.
Right?
And this is now means that everyone knows if it's an old server running
on one machine with this address,
that website will run on board date.
Okay?
So now let's go a little bit more details about how things are happened.
To see how this new connection are created.
The server,
you create a socket,
and you bind it to a local address to another,
which is the local address of the machine, typically,
and a port.
Right?
If your website about,
you bind it to port eight,
and then you listen for connection from the clients.
You get a connection,
you accept it.
Right?
Now let's move to the client side.
On the client side.
I create a socket.
Then I connect to the server,
specifying the host,
ip address and the port number.
It's a host and support.
Number two is a server has bind it.
Right?
This is a little bit of pattern we saw before.
You send a client send a connection request to the server,
which was listening and the server accept and send back,
accept calls and now and new,
and creates also a socket, the server.
And now you have a connection.
Now the server goes to read into it,
blocks into it.
And the client writes, so eventually,
when the data written by the client gets to the server,
the server read it and write a response.
The client reads a response.
And then at the end,
you close the socket.
Right?
If you can see about,
everyone is closing, the socket was a client and a server.
And the client has create the socket.
This is a cuban with an open.
And the equivalent socket,
which is the server creates two sockets,
one on which is listening for requests, for new connections.
And then when it's going to accept a request for connection,
is going to create a socket for that connection.
So seek, accept,
cisco is going to create a socket for that connection,
the connection corresponding to the connection request from the client.
Here is a question.
How do you have multiple web servers on the same machine?
Is there is only one port.
Typically, you don't have multiple web servers on the same machine.
If you want to have multiple web servers on the same machine,
you have to assign them to a different numbers.
And by this web number numbers,
you need to tell other clients what the new poor numbers are.
Like.
For instance, typically,
another poor number website values.
If it's not 80, it's 8080.
I didn't say that.
But this the well known port number from 0 to 1 to 1,023,
you can only bind them if you have a rude privileges.
Right?
If you are just user,
you cannot bind on the sports.
And so if you want to use to run the website about only as a user,
typically people put 88 the port number.
A few questions here?
Another question?
No answer the question.
Sorry.
Pipes are one way.
You need to create two pipes,
you want to communicate both ways.
There is another answer for allison.
If you have multiple websites on the same server,
you can do it at the application layer.
Http requests have the horse header,
which tells the server I want to talk to excite.
And the server can just send back the eyesight.
That's a little bit more complicated.
I guess everything is possible in software.
But typically, this is,
you can have the content distribution networks.
They do something like you propose here.
We'll talk a little bit about that later.
But for now, if you, again,
the one thing to know is that if you really want to run multiple observers
on the same,
not only the same house,
you need to provide different phone numbers.
This is a client protocol a little bit in more details.
This is how you create the socket.
Right?
Remember.
And when you create a socket, first of all,
you create this kind of addressing from address, info,
data structure.
When you provide the horse name and the port name,
then you create the socket by using this data structure just graded.
And it has three things.
Typically, you can add more address family.
You basically, this is whether it's ipp ipp six or something else set up.
You can have ice.
You have soccer stream type here.
It's a sock stream or soccer diagram.
Soccer stream.
This is a stream of bytes, the data ground,
right?
Is something we are not discussing,
which is udp in udp you don't send a stream of bytes.
You send packets,
then you have,
it's also pcp it says this is a protocol type,
so this is can be like dcp zero.
You can have any protocol.
Then you connect,
this is a connection request.
You say,
if you define the server address and the phone number,
then you run the client code on that file descriptor, soccer descriptor,
and your clothes.
Right?
Again, the ceremony here,
just to make sure that I I didn't say something wrong.
The server here,
when you do the look of,
you basically provide the host name.
This is a server name and the server port number.
This is what you provide in this server.
What you're doing is several data structure.
And for the server protocol,
it's a little bit more involved.
You create a socket.
You brought you give the poor name where you want to bind to each one
to bind this server,
and then you bind this server to the typically to the local address
and the port number.
Then you listen for connection requests.
Now, what you do,
you go into a loop,
and when you get a connection request, you accept it,
you create a socket.
This is connect socket.
And then you serve the client and you close the socket.
Eventually,
when the server ends,
then you also close the server socket,
but the server socket is the one on which you are listening.
Remember.
So then now you are going to have requests from different clients.
We saw that for each of requests,
for each request connection,
we are going to create a different socket on the server side.
Now, where is a code running on the server side?
Going?
Where is the code running on the server side going to run?
What is this set of client going put up?
You see here?
Where is that going?
Put up?
There are multiple ways,
multiple methods here.
One, if you want to really protect yourself about The client,
sending you something stupid or send,
and you you do some bad things.
It causes you to do some bad things.
You can do it.
You can run that code in a separate process.
You remember the processes as the unit of protection.
Right?
Processes are protected from each other, right?
In this particular case,
the idea you have a connection when accepts is called create a connection socket.
You are going to create a child,
and you are going to answer the client between in the child.
While the parent doesn't do anything,
it may be ways for the child to finish.
Right?
So this is a scout on the several side.
You accept not all the code.
It's only in the while loop.
You accept as a connection request,
then you for remember,
if the result of the four pid is zero,
this means that you are here executing what?
The child code, right?
The child, it's closed the server socket.
This is a socket, only the server listen for new connections.
So the child only needs to reply to the client,
so he's not going to listen for new clients, right?
Then you set of the client and you also close is a connection to that client.
And you exit on the server side,
on the pattern side,
which is a server itself.
You close a connection socket,
you because you are not going to communicate directly with our client.
The child is going to communicate and then wait while the weight is going
great for the child to finish.
And then at the end,
you close the server connection, right?
So to summarize a in a server,
you listen for connection requests.
If there are multiple requests at the same time,
they are going to be cured.
And then you create connections and then use this connection to communicate
with a child.
Okay?
This is aa server because it leads an increased connection for his child.
Can answer at the same time to mark can talk at the same time
with multiple clients.
Okay?
One potential thing here is that in this code, like I said,
the parent, this is a parent code in this else on the else branch.
You wait for the child to finish,
but if you wait for the child to finish,
then you cannot listen,
and you cannot satisfy other connection requests.
So actually, if you write this code,
the server, although you have a different process for the connection,
you cannot accept new connections.
So you are talking with one client at a time.
So what is the fix here?
The fix is very simple.
Don't wait to go back, don't wait.
And that go like if you had a server,
go back and accept be ready to accept new new connection requests from new clients.
Okay?
This is address how you set up the address again.
I'm not going to go from.
So details you have the same things like socks stream is like,
it's a data stream.
This is what you have for pcp this is you don't specify the ip ib family
and things like that.
But again,
a it's a boiler plate code to set up this address information data structure.
This is a boiler.
It's from the client side.
This is how you set the address.
And this is how you get the address of the server from the client.
Right?
You get it from,
you specify the host name and the port name.
You get the address information,
including the ip address of the server.
Now,
so far,
I said that you can provide concurrency if you run and you for each client,
you on the several side,
you have a different process to talk with that client.
Now you have concurrency because processes can run concurrently.
But now the problem is processes what it is that they provide protection,
but they are heavyweight.
If you want to provide concurrency,
but more heavyweight and you are not as concerned about protection.
What you do.
You can use threads,
right?
The thread.
You can have multiple thread in the same process.
Now,
what you are going to do when you are going to accept a connection request
from a client,
and you are created creating a socket,
you are going to spawn a thread.
But if you spawn a thread,
what is a problem right now?
This was also in the case of that,
when you use the processes,
what is the problem?
Right?
See any problem here.
What if you have many clients?
You can have actually an attack.
I can have many clients opening new connections and never closing them
and exhausted that is.
But in this way, exhaust resources on the 7th side, how do you do that?
What is the solution here?
The solution here is to create what is called a thread.
So you create a bunch of threads, say,
100 threads,
which means that a given time you can talk concurrently of with 100 clients.
What if there are more than 100 plants?
They have to wait for some of the current clients you are talking with to finish,
and the leads a threat.
This is a concept, and it's a very useful concept about the threat pull.
And the main goal of the third world is to protect the resources
of the server from being
exhausted very soon.
How do you have that?
You have,
you have to hear a master thread and the master thread.
This is actually the server,
which is going where the code of the server which is waiting
for the connection request,
runs a when you create,
when you create a connect,
when you accept a connection request and you create a socket,
then you put that you incur a request.
Now is the request for a thread.
You ask for a thread.
This is nq to the cube of threads, the connection.
Right?
You can the wake up the queue.
This is another thread,
actually, which basically you will keep you wake up to run the code.
And on the huge side,
you are going to look at the connection you dick,
you from the queue.
And if the connection,
if connection is not known, it's not,
this means there is nothing in the cure.
So you'll just go to sleep.
And that's why the master needs to wake you up, right?
As you set up the web page.
So i'm going to have the announcement before.
Then.
Let's see.
What are the other questions?
Does this newly creative process start listening for new requests as well?
Now,
this is a great question.
Now the new creative requests do not.
And i'm going to show you the code.
You see,
here,
again, the new creative process.
It's a child.
And this is a code under the pid equals zero,
which is executed by the child.
The first thing the child is doing is closing the server socket.
The server socket is the one only the server listen for new connections.
So this tells you this instruction tells you right away that the client
that the child doesn't
listen for new connection to be created.
The only role of child,
the child is to deal with a connection to the client.
It was associated, too.
Okay.
Let me see.
Wait for the threats to join
if you create a new threat and you have to wait towards the threat to join,
because the strategy is a process.
So if the process goes away,
then just the thread you created is going to go away.
Right?
So you need like someone like christian or simon said,
you need to wait for the strategy joints.
Oops,
announcement project one,
the design documents are due to friday.
This friday, the design reviews are going to happen next week,
and keep a look out on piazza for sign ups.
You are going to sign with your pa to probably give the pa will provide.
You is a feedback on your design.
And the design is something very important design documents.
But I you may not have been used with this in other classes.
But in this class,
before you start writing the first lines of code,
you are going to write a design document.
That is as a theory.
Therefore, it's going to force you to think about about the design.
And then the idea is,
at once you have a good design document and you got the feedback,
you address the feedback,
you'll have a much easier job to write and finish your project,
to do your project,
sing more or less, something like that.
By the way,
probably with the people that many of you you want did summer internships
at software engineering companies,
very well that everywhere you need to have a design document
before your eyes a code.
This is great practice for your next job.
Even if you do the next thing, you are going to do,
you do aphd still,
the design documents are great.
The homework one is beyond thursday,
and the midterm is due in15 days,
5 to 6 spam,
or it will be 2 weeks from now.
2 weeks from tomorrow.
Sorry, and it will be online and propped out,
and we'll get more details,
will get more details next week.
Okay.
Now for the last 15 minutes,
we are going to switch gears,
and we are going to talk about a very important topic,
synchronization.
And we are only going to start here about synchronization, concurrency,
and synchronization.
Everything starts from the need to multiplex processes.
Right?
And you need to run multiple activities concurrently.
Like we've seen just a few minutes ago that if we want a server to handle
multiple clients at the same time,
the way is doing it either using processes or multiple threads running
at the same time.
Where is thread or processes is associated with the client?
Good.
Now, again,
remember, for the and thine, right,
is like a process is a unit of protection.
It has another space which is protected from other processes.
And the processes is represented by the process control block.
We talk a little bit about that.
If you remember,
this process control block has all the state that represents that process.
In short, if you save that state,
then you can restart the process from that state as if nothing had happened.
So what do you have?
It has a status.
We'll see what is the status where there is a process of running radio block?
You have some register state one,
not ready process id some some other information,
like the cushion pain of time, memory space.
This is a big one, the memory of the process, right?
It has to be summer.
You need one memo you are using.
You have to know it.
Translation, how you translate.
Remember, you have virtual memory,
the process since it is a virtual memory.
But the data is starting in physical memory.
You need to translate between the address of the virtual memory
to the physical memory.
You need to have this translation paper.
Again, why do you need to define this contrast state?
It's because this allows, again,
you the process to be to switch between processes.
Right?
You save, you give a process.
If you save all these states,
associating the bcb is a process.
And then you can give the cpu to another process to run.
And then you can come back to the preview to the previous process.
And we started from the same place so to speak by using all the information
in the pcp
and this is what happens,
right?
This is how you are going to multiplex.
For instance, once if you between two processes,
p zero and p one,
this is what you do it from p zero.
You want to switch from p zero to p one.
The operating system is going to save the state of the pcp zero in pcp zero.
Then is going to reduce to load the state of process b one from pcb one.
Then it's going to run the process to run process beyond.
And then at some.,
when the time quanta for that process beyond expired,
or when it's waiting for something,
then is going to do the same thing.
But the other way around is going to save the pcb one over the state
of process b one in pcb one,
and then reload the state of p zero and pcp zero,
and then resume the execution of p zero.
That's all.
This is operating system.
High level of privilege,
meaning that this code cannot be executed by the applications.
All of these yellow stuff,
what are those function calls interrupts?
Now you remember that here,
we are talking about the status of the process in the PCB this is a status.
This is a state or the state of the process.
A process first is created,
then is put in the queue if he's ready to execute,
from the cure,
from being ready to execute,
it can go in the running state.
Ready to run is running,
and can terminate,
or it can be interrupted.
Right?
For instance, it's time quant expired.
So it's put again back in the real estate.
Or is doing an io event,
is waiting for is doing it,
waiting from some data from the network to get some data from the network.
Right?
Now you are annoying state.
Again, you are no longer running.
When you are going to get the data you are waiting for,
you are going to be in a real estate, so you can run again.
Right?
So we have also the animation.
So look, process is created.
You are going to go into any state here.
You can run when the processor,
when the CPU is available,
then you run, you can get an interrupt,
like I mentioned when your time.expired.
And then those are multiple times like we saw in the previous slide.
You can switch between p zero and p one, right?
Then you can,
if you execute and I operation,
the process can wait,
should wait no longer running when the weight ends,
because it got the data, for instance,
for which is waiting for going to a real estate.
You run for a little bit again,
and then you are done exit.
The scheduling.
This is just a part is ridicule.
And the scheduling.
Basically, what is the scheduler?
What is the role of the scheduler?
Right?
We talk about the scheduler picks, which one do you want?
Ready?
Process to run?
Next?
That's it.
Okay.
And here you see that once you run,
there are multiple ways you can stop running.
Like I said, time slice expires.
You are doing an io request and you need to wait for that to come to Complete.
You can fork a child or you can wait for interact like for instance,
yeah,
from a diamond interrupt or interrupt from the keyboard or something like that.
Ok let me see about examples.
Questions?
Sorry.
Why do we need struggles?
Can we just create thread as request comes?
Philip, so what happens if you have 11 million requests?
Each thread actually consumed resources.
So that far as at some.,
you exhaust the resources of a machine.
And then everything becomes extremely slow.
You get trash.
You want to avoid that.
Ramirez, assuming one CPU,
how does a kernel ensure each process is run smoothly?
Is there a timer for when the scheduler interrupts for each PCB?
That's correct.
This is the one time slice expires.
So the time slice the kernels, they typically have, say,
10 million seconds or 1 million seconds.
A process or a set, actually,
the thread runs when I say a process.
In this case, I am using interchangeably.
But the process like thread runs,
it can run only up to, say,
10 millisecond or 1 millisecond.
When that expires,
the process is or is swapped out.
No question.
How is the process PCB distinct from the threat control block?
The PCB,
it's again, contains a state associated with a process.
It's a lot of more state.
Like, for instance, the state about the memory,
the pages,
and the translations.
It's also contains a file descriptors.
Okay?
The thread, it's only touring the thread control block.
It's only typically registers and the stack.
Right?
It's much smaller.
Hopefully answer the question.
Okay.
If the process is not running,
is PCB which represents a process in the kernel,
is in some schedule cube,
may be waiting for the eye operation to Complete or waiting
for an interrupt or things like that.
Okay?
And each queue, again,
can have different scheduling policies about how you are going to set
of the next
PCB from that queue.
This is already queue.
Here represent, you have this kind of each node,
represent one process.
You see, here is apcb this is a cure for this device.
You can have for the USB for the disk.
If and this is for networking,
there is nothing there.
Now, for the list, for in this case,
we have two processes which are waiting to operate,
which are operate awaiting to operate a read or write on that disk.
The kernel will decide with what is the other news that are going to be scheduled?
That request is as going to be satisfied.
Okay?
And the same for the network.
So the schedule is actually,
the core is very simple.
Like this is for the ready process, right?
You go to the ready process.
Is there any process?
It's already process?
You if the queue is not empty, so what does it mean?
You select the process.
This is what?
From the queue.
This is a scheduling operation.
And you get the next the PCB of the next process to schedule.
And you run the next PCB.
Otherwise, you are idle because there is no process to be scheduled.
The process, like I mentioned,
the scheduling is a mechanism for deciding which process or thread to run
on the CPU there are lots of different scheduling policies.
There are thousand tens of thousands of papers on scheduling policies,
because there are different properties you want to enforce may be fairness
between different application or processes.
Provide real time, guarantees blood, latency,
optimization and things like that.
And remember that actually,
the part which is running from a process,
it's kind of is that thread.
That's the active component.
Other space is passive, its protection,
its protection.
Why have multiple threads where other space we already knew?
Now that we saw that an example,
you can have one thread for each connection for each client.
This again share is showing you the share the state between the trading
the same process.
And then but stress states,
right?
Is a strength control block and you have registers a stack Information.
That's pretty much it.
While the shared state,
you have global variables,
the hips and memories of code, and things like that.
The core of the concurrency is this dispatch loop, right?
Is a loop.
You run the strategy, choose an extra,
save the state.
This is now is written in terms of the threads at the Serena ID but this is
exactly what this core,
this loop in the kernel is doing.
You run the current thread,
then when that thread terminates or it's interrupted,
because the timer and so forth,
you choose an extra that I from the queue.
You save the thread,
the state of the current thread,
and the state of the new thread.
Now you run the new set.
This is an infinite look, like you never stop.
Okay.
Let's stop here.
And let me see any other question?
No, more questions.
So let's stop here.
Like on the..
Good luck with the homework,
the good luck with the project.
And let me know if you have any other questions.
If not, I'm going to see you all on Thursday.
I have a great day.