Hello, everyone.
Welcome to the seven lectures.
So today we are going to continue our discussion about concurrency.
This will happen also over the next couple of lectures,
as well as we are going to discuss about lock implementation,
which is one of the main primitives helping us or is controlling concurrence.
Remember about, again,
this picture.
Excuse me,
it's basically we are going to have a program.
And here what we are trying to do is about it's how this program we
is going to give,
yield the axis,
the cpu to another product.
Right?
If you remember, this was the old examples.
Each one of the first examples,
you have two instructions.
The first one,
trying to print to compute pie and print pie.
Then the second instruction trying to bring the class list,
if I remember correctly.
And the point there is that if you try to print by,
which means also need to compute all the digits,
you'll never end,
because spy has an infinite number of decimals, right?
Then the solution was that while you are computing by,
you are the one to give from a time to time,
access to the cpu to another process to continue other.
Otherwise, the cpu will be only hauled by this computer by program.
Now yield.
It's a system call and the system call.
It's going to result in a trap to the kernel.
And the kernel will then take over.
And it will suspend the current program thread.
And that on the new one,
this is a pseudo code, very simple.
So this kind of you see that on your thread,
this is what is a function run by the kernel,
which basically picks a new thread and switch from the current thread,
which is in blue here to the new stretch,
and is doing some housekeeping and some clean up.
When he's going to do this,
update some counters at the time,
as a for instance,
a thread run and things like that.
Now the question, obviously, the key is like,
there are two things we want to understand.
It's like how to pick any thread and how you are going to switch
from the current thread to the new thread.
And if you remember, obviously,
in order to do that,
we need to save the state of the current thread.
And then to initialize the registers of the processor,
the bc counter,
with the values, with the state of the new thread,
and then execute that new thread.
Okay?
One of these111 important part of the state of a thread, if you remember,
is a stack, right?
And let's look a little bit more into more details about these four simple examples.
If you are going to have two functions,
a and ba calls b and b is that executive look.
Within that loop, you yield every time you execute the loop.
Right?
And suppose that we have two threads,
s and d and running this program.
Both of them run this program.
Thread as right,
is called function a here.
This is on the stack.
You remember that the stack grows from the high addresses to the lower addresses.
On the stack,
you are going to have the return values as a return address after executive
to the function,
as well.
As when you call a function,
you are going to put on the stack,
the argument for that function.
Here there are no arguments,
but that happens, in general, right?
You have a first which you call you put on the stack,
then b and this is a one which execute a while loop,
and then is going to execute and run yield.
And then,
again,
yield is going to to call the operating system and the operating system.
It's going to execute the run new thread and switch to the new thread.
And when you switch is going to run the other thread feel.
He said that we have to thread in the system, right?
And the threes,
the new thread will basically they could the same thing.
And the example is going to execute a and b and b whenever it's going to execute.
So while is going to yield,
go again, you go to the operating system,
and then your ping pong between the two threats.
Okay?
This is what we have.
Now, it's, again,
like one thing we need to do in when you are going to switch
from the current strategies and you thread is we need to
save the state of the current stretch,
right?
What does it mean?
This is that registers.
You see, r zero to r seven is that registers.
And then sp is a stack pointer.
And cpu is a return, a pointer.
This is the pointer of the next instruction we should be executed when I
am going to resume the execution of this thread.
Okay?
Now the next thing we need to now to take care of the new thread,
we are going to update the register of the processor,
the stack pointers,
npc with a new.
We started a with a state corresponding state of the new of the new thread
we want to run.
And by the way,
you see where this state it's stored, what is stored.
It's in dcb it's thread control block.
I hope this kind of makes sense,
and this will be pretty simple.
Right?
Now, obviously, you need to be careful and implement that.
And by the way, if you have any questions,
let me know i'll be happy to answer as always.
So you need to be very careful, right?
I for instance,
if you forget to save or store a particular register, say,
and register study too,
then what will happen?
Right?
Something that happened,
what happens?
It will very much depend about whether the value is that register
is going to be used by the program.
If it's not going to be used,
nothing will happen.
But if it's going to be used,
you are going to see probably a random is a random results or random failures.
You will say, why wouldn't you then start?
You test carefully the entire code?
Is that testing the entire code,
especially passing its exhaustively?
It's very difficult because there are many combinations.
Why is there are many combinations?
There are many combinations because you a thread can be interrupted anywhere.
So if you have a thread,
which is you have 1,000 instructions,
it can be interrupted after each of these instructions.
Right?
You have another strategy and other ones of the instructions.
Now you have combination about where you are going to interrupt the first thread,
and we are going to resume the second thread like 1 million.
Right?
There are many stories about errors.
In some cases, you are found after a long time,
like, for instance, in this case,
it was aa very early kernel top,
as you can see,
based on the sale on the size.
It was obviously very well tested.
But it was one thing.
What happened is that it was one instruction,
one correctly saving the state of a thread,
depending of whether the kernel size was less than one megabyte,
initially was the less than one megabyte, right?
But over time, like with any software,
the size increased.
And people are developers forgot about this limitation.
And when it did happen and the size increase overall megabyte,
then they start to get superiors errors.
This kind of like we'll discuss,
this kind of errors are also very hard to to the back,
because they are not deterministic.
Be honest again, like when you design be very,
very careful design, for simplicity, simple code,
it's easier to check than more complex code and all.
Now,
one of the question is about we are switching between when are switching
between two threads.
We are also switching.
It's compact switching.
We also refer as contact switching when you are switching between two processes.
Okay.
Now,
and this, again, we discuss this in the past,
but let me repeat because it's a very important aspect.
When you do process switching,
when you switch between two processes,
which means that the boat at the end of the day,
because you are switching between two threads in a different processes
that sewage is much more expensive.
Okay?
The reason that switch is much more expensive is simply because the state
associated with the process is much larger.
Right?
You need, again, the process is also on another space, right?
It's also on the file descriptors.
Okay?
Fundamentally,
it's a lot of more things you need to do when you switch a context versus
switching a threat.
These are the numbers.
Actually, the frequency context,
the switching between processes can take between,
in this case, for these numbers, again,
depends on the implementation,
depends on the hardware.
Take these numbers, a great grain of salt.
They are only supposed to give you the relative a sense about the relative difference.
When you see between processes,
it can be like between 3 and 4 micro seconds.
When you see between two studies only 100 and a second.
In this particular case,
you can see that the overhead is 30, 40,
times higher when I see between processes,
as compared when you switch,
just behind be between two threats.
And the frequency of context switching.
Here we are talking is about10 or 100 millisecond.
You don't want to contact switch all the time.
You want to contact switch.
Still fast enough,
but not as fast.
So that the amount of computation is the same order.
Remind you of squeeze the amount of overhead, it takes the switch.
Okay.
We have a question here from a sheet.
Isn't it trivial to change the address space?
Because you just change the pointer and for fallacy that again,
don't you just change this process structure?
.2is more than that.
You also need to have.
You have the buffers,
if you remember the, for instance, files tomorrow,
io the other things you need to do,
fundamentally, you need to have the entire page table.
You need to take care of it,
because the page table that is a translation of the address
virtual addresses to physical addresses.
It is.
This is what?
Each process outs.
Yeah,
what?
And also when you see the address space,
then you can because you are going to have probably some of the babies
which of the process,
which are going to be,
we have a big deal from the memory to make room for new processes,
and they are going to go to disk or whatever ssd therefore,
you may also have to do some work to get some pages in when you switch
between the processes,
even cheaper you can actually use without the operating system support.
You can use as you can use yield in the user level.
So the application actually is 50 that are thread libraries,
user levels for several thread libraries.
These are the libraries which provide you like a thread interface,
but the operating system doesn't know anything about.
And then what happens when you use a thread,
use that level thread,
then when you call yield,
you call the library which running the same process.
Again, it's not a system,
kernel.
And then that library is going to invoke,
you are going to just make a call a function,
call to another thread in the same process.
This is very, very lightweight,
is just a function call.
This is some of the first stress systems have been implemented.
That is the application level.
In this case, all fundamentally,
all these user level threads are going to be basically mapped on, say,
one cpu now.
With a kernel, in general,
kernel also uses some threads, right?
And the number.
And these are kernel threads.
And you then, in general,
you map the user thread on the kernel threads.
The kernel said, typically,
you uses a number as a number of catalysts.
The number of kennel thread is typically equal,
is a number of cp us or a number.
Okay?
And again, you have it difficult.
You have few tens on your cpu but you can have then thousand or tens
of thousand of user level threads.
When the kernel has a concept of thread,
then what you happen,
you are going to map the user thread on top on calendar sets.
Let's look,
is this server overhead on context?
Switch between process is purely,
do you have to switch of the address space?
That's a big part of it.
Again, there are also file descriptors and things like that,
but the address space is a big partner.
Okay.
In today, lecture,
we are going to talk what in the first part of today lecture,
we are going to talk about this,
12the 1~1 thread model in the one grand thread model, actually,
in this particular case,
we are going to have for one users said we are going to have assumed
there is a kernel said.
So this means that for one user said,
we are going to have a cpu to run on.
Again, it's another figure,
another representation to for you to better understand how things
are working under the hood.
So here is, again,
you have two processes,
these rounded yellow boxes.
Each process you have a few threads.
A thread has its own state.
Then for they have some state they share is a process like memory and our state.
Then this is os with green,
and you have acpu scalar,
which speaks on which cpu the threat that will run.
And you initially, let's assume that we have one.
Okay.
Now,
let's look at the switch of our heads.
Now, the switch of our heads.
There are multiple cases here.
The switch overhead of two threads.
Again.
Eventually, what you run on the cpu is a strap.
Right?
So the switch overhead between two threads.
If they are on the same process is very low,
right?
Because all you need to soldiers abuse the you need to save and resume
this the stress state,
right?
Which is small.
Now,
if you need to go from one thread in one process into a thread
in a different process.
Now, you need also to see the context of processes.
So then the switch overhead is high.
Now, why do you have threads and processes?
Because the processes,
while it is a context which between processes is slow,
they provide some things that do not provide.
That is protection.
Right?
The protection between two strides running in the same process is very low.
It's because they are sharing the same memory.
One thread can read and write from the memory of the data,
from the data of another thread.
While if the strategy could run on different processes,
that's not possible.
Okay?
Now sharing overhead, as we know,
and we learned last past lectures,
threads.
And you may want to share data because the applications are pretty complex.
And they want to communicate with the multiple step.
They want to communicate with each other.
Now, if there are two threads are in the same process,
it's very easy for them to communicate.
It's also low overhead.
Why?
Because they can't communicate through the shared memory,
the memory they share in the same process.
They just read and write to the memory super easy.
On the other hand,
if these are two processes,
the sellers are into processes,
then what do you know what the overhead is much higher?
Because how you can communicate between the processes?
Do you remember?
You can use pipe, you can use sockets,
but all or you can read and write from a file.
All of this operation are far more expensive than reading and writing
from the memory.
What about the parallels?
In the case of parallels here, there is no parallels,
because you have only one core.
You can run only once at a time.
Here, it's a model.
General example is you have four course.
You can have four different kernel threads running at the same time.
So now you have parallelism.
Now you need to the sharing of our head is a little bit even more complex,
because if you have the same process is low,
different process is high.
But now there are different process.
If actually, it turns out that if you have simultaneous scores,
that's so they are running,
you can have processes.
So this is more complicated,
but you can have kernel stress running on the same car.
And we see next slide how you can that have that.
Then the overhead of communication of sharing is lower.
And this is what I meant is a concept of multithreading or hypothetic,
actually is hypothetical, right?
Simultaneous multithreading or hypothetical.
This what they are talking about so far in everything I I said,
you can run one thread on one core.
But it turns out that in practice,
you can run at the same time,
multiple one multiple setting shadow, in general,
only two threads on the same call.
Right?
And this is called hypothetical.
And almost all processors today provided,
right?
It's actually, when you look at amazon for those of you, they give,
they say bcpu virtual cpu a virtual cpu is actually a hyper threat,
is not one core necessary.
So what is the idea?
Here is as things look at these figures,
do you see my pointer on the screen?
Can someone ask us if you see my point?
Perfect.
So here is a time on the vertical.
Here are, if you remember,
from 61 c the processor have in the aromatic logical unit and everything
there are different components that you need to fetch the instruction,
then you need to.
Then you may use different components like ads
or from the aromatic processor units,
a logical unit to perform that operation.
Each of this line, it's an instruction.
And vertical.
Each of the vertical is one component in the process in that core.
So this color, what is color?
This means that this instruction,
where is a colored?
Is that particular instruction uses that component.
Right?
For instance, from in this example,
in the first instruction using the first and the third component.
Okay, but not using it doesn't use the second one.
And then for the next,
actually,
ii I was not accurate.
Sorry, each of this line represents a cycle instruction cycle.
But at many instructions,
they run in a single cycle, some of them,
but some of them do not.
Okay.
It's instruction cycle in this cycle.
These two first and the third component are yours.
In the next cycle,
there is no component being used.
And maybe this is because it has stalled.
The data is not available,
and the instruction cannot proceed or something like that,
and so forth.
The main point here is that not all components are used at the same time.
So then what you can do then,
is basically to run two streams of instructions from two different threads.
If a stream doesn't use all the components at the same time,
then the other string can use them.
So that's kind of the intuition.
One stream of instructions doesn't use all the components of the core
at all times.
So you can take advantage of that to support the second stream
to better use other components.
So that's why you can run two streams of instruction on virtually the same harder.
So just better utilizing the particular core.
All right.
That's what it is.
Okay.
So it basically provides you the illusion that now you can run multiple.
You like, you have multiple,
the speedup is nonlinear,
because sometimes you have conflicts,
like you have the two stream instruction at the given cycle.
They want to use the same component.
But this is super useful and technique.
And it's used by almost every processor.
Now,
if I remember a process,
can relinquish access to the cpu in multiple ways.
Right?
One is voluntarily yield.
Another one is io when it's making an io one is calling an io operation,
like, in this case, it is from a file.
Then it's another question.
Let me try to answer the question.
Are some components not used,
even if we do pipelining?
Yes, because pipelining means there are multiple.
You are also going,
you can also have stalls and dependencies in the pipelines
across instruction in the pipeline.
The answer is actually all the processors are all already do pipeline,
right?
Pipelining.
It helps you to each instruction, new instruction,
to every clock cycle.
You start the new instruction,
but pipelining helps with the use it utilization,
but it doesn't solve it entirely.
Great question.
Let's go back here.
Again.
We are going to show the stack,
and you have copy file,
cold read.
And when cold read,
read it, again, it's a system call.
You call it a kernel read.
And what is the kernel doing?
Is going to start the read operation.
But before you get the answer to the read operation,
the cpu is free.
So therefore,
is going to switch to suspend your being the copy file program,
and give the cpu to another thread.
Right?
The same thing happens.
And the same,
it is similar when you have signals and joints or operate operations on other.
Okay.
Finally, one question.
So we also ask in the past,
what happens if there no is a program?
Doesn't voluntarily yield the cpu there is no io and in general,
never waits.
Right?
In that case,
you still needs to multiply the cpu between different threads.
The way you do it using external events.
External events like in this, like interrupts.
In particular,
timer interrupts a you program the timer to give an interrupt.
Every 100 millisecond.
When you get this interrupt,
the kernel is going to switch from the current threat or infrastructure.
Okay?
That's what it is.
Let's see another question.
It seemed like the hyperthreading benefits concurrency.
What about parallels?
It definitely also benefits parallels because you are going to have
now if you have you are going to double the number of threads you
are going to to run at the same time.
So this is a picture which basically show you here is acpu and then I show
you how you are going to interface with different devices.
Right?
Again, the way interface, actually,
the operating system with a different devices is through these interrupts
when an event which requires the attention of the kernel happens,
that device has to going to jane to generate this kind of event which is interact.
Right?
You can also have software interrupts like seek kill is a software interrupt.
It doesn't come from a device.
It comes from another process or it comes from the kettle.
This is a timer, which is a special kind of interrupt like we discussed.
For interrupt, you can mask interrupts and we'll see.
And the interrupt they have some priority.
The higher priority interrupts,
for instance can interrupt the lower priority interrupt.
Okay?
But this is what have you have?
Basically this is actually this hardware,
this kind of different lines,
how to go to lines in the interrupt,
least.
And then the key kernel will always look at the highest interrupt
and will treat the highest interrupt.
Okay?
If higher interrupts and the one you are currently treating occurs,
then you are not going to switch to treat the higher interrupt and then you
come back,
finish treating the lower interrupt.
Okay?
The software interrupts can be cleared by software and cpu can disable
all interrupts with some internal flags.
Okay?
So I don't want to be interrupted because what i'm doing is very important.
And there is also some non maskable interrupts which you don't have
anything what to do like,
for instance,
reset is a nomas couple interrupt.
Right?
So you have to just kill and reset everything on the computer and restart,
right?
That's one example.
Now, this is an example about how the network interrupt occurs.
Let's say you execute this,
call these instructions.
Now, you get an external interrupt because a packet arrives.
So the kernel needs to copy the data into the kernel buffer.
So what do you do?
First of all, your pipeline,
you flash the pipeline, right?
The pipeline of the processor from the state of the current Instructions.
You save the program counter,
right?
To know when you are going to resume where you are going to come back,
what is a program counter if you have to come back to and disable all the interrupts?
Because now you need to do some work,
and you don't want to be interrupted.
And basically what you do here,
you raise a priority and you mask all the lower level interrupt,
because I don't want to be interrupted by lower level interrupts when you
do that.
And you save the registers for this current thread,
you dispatched to the handler of the interrupt,
because you need to treat the interact.
In this particular case,
read the data from the network,
transfer the network packets,
from harvard to the canal buffers.
Once you're done with that,
you restore the registers,
right?
You clear current interrupt because you are done with it.
You desirable, all interrupts are going to do your work.
Do you don't want to be interrupted as a journal?
And you restore the priority?
You then clear the masks.
Right?
The set, the mask which are clear here,
the mask, which you said here to not be interrupted.
Now you clear it,
basically saying, now I can be interrupted by anything by any.
Right?
And now I return from the interact.
That's it.
It's very simple.
And it's, again, an interim, though,
it was to think about it's a hardware involved context switch.
There is no separate state.
There is no decision of what to run next.
It's very clear.
I am going to run the handle to treat the interrupt.
And i'm going to go back to this program.
I just interrupted.
So like we mentioned,
one way to interrupt a program now and give and give
control to another program is simple simply by using the time of interact.
Right?
As the time I interrupt on the interrupt, happens,
time I interrupt happens,
you are going to kennel is going to execute this time or interrupt handle.
And the time of interrupt handle or a pin,
it's doing some housekeeping.
It's again,
update some counters and things like that,
and then run new thread,
right?
And that you run new threads, what he's doing,
save the state of the current thread.
Initially,
the state is a state into registers of the new thread and start the new threat.
And in between,
you need to decide which instead you are going to run.
This is what we are talking about.
You initialize the registered field of that dcb or stack pointer
with pc return address.
Also, in this case,
is the functions and the function arguments.
You.out to this function and the point of the function to the list of
function arguments,
which you put into registers, in this case, a zero and a one.
Then all about the stacks.
Again, the stack is in the memory, served by the processor.
You don't need to do anything other than pointing to the rockaric location
of the stack,
which is a stack pointer.
Again, let's see what happens here.
In this particular case,
this is the old one.
It's basically we went through this one here, use yield,
which is voluntarily relinquish the cpu to be used by another thread.
And when this happened,
you and you set up the new thread,
you are going to initialize the greatest,
the pointers and registers of the processors with the values from the pcb
from the thread control block.
Right?
And then you are going to run the newsletter.
So this thread road,
this is a route for all the thread routines.
So when you have to switch,
which from one thread to another thread,
this is what you are going to execute.
Okay?
The thread wrote what it takes to take this address to the function
of the thread you want to execute,
right?
Remember a strategy,
just a function you have to execute at the end of the day, right?
You need to provide to this thread route,
the function of the new thread to execute and the front and the arguments,
right?
Again, you lose some households,
housekeeping.
You do the user mode switch.
So now you are in the kernel,
so you need to go to the user mode,
because the application runs in the user mode,
and then simply invoke the the thread function with the arguments.
And you are done.
And like I mentioned,
the housekeeping includes things like recording the start time of the strategy,
how long the thread is spare run of the cpu while other statistics,
number of context switching and things like that.
Obviously,
the struck stack will grow and shrink with the execution of a strategy.
And when you return from this function,
you this is you call the thread finish, right?
What is the thread finish?
Is you need to execute another thread,
right?
You need to find and wake up a sleeping threat.
So now we really go into concurrence.
It's again, once you have multiple threads running at the same time,
and have the kernel,
non deterministic decide at what point to interrupt a threat to suspend it
and regime on other side.
Now you need to be very careful.
And you need to be careful because these threads can share the same data.
If there is no share, state,
is fine, no problems.
But if the state is shared,
then you can run in,
we can run into problems.
Here.
Are you want to be very careful on the design?
And you should try to what we call correctness by design,
meaning that we need to convince yourself.
Maybe in some case,
you can even prove that the design of,
despite the fact that multiple concurrent threads can access the same data,
the design is correct, nothing bad.
Happened.
Recall again, different executions.
And the execution we really care about is b and c where threads
are interleaved or they are running at the same time.
So they can touch the data at the same time.
This is extremely important.
Right?
Here is an example to drive home.
The point is that handling the concurrency is important.
So think about idea.
You have an idea.
You have, obviously,
with atm you want to either deposit or withdraw money.
And the state assumes that it's in a database.
So we need to be very careful here.
So you're supposed that you want to implement this functionality.
Then you need to process fundamentally,
you have to have an infinite loop where you wait for request from the users.
And then you process the requests.
Right?
And the request is basically specifying operation,
withdraw,
or deposit,
account id as the amount.
Right?
This is you receive the request and then you process the request.
The process request is simple, right?
If it's a deposit,
you deposit the amount in account id if it's if it's withdrawal,
you subtract the amount from the deposit,
the deposit functions.
What is a deposit function?
How does it look like?
You get account id you get the account data structure from the account id
and you add the amount to the balance.
And then you store the account reader account,
modifies the account, store, the account.
So if you do this thing,
right?
At one given time,
you are only to set up a single request.
So what is the problem with that?
The problem is can be very slow.
And why is slow?
Not because of computation.
Adding numbers is super fast.
Right?
What is slow is to access a database to get the account information
from the database and to store the account information to the database.
That is what is slow.
And during this time,
the program is blocked,
just waiting for the database operation to complete.
The opportunity here is to overlap communication is a database io who is a computation.
While you wait for an account to be read from the database or written
to the database,
you can very well serve as a users.
And by the way, the users actually, in this case,
they can operate on different accounts on their own accounts.
Right?
So how do you do that?
One way to do it,
and this is typical is called event driven.
And with the event driven approach,
you basically split the requests,
right?
In multiple pieces.
1 piece, for instance,
you start on the request is basically, for instance,
this piece can only start the aisle.
It can only makes any questions, a database.
And then you switch, you end up,
and you wait for an event to come from the database,
basically saying from then the operating system saying this request set
has been completed.
Now there is a data.
Now you can go to continuous requests to read the data.
Okay?
This is kind of the things you do it, right?
By hand, you are going to basically say that in the programming by hand,
I think that explicitly in the program,
you make sure that there is no part of the program that's wait
for is blocked further than I already quest to complete.
But now this way to write programs,
it's pretty hard.
What if you miss the blocking aisle?
Then you are going to block.
The performance is going to suffer.
What do you have?
Your function?
Has hundreds of aisles.
You need to split into hundreds of pieces,
very hard to reason and be back.
However, this is super fast.
It's even faster than threads.
Right?
There is not even context switching between threats super fast.
This is used when you really,
really need performance like graphical program.
Now,
the obvious question is that and this is what we brought in this example.
Then you may say,
but what about threads?
We just said that threads can handle concurrency.
It's a unit of concurrence.
Indeed.
And using threads,
you can do this much easier.
Right?
So let's see how this is done.
Basically, you run each of this operation in different threads.
Right?
You can do another thread.
Each operation can be another thread.
You have a thread,
you can have a thread pool to make sure that you don't have a huge number
of threads.
So the system is going to crash,
like we learned the last lecture.
But otherwise,
the only thing you need to do each operation is a differential,
because if you remember from what you learn,
what a thread is going to wait for an eye operation,
it's going to be suspended.
And the kennel will let another thread to run.
Okay?
The problems are here is that,
okay.
Now, it's the two threads can access the same data.
Here is a very simple example.
We have maybe here two threads which are depositing in the same account.
Right?
What happened here?
The straight one is reading the balance.
After that the threat to read the balance,
and then add the amount to the balance,
which is in other one,
and then save the balance.
But now I am going to resume to set one.
I said one, the first thing is doing,
it's at its own amount to the balance,
and then start the balance.
What did they do?
What is this code accomplish?
What is not accomplishing?
What happens here?
What is your own behavior?
I have an ebola thread one, say.
I want to add the balance $100 thread to,
I want to add to the balance $200.
I should have added to the balance behind the dollars.
But if I execute the code, what happens?
A mountain is lost.
Very good, simon.
So basically,
in our example,
only $100 are going to be added to the balance and the 200 will be lost.
Okay.
There are many examples,
like in this example,
thread one is x say,
x one and set by is still.
This case is simple, right?
They are separate thread, separate data structure.
They don't interfere.
Everything is fine.
However, in this case,
they have operate on a common variable.
What are the possible values of x here?
Why don't you take a little bit of time and answer this question?
If I run thread one and thread a and thread b the initial value of y is 12.
What results I can get here?
One answer.
Please more answers.
Okay.
Excellent.
Right.
So you need to take all why is 12?
But I still remember so in,
say, 3 days is running to completion.
Right?
Then what you get is 13.
Now say thread this,
france before saturday.
What happens?
Why is to it over as well?
Then you multiply by 2 service 4.
And then here you are going to have five,
right?
Or you can only run the first instruction of b before you run a again,
you initialize y we stood over I 12 initial value,
and the result will be three.
You see pretty complicated,
but also fun to write for to do this exercises.
Oops.
But this is even simple examples.
X is equal one and x equal two.
What is the result?
Not that means you get one or two.
For fun, if the instruction to store data is not deterministic,
you can even get something in between.
Right?
Sorry, if the instruction to store the data in memory is not atomic,
I said, no, not their music, which is wrong.
It's nonatomic.
Right.
We learn more about atomic instruction.
So it's a mess.
So to understand the concurrent program,
like in this past example, you've seen,
you need to know what is the indivisible operation?
What is atomic operation?
An atomic operation?
What is an atomic operation is indivisible?
You can interrupt in between in the middle is a run or doesn't run at all.
That's all right.
You cannot just have upset of the output of running half of atomic operation.
Now, your output is the upset.
Output is either as if the entire operation runs or none of the operation
as a run at all.
This is a fundamental building block.
On most machines,
load and stores are atomic.
The world exam wild examples in the previous slide cannot happen in this case,
but many atomics,
many instructions.
And here we are talking about processor instructions are not atomic.
Double precisions have not atomic,
so you can interrupt in the middle.
And there are instructions on the old computers run,
which copy a whole area.
They are not atomic.
Right?
If bad things happen,
you can see the results only of a partially running instruction.
Now,
if we run, if we know only what are the atomic instructions,
this is helpful,
but it's still not enough,
because you can see that atomicity,
it's a very convenient way to control the access to a share of variables.
Because atomistic,
if I can say all this bunch of instructions is not going to be interrupted.
I don't need to be worried that someone will read.
All right?
Or I am executing these operations.
You remember how these are called?
It's critical section, right?
The way to do it,
in general, you do is, example, is a lock.
You have one lock,
and you acquire the lock,
and you execute some code.
While you have the lock,
no one else can acquire the lock.
So no one else may be able to execute these instructions.
And then you release a lock when you are done.
And the threads, libraries,
they do have the lock,
primitive.
How do you fix it?
The previous example,
remember, when multiple threats can run this at the same time,
they can run at the same time and then can access data at the same time.
Simply simple,
right?
You acquire the lock before you execute all the instruction on operation,
on an account,
and then you release a clock.
This is what in the middle of the acquiring and releasing the lock
is called critical section.
If multiple threads want to execute the same code,
only one will execute at a given time.
Very simple on thread,
and then thread b and thread cok
but you need all this value of the same lock or the same lock
should be shared by all states want to access the same critical
section.
So remember,
okay.
These 23 notions synchronization using a topping operation to ensure
cooperation between threats for
now only slows and stores,
we assume are atomic mutual exclusion.
We ensure that only one thread as a particular thing at a given time.
Right?
This means that one thread exclude another thread from running the same code.
And critical section is a either side of the mutual exclusion coin.
And critical section basically define,
which is the sequence of instruction on the code,
which is can be executed by a single thread at a given time.
Here is another example,
thread a and thread b thread a start with I initialize to zero,
and then adds one.
Has a loop adds one.
And when you get to ten exits and say, brings a wings,
thread b is doing similar things,
but decrement.
Start with I zero, decrements it.
And if you reach to minus ten bos both of them,
they share these variables.
What is the result here?
Who is a or b
let's only 200 minutes remaining.
So let's get a little bit of energy.
Could be easier, right?
You cannot know.
Right?
Let me ask you another question.
Are you guaranteed that at least wanna win?
Now?
Excellent, at least on induction.
Now,
because in the worst case, you see these three instruction,
I is equal I plus one.
I is equally die medicine.
What happens if you have contact switching
and between saturday and thread b and this thread only execute
this instruction.
Right?
You are get stuck with the same value.
You never finish.
None of this.
Let's finish this.
Excellent.
Thank you.
It's again, this is the inner loop,
and this is we see what is happening under the hood.
Although the fact that what you see is that in the program,
it's even more subtle.
Because when he sees a program in the previous slide,
let me just we should have said,
when you see this, I I plus one or I I minus one,
actually, maybe you think that this is also atomic,
that means executes to completion,
cannot be interrupted.
It's not true.
Remember, only lord loves and stores are at all.
Actually,
things are even more complicated because I and I plus one and I is I
minus one can be interrupted in the middle.
And this is one example,
right?
Where you execute,
you interleave the instruction from three and three b and the result
here is what?
Nothing changes.
Because in the middle,
you read the same values,
you write the same at the same location.
And in the middle,
we want is a value on and is abstract on.
So nothing changed.
Okay?
So,
and typically,
this is called race conditions.
When you have two strides attempting blocks,
the same data at the same time with one of them performing the right.
So how do you fix it?
We know now you put a lock that is fix it.
Not really, because we discussed, right?
You can execute this block of instruction,
ysy plus one,
and then execute the second block of instruction.
And it's true that you are going to see the changes.
But before they execute the next while,
the value was updated to the same value.
Right?
And the main.here,
and I need probably to got it be faster.
Concurrency is hard like, look,
these simple examples.
There are a bunch of instructions,
just a few instructions.
What?
Three instruction, four instructions,
even that is hard.
Now, imagine that you have thousands,
tens of thousands of instructions.
There are many such issues.
And these are just some examples.
He says there are 25 radiation therapy machines.
As a result of this kind of race condition,
concurrency of not being careful,
accessing the same variable from different threads resulted in an overdose,
which cause even death.
It was improper synchronization between the input thread
and the positioning high software where to apply the
radiation marked by find a priority inversion.
Proud you.
Inversion here means that basically,
what happens?
You have a high priority job.
A high will learn more about that.
A high priority thread waiting for something from a low priority thread.
But the hybrid thread contains a lock,
maintains a lock,
which is required by the operator threat to update that value or to do
something for its high priority thread.
Wait, but you cannot do it,
because the critical section is owned by high priority threat.
So you get hacked.
It's another things,
toyota and control acceleration.
This was 256,000 lines of seek out and whatever 11,000 global variables.
So here it is inconsistent with your exclusion.
Right?
Acceleration was uncontrollable, right?
You just doesn't respond.
You click a little bit.
The carrot takes off,
like you would floor the acceleration battle.
Next, let's look about a little bit more sophisticated things.
Let's look at about queue,
producer, consumer,
with a banded buffer.
Why this is important.
Remember about pipes.
Last time, we learned about pipes.
Pipes is above,
is a cube.
You put that one in the queue,
one end of the queue and get the data from the other end of the queue.
When you do a pipe,
all this is also and you do the piping between different pieces.
When you change different shell comments,
the same thing happened.
And we'll have another example of cover machine later.
Okay?
And there are many examples.
But this is what you want.
Ideally, you put at one end of the buffer,
and you read from a different end of the buffer, and typically,
there is circular buffers.
There is years to handle.
You have immediately to deal with several problems,
how to tell if full,
how to take the buffer is empty.
What to do, if is a buffer is full?
What to do is above?
For example,
one needs to be atomic.
Let's take a simply that let's think about what is the simple implementation.
All right?
The producer, what you need to do while the buffer is full,
don't do anything.
You cannot put another item because you don't have anywhere to put it.
If the buffer is not full,
you incure the item,
because you need to do this operation,
you want to be atomic.
You are going to guard it,
be a a with a lock.
Can anyone tell me why you need to do this?
What can happen?
What can happen if I don't look?
You may have buffer overflow.
Excellent.
Right?
Because you can have two producers, two threads,
and one execute while both executed, while buffered.
Both are happy.
The buffer is just one place for only one item,
right?
But both are going to pass of the wild.
But now, once is interrupted,
obviously, right?
And the other one is going to include the item.
Now, the buffer is full.
But for the first,
for the soldiers interrupted or were suspended resumes,
he doesn't know he's going to try to add another item,
and I have the overflow.
Okay?
Now is at the queue, the same.
You do lock for this critical section,
and you wait now is a buffer is empty.
You don't do anything.
If the buffer is not empty, you are going to delete it.
Right.
Now,
let's assume now for this crowd,
if we do this,
will we ever come out of the way?
This is a question.
Say that is nothing is a buffer.
Right?
Then that's fine, right?
You are going to build a buffer.
But let me ask you this question.
Maybe not an answer I see.
Now you can block on the consumer exact,
let's say that the queue is empty,
and the consumer executes,
it acquires a lock,
and then it executes a while and is stuck,
because there is nothing in the buffer.
The only one who can put something in the buffer a is a producer.
But in order for the producer,
but something is a buffer, is to acquire the log.
But it cannot acquire the log because owned by the brasilia.
So your hand,
you don't work.
How can you do it?
One solution is to release a lock.
If the buffer is full,
we need to release a look if the buffer is full to give a chance
to the consumer to consume from the rough,
right?
And then acquire the buffer.
Right?
You see what you done here.
You acquired before you check again whether the buffer is full.
You release this to give a chance to consumer to execute.
You acquire the buffer back to check back whether the buffer is for the loop.
What happens when one is waiting for the other?
Like I said in this thing will be
it could work for multiple clock.
Orders will discuss this a little bit later.
Let me just,
then there are other things we can do here.
And this, right?
Abstraction of synchronizing threads that share memory.
Locks is an abstraction,
but it's not the only abstraction.
And let me just see it's a question here.
Let me go back,
and it's important to understand that.
The question here,
it's what happens when one is waiting for?
The why do we need to acquire the law?
We need to acquire the log,
because here what happens in the while loop?
In the y loop,
it's an empty instruction.
You need to repeat the you repeatedly.
What you want is this.
Why?
You repeatedly check whether buffer is full and been between the checks,
you release and acquire the buffer.
We need to be in critical section through check the buffer,
because you don't want to be the buffer to be modified while you
are checking about checking whether is full that has to be
critical section.
But between multiple checks,
you want to release the lock.
So the consumer can consume.
That's right.
So another way to do it is a more generally using some of us.
We did this summer force.
We learn slightly a little bit about them.
This is just recalling what we learned.
There are two similar force,
sorry, to primitives on the same time for is p is an atomic operation,
which waits for the semaphore to become positives and decrement by one.
If zero is just,
it's weights is blocked.
And b we just increment the semaphore and wake up any other thread which
wasted for which waits for the semester.
All right.
Some efforts are like integers in the sense that you
can increment and decrement them,
except there are no negative values.
The only way you can increment and they could be commanded them is to use
AP and b function.
Right?
This operation,
December for these operations are atomic.
Bnb are atomic.
This is a railroad analogy.
You can implement, like, for instance, in this case,
you have two lines, two railroad lines,
two rails.
Right?
You increment, you put the value of the semaphore to two.
So you can have an engine parked on online,
then an engine park on second line.
You notice that every time I haven't accepted an engine,
I decrement the value.
Now its value is zero.
You have another engine is stopped.
It cannot get in because the value is zero.
Now, when one leaves is going to increment the semaphore and the slide,
the third engine can enter,
right?
And so forth.
So you can use some of us to implement which mutual exclusion.
This equivalent to having a semaphore is a binary value 01.
How do you do that?
You do AP on the summer for you initialize the summer for to one and use AP
so the first thread which
calls some p is going to enter the critical section because you
can decrement value to zero.
The second one is going to copy.
While the first one is the first study,
the second in the critical section cannot enter in the critical section,
because some are four is zero,
where the first summer Ford leaves,
the summer critical section is going to increment the summer for.
So second one comes.
Right?
We also say,
in this case that the summer for implements scheduling constraints,
and also,
this is about,
sorry,
we a second use case which you also learned last time.
It was about waiting,
a thread waiting for another thread to finish.
You need the call, and this was implementing joint operation.
But I remember this code.
You have a thread join.
And that's your,
you are going to wait for the thread to finish that adjoining.
You run a thread and you added for Free to finish, right?
How you do that?
You are going to have a semi for which is initialize to zero.
When you start the thread,
when you sorry, when you start when you finish a thread,
you increment the semaphore to one.
And then let me take it back.
We initialize a thread to zero.
When you start the thread,
nothing happens.
And the main thread is going to wait to execute strategy.
And it's going to be blocked,
because the summer 40,
when the set finishes on for which I'm waiting,
then the thread is going to increment the Singapore.
And now,
the p in the thread join can decline the summer for and can finish.
And this is only say we implement scheduling constants.
Okay?
We are a little bit slow.
Let me just go over announcements.
Let me find the announcement and we had a going to be done.
So announcements,
very quick announcements today.
Please sign up for design reviews.
The design documents also don't forget that due Friday.
Next week,
you are going to get the feedback on your design documents from your ta you
need to
assign for that to schedule that meeting.
And the homework one is due today.
So good luck with that.
So good luck again with the homework,
good luck with the design documents and see you all next week.
Thank you.