Hello, everyone.
Welcome to the 8th lecture.
This is really an important lecture.
We are going to learn a lot and continue to learn about synchronization
and how we are going to solve
the problems and ensure a critical provides a critical section abstraction and
and synchronization primitives.
So let's recall a few things from the last time, in particular,
summer force.
If you remember,
some of us are like generalized locks,
and they are defined many times,
many years ago,
like 60 years ago, almost.
And it's it was a main synchronization,
primitive used in original units.
And when we are talking here about synchronization,
we are talking about in the context of implementing a critical section.
If you remember a critical section,
a it's a sequence of code as in which only one thread can be
active at a given time.
Therefore, if one thread is active in a critical section,
the other threads which want to enter the critical section,
but they could the code they need to wait.
But I so need a mechanism to synchronize this kind of entrance
to the critical section,
and then on a thread exit the critical section.
And as a thread from the waiting ones is going to enter the critical section.
And there are two primitives,
b and b b is,
if the sum of four is zero,
it be it's waiting.
If the summer for its greater than zero, it decrement it.
The other one v basically,
it's just increment a similar follow up by one.
If the similar for a zero and if it's increment to one,
then is going to wake up one of this,
one of the threads,
which was waiting on a summer for if any.
Okay.
These are 2 years of the summer force.
We went over last time.
One is mutual exclusion.
Again, this is about implementing critical sections.
Here.
It's very simple.
You are going to initialize the same effort to one.
And then you put before and after a critical section,
ap and av the first thread,
which is going to execute the instruction p that's enough for each one
is going to decrement.
It is going to enter the critical section.
If another thread comes and right execute the curve,
the summer for now is zero.
It has to wait when the first summer for x is a critical section,
is calling v and v it's increment in the summer for.
And therefore,
as a result,
we signal the thread who is wiping to enter the critical section.
Right?
And it's also the scheduling constraints.
This is basically we want to signal to wait for a thread or a signal,
a thread to do something.
Here, the initial value is zero.
And the classic example is a joint implementation for the thread.
You remember that with a join,
the patterns of the thread,
which execute the joint ways for another step to finish.
Okay?
And so basically, the threat,
which way is to finish the join?
They use to implement this.
So use the same semaphore.
So the thread in initialize them for 20,
and the thread who waits for another thread to join,
to finish, then it just calling p right?
And if the other thread and the other thread when it finishes,
is calling me.
So if the thread hasn't finished,
the semaphore is zero,
the join operation will just wait.
And it will wait until one until the thread.
We are way it's waiting for its executing this thread finish,
which calls v is increment in the summer for the one,
which means that and seeing signals a waiting thread
and there's waiting thread now the summer for each one and going to
start executing and decrementing it to zero and finish a code,
finish the joint operation.
Any questions?
Please ask any questions.
If you have any and then we want to to this bounded buffer.
So you remember the bounded buffer.
We have a bunch of producers,
a bunch of consumers,
the producer put elements in the buffer.
The consumers get elements around the buffer.
You hear, if you look at the constraints,
what we are talking about here is that for the consumer must wait
for the producer to fill the buffer.
If the buffer is empty,
then the consumer have to wait.
On the other hand,
the producers must wait for the consumer to empty the buffer.
If the buffer is full,
then the producer has to wait,
because there are no place in the buffer doing to put new elements.
And there is, obviously,
there is the buffer is self manipulating the buffer or the queue.
It's basically,
it's a critical section,
and only one thread is going to manipulate iq right?
Is that one consumer or one or one producer?
Right?
Okay.
So how we are going to implement it, one implement.
We are going for each of these constraint.
We are going to use a semaphore.
We are going to use a semaphore for full buffers.
This is consumer constraint and empty buffers.
Basically, each of these singapore,
at a given time,
will show how many elements are in the buffer full buffers,
and how many elements you can still put in the buffer.
Basically, if you add that to this to similar force,
you should get the total number of elements that buffer size.
Then a mutex are for mutex,
for the mutual exclusion.
To make sure that you have only one thread manipulating the queue that is
whether inserting a new
element or removing an element from the queue.
Let's start full slots is basically zero,
because initially,
there is nothing in the queue.
Empty slots is a buffer size.
Remember, if you add here full slots with empty slots,
you get the size of the buffer.
And mutex is one like that.
No one is in the critical section.
And the producers and is very simple, right?
It's like, basically, you are waiting for slows to be available.
Then you use a mutex to protect the critical section.
And then once you are done,
you are implementing the number of slots or full slots, right?
Because you added on element.
And the consumer is very similar.
You are waiting for to full slots to be greater than zero.
This means as at least one element in the buffer.
If it's you have more than one element in the buffer,
you can be cue that element.
Again, the dq operation is protected by the mutex.
Then once you are done,
you are going to increment the empty slots,
because now it's one more available slots in the queue and return the item.
So that's basically here in use a mutex to protect the critical section.
Therefore, no two threads at the same time operates on the queue to remove,
to manipulate the pointers, to remove that,
the elements or to add the element to the cure.
The other one are scheduling constraints of full slots,
is incremental by the producer,
and then is diplomatic by the consumer.
And similarly,
the empty space is implemented by the consumer and decrement it by the progress.
Any questions?
A discussion about solution?
You can see there is a symmetry, right?
The producer is doing is calling p and then v on empty graph buffers
and full buffers.
The consumer does the reserve reverse is calling people on the full buffers
and be on the empty buffers,
right?
It is this asymmetry.
Okay.
It's exactly what to expect, right?
Because the producer has to decrease the number of empty slots and increase
the number of occupy slots.
And the consumer,
sorry, the producer has to wait for the producer.
Yeah.
It's as to wait for empty starts to be available.
But then once you put the element,
you decrease the number of empty slots and you increase the numbers
of occupied slots.
As a consumer is the other way around.
When there is at least one element in the buffer,
you decrease the number of occupied slots because you take one element,
then also this increase the number of empty slots.
Right?
Now, this is a question for you.
If there is that you remember in the original code,
let me guess what this we called first produce that calls first smfop
on the empty slots,
and then the mutex.
Now, is that order important?
That's a question for the class.
Looking forward to your replies to your answers?
Yes.
It is.
If you do this, it can be, we can deadlock.
Can someone explain how you can get the dialogue?
Here?
Is?
Very simple?
Thank you.
I don't know.
Actually.
Basically, it's very simple, right?
For instance,
you imagine that he's a producer,
the empty slots that are now empty slots.
Empty slots is zero.
What happens?
You acquire the mutex for the critical section,
and then you are going to start waiting,
because empty stocks is zero.
Right?
There is no place in the cure to insert a new element, rather new element.
But now you are going to wait in the critical section.
And the only way the empty slots can be increment.
It is by the consumer.
But in order to do that,
the consumer has to
the consumer has to be cure and operation.
But for that, you need to acquire a mutex.
But you own the mutex.
The producer owns a mutex.
So you cannot acquire the mutex,
because you can have only one thread in the critical section.
So therefore, consumer cannot be cure any element.
Therefore,
the producer will continue to wait for the empty slots to be implemented,
which will never happen.
Very good.
Is the order of the important.
I have the answer here is that yeah,
now because they just do the increment.
What if you have to produce and to consumers?
Is this?
Do you need any changes I to the previous code which is working?
Not to this one?
So assuming that some of the end mutex and empty slots are not,
are you ordered?
So do you need to make any changes to this code?
If I have to go to seven to consumers
on ali,
you are correct now.
You don't need to do it to do to make any change is going just to work.
The reason is going to work.
It's again because no matter how many consumer and producers are going to have,
you can at its only one of those can be in the critical section.
Yes, exactly.
Thank you.
Good.
It's again.
So you can see that b and v are the synchronization primitives.
And now,
what we are going to do in the rest of these lectures,
we are going to try to figure out how to implement the synchronization primitives.
Synchronization, primitive pnb are at the higher level.
But as a low level,
you have what you have on you up in the when you talk about when you
are talking about the processor,
what you can do,
you can execute instructions,
like load and stores.
You can disable interacts.
And then we'll see there are a few other specialized instructions,
like test and set,
and compare and swap,
which it make it much easier to implement higher level synchronization primitives.
Because like you'll see,
using just slowed and stored and disabled interrupts,
they are not ideal solutions.
Right?
Then as a higher level, we have blocks.
We discussed last time,
we are going to discuss more this lecture,
summer force, and then monitors and send receipts operation.
But money we are going to discuss locks somewhere for their implementation.
And hopefully you are going to also get to monitors during this lecture.
And then programs is a higher.
There are higher.
Abstraction is a program level,
and we are not going to talk about them at least this week.
And here is a motivating example, okay?
If you haven't paid too much attention until now,
at least from now on for these examples,
pay attention because it will earn you a lot.
And remember that next wednesday,
we have the first meet up.
And the next lecture are going to be part of the topics covered by the meter.
So here is a problem.
And basically,
the problem is that there are two roommates and both of them like mom,
they like milk.
And the the question,
the problem is that if there is no milk in the fridge,
then whoever discovers that they are going to go and get milk,
right?
And we want the goal here is to not get too much milk.
And how can you get too much milk?
Well,
think about The same sequence of events at 3 o'clock.
First from my parents,
let's call her a person a look in the fridge.
There is no milk leaves to goes to the store at this star.
And while arriving at the store is a closed door.
The second roommate called her person b look at the fridge and it's out of milk.
She's going to do the same thing before store and arrival store.
During this time,
the a person a left,
the store arrive at her home,
put the milk in the fridge,
while the person b is at the store buying milk,
then we are going to get at the end of the day.
We are going to have 2 bottle of milks in the fridge.
Okay?
This solution certainly doesn't do what you wanted and what you
wanted to not buy too much milk.
How do we do that?
Obviously, we want to,
we can,
the problem here is that,
in some sense, both person a and b execute the same instructions,
and so to speak,
take the same actions without kind of any coordination, they do.
They execute that kind of code each of them at the same time, right?
What do you you want only one person of the two to go to the to the store
to buy milk.
Right?
So basically, you can see now the concept of critical section,
if you think about the program is going to the fridge and going
to the store to buy milk,
we want only one person to do it.
One way to prevent that,
like we learn and we saw.
So last time is to have locks.
So you look before entering the critical section,
you unlock after leaving the critical section.
Now,
the one important things which will come over and over again,
and what makes the implementation of locks challenging
is that any lock implementation or synchronization,
primitive implementation involve waiting.
And why is that?
It should be obvious, right?
Because if many threads wants to enter the same critical section,
and only one at a time can do it,
this means that why not go in a critical section and the other ones?
What they can do, they have to wait.
There is no around it.
Right?
So remember the boat.
So you can,
one way to do it is to lock all the way, also the fridge.
And basically, you go to,
before you go to the store, you lock the fridge.
If the other person sees come to,
the fridge is locked,
but is going to wait for you to unlock the fridge.
And then this guarantee that it's only one person you're buying the milk.
But this is not ideal,
because what if the other person wants something else and milk from the fridge?
Is so this is kind of very coarse grain solution.
Let's see how we are going to solve this problem.
And before doing that,
again, it's like this is a tricky problem.
And this general these problems when concurrency problems are tricky,
and they are tricky fundamentally because there are many entities doing
the same things at the same time.
And it just,
as a human said,
we are more used to thinking linearly than thinking about many things
happening at the same time.
We are not very good at that.
So that's one of the reason you can very well miss different edges.
So what you want when you have to deal with this kind of problem,
actually, you want to do that when you deal with any kind of problem,
programming problem.
But in particular, this kind of problems,
you need to be very careful and think quite a bit about what you
want to achieve and how to make the development solution to meet those,
the requirements you want to achieve.
Okay?
Don't start to code.
First, I just think,
first,
again, the way to think about it is to write down what you want to happen.
Right?
And what do you want to happen here?
Or what are the correctness properties?
You want no more than one person buy some milk at a time, right?
If two person buys milk at a time,
you end up with the bottle of peace.
I I at the same time.
If there is no milk,
there must be someone buying the milk,
otherwise you don't get the milk.
Okay.
And let's think about if you restrict yourself to just load and store.
So load and store meaning that you are going to modify some variable
in the memory,
which can be legal,
which can be read by any program.
Here is an example,
the way we are going to emulate this loud in stores in in this problem is
through notes.
Right?
You put an out on the fridge with a message.
This is basically it's equivalent to studying.
And you read the note,
obviously, and it's a cable entries are allowed.
Let's say what we have here.
We have do notes the kind of notes one,
and it's, sorry, 1note.
And then what is what is a code?
One possible power code can be one a possible solution is like,
if there is no milk, right?
And there is no note,
we assume here that a note indicates that someone else is going to buy the milk.
Then you leave note and yourself going to go to buy the milk.
And when you come back, you remove them out.
Right?
Simply enough,
what can happen here?
Right?
Do you think is a good solution?
Let's see, no answer here.
It's not a good solution right?
In.
We have an answer,
not atomic that could cause problems.
There are problems here.
And the way to look at, again,
these people this can work.
But if this is done by machines,
the machines are myopic.
They only see this instruction,
they only nothing else.
So let's see what can happen.
And always in these concurrency problems,
the bad things can happen if somehow the instruction are interleaved
in an unfortunate way.
So let's see here what can happen?
Let's say we have thread a and thread b now,
thread a is looking and check for the milk.
And then once thread a checks for the milk,
it's context switched is suspended by the operating system by the scheduler.
And thread b can start to execute.
And thread b is, again,
check for no milk.
And in both cases,
the answer, it says through there is no milk,
right?
But after and then thread b is checked for the note.
Okay?
There is no note.
But after checks for the note,
again, that we contact switch to thread a they check again for the notes,
and there is no note and leaves a note.
Right?
Buy milk,
removed note.
Thread b is going to do the same thing.
Right?
Because from the point of view,
there is thread b is there is no milk, is there is no note.
From the second point of view of saturday,
the same as true when you check or it was no milk.
And when he's checked was there is 00.
Now, note you have now both thread a and thread b buying milk.
Any questions yet?
So it's too much milk.
This happened occasionally,
right?
If you don't have this unfortunate order of execution,
actually, this code will work.
The problem is this what happened occasionally is that you may say
it's good news,
right?
It's like, it's only happens from time to time.
But the problem that when this happens is very hard to remember,
because it's not happen all the time.
Right?
That's what also makes these problems.
All this program frustrating,
because they are very hard to debug.
Another reason to think very well before starting took out.
Okay, so how do you solve this problem?
Right?
So clearly, this note is not exclusive enough.
And one, good.
So one solution, am I saying,
is because it's not why don't replace a note?
First, right?
What if we do this code?
Right?
Instead of checking for the note,
leaving the note,
before buying the milk?
Let's leave the note even before we check for the milk.
What about this crowd?
Any problem with this crowd?
Yes.
A actually,
this is a pretty stupid coach,
because if you leave that out here,
then if now it will be always true.
Right?
You don't know.
Sorry.
If now there will be always false and no one will buy me.
Let's see if you leave them out.
Good night.
If you leave yourselves a note,
and then you check for the note.
There is a note.
So you don't buy milk.
That's I was saying this is stupid.
So you don't do a given for one user.
Okay?
Let's go to solution to this kind of didn't work.
Maybe we need to be more sophisticated.
Maybe we need to have 2 kind two notes,
right?
One for each person.
Let's rewrite the previous code,
thread a leave note a thread b leave not b and thread a jokes for checks
was a thread b left and out.
And thread b checks was a thread a left or not.
Seems more sophisticated, may work, maybe.
What do you think it is going to work?
Okay, why don't you guess?
You don't need to tell me?
But whether why is going to work or not?
Just take a guess.
Now, good answer.
Ii hope that this answer is not given,
because you looked at the next slide.
But anyway,
so now it doesn't work.
And here is a reason and another an example.
Again,
it's about how this instruction instructions are interleaved
from saturday and saturday.
B you live now day.
You leave now be thread a leaves note a then we contact switch to thread b sarah
believes not be is checked for them if there is no day.
And basically a nowadays.
So this is false.
And this is not going to execute it.
At the same time.
Said a is looking or there is a node b there is a node be.
So this is really false.
So it's not going to execute the if what is under the wave condition.
And at the end of them,
at the end, both of them removed them their own notes,
but no one bought the milk.
Make sense?
Any questions here?
Okay?
It's again possible for neither of the threat to buy milk.
And again, this is really,
really hard to debug,
because it happens rarely.
Now, let me tell you,
I told you something about initially about any synchronization limit.
You should involve something.
Actually, even without reading the code,
you could have answered the question where there is a code is correct or not.
Can you tell me why and how you could have answered this question immediately?
Whether the code is correct or not?
Actually, the question is more clearly.
You could have immediately see that the code is not
correct.
Nicholas,
that's true.
There is no wait.
I told you that fundamentally,
any of these synchronization primitives has to involve a weight,
because if someone is in the critical section,
the other one thread has to wait.
If it wants to go into the critical section, there is no way around.
It is fundamental.
But so far,
none of these codes has a weight instruction or something equivalent.
So that's how you can immediately say these codes.
It's not going to work.
Finally,
okay.
So let's go.
Obviously,
this,
if no one gets the milk and this continuous, and obviously,
this is called starvation.
We're going to learn more about starvation in a few lectures.
Now, finally,
here is solution three.
There are turnouts,
but not yesterday.
It has ay a while.
This is a waiting instruction,
because you wait for the node b if there is a node be,
then you wait until the node b is removed.
Okay?
So in other words,
thread a will not execute or not buy the milk or not,
even look at whether there is a milk in the fridge.
If thread b it's checked and already went to buy milk
testing set as a synchronization.
So the question is for michael,
instead of waiting countries keep the critical section,
do we consider test and set as having a critical section?
The test is said,
they are going to be used to implement things like locks.
That's it, right?
You need to have a while in order to wait on a distance set.
At shake.
Answer is correct.
Right?
You need test and set alone.
You need to also have, again,
a while be around you to see that it is going to work.
Yes.
How you to convince yourself you see these 2 points,
x and y in each of these thread programs.
What you say here is at x if there is no node b
that is safe for a to buy,
right?
Say, for a dubai, sorry.
I what i'm doing,
right?
Because if there is no node b the thread b will for sure is
outside this section of code.
For sure, it doesn't thread.
B doesn't buy milk.
So it's safe for a to buy if there is no milk.
Now,
if I am at y if there is no node,
a is safe for bitter,
but why?
Because if there is not a
this means that thread a it's not in exactly in this code.
So we cannot buy me.
Here is another way to look at it.
There are these two actions leave,
not a and no,
not a when is checked.
So if leave node a happens before,
no node a is checked by the second thread,
right?
Then it's obvious that
thread b will not buy milk,
because there is a nowadays,
and it's over so obvious,
at least for now,
that said a will wait,
because there is a no b right?
Now, at this.,
now the thread b is, again,
there is a nowadays,
so we skip buying milk and then go all the way and buy and removes.
And i'll be without doing the anything without buying milk.
But notice now what happened yesterday once?
Said b removes note b thread a exits the y loop.
It check whether there is no milk and there is no milk and buy the milks.
Okay?
In this particular case,
thread a bought milk.
Now, let's assume that if no node a happens after thread b checks,
whether there is no take what happens in this case.
Right?
So thread b found no note a there is no milk,
so is going to buy the milk.
Then it's removing the node b as in parallel node a
is going to execute while node b and is going to wait
for a to remove node b when that happens and b
no thread b removes no b only after it bought the milk.
Now, when it be removes not be,
this means that thread a will exceed the while loop,
and now check for the milk.
But now there is milk in the fridge,
because we put the milk in the fridge,
you bought the milk.
So therefore, they will not buy milk.
So we are done.
So you see, in this case,
in both cases,
only one thread and exactly one thread, but milk.
The solution is easily protects a single critical section piece of code.
This is the critical section.
If no milk, you buy milk,
solutions three works,
but it's as if is not very satisfactory,
it's pretty complex, right?
Even in this simple example.
And like you see,
we got like what five six instructions.
It still took us like whatever 10,
15 minutes to convince ourselves that is working.
And also, a code is different from b code.
What if you have not to stress by three stress of or ten threads?
Finally, we have a wait here,
but she's busy waiting,
right?
This said a consume the superior resources while waiting.
We don't want that in general.
So let's look for a better ways.
Think about locking interface.
You are considering you want to acquire the lock and release a lock.
These are the instructions.
If the lock is taken,
you are waiting in the choir until someone believes along.
And then your milk problem is a it's a very simple.
You acquire the lock.
If there is no milk, you buy the milk.
I said it really is a lock.
This is like our very first solution with a lock, right?
A physical lock to the fridge.
But now imagine that you can put the lock only on a on something
in the fridge were contains only milk,
right?
On a container, in the fridge or contains milk.
That's a cuban.
Right?
Now, the question is how to implement lock?
This is what we are going to discuss.
Remember, all synchronization primitive involves wait,
but you don't want to do the waiting, busy, waiting,
just spending the cpu resources while waiting.
Instead, you want to sleep when you wait,
and you want to be open up when you can acquire the lock and enter
the critical section.
Solution three from the milk or milk three solution was
basically equivalent to using atomic load and stores,
again, pretty complex and the opera.
So now the question is about how it does this implement the locks,
because they saw that if we implement the locks,
the solution is much easier.
One way to think about is to implement its in harbor.
However, if you implement it in hardware,
a lock,
it turns out that it's pretty complicated.
And there are some processors doing it.
But it's, again, the complexity is high,
and it's also slow,
because the chip is more complex.
It's actually slow down,
many other instructions.
So one simple solution to implement it with what learn so far.
It's about using the internet.
Right?
Remember that we have these external interrupts,
internal interrupts,
but fundamentally the interrupts.
When you execute an interrupt,
you are you are going to run some code.
And what we are talking about here is that think about like locker choir
disable all interrupts.
So this means also there is no contact switching because in order to have
also the context switching,
you're going to have the timer interrupt, right?
Or they interrupt another interrupt external interrupts to do it.
And the local release you enable interrupts.
So it is a problem with this approach is not going to work.
Right?
Before we acquire an interrupt.
If you're sorry,
if you do acquire a lock and you disable all the interrupts,
then you do something like a while through your hank computer hanks,
again, it cannot be interrupted.
Right?
You need to do something like ill to voluntarily provide give access
to the scheduler in order to the kernel,
to schedule another thread.
But this code will lock the entire computer.
It's very risky.
You don't want to do that.
And there are many other reasons like for real time systems,
there is no guarantee of timing,
because the critical section can be arbitrary long.
Obviously, what happens when there are very important io events?
So let's think about a better implementation of the locks by disabling interrupts.
So here it is on.
Basically, you maintain is a way to think about.
You use a lock to implement a lock.
Right?
What you want is that when the segment that you want to minimize the
code between disable interrupt and enable interrupts,
that's what you want to do.
Okay?
Because the problem is the previous in the previous case,
the problem is that you disable interrupts and you enter the critical section,
then the critical section can be arbitrary along.
Right?
Depends on the application.
But in this case,
we are going to implement the lock with a disable interrupt and enable,
interrupts,
and then expose acquire lock and release lock to the application,
implemented under the hood by the disabled interrupt.
But notice here,
the disabled interrupts and enable interrupts.
You have a very small piece of code here.
It's going to run very quickly.
Ideally, what you do for the choir say the value is a lock value.
It's either free or busy.
So to acquire it,
if you disable the interrupt,
to manipulate this value,
if the value is busy,
what did we say?
We want to sleep.
So put thread on the wait list and go to sleep,
and somehow you want to enable interrupts.
So as I said can execute alice,
you acquire the lock value is busy and enable,
interrupts and for relieves,
you disable interrupts.
You look, if there is only anyone on the whale queue waiting for the lock.
If it is, you give the lock to one of the thread or from the way queue.
And you play the thread on the ready queue,
that thread can execute a critical section.
If there is no one on the way q the value is free and you enable the interests.
You see here the way it happens,
because you put the thread,
we're waiting on the waiting queue.
And then you you'd get that you take that thread from the waiting queue when
another thread released the lock.
Any questions here?
Now, it's against what I was saying.
You inclement input in increment a lock by used by another lock.
The reason for that because the second lock you are going to use,
you can use disable and enable interacts by making
sure that the critical section protected by disabling and enable
interrupts is very short.
This can be implemented by the operating system.
You have control about on the length of the critical section protecting
by the interrupt,
disabling and enabling.
So that's the main difference from using disable,
interrupts and enable interrupts directly.
With this design,
the users can take as long as they want in the critical section,
because their critical section is not protecting by disable interrupt
or enable interrupt.
Now, what is a big problem?
Here is a big problem.
We need to enable interacts when we put the thread on the wake you,
because we need to allow as a threat to execute in particular,
the strategies in the critical section.
But the question is,
where do you need to install to enable the interrupts?
There are three possibilities.
One is here before putting the thread on the way it is correct.
That's it's not because the release can check the cure and not waken
up the thread.
Right?
So enable upon in inputs of enabling traps here.
Before the study sponsor put on the weight queue,
you do contact switch,
the current context switch to the thread, another thread,
which is executing the release.
Right?
The release is going to look at the if there is any set on the wave queue,
and there is none,
because acquire was didn't have a chance to play the set on the way.
So the threat will not be awkward.
What if you put the name the enable interrupts before go to?
These are corner?
Does if so here is a question michael from michael does if have
to be replaced with wild?
Now i'll let you know why,
because let me go through this slide and i'll tell you why after that.
Now, because this is not correct,
either because the release put the thread on the ridicule,
but the threat still think it needs to go to sleep.
So you put the threat on the waiting queue.
You enable, interrupts,
now assumes as a release of their from the other side is executed.
Right?
And here the release is looking on the way q and you have a set on the way
to q
and take that thread to execute it.
But then when the australians executed,
it goes to sleep.
So you don't execute.
Now it is a question.
I said that it's a busy that we need to have some waiting for any synchronization,
primitive.
You need to have waiting.
Why we don't have a while here?
The reason we don't have a while here is very simple,
like I mentioned,
but probably I was not very clear is because of waiting here happens
implicitly by acquire.
If the value, if the lock is busy,
you put the thread on the waiting queue,
putting the thread of the waiting queue.
That act means waiting.
Right?
It doesn't happen in the program.
It happens in the kernel.
Right?
You put the thread on the waiting queue,
and the thread will wait until the release is going to be exactly.
And here's a lock is at least,
anyway, in order to solve the problem,
you need to put to lisa log after going to sleep.
But how you do it?
Because the thread is sleeping.
So how can execute an instruction to enable the interrupts?
Any
suggestions?
So the problem is very simple.
It's like I want logically to enable the interrupts after I go to sleep.
But how can I do that?
Because I am sleeping,
modify sleep instruction,
obviously functional.
That's good.
But I need to how you modify that's not easy.
You can try it, but you'll see that it's not easy,
because you still have a bunch of instruction.
And you'll see the same problem like you have here.
Have the kernel do it for now.
You can have the kernel do it for now.
But how do you do it?
You do it on whenever you lose your sleep.
That's not good,
right?
Because you can call a sleep for many other cases.
So actually the solution is quite brilliant.
In my opinion,
if the threat which go to sleep cannot enable the interrupts,
the solution is that another thread,
which wakes up is going to enable the interests.
So you do it on contact switching.
In some sense, you can argue this is done by the kernel.
You can do that in the kernel.
But this is a solution here.
Right?
The nice thing about the solution is, again, is like,
if the thread which goes to sleep cannot enable the interrupt because
already went to sleep,
the solution is for the next thread,
which when you return from the sleep to enable the interrupts.
Right?
You have another strategy able to interrupt.
So this is pretty nice.
So when you wake up,
you enable interrupts some announcements,
design, review schedule,
as soon as possible you haven't done already.
The review is your da needs to be done by this thursday,
so you have 2 days and show up on time listed.
There is no vertical time we have.
Now 10 minutes after meter,
it will be between 7:00 and 9:00 pm 8 days from now.
We is going to cover everything up,
two.
And including the next lecture,
there will be a midterm review of monday,
37and 9.
And for logistics on profiting policies and so forth, shit.
Look out for the boss.
Let me see, sorry, it's 29.
What i'm saying?
Wednesday 9:29,
thanks for catching.
So question here was how do you can contact switch?
Because here,
everything disabled that the interrupts are disabled.
So here we are not talking about contact switching based on the timer event.
We are talking about here.
This is here.
Let me just see all the code.
This is a code.
You see this part where if anyone on the waiting queue,
so when you do this,
you go to sleep by the go to sleep means you yield the control to the kernel.
And the kernel,
the interrupts,
you are going to execute this instruction
and take the thread of the wake queue.
And when you do this,
you enable the interrupts again.
So this enable interrupts from here.
I hope that you are seeing what i'm highlighting is going to have.
It's going to happen here.
You take the thread of the wake you and you are going to you return
from the this means you return from the sleep,
and you are going to enable the interrupts just before place on the ready.
Hopefully it answers the question.
So let's see how here and we have another 20 minutes.
So here this give you a sense about how this is working,
doing a kind of assimilation.
So here is local choir.
We have a release.
This is a code.
We have two strides executing the code saturday and said each of them
is doing local choir,
go to the critical section, local release.
Let's say, said they acquire it is able the instruction,
it is able to interrupt, sorry,
the value.
So in this particular case,
someone doesn't anyone has a critical sector?
This is the first thread,
a we look executive choir.
There is no one using the critical section.
The value is zero.
Increment, the value to one,
which means that it acquires a lock,
and it enables the interrupts.
And now you are in critical section.
Right?
This is what happened, right?
At the same time,
let's assume that while you are in the critical section, thread,
b is starting to be executed.
Again, while you are in a critical executive section,
the interrupts are enabled.
Thread b is going to start running saturday in the same in the meantime,
it seems a ridicule.
This is just contact switching,
traditional contact switching.
You do the local choir,
execute local choir.
But now you look, and what you can see is a value each one,
because the lock is acquired by thread a you cannot acquire the lock.
A beard cannot acquire the lock as well.
So you go to sleep.
Right?
You are going thread is going to be waiting,
it's going to be on the wake you.
Okay?
And now you are going to start executing thread a because it's ready to execute.
And this thread b went to sleep and thread b 111 is going to sleep,
is going to voluntarily release the cpo
the kernel is going to start executing saturday,
resuming the exhibition of saturday in the critical section ends,
and then is releasing the lock.
And now, if anyone waste on the waiting queue,
is anyone waiting on the waiting queue?
It's thread b right?
Thread b is placed on the ridicule from the waiting queue on the ridicule.
And now you enable the interrupts.
You are done.
Thread b is ready to execute.
And then,
next time you are going to execute thread,
instead be executes acquire the locks and continue and enter the critical session.
So please go and try to go carefully through this example.
Any questions?
So what is the problem?
So it is working.
Yes, he's working.
But there are several issues.
You cannot give lock implementation to users.
They are going to make mistakes.
Now,
you can solve that by saying, operate,
the kernel can do it.
And that's a very valid answer.
But the other problem,
especially with the interrupts,
is that it doesn't work well on multiprocessors.
You have multiple cars which execute in parallel.
And all cars can access a memory.
Therefore, the value of the lock.
When you need to disable interrupts on all the course,
you need to send messages between course,
to do it,
to disable interrupts or enable interrupts which is very expensive.
The alternative to this is to have atomic instructions,
right?
And typically what they do,
they read a value and write a value atomically.
So instead,
loading stores only is reading a value is atomic and writing a value is atomic.
But this adds another element.
The read you can have a read and write,
which is our atomic like one operation.
These are great.
They are working both only processor and multiprocessors.
And they are quite simple.
And here are a few of them.
The first one is test and set.
Okay?
What is doing best and set?
Read a value of a particular memory,
a a particular,
the value at a particular address and returns it,
and also at the same time set it to one.
So reading the value,
setting it to one,
and returning the previous values of value before us at one original value.
It's atomic.
That's it.
That's atomic instruction.
You see, there are multiple operations in this, which are atomic,
which are in this atomic instruction.
Then it's a swap.
And a swap is basically what is doing.
Right?
You get a value.
You sorry,
you put a value in a register.
That value put in the register is going to be swapped with the value
at a particular address.
This is what it is.
So you shall give a value in a register,
which is going to be swapped with a value at a particular address.
Finally, it's compare and swap.
It's a little bit more complicated.
You give two registers here.
It was a memory address is still equally registered,
is still equal with register one.
Then you put the memory value and register to.
Otherwise, you don't change the memory.
These are exactly six.
Obviously, it's intel.
6,800 was a very popular chip,
motorola chip, which was the cheap for used by apple, early apple,
and macintosh.
Computers.
Testing said it's actually in most architectures today.
Here is an example about how to use,
compare and swap.
And this is about how you are going to use to insert atomically.
A new element is ahead of a queue.
This is what you want to do it.
This is n cube operation.
Insert.
A new element is ahead of the queue.
Here, how do you do it?
First of all, you have a while.
Do you see do until?
Right?
It's a loop.
And in the low in the condition breaks it from this slope.
You can tell and stop at one and object.
Right?
Object is the object identifier,
r one.
You can see is a route address.
Okay?
It's your original route.
Right?
So what happens here is basically,
you are going to wait until what you do here.
You set the route to the new object.
Okay?
And then you are waiting until the route is pointing.
Sorry.
What you do is the following thing.
You set the next the object to point to the first element in the queue.
This one.
This is what you do.
Right?
This is you get the pointer from the root,
which is the point of the first element in the queue.
Then you set the next,
the new object to point to the old first object in the queue.
Then you are going to use a compare and swap to move the pointer
of the route to the new object.
You wait until that is done.
So that's what happens here.
Now, how we implement lock switch test and test.
Test and set is very easy acquire.
You will set up the value to zero here.
Acquire it's,
you just wait for test and set to be one,
then release you just set value to zero.
What happens here?
Remember, what does test and set is doing?
The test and set is going to read to return the
value and set it to one in one instruction.
If the value is zero,
you return as a value to while while is going to exit and set value to one.
It's great.
Lock is not busy acquired as a lock.
If the lock is busy,
so value will be one.
You are going to set the value to one.
It's already one.
Nothing will happen, but you return one.
You are going to be stuck in the while loop until the release
is going to be executed and the value set to zero.
It's quite elegant.
Obviously,
the problem here you have the while you do the while in the program.
Right?
So very inefficient.
You don't want to do that.
But this is a correct implementation,
very simple implementation.
So you see our test and set allows us a very simple implementation of a lot.
Right?
And again, the testing set very easy to remember.
You do two things,
return the value and set this one.
That's all
the problem is busy waiting,
busy waiting.
Again, it's a correct implementation.
The machine can still receive, interrupts.
The user code can still use a lock work on multiprocessor,
all positives, but you don't want this busy week.
It's inefficient.
Also can result in what we call priority inversion.
Right?
If the busy waiting thread has a higher priority than the thread holding
the lock,
right?
This is a another way to think about it.
Oops.
Another way to think about it is like you have two threads,
one has higher priorities,
and the other one higher priority is going to be always executed
before the other.
The one is a low priority.
Now, the thread is a low priority is going to have the lock.
If the third is a lower priority has a lock,
the third is a higher priority will be stuck because it's going to be stuck
in the while loop.
The thread is allowed priority cannot execute,
because the surveys are our higher priority,
but because the thread is a lower priority cannot execute.
It cannot exit the critical section.
It cannot release a lock.
This is priority inversion.
And this happened in many cases.
So that's the problem, right?
And so we really want because we don't want us as
to this busy waiting,
we need to find another solution.
And in general,
when you have the homework problem or exams solution,
unless as always specified,
you should avoid busy waiting.
Okay?
Now let's see for the next couple of minutes,
think about maybe better logs using test and set.
The question cannot use the sunset to implement locks without busy waiting.
And this answer here,
we cannot, but we can minimize a busy waiting section.
And again, the solution here is like with,
if you remember, with interrupts,
we use a lock to implement a lock.
In some sense,
the local and implement is is called value.
And then what we do,
we protect the critical section of the acquire
and release the critical section being the one,
which modifies the lock,
which is value by a test and set.
So use a testing set to implement and protect these critical sections
in acquiring release.
The solution is very simple.
We have define another variable.
It is called guard.
This ensures a mature mutual exclusion for these critical sections,
which are in the acquire and release.
Okay?
While we initialize to zero,
while god,
if god is zero,
then you are going to acquire the lock.
So I will exit,
right?
Because remember,
testing set returns the current value of water that is zero and satisfying.
You exit the y loop,
and then you set up the value.
But what do you know?
And the release is a sense.
Again, you protect the critical section by test and set.
Here you have the same problem like with the release interrupts.
When you go to sleep, you also need to put set a guard to zero,
then when you need to set up it.
Right?
But this will be much easier
when sleep has to be sure to resell the guard value.
We are going to end up here this lecture.
On this note.
We are going to continue next time.
You should think a little bit about this code.
And there is a question here.
Why?
Let me see.
I'm going to stop here, because for some reason,
I lost my pointer, so I cannot see my pointer on the screen.
So there is a question at the end of the previous slide,
please think about it until the next time without looking at the next slide.
And that is,
yeah, that there is a question here.
If while test and so we are the lecture is done.
I am going to try to ask the last question,
which was on the chat.
We'll meet next time.
So for people who want to hear the answer can stick around.
And the question here is that from Michael is well test and set ball,
you yield critical section.
Then while is zero,
then you set up all to zero.
Yeah,
I think that should work.
So,
yeah,
if you that should work,
the problem here is all that.
If you yield,
then you are still going,
you yield the processor.
You are still going to be wake woken up before the lock.
It's available.
For instance, you again,
it's like you go,
you yield the processor to.
And for another thread,
the threat can execute.
It may not be necessary.
The threat who acquire, who has a lock.
When that thread finishes on,
a time quantity finishes,
we are going to be open again and so forth.
So it's still not as efficient.
It's better than just doing busy wait,
but it's not as good as putting the thread on the wake you and being woken
up only when the lock was released.
In this case, you are going to be open up multiple times.
So is that i'll see you next time.
Thanks, everyone.