Hello, everyone.
So welcome to the nice lecture.
This lecture, it's the content of this lecture.
It's included in your first meter.
That's quite important.
It's also a very important lecture for your future homeworks and projects.
So,
and we are going to continue our discussion about abstraction to implement critical
sections and synchronization between processes.
If you remember,
last time we discussed that one of the main abstraction,
which it makes it easier to implement critical sections,
exclusion from critical sections.
So only one thread it should be active in a critical section
at a given time or locks.
And we discuss the implementation of locks using interrupts.
And then we said there are some disadvantages of using interacts and some dangers.
And then we discuss about,
then using atomic operation,
which are more sophisticated than load and store to implement these locks.
And one of them,
it will be like best and set.
I if you remember,
is a test and set,
it's takes a value
and maintains a local variable.
Think about distance that maintains a local variable.
The atomic operation is that taking a value,
updating the local variable is a new value,
and then returning the previous value of the local variable.
That's pretty much.
This is and implementation.
Again, we discussed last time of a lock acquire and lock release and
using test and set,
and basically use test and set here also to implement mutual
exclusion are of operating of the is the value of the lock.
The lock,
value of the lock, which whereas is busy or free,
determine whether you can enter or not in the critical section
of the program of the user.
Now we have a second,
we use test and set for a second smaller critical section,
which is only concern of updating the lock value to be your free.
If you remember,
all these synchronization primitives involves weight,
the reason for that is because it's fundamental because if you have
two threads which wants to enter in the same critical section,
you can only allow one thread to enter in the critical section.
Therefore, the other thread has nothing else to do,
but wait for the first step to finish.
So that's why waiting is fundamental.
Okay?
The other thing you remember,
if you wait one way to wait,
it's easy to implement the still busy waiting.
You constantly check whether the critical section is free,
whether you can acquire the lock.
But this consumes the cpu cycles without doing any useful work.
So therefore,
waiting, what you want to invent,
the best way to implement,
waiting and the preferred way is to go to sleep,
to put the thread when the waiting queue,
and then to be open up when there are the previous thread exceeds
the critical section.
Okay?
This is what you see here.
If the value is busy,
if someone acquired a lock and has acquired a locker in the critical section,
you put the thread on the weight queue,
and then you go to sleep,
and then you reset this card, which is, again,
this card it's about.
It's basically you freeze a lock for the critical section,
which is concerned with updating the busy value.
As it's the value is busy,
you set the value to be,
this requires a lock,
then you again, said,
go out to zero.
So that for you are going to allow another thread to look,
tend to read the log value and modify it.
Any questions here?
So not, again, that we have the same discussion.
We have the same discussion like in the in the case of when using interrupt
to implement the choir and release.
And that is is when we are going to set the guard to zero,
there is one you are going to disable the interact.
And this needs to be done.
You cannot do before sleep,
you cannot do before the thread on weight queue.
Just remember.
Why is that?
You can look at the last lecture.
So you need to do, in some sense, after,
but then after the thread itself,
which call acquire cannot do it because it's sleeping.
So that has to be done either by the operating system or by the next trend,
which is going to be scheduled to reset the guard.
Okay?
Here it's a simple example.
This is a great question.
So one question here, it was a the guard and value will be on the hip.
They are going to be on.
They're going to be a global variables,
so everyone can access them.
Now,
we've seen two implementation is actually of acquire and release locks.
One is using interacts,
and the other one using test and set.
And this basically shows is to show you that actually the logic is very,
very similar.
And you can think about while test and set,
it's similarly disabled interrupts and enabling and guard a reseting guard
to zero is like enabling the interacts.
This is against the code for we went over last lecture about implementing,
acquire,
and release by disabling and enabling the internet.
And if you remember,
also what they did last time,
when we talk about locks we did in two stages.
First of all,
we said we gave this very trivial implementation of the locks acquire.
You disable the interrupts,
why it is able to interrupt,
because you don't want new new threats to interrupt you, right?
While you are in the critical section, right?
And then the release is enabling the internet.
But this was very dangerous because if you call as the user level,
acquiring, disable, interrupts,
and you have a very long critical section or you make mistakes and you have
an infinite while loop in the critical section.
Then your computer will hack.
You can do anything about.
The only thing probably is power off power on.
Right?
So therefore,
is a more sophisticated implementation was to use disable and enable
interrupts only for updating the value of the lock.
Now you have a value of the lock which set to zero and you disable
and enable interrupts to update that value,
right?
Or to leave that value.
Now you still use disable and enable interacts.
But now it's very short.
The critical section is very short and is going to finish very fast.
Right?
If you look,
again, if you look now at the same example,
but now implementing, acquire, and release,
using test and set,
we went again through two iterations.
The first iteration was very simple that while distance set values,
you are doing the values, a lot of value.
While this is why the value is one.
Right?
Again, the distance said here,
if value is one,
is going to returns the previous value of the internal variable
of test and set,
and then set that variable to the new value.
If it's the previous one was zero, returned,
zero means there's a lock.
It's acquired.
But now he said to one next time,
when someone tries,
the value is one,
the internal variable is one.
The internal variables will not change.
And the test and said returns once you are going to be stuck in the white group.
Okay?
But it's, again, the problem is this one,
and the release is simply set the value to zero.
And the problem with this one,
remember this while, look,
again, it's like it's busy waiting.
I which we discuss that you want to wait, we want to, sorry,
it's busy waiting.
You should remember we want to avoid.
Right.
Again, in this case,
we went to the second iteration,
which we just also presented again,
earlier in the lecture, today's lecture.
And you use the test and set only to protect the critical sections,
which are concerned with updating the value of the lock.
Now, again, this is much shorter,
critical section.
The test and set will be,
will you wait only for a very short time?
And now,
instead of like, in this case,
you wait pink, you are waiting.
In the previous case, you are waiting.
As long as someone is in the critical section, do busy waiting.
So constraints as if you cycles.
In this case,
in the more refined iteration,
you are going to put the thread which is waiting on the wake you.
Right?
So there is no busy waiting.
Any questions here?
So what we are going again with synchronization?
So let's see what we've done.
We look on the hardware support.
The love stores is able to interrupt test and set and compare and swap.
These are similar contest and set and compare and swap.
They are much more useful than load and store.
And we saw how you can't use these to implement locks.
And also he discusses abstraction about singapore's.
And and then next also like that,
we are going to talk about monitors.
It's, again, the higher level,
the abstraction, the easier will be for the programs,
for the application to implement mutual exclusion and critical sections.
Next, we are going to go and talk more about this abstraction.
Let's talk again about summer force that, right?
And if you remember,
just to remind you the summer force,
you have that a little bit more sophisticated than locks.
A lock can have only two values,
01, or busy and three.
We summer force is like a counter,
write a special counter,
like you have a primitive which increments the summer
for and a primitive decline as a summer for.
Then if sum of four is zero,
then you are going to wait that you are very much.
You are waiting for a lock,
which is busy,
if you remember.
So that provides you a little bit more,
a little bit more power.
And therefore,
it also gives you more,
if gives you more functionality,
you can implement with the summer for both critical sections.
But you also implement and material exclusion,
but you also implement can scheduling constraints basically telling
signaling one approach a process
from another process or a threat from another threat.
If you remember,
the example we gave last time about this was about,
if you remember,
it was about implementing the strategy,
waiting the thread who launches a create another thread,
waiting for the new creative,
for the greatest thread to finish.
Right?
It's again.
Now, we are going to move from locks and some efforts to a new abstraction,
which is called monitors.
And monitors are better,
are simply more powerful.
And and the main idea is to split between and
supporting explicitly these two functionality
about mark mutual exclusion and scheduling constraints.
You use locks for mutual exclusion and what are called condition variable
for scheduling constraints,
right?
A monitor.
It's a lock and a zero or more conditional variable for managing
concurrent access to share that.
And we'll talk more about that.
Some languages provide this negatively.
And most of the others,
you can use lock and conditional variables as a distinct abstractions.
I'm going again,
if you have any questions,
let me know this is, again,
these lectures,
the past lecture in these lectures are not very easy to follow,
because they are about concurrency,
are about programs which execute come correctly.
And like we discussed last time,
it's we,
as humans are not very used about handling many things which happen
at the same time.
We had much better in equalizing sequentializing things.
So it's perfectly fine.
I if you feel this is a little bit more challenging,
but at the same time,
this also means that you should spend a little bit more time
to try to understand deeply what's happening here.
Again, some languages provide monitors.
And let's see what is conditional variables,
conditional variables,
what is a conditional variable?
It's a queue of threads waiting for something inside a critical section to happen.
And the nice thing about the critical section send the conditional,
sorry,
and I think about the monitors and conditional variables is conditional variables,
allow sleeping inside the critical section by atomically,
releasing the lock at a time regardlessly.
So what I mean by that,
here is what I mean.
Remember about this slide?
I'll go soon in again in presentation mode.
Here,
it's a game.
If you try to acquire the lock,
and the lock is busy,
so the value is one.
You have to go to sleep.
And what you want,
we want this,
how we want this to happen is to put the thread in the waiting queue.
But when you put the set of the waiting queue,
you need also to really to resell the guard To let other threads.
And there is a critical section to look at the value,
maybe to modify the value.
So now the sleep and the guard have to happen at the same time.
Okay?
They need to be atomic and monitors,
provide and conditional variables for monitors.
Provide you this atomicity between the threads going to sleep and giving
up releasing the lock,
because it's equally zero release a clock associated with a guard atomically.
You don't need to worry about that.
That's what conditional variables in monitors are going to do for you.
And that's why they are very useful.
Here are the operations,
the operation you wait for the lock,
which I thought you can you can automatically,
this is going to,
the operation is going to automatically leads a lock and go to sleep.
You can acquire the lock like that.
Will also have a few examples to make it more understandable.
Then you have signals.
You remember that one of the use of the summer force was to signal when one,
a thread, one,
an event right between two threads.
So now you have a very primitive,
which is called makes a lot of sense.
A name is signal.
You have also something which is called broadcast,
the signal,
its way, its waking,
a thread, which is waiting for some particular event to happen,
broadcasts,
its waking multiple waiters,
all the waiters, which run,
which waits for the people.
Signal, if there are multiple waiters,
it's going to wake only one.
And that's non deterministic.
You don't know which one is going to be waking up.
And in many cases, you don't care.
Broadcast wakes all of them.
Okay.
Now, when you do that,
when you do operation on the condition variables,
you need to own the lock.
Right?
Because this is in critical section.
This is one way to represent it.
The monikers,
x and y are conditional variables.
Each of them is associated acute.
And you have a log,
which provides a mutual exclusion with a shared data.
In this monitor.
The conditional variables are shared it.
But it's, again,
one of the main advantage you are allowed to wait in the critical section.
This is not allowed for summer force,
which makes the summer falls very,
how much harder to use.
Now, it's, again, let's see.
And we are going to have a lot of examples.
So we give you a better sense about how these monitors,
how you use the monitors.
And also we are going to talk about how they are implemented.
Hopefully, by the end of these lectures,
we are going to have a pretty good feeling about monitors.
Okay.
Here is an infinite cube, single eyes.
You got producer, consumer.
It's infinite in the sense that the producer can put any numbers of items
in the queue is infinite.
How do you do it?
The producer is like your choir is a lock.
It really is a lock.
You have a buffer lock,
and the consumer also acquired the lock and release a lock.
Right?
This is in order to protect the critical sections which are operating
on the queue.
Right?
You don't want a producer and the consumer to operate on the cure
at the same time.
Because inserting adding a new element to the queue,
removing an element from the queue are not atomic operations.
Therefore,
bad things can happen while you both of them are manipulating the pointers,
right?
To insert or remove the element from the queue.
Now, you need to you,
you can use these conditioned variables like buff cv
in order to signal the producer.
That's basically what says.
The buff cv is a signal,
a is a way for the producer to signal the consumer that there are elements
in the buffer in the queue.
This is what it is, your signal.
It what do you do from in the consumer?
While it's empty?
So you look for the cure as it's empty.
Right?
It's in the critical section,
so it's far as fair to look at the queue,
because no one else will modify the queue while you are
in the critical section to operate on the queue.
And then you call this condition, wait.
So you're waiting for this signal for the best subsidy.
And you also, you see,
this is the first argument of condition weight.
And the second argument in buffalo, why is that?
Because if the queue is empty,
this is true.
This in condition wait.
And but what you are going to do is basically you are going to put
the threat to sleep,
and you need to release a lock.
Right?
This basically tells the condition wait to release the lock once the thread
is going to sleep.
Remember,
we want here to have atomic operation.
The slip, these things above it should be an atomic operation.
Aaron,
it has a question here.
If you use a broadcast,
it will create a race condition.
Not necessary.
We'll see that in an example.
Right?
Because still,
not all you can wake up all the waiters,
but only if all the waiters want to go to the same critical section,
still only one will succeed.
Okay?
And the other one will go back to wait.
So you you are still going to be, okay.
Sorry.
So this is basically what happened here.
Now, and I think this was a question last time.
I don't remember who has that question.
It was a great question about what you remember.
If you go to,
I think, was in the context of test onset,
why do you use while and not if it's a similar thing here,
and we'll explain why.
And what is the difference.
And the problem here is that if you look at this piece of code,
will you just the consumer wait for the queue to be non empty to have elements?
In order to be queue?
A new element from the queue?
It has a wire.
Right?
And the natural question you can ask, look, why?
Because the thread is going to sleep, right?
So why do you do that?
And it's true that it's a good question.
Let me start with that.
You see that why should I do the while?
Because again,
it's like the study is going to sleep,
and it's going to be open up if another thread exceeds the critical section.
Right?
So I should test again.
The answer here is that it depends on the implementation.
Okay?
You can actually, depending on the implementation,
you can replace while with if.
And that will be correct.
And there are two implementation,
one in which you need to put while,
you have to have while.
And the other one you need to have, you can do,
you can use if the first one in which requires you to have to save while,
is called messer style,
right?
Because it was implemented in xerox parc mass operating system.
And this is what most operating system are using.
The one in which you can use if is horror,
style implementation.
This is a british musician tony hall.
And in this case,
you can use if let's see how her monitor.
So this is the one you can use if how they are implement.
Here is for how it's implemented.
You have acquired on both sides.
And let's say the first,
you so, sorry,
so in both cases,
you obviously,
you protect the critical sections by above lock.
And the code on the left hand side is going to send a signal.
And as a result of the signal,
the thread which are waiting on this conditional by variable,
buff cv is going to wake up.
The sled on the left is going to send a signal.
And this the code on the right is going to be of a thread,
which is going to be open up by this signal.
Let's see what happens.
So it's hard what happens when you execute this signal.
You automatically release a lock,
the buff lock here,
and the cpu and your schedule immediately,
the thread which is waiting on the above cv conditional barrier.
You are going to execute it.
And then at the end,
you are going to release the lock.
And then you go back and continue to execute the first thread,
which signaled the second one.
And that's what it is.
Right?
This is the implementation now.
So this seems like good, right?
Is basically in the signal.
When I signal someone, I stop,
I give the lock to the thread which is writing.
And this and I the the operating system will schedule that thread to execute,
exceed the critical section.
And after that, I gave me that I I get the control back.
Good.
This is correct.
What is a problem?
The problem here is,
it's a little bit harder to implement and may lead to a lot of context switches.
Furthermore, as you'll see,
from the next messy style implementation is not really necessary.
And here it's about messer implementation with a messer implementation.
When you after your signal,
you do not give the control to the thread waiting for unconditioned barrier.
Instead, what you do,
you just take that thread,
waiting on the conditional variable,
and you put it,
move it from the waiting queue to the radical,
is ready to execute.
And then you continue.
And eventually later,
when you are done,
you are going to schedule the operating system,
is going to schedule the thread,
which is now in the radical,
sometimes later.
But you see now,
so what is but we see now that now you need to check this condition, again,
is mpq why?
Because in the meantime,
there can be another between,
in the meantime,
you can have a race condition.
And another thread comes and wants to acquire acquires a lock,
because it's free.
And now, you are going to have two threads on this,
which are on the ridicule,
which one to enter is the same critical section.
So that is not good.
Right?
So that's kind of the problem,
right?
That's not.
But by doing so,
you are going to have less context switches, right?
In this case.
Right?
You have the first thread finishes exceeding the critical section.
Then you are going to,
after that, you are going to execute the second set.
So it's one context switch.
In the previous case,
you have one context switch,
going from the signaling thread to the thread which is writing and back.
So at least you have to.
Right?
Okay.
Any questions?
Let's not look now at our buffer,
q example and use a more.
And now we are using,
we are using two conditioned variables for producer and the consumer.
Let me give you the code.
We are also looking now is bounded buffer.
So in previous case,
we use only unconditioned variable that it was unbounded buffer,
infinite buffer size.
Here is bounded.
How do you have two variables?
You can check whether the buffer is full or empty.
And then,
if the buffer is full, while the buffer is full, obviously,
the producer weights.
Otherwise, you incur an item in the buffer and you signal the consumer.
Because now the buffer is no longer empty,
and the consumer can drain,
can take that element from the buffer.
The consumer is the same.
If the buffer was,
if the buffer, if it's empty,
you can do anything.
There is no item you can take from the buffer.
If the buffer is not empty,
you decue it and you signal a producer,
then there is at least one free slot in the buffer.
You can insert a new item.
Right?
This is what any questions?
You see that fundamentally,
what you do is condition variable.
Here is like you mentioned earlier,
is to signal between threads.
When an event occurs.
In this particular case,
the producer signal to consumer when it's inserted an element in the buffer
and the consumer signals to the producer when it removed an element
from the buffer.
Now, the producer now that for sure it can add a new element is above.
Also, again, I want to reiterate that the thread when he's waiting,
it doesn't do busy,
waiting is sleeping.
The condition variable,
the semantics there or can't wait,
is to take that thread,
put it on the wait queue and release the lock to the critical section.
Rough lock.
Can you construct monitor from some of us?
The locking aspect is easy, right?
Remember,
you can use a semaphore which has only two values.
And the way it's basically decrementing, the semaphore.
If it's one, you initialize on 4~1.
If it's one, you require the lock, and it's zero.
If someone else said calm since one to decrement it,
then it came out and discussed the white.
Right?
Because you need to wait for the someone else,
increase you to increment the semaphore back to one.
Right?
This will be the signal, right?
So you see things.
But the biggest problem here is that the wait,
if you do that,
while you are in a critical section,
and you have to do that to be in the critical section,
then we are going to wait,
and you are not going to release a lock.
Right?
So that's the key.
The monitors on the conditioned variable, conditioned weight,
that function is releasing the lock atomically when you go to sleep.
Right?
And are this working?
This is what about this?
One, right?
You release a lock, you put that you release a lock immediately.
Right?
You after wait, right?
This will not work in one of the reasons the conditional variables are have
no history in the sense that I always signal.
If I signal you 5 times,
you are going to be open only once, right?
But some of us have history.
Let me see.
So this is exactly what I was saying.
It's a great question that I will.
The question is,
if the buffer is half full,
will the condition variable still going to signal in a a is a in the either
case?
Absolutely.
That's exactly what we mean here.
The condition variable has no history.
You are going to be signaled.
In that case, a signal doesn't mean anything,
because you may not,
if you signal and there is no thread on waiting, then nothing will happen.
Very good question.
And,
yeah, this is exactly what I said.
It was if the thread signals and no one is waiting,
there is no operation.
There is no.
If a sled later waits,
then it's a problem right now here.
But because it's, again,
if that happens,
then it's going to you wait with your visa lock.
And the other thread cannot increment the semaphore.
Which correspond to the lock.
So you are going to be to be stuck.
Anyway.
So there are a bunch of questions here,
and I invite you to answer the questions.
And I just want to as an exercise for you.
And you may be very well get some problem like this one and asking you
these questions.
But instead,
because you have running a little bit out of time,
I want to go to the next part of the lecture,
which is extremely important part of the lecture.
And this is about reader and write that problem.
Let me just see.
Ii think I don't have the announcement before going there.
Let me do verbally.
And i'm going to add the slide about the announcement to the lecture right
after the lecture slide,
right after the election.
So basically, the most important thing is that obviously,
next week,
we are going to have the first meter and to be between seven and nine.
On wednesday,
we are going to have also a session for between 7:00 and
9:00 pm on monday for the midterm.
So you can come and ask any questions you have.
And this is pretty much it.
We are going to provide more informations as you go close to the meter.
But if you have now, any questions?
Let me know.
Now, this is a more complex problem.
This will really illustrate very clearly the use of monitors.
So here is a problem.
The problem is about accessing a database which is shared by multiple people.
A can have a bunch of people who want to write and a bunch of people who
want to read to the database.
These rights and read operations happen concurrently.
And they modify the same data,
right?
How you are going to implement it.
One thing is to use a lock for the entire database.
Right?
You read or write,
acquire the lock.
You do your job, and it is a lock.
So is that
sufficient?
That's a question for you.
Yes.
It is sufficient, meaning that.
Correct.
But it can be very slow, right?
I if you think about fundamentally give me two examples why this is inefficient.
It's exactly, I don't.
Aaron gave a great answer.
So basically,
for instance,
if people only read from the database,
there is no need to lock it,
because nothing will change.
Also, there are other reasons we are going to discuss later.
But what even if you do,
if you have rights,
then the rights can be different records.
They don't need to wait after each other.
We are not going to solve this problem.
Here.
We are going to solve the first problem on multiple readers.
We should allow them to read the database if there are no writers.
Read writers, yeah.
Very good.
Let's see what you want the less from the solution.
Readers can access database ones.
There are no writers.
This is exactly like we said.
If there are no writers, no,
no value will change.
So therefore,
the readers, any number of readers can read concurrent.
Writers can access database,
a writer can access a database when there is no reader reading.
Now, as a writer modifying the database.
And finally, we have some state variables.
We want only one thread to modify them at a given time.
Right?
This is,
so this is the basic solution,
the structure for the reader.
You wait until there are no writers access a database,
check out and wake up waiting writers and the writer
waiting wait until there are no active readers or writers access database,
and then you check out and you wake up as awaiting readers or writers.
So let me ask you this question.
You see here,
there is some asymmetry, some asymmetry.
There is the river driven is derived from our constraints.
Right?
If a reader,
it doesn't need to wait until there are no other readers,
because it doesn't conflict with other readers,
it can only conflict with writers.
That's how you wait until no writers.
The writers is going to conflict bosses, readers, and writers.
Because if a reader is going to read the data,
while the writer changing the data,
it can read, the reader can read garbage.
But then there is another estimate when a writer is done, is done,
is going to wait three wake up readers and writers.
While when the reader is done,
is only tried to wake up writers.
Why this asymmetric?
Why do you think?
Why do you think the reader is not just waiting algorithms?
Waking up algorithms?
Very good.
The readers are all concurrent so that it should be known
as any other reader to wake up.
Very good.
Okay.
Let's move on.
How do we implement this with our monitor?
Is a beautiful abstraction we just learned about.
Right?
So, you see,
wake up a waiting a writer and wake up waiting readers or writers.
What are these?
You can implement them.
Condition variables is like signals and wait and waiting,
going to that conditional variable.
We have two conditional variables to read to write.
Then what are the state variables?
The number of active readers,
number of active writers,
how many active writers can have at a given time?
One.
Right?
Remember,
we cannot have two writers at the same time.
Then the number of waiting readers are the readers which are waiting to read.
And the number of waiting writers,
when do you have adidas waiting?
When there is one active writer?
Very good.
So let's write the code for the reader.
Here.
Is it now look like acquire, lock, release, lock,
because we within this code,
manipulates the state variables.
He said either.
So I am looking if there are no active writers or waiting writers,
right?
So if is there active writers and work waiting writers,
then you wait,
you implement the number of waiting readers,
because now is myself.
I am going to wait.
And then i'm going to wait on the condition variables.
Do it.
I'm always need to wait until it's okay for me to read and release a lock.
Now,
why am I looking?
Why am I going here?
I am waiting for a boss.
Active writers is normal, right?
I cannot read on someone is right.
But why I am waiting also for writing writers because this means that I
am going to wait for other
writers to write before me before I can read.
Why do you think is that
a few people say we don't read garbage or we don't read one wrong results,
but why is that?
Because why we do that?
Right?
Because in that case,
you can have,
so here is what can happen.
You have a bunch of readers,
no writers in the system.
And now I have a writer which wants to write,
and that writer has to wait for the current readers to complete.
And in the meantime, I have another reader which wants to read.
I'm not going to let these readers read the database
together with the other readers before the
writer is scheduled to write and update the database.
So it won't the resulting wrong results, right?
What the reason you do this,
but it is fundamentally what it gives priority to the waiting writers,
right?
That what happens?
And why do you give priority to the waiting writers?
Is the reason was the answer is correct is from actually is that
you want to read the most up to date information.
Otherwise, you can start of fighters.
If you always have readers coming in,
you will never update the database.
Before a reader.
30 minutes finishes you have another reader sharing to schedule
that reader and so forth.
Life as a writer will not be able to be scheduled.
Sounds good.
Anyway,
after if there is no active writers or waiting writers,
then you are going to increment is a number of active readers,
because now you are allowed to read.
So you are active reader,
and you release a lock,
you access the database.
Is it only, right?
It's and then after you are done,
you acquire the lock and to manipulate the state variables,
and you decrement the active readers because i'm done.
And now what do I need to do?
Well, what I need to do is to wait,
wake up threads, which may wait,
for instance, to write to the database.
Here, if active readers is zero,
and there are waiting writers,
then i'm going to send a signal to write.
Simon has a great question here.
What new writers are coming all the time when you get to read,
if you keep waiting for all writers to finish.
That's correct.
So in this particular case,
if writers come up all the time,
you are not going to get a chance to it.
In practice, you need to be a little bit more sophisticated.
But that's a good..
This is one question here,
is why do you want why you release locks there?
Why don't you release a lock all the way to the end?
Why is not access database part of the critical section here?
So any readers can get the lock.
You don't change the state variables.
The locks are for changing the state variables.
In this particular case,
you also want all the readers.
If there are only active readers in the system,
if there are only leaders in the system,
you want them to read concurrent,
right?
Very good answers.
Now, let's see.
The code for the writer is very similar.
Right?
You acquire the lock.
And now you check whether you can write and what is a test.
There should be no active readers.
You cannot write.
While you have readers reading the data,
you need manipulating the state variables.
And obviously you cannot have writers,
active writers.
You don't, if you have any of those, you go to wait,
you wait on the conditional variable to write,
because you are a writer.
If not, you are going to increment active writers,
because now you are an active writer,
it is a lock.
You ask the database, read, write.
Then once you are done,
you acquire the lock again to manipulate the state variables,
to decline the number of active writers,
because now you are no longer writing.
And then you check if the number of if there are still waiting writers,
you are going to wake up one of those by sending signal.
And now, if that's not the case and the number of waiting writers is zero,
but there are waiting readers,
then you send a broadcast to read.
So now you see the use of the broadcast.
You are going to wake up all The readers,
because all the readers can read at the same time conqueror.
Let me ask this answer this question.
Does the question is,
does there exist some situation that the reader is waiting to read
some the media state?
While some writer joins the way?
Definitely.
Yeah, but the writer is not going to be able to modify the state.
So we are going to be fine.
Sorry, so basically you say if I read so that is already waiting.
And now, yes,
a new writer joins the way.
So that's valid.
In that particular case,
the writer will be prioritized over the reader,
but it's again,
at a given time,
only one reader and one or only one writer can manipulate the state variables.
So you should be fine.
We discussed why giving the prairie to write us earlier on.
Okay.
Now,
let's do the following.
We are going to,
in order to get,
hopefully, you do better understand what's happening here.
Let's go through a simulation.
Okay?
Let's assume the following sequence of operators operations.
We have three writers and one writer,
siri, the story three readers,
are one, are two and are three and one writer.
Okay?
So first we get the first reader,
the second reader, then the writer,
and then the third reader.
Initially, all the state variables are set to zero.
Let's see what happens.
R one comes along.
There are no waiting threats.
There are no other threats in the system.
So let's see what happens.
It acquires a lock,
check whether there is an active writer or awaiting writer.
Both of these variables are zero,
none of them in none of such straight in the system.
You exit the while loop.
And r one can start reading.
You increment the active reader variable,
you raise a log.
We know that why you access a database.
Let's say that while you are accessing the database are two comes along.
Okay?
Remember, now the number of activators,
it's one,
because r one is still accessing the database.
What is r one?
R two doing?
Obviously is going to execute the same code,
is acquiring the log.
Now it's checking whether it's an active writer or a waiting writer,
none this none such strategy in the system.
So,
again, you skip the while up and increment the number of active writers.
These are lock and you access the database.
Now, both r one and r two are accessing the database.
The number of active writers is two.
All the other state variables started zero.
Now, it's again assume that it does take a while to access database
and assume that during this time,
now when w is a writer,
the writer comes along w one.
So what is that?
The writer is going to execute the writer code.
So it acquires a lock and now it looks at active writers and active readers
in the system.
There are two active readers.
Now active writers still,
because there are two active readers.
The writer cannot proceed.
So what do you do?
You increment the number of waiting writers,
right?
Because now you have to wait,
and you call your weight on to write condition variables.
And you release a lock.
W one cannot start because of readers.
Finally, r three comes along,
choirs a lock, and now it checks whether active writers or waiting writers.
There are no active writers,
but there is one waiting writers, w one.
So therefore,
the new reader r three has to wait
increment writing readers now by one.
And you are going to wait for the condition variable to read.
They release a lock.
Any questions here?
Is that clear so far?
Let's go with our simulation status like this time.
R one and r two are still reading.
W and r three are waiting.
So let's say r two finishes,
add one, still accessing database.
W one and r three are still waiting.
R two is going to acquire the lock to update the state variables,
in particular,
to update the number of active readers now is less to decrement it,
because out of finishes.
And now is looking whether the active,
whether it can wait,
can wake up any threat.
And she's looking whether there are active readers,
if there are no active readers,
and that are waiting writers,
you're looking for that.
And then the condition is false,
because there are still active readers.
This is r one.
Then you release along.
And r one now is done.
Okay.
Now let's say r finishes, sorry, r two is done.
Right?
Now, say r one finishes.
He's doing the same thing.
Acquire the lock, decrement the number of active readers.
Now both are one and are two are going to be done.
And our active readers become zero.
And there waiting writers,
there is w one.
So that now this condition is true.
And now you are going to signal to the writer that it's okay to write.
Right?
Readers are done.
You can see it's the signal to write aw so now,
the writer,
which was waiting was a condition variable to write,
to receive the signal.
It's moved to the ridicule.
And now we can start executing it,
executing this slide.
It acquires a lock back because remember,
we are still in the critical section decrement number of waiting writers.
I am no longer waiting now.
Increment is a number of active writers.
I am active now,
but it is a log and access a database.
This again, although I am writing now,
is still okay to accept to access a database outside the locks.
Because this database is going to be accessed can show only if the number
of active writers.
It's one.
You are guaranteed it will not be greater than one.
Then say you are done,
you acquire the lock,
you decline the number of active writers.
And now you look to signal.
Again, you give priority to the waiting writers,
right?
Because you are prioritized writings of readings.
So now is there are awaiting writers,
you call okay to write.
But in this case, there are no longer waiting writers.
Therefore, you are going to look where there are waiting readers.
There is one is r three.
Then you are going to signal to r three that it can is okay to continue to read.
Now we start executing the code for our three,
who is resuming the execution,
acquires a lock back,
decrement avoiding readers,
access the database requires a lock,
decrement the number of active readers.
It is a lock.
So we are done.
Now all the readers are done,
all the writers are done.
So here is question.
How from how young if we want to signal the writer with a fixed order?
How should we modify our code?
Any suggestion here?
The question, if the way I understand it,
if we want to signals the writers in a particular order,
how do we signal them?
Any suggestion here from the class?
That's great.
Quite.
There are two ways to do it.
One easy way.
You can use a different condition variable for each writer.
Very good style.
The other one is to be five more conditioned variables than to have a queue
of writers.
But I to maintain it and only wake up the one from the head of the queue.
But this is pretty complicated.
But anyway, it's a possibility.
Very good.
So we are all done.
So here are some questions.
Let's see.
Let's check your understanding.
So let's say,
sorry,
can read a starter.
We answered this question.
Readers can start off if that or you have continuous stream of writers.
Here is the second question.
What if we erase a condition check in reader x this one?
Basically, we say wherever a reader finishes,
say it's okay to write what will happen.
It is a good idea,
it is worth going to work.
Any drawbacks?
Okay?
Question here,
one answer here is writers can start writing when readers are separating,
as I said, can be reading.
Okay.
Let's look at this one.
In order to answer that question,
let's look at the code to write.
This is a greater code here.
What will happen here?
Guys?
You see?
You get okay to write.
You go out here is waiting right to you decrement waiting writers.
But then what do you do next?
You go back to the while look.
And in the while, look,
if there are still active writers or active readers,
you still cannot write.
You go to sleep again.
You see,
because it's wild, because you check again,
the state variables.
You are going to be fine.
While this will happen is that he just wakes a writer,
just for the writer to go immediately back to sleep.
So just graduates contacts region.
So it's an efficiency problem,
is not a correctness problem.
Okay.
Good.
Let's go to the next one.
So go
farther.
What if we turn the signal into broadcasts to,
instead of having a condition broadcast to write?
You broadcast to write every analog instead of the signal?
What will happen in this case?
Is it correct?
First question.
Let's try to give an answer to anyone.
Yes.
It's correct.
Somali.
Yeah.
Yes.
And it's absolutely correct.
It's for the same reasons.
You see the fundamental observation here.
It's,
again,
the fundamental observation here is, again,
for the writer,
i'm going here to the code.
You are still in the while loop.
So no matter, even if you are going to be okay, not by mistake,
no matter who is waking you up,
you are still going to check whether there are active writers and active readers.
And if they are, you go back to sleep.
It's inefficiency problem.
Again.
It doesn't matter how many times you are waking up open up.
You are not going to do stupid things.
Okay?
The last one.
Finally, if we use only one condition variable,
call it continue instead of two separate ones,
both readers and writers are going to wake up.
These are going to be correct.
It's going to be correct for the same reason.
Neither writer nor the right reader are going to continue if the test
for the while loop.
It's still true.
So here is what happens,
right?
And this is what i'm going to end up with this one.
So you can use one.
But,
okay,
although there is in theory that there is one thing here,
but I this is subtle things.
This is correct with one condition to continue that it's actually,
if I continue is going to wake up one single thread,
and that single thread is an incorrect one and go to sleep here is a sink.
If I wake up,
if I do, if I have only one continue conditional variable,
both the writers and readers are going to wait up, wake up on that.
And now assume that by mistake, not by mistake,
it just happens.
I wake up the reader,
the reader is going to check and there are waiting writers
and it's going to go immediately to sleep.
But now these signals were spent out.
Okay?
And the writer cannot continue.
It's already,
it's a slip.
The reader is a slip.
If there is no, as I said, coming in,
we are deadlocked.
In order for this tour at work,
need to also change this signal from the right reader to broadcast.
Okay?
Okay, so you need to broadcast.
And you also need to broadcast,
so you need to do some changes.
So,
so the summary here and we are going to end up with this is
that these wild looks are extremely powerful,
right?
Because they are going to guard against doing stupid things or incorrect things.
If you are woken up by mistake.
So we are safe.
So what we need to be careful about is that because there is no history
with this condition variables,
I am protected to waking up the wrong,
but the wrong thread.
But then if I am waking up the wrong thread,
that signal was wasted,
and the correct thread will not be open up.
So you can have deadlocks.
So that's why here you need to be careful what you need to be careful about.
That's why you have to be a liberal with a broadcast.
So we are going to end up with this one.
And I think that it's a good place we are done with this example.
Please take a look at these examples,
careful carefully.
And for the exam,
and i'll stop here.
And the lecture is done.
I there is one last question.
I am going to try to answer.
Thank you.
And i'll see you on monday,
on tuesday and monday.
And thank you.
So two questions.
Why not question?
The why look give us good protection?
But doesn't that cost a lot of cpu cycles since we are constantly pulling?
Absolutely.
It's inefficiency.
It's your absolutely correct.
It's inefficient.
It's correct, but inefficient.
And from Chad,
wouldn't this possibly make a finished writers broadcast hit awaiting reader?
First before awaiting reader,
if there was both waiting read as a writer,
which means observed ordering priority of writers of writers before readers,
this will no longer guarantee the priority order between writers and readers.
If you have only one conditioned variables,
you are no longer going to be guaranteed this one unnecessary,
although it is still,
II you are not guaranteed readers when you wake up,
but still in,
if you want to proceed,
you are the while loop will take care of that.
In from the point of view of accessing the database,
the while loop is going to enforce a priority because a reader,
it's going to look whether there are active writers or waiting writers.
And if they are waiting writers,
it's not going to proceed.
Right?
So as long as they are waiting writers,
these wire conditions will ensure that the reader cannot proceed.
So actually,
the priority is still enforced.
Okay?
The priority is enforced by the while of conditions.
But the priority is not enforcing the sense that you can wake
up every a reader while you shouldn't have woken up.
And this can lead,
again to deadlocks without without changing the code and more be
more liberal in broadcasting the ok continue.
Okay.
Thank you.
And i'll see you on Tuesday and Monday.
Bye.