Hello, everyone.
大家好。
Welcome to the last lecture.
欢迎来到最后一堂课。
And today we are going to go over some special topics this being the last lecture.
今天我们将讨论一些特殊的主题，这是最后一堂课。
In particular,
特别是，
i'm going to talk briefly about apache spark and ray two systems.
我将简要介绍Apache Spark和Ray这两个系统。
We developed that berkeley you may have heard of.
我们开发了你可能听说过的伯克利系统。
And i'd like to go quicker,
我想要更快一些，
although there are a lot of slides,
虽然有很多幻灯片，
because really,
因为真的，
I like to give you opportunity to ask any questions you may have
我很乐意给你机会提出你可能有的任何问题
about these lectures about this class,
关于这门课程的讲座，
or in general,
或者一般来说，
as always,
一如既往，
at any point,
在任何时候，
please feel free to ask any questions.
请随时提出任何问题。
Basically, we have these labs,
基本上，我们有这些实验室，
and as you may know,
正如你所知道的，
each lab is around 5 years.
每个实验大约需要5年的时间。
Each lab has a particular mission and consist of a bunch of faculty,
每个实验室都有特定的任务，并由一群教职员组成。
some quite a few graduate students and post docs.
有相当多的研究生和博士后研究员。
This is what we started.
这是我们开始的内容。
This is one of more recent one,
这是其中较新的一个。
because i'm lab 2011,
因为我是2011年的实验室助教。
2000.
2000年。
It had a faculties across different disciplines of computer science algorithms,
它拥有跨不同计算机科学算法领域的教职人员。
machine learning,
机器学习
and sorry,
对不起，
algorithms, which in what do you mean?
算法，你指的是什么意思？
Bargaining is mostly machine learning.
讨价还价主要是机器学习。
The machines means systems.
机器指的是系统。
And people,
大家，
we are looking at some projects,
我们正在考虑一些项目，
which i'm not going to talk now is about crowd source.
我现在不打算谈论的是关于众包的话题。
That's why hands the name of the lab,
这就是为什么实验室的名字叫做“Hands”。
ampr and this lapse, again,
再次提到ampr和这个间隙，
like some of you may now are a is a floor plan in open space,
就像你们中的一些人可能已经知道的那样，开放式办公空间中有一个楼层平面图。
even the faculty have open sitting, stay in open sitting.
即使是教职员工也有开放的座位，留在开放的座位上。
And as islam,
作为伊斯兰教，
they have twice a year retreats with the industries that are working
他们每年与合作的行业举行两次团队撤退活动。
very closely with the industry.
与行业密切合作。
Anyway, between 120 and 200 people,
无论如何，在120到200人之间，
half from berkeley, half from industry.
一半来自伯克利，一半来自工业界。
In general.
一般来说。
Before pandemic,
在疫情爆发之前，
there are that be nice places like tahoe and monterrey.
有一些很好的地方，比如塔霍湖和蒙特雷。
You go there for 3 days,
你去那里待三天，
and then you present the latest reserve results,
然后你展示最新的储备结果，
and you get feedback and you network with people from industry.
你会得到反馈，并与来自工业界的人建立联系。
And we also have this kind of arm camps which are basically things.
我们还有这种军营，基本上就是一些东西。
Once you build some systems, some artifacts,
一旦你构建了一些系统和一些工件，
these are some events.
这些是一些事件。
It's your basically train,
这基本上是你的训练。
provide tutorials to people, in particular,
向人们提供教程，特别是
from industry to use for these new systems you built.
从工业界开始使用你们建立的这些新系统。
Anyway.
无论如何。
Let's start.
让我们开始吧。
So this is spark.
这是Spark。
But I started using berkeley in 2009,
但是我从2009年开始使用伯克利。
so actually started in the lab before i'm lab that was called a rad lab.
所以实际上在我实验室之前，有一个被称为Rad实验室的实验室。
But the main developing development happened during the amp lab.
但是主要的开发工作发生在amp实验室期间。
It became open source 2010.
它在2010年成为开源软件。
It becomes an apache project 2017,
它于2017年成为了Apache项目。
and also data research is a company behind.
而且数据研究是这家公司的背后支持者。
The open source project has been started in 2013.
这个开源项目始于2013年。
Today is the factor standard for being big data processing.
今天是进行大数据处理的因素标准。
How did this happen?
这是怎么发生的？
So what does2009 when we started to work on this?
那么我们从2009年开始做了什么工作呢？
What was the state of the world?
世界的状况如何？
So at that time, the most popular system to process huge amounts of data,
当时，处理大量数据最流行的系统是
large amounts of data was apache handle.
Apache可以处理大量的数据。
And apartheid had was an open source clone of the maverick use,
种族隔离制度是对马威克使用的一个开源克隆。
which a maverick use, which are the system,
一个特立独行者使用的是哪些系统？
a high profile system developed internally at google.
一个在谷歌内部开发的高知名度系统。
And this process huge amount of data,
并且这个过程处理了大量的数据，
the procedure amount of data.
数据量的处理过程。
But it was more bad.
但情况更糟糕了。
It was quite slow.
它运行得相当慢。
But it had the rapid,
但是它具有快速的，
it had a lot of industry adoption,
它得到了许多行业的采用，
some of the big high tech companies,
一些大型高科技公司，
and cloud are hot and there are two companies
云计算和云服务很火热，市场上有两家公司。
which are to new startups which are promoting.
正在推广的新创企业有哪些？
I do open source.
我参与开源项目。
At that time, again,
那个时候，再次，
this is open source.
这是开源的。
It was free.
它是免费的。
It came at the right time.
它来得正是时候。
Because if you probably remember of your heart,
因为如果你可能记得你的内心，
2007 2008,
2007年 2008年
or this big financial crash,
或者这次大的金融危机，
so sorry, it should be,
非常抱歉，应该是这样的：
this should be hard, though.
这可能会很困难。
Let me guess.
让我猜猜看。
And let's not simplify.
不要简化。
This is like hard or how hard is working.
这很难或者说工作有多难。
The hardware has two stages,
硬件有两个阶段。
map and reduce.
映射和归约。
And in each stage,
在每个阶段中，
each stage is done in parallel.
每个阶段都是并行完成的。
A bunch of map tasks,
一堆的映射任务，
read the data from the stories, from the disk.
从磁盘中读取故事的数据。
Then they process the data,
然后他们处理数据，
then they shuffle the data.
然后他们对数据进行洗牌。
And there is a second stage,
还有第二阶段，
which is the radio stage.
哪个是无线电阶段？
The new stage provides you the last the final results.
新阶段将为您提供最终结果。
Right?
对吗？
The classic example of a memory of this job is you count how many occurrences
这个工作的经典例子是你计算出现次数的数量
of each word you have in this ten nominees and documents.
对于您在这十个提名和文档中的每个单词，
Right?
对吗？
So this is basically the high level.
所以这基本上是高层次的。
And I think that many of you already know about it,
我认为你们中的许多人已经知道这件事了，
you may have even done projects for each other.
你们甚至可能为彼此完成了项目。
Any questions about the task are typically co located with the data is
通常，与数据共同放置的任务有哪些问题？
at least with the data,
至少有了数据，
with the input beta.
使用输入beta。
And like this figure shells, the input data,
就像这个图中的外壳一样，输入数据，
as well as intermediate data is stored on the list.
中间数据也存储在列表中。
The question, can I briefly explain what the map reduce means?
这个问题，我可以简要解释一下 MapReduce 的含义吗？
So think about this one.
所以请思考一下这个问题。
Sorry, I don't have an example here right away,
抱歉，我暂时没有例子。
but I think that we can,
但是我认为我们可以。
it is hopefully that reasonably easy to explain,
希望能够相对容易地解释清楚，
even without an exam of sound figure,
即使没有一个完善的考试
say you have 10,
假设你有10个。
millions documents,
数百万份文件
you have a large number of documents,
你有大量的文件。
and you want to count the occurrences of every word,
你想要统计每个单词的出现次数，
write english word in these documents.
在这些文件中写英文单词。
One way to do.
一种方法是这样做。
It is very simple.
这很简单。
First.
首先。
You if I say you have 100 machines,
如果我告诉你有100台机器，
you take these 10 millions documents,
你需要处理这一亿份文件。
and you divide them between 100 machines and you give to each machine.
然后你将它们分配给100台机器，并给每台机器分配。
I think 100,000 documents,
我认为有100,000份文件。
and each machine takes its pile of documents,
每台机器都会拿走它的一堆文件，
and it counts each in each word,
并且它对每个单词进行计数，
like, for instance,
例如，比如说，
were the world better place?
世界变得更好了吗？
How many times it appears in each files of documents?
每个文件中它出现了多少次？
One machine would say, okay, berkeley,
一台机器会说，好的，伯克利，
it's appears200 times and other machines finds 150 times and so forth.
它出现了200次，其他机器发现了150次，依此类推。
This first phase in which each machine is being independently discounting
这是第一阶段，每台机器都在独立进行折扣。
on each piles of documents is called map.
每一堆文件上都被称为地图。
Now,
现在，
each after the first stage, you want to aggregate, right?
每个阶段之后，您想要进行聚合，对吗？
Because in order to know the total number of occurrences of work,
因为为了知道工作的总出现次数，
the world berkeley,
伯克利的世界
in all the documents,
在所有的文件中，
you need to sum up, right?
你需要求和，对吗？
Because one machines in its 100,000, like, again,
因为一个机器在它的10万个中，再次，
found that very clear occurs 200 times,
发现"very clear"出现了200次。
another machine 150 times and so forth.
另一台机器150次，依此类推。
You need to add them up.
你需要将它们相加。
This is very new space.
这是一个非常新的领域。
In the reduced phase,
在缩减阶段中，
you are going to map each english word on one of the machines.
Say, for instance,
a one machine,
b on one machines,
we were starting a with on one machine were started
with beyond the other machines and so forth.
And then each of the mapper will send,
for all words,
the account for all words,
which starts with a to machine one.
So machine one now gets from gets all the accounts for the world starting
with a so they can sum up and finally gives you the world that give you
the result.
The second machine which counts all the get receives all the accounts
for all the water started with b is going also to
count the number of I aggregate the total number of occurrences
after received the information in the partial accounts from each of the
mappers for the world berkeley.
This is the radio space.
Make sense?
The shuffle pay the shuffle as stage.
It's exactly this.
What I describe.
This is what it is like.
Each, for instance,
if this is the second machines,
the second machine here is storing the counts of computer final count
for all the final accounts,
for all of our starting with b then it has to get the data from every mapper.
Right?
Therefore, the arrow,
this is why the shell communication.
So every map will communicate with every other reduce to send
these partial informations about the accounts for
the words it found in its passing of documents.
Make sense?
Okay.
Great.
Thank you.
So at the same time,
we are working on at that time.
We are working on harder quite,
quite a bit, right?
So improving the scheduling and things like that.
And in 2009,
leicester was a postdoc with michael jordan some machine learning.
He came to us through people on seizing the system because net flicks have
this challenge.
So the challenge it was they have this challenge for a competition with $1 million prize
for whoever can develop the best algorithms,
recommendation algorithms.
It gives you a set of data.
It was supposed to anonymous to be anonymous that in the end,
it and it ended up.
Not people realizing that it was not as much anonymous as I thought it is.
But anyway, at that stage,
that was a problem.
They give a set of data,
and these are the preference of the users.
The question is that can you predict what movies this particular viewer
is going to like?
Right?
This is a competition, public competition.
He came to us because the team in the umbrella with that,
they wanted to compete,
obviously.
And we obviously told them, and obviously,
with this amount of you need a lot of data,
because the more data you have,
the better models you are going to build.
This is one example.
For instance, if I want to the question is that given your age,
can I predict what kind of what kind of movie you like?
And basically the way I predict it,
I am going to predict what is the rating you would give to a particular movie.
So then i'm going to return the movies for which I predict that you
are going to provide the highest rank.
You have a few data points,
and then i'm asking you here in the middle, what is there?
What is the prediction?
What, and that's a question.
And the the intuition is that the more data you are going to have is
a better prediction can make.
Right?
That's why you want ability to process a huge amount of it.
Makes sense.
So this is a problem.
So obviously, we told them use huddle.
They use hard work because it process a large amount of data.
But how do it was extremely slow?
So let me explain why machine learning.
And at that, we are talking,
then we are talking about collaborative filtering algorithms.
This is before the deep learning,
is before neural adults.
It's more classical martial arts.
And but still,
each machine learning algorithms are typically algorithms.
It are iterative algorithms,
meaning that you start with some kind of predictions.
And then you train model the model, right?
You are getting more and more data,
and they are going to hopefully improve but improve the prediction,
but I think better and better.
Now each iteration,
if you want to implement this hard loop,
is going to be a map reduce job,
one job,
100 job.
And for each job,
you need to read the data from the storage.
And you need to write the data on the storage.
Each iteration,
mister read and write a lot of data from the storage from the disk.
And you remember the reading and writing is that this is slow.
Right?
Now if you have a few thousands of iteration,
this will take forever.
That's kind of what's the motivation on the motivation?
At the same time,
again,
this is an example of machine learning application.
But there are many other people,
because once you have data,
what you are going to do is if you want to do some forecast,
some prediction,
some optimization, so you need to process a data.
And in many cases,
this means machine learning or iterative computation.
The other one is that once you have the data,
the other application trend is,
once you have the data,
it's you want to start to queries a date,
right?
You don't want to attest to just run a job,
a run up which takes a few hours to produce the results.
So you also want to provide my 1/2 of like sequel kind of queries you
want to ask and to get
answered very quickly.
So this is what was happening back then.
Right?
At the same time,
we are starting to look around and we are working with facebook,
the microsoft, yahoo at that time was a big company at that time.
And we are starting to look at the workloads.
And to our surprise,
it turns out that despite that,
they had huge amount of data,
many working set.
Remember, what is the working set?
What the king said, it's how much space would you need in, say,
in memory so that your application works well.
That means your application will not access a lot of data,
which is not in the working section looking here.
This is what?
I remember,
this is the data seen the team back.
Then.
This basically shows, you say, basically,
you have here 3 columns,
4 columns.
The last 3 columns are for different workloads from these companies,
facebook, microsoft, and yahoo.
The first column is a noun is a memory of those machines.
This again, 2010 around 9,
10and so forth.
Certainly garbage ram for a server,
it was a lot of that.
And the numbers represent how many of a percentage of these jobs
can fully fill their data in memoirs.
It's basically say that, for instance,
if the several memory is 32 gigabytes than 96% of the jobs of from facebook
were load,
can feed their data in memory,
82% from microsoft to 90 75% from yahoo.
For 64 gigabytes,
97, 98 and 99.5, respectively, and so forth.
That's kind of the idea what is the solution?
And this is what spark comes in.
This was a new parallel execution engine for big data processing,
provides those general provides efficient support for multiple workloads.
It was,
because has a powerful api it reduces a code you need to write
for the same application,
right?
Because each api was doing more.
The original ibi was in scholar,
right?
It's a functional language.
But you also have api in java and later in python.
But the one thing, what but did
was very good at those performers,
at least compared with struggle.
It was for some jobs,
it was 100 times faster than how to mmr it means my videos,
because it was aggressively exploiting the memory.
And for the most water clothes,
like we just seen,
the data was fully fitting in memory.
Again, it was general.
There is a spark core.
On top of that,
you have a bunch of libraries like to provide sql interface,
provide streaming functionality,
machine learning,
graph processing, and the spark car.
It's provides support for the other language.
Is it to write code?
This is our account.
This is the application I mentioned to you.
On the left hand side is how the size of the code to write
that application using
hardware memory use ap is.
And this is so for 50 lines of code to 3 lines of code,
the main key abstraction of the original spark was what you call
the resilient distributed assets.
This is a set of data which is partition across machines.
And it was stored on ram or on disk and resilient,
because those resilient to failures will learn more about that.
There are 2 kinds of operation,
transformation of the data and actions.
The action,
the difference is a big difference is that transformation can be filtered
on about data selecting just a few lines,
a few rows,
selecting order or all lines in a text which contains were better.
Like, for instance, the actions are the one which produce an output,
a visible output.
Like, for instance, I want to get the account for berkeley,
like how many occurrences of berkeley are in all these documents?
This is spark.
It's again, i'm going to show you a very similar figure,
like i've shown you in the case of had book.
They have these rb ds.
And then now,
instead of only two stages,
memory user can have many number of stages.
Map radios are only particular form of stages,
but you can have much more, in general, any stages.
We are going to be calling these stages or the steps.
And then you have this kind of stage at the stage and between stages.
You can reshuffle the data and create new these rv ds.
Now, all stars in the same stage implement the same operation, like,
for instance,
map or reduce.
And typically they are a single strategy and they have determined to execution,
meaning that if you execute,
if your execute is the same task on the same data,
you get the same results.
And this will be important for a full tolerance that you are going to see next.
But I think that you already can start seeing these advantages, right?
And our advisory,
the resilient data assets are also immutable.
Immutable means that once you created them,
you don't change.
If you want to change them, you create a copy of them,
and you change the option.
The shuffle kind of plays a lot of implicit barriers,
a meaning that one stage cannot finish before the previous stage finished.
Because the stage the current state depends on the data being produced
by the previous stage.
So therefore, by definition, you cannot feel.
Right?
So again, these are examples I mentioned earlier on about transformations,
map, filter, goodbye,
or actions,
count, and things like that.
So now you see,
probably you can guess why now spark is
much better for about our application of mention that.
Because now each iteration it's one or more stages spark of a spark joe.
And if you go from italy one iteration to another,
you are going to pass the data through up,
right?
Directly to memo.
You don't need to hit the disk.
So here you are each iteration processing,
except for the first one process,
the data from the ram output the data into the ram for the next iteration.
She's going to be so much faster than re reading and writing the data
from the list between the iteration.
Again, this is a question about why do we need to shuffle?
There are two questions here.
Wouldn't the data need to be sent over the network in the shuffle stage?
Absolutely.
But it's actually the network is faster than the disk.
That's number one.
The number two is, again,
you don't need to send them and depend on the what each stage,
what happens between the stages?
You don't need to send all the data across another.
Again, to answer against the question,
why does the data needs to be shuffled between each step steps?
Again, it's like in our example about counting workout.
In the first stage,
you devise the documents and each machine counts of occurrences of berkeley
in the sets of documents.
Now,
each machine has a partial count of berkeley occurrences to get the total account.
You need to aggregate those.
So each machine needs to send to another machine is partial account.
That's why you need to communicate.
Now, we have every machine in the first phase,
which has a partial account of berkeley,
in the first stage, sends,
especially account to the machine in the second stage.
Now, imagine that you do this for every word.
So you have to have all to all communication.
Simon,
great question.
How do you guarantee the internet?
Are these things that i'm stay durable since that i'm is
not as% of this great question?
We'll answer it very quickly soon.
Okay.
Now you may ask what happens.
So basically leicester with his group bmu spark and to compete
and their team is the ensembles.
Okay?
As you can see, is a time for the best for.
But they were second because they submitted 20 minutes late.
So therefore, they didn't win.
Is that teams, which are $1 million,
sit down just 20 minutes.
Maybe if we have started working on spark 20 minutes earlier by the other story.
Now let me give you an example, another example of mining.
We spark.
And then i'm going to address a question about the photographs.
So the here is log minding your loud error messages from a log
into memories and interactive research for various patterns.
Spark has a driver which executes which runs a code you fit in the code.
And workers.
The driver will send some function to the workers to execute any step.
Basically,
this is a scholar code.
Don't worry if you don't know scholar,
I think it would be the this instruction will be self explanatory.
So basically, you read the text,
you read the lines from the text file.
This you are creating the rvd this will be the rvd these lines
are going to be a big set,
and then it's going to be partitioned across machines,
across the workforce.
Then you are going to filter each line,
which contains we start this error.
This will create another data set,
again, is represents all lines,
which starts with error,
is a second transformer,
right?
And now I want to read the messages.
So i'm going to split by tab like because errors and the legs
of the message separated by tab.
I'm going to split between the error and the message.
These are messages.
And I am going to catch the messages.
I want to count,
for instance,
all the messages are all messages contained my sequel.
So basically how many error messages I have containing my sequel.
And this is the action.
Remember you have transformation and action filter map,
cache or transformation.
The code starts to this spark as what is called lazy evaluation.
Only on you trigger an action,
you start to execute the code.
And the core thing about this is that when you start execute the code,
you see all these lines you need to execute and you can optimize.
You can do data placement,
compute placement,
so you can have higher accurate data localities.
So you reduce the amount of data transfers over the network and sing like that.
Right?
It's like a a sql query.
You present a sequel or the entire single query to the optimizer
and the optimizer season that is equal query and can do small things
about optimize.
If I give you one instruction at the time,
it's not much you can do to optimize.
But anyway,
all this code is run by the driver.
Let's see what happens.
Let's say the original data,
it's in this adfsa distributed file system.
These are different blocks from this file I am reading,
and they are across the different world.
So the driver sends a task to the worker.
The task is to read from the first line, for instance, to read from this,
the blocks from adfs is partition.
They doing the transformation.
And then eventually you are going to cash and send the results back.
This is what the results back are.
This kind of partial counters,
because each of these workers is going to count the number of occurrences
of my sql across this data.
So to get the total account,
you need to sum them up.
These results represent this partial counter just sent to the driver.
And now you send the second.
Now i'm doing the same thing,
but I want for php errors.
Now the key point here is that now with aphp errors,
you when you count the php errors,
you don't need to go all the way to read from the original files,
do the filter to the map.
Now, you are going to read the cash message.
If you do that,
obviously,
the first time is a follower because you need the game to do the read
from the disk.
Do the filter?
Does a map?
You told you was taking in these examples to on60 gigabytes,
22 machines at that time.
20 seconds for the first to get the number of the count of my sql errors.
The second time, when it's already in the cache,
it's only half a second.
So that's about this.
Again, you have language support for python,
scholar and java.
I mentioned to you is far more expressive.
Ap is,
and you see map and reduce are only towards the ap is even back then it has
around 100 ap is.
And still we have another question.
Now, in hard,
do you can maybe aggregate in canopy,
you have only two stages.
You need to stay to have map and reduces.
You have only two tasks to functions.
That's the only thing you can do.
Right?
You have two special tasks.
Here you have much more general, like you said, filter,
maps,
count things like that.
Now,
it was this great question about what you do about recovery for tolerance.
This is distributed systems.
We know the machine fails.
We learn about that.
We want to make it more for tolerant.
So how do you do about that?
Let's see.
Let me before going that.
Let me ask answer this other question, ask shift question.
For this log mining example,
are the main reason why spark is faster?
Because it's using graham instead of this totally and lazy evaluation,
allowing for optimization in part of it and sleep transforms
and multiple action following it,
as opposed to my reducing.
On repeat.
These are all good reasons.
These are all through the lazy evaluation does a lousy.
And we now spark as an optimizer or catalyst,
doing quite smart optimization.
Like a database optimizer.
You can link multiple option actions and more multiple transformations.
So you don't need different jobs for those.
The biggest reason actually is because of data between stages is is started
in round instead of one,
that is.
So.
Now, this is a question,
and this is what Actually one of the main innovation of ray.
It is to make this data set to reliable.
How do you make reliability?
How to achieve a reliability?
One is replication.
We learned about that if you remember the rate,
but you need to write the data over the network,
and the memory can be inefficient.
You inefficient use, right?
Because now you still remember the memory is expensive.
You don't have as much memories on the disk.
And now to use as a memory to store multiple replicas.
So the effective memory size will decrease by half or by once by 3 times.
If you are going to store to have three replicas is not good.
You can do backup on pakistan storage.
Right?
But still, if you do backup, right?
Is slow.
I still mainly mean to go over the matter.
So the spark choice is what is called lineage,
basic construction.
Our spark is doing.
It tracks the sequence of operations.
It records the sequence of operations that creates a partition
of a particular rvd and if that partition misses,
it re executes the sequence of operations which created that partition is
the first place.
This way it recreates a factory.
And this is working because the inputs are immutable.
Once the inputs are used by a task,
they don't change after that.
So you can reuse later.
The task are deterministic.
So here is an example.
You have an rbda you have some filter,
creates an rdd bs,
and you have a join operations,
have a shuffle here.
Then you create an rvdc and you have aggregation of creating an rvdd
here we have two machines,
each like a one, a two, b one, b two, c one,
c two corresponds to two different machines.
And now assume that before the aggregation get a chance to read the input c
one that machines fails.
Right?
What does it do?
The driver from spark side is going to notice that and is going to
just replay,
re execute the task who created sichuan and find another note
eventually to run the passport.
Right?
So it reconstructs you on.
And now the aggregation function will have boston pursue an answer to the creative.
Right?
Now here, for instance, maybe beyond, it's also lost.
It's okay.
If beyond is lost or not beyond,
b two says beyond is lost, it's okay.
You are going to go all the way to a one.
In the worst case, you go to a one to all the data, which is input data,
which is stored on the disk,
which is persistently stopped.
But in general, you don't need to go all the way.
So that's a key.
Make sense?
This is an iterative algorithms like our machine learning algorithms,
the first iteration,
basically 1 to 3 iteration on the y axis,
how long the iteration takes.
So here,
the first iteration takes longer because they need to read the data
from the disk.
And then you are going,
then each iteration takes much, less.
And at some point,
you have a failure.
But the only three things,
what happens when you have a failure is the next iteration will take
a little bit longer,
because they need to reconstruct the loss take.
That's all, but as always is transparent.
So now i'm going to end with a spot,
like I mentioned,
right now,
parkers and effective standards for distributed for data processing,
very successful data,
which is a successful company.
So it was pretty much a success scenario here.
Yes, ii sorry, what I said here,
not beyond his back comparison storage,
I said a one is back complex and storage.
The inputs are read from a persistent storage, which is resilient.
In the worst case,
you can go all the way back to the input to reconstruct the lost outputs.
But I assume that a one and a two are stored.
The inputs are stored reliably.
Announcements.
Congrats for taking the last meter.
Project three due on projects three is due next wednesday.
But sunday,
there is a party in wozniak lounge.
You can get held there.
If you are around,
you can, it should be a fun and very useful.
4 hours you can spend.
Discussion will be office hours,
like you will be seen, probably.
And the officer will continue to that of that week.
And the homework six is due next tomorrow.
Now, let's switch the gears and talk a little bit, right?
There is a system.
I'll give you the history as well.
We also build after the trends.
And i'm going to go quickly.
We went through these trends earlier on when I started the class.
Ai demands are exploding.
I show you the plot.
This is a plot from open ai which is the computational requirements
to train the state of the art machine learning models.
And it was growing 35 times every 18 miles between 2012 and 2019.
The growth continue after that.
This is 2020 data point for gpt three from open ai it's not only for kind
of esoteric
workloads like playing games or things like that.
It's also for image processing or natural language processing,
really, very useful applications.
The other thing is a more slow is ended, right?
It used to have it use that like27 years ago,
every one year and a half,
the performance of the processors doubled no longer true.
Now we're just growing by a few percents every year.
So then there is a huge gap between the motors law.
And actually,
the end, the morsel is no longer.
It's even worse because the morsel has ended,
like we just mentioned.
It's a huge gap between the demands of this kind of machine learning
application and capabilities of a single processors.
This is also true.
Even if you are looking at gp us and dp us,
the gap is a little bit lower smaller,
but it's a log scale.
Wise, or the why coordinate.
It's a log scale.
It's in log logarithmic scale.
All these kind of differences means that the gap increases exponentially.
So huge gap growing, by the way.
So this means that really, you cannot,
there is no other way to run this kind of variables,
others and distributing these variables.
Spark was more about data scalable data processing.
This is ray is more about scalable, compute process,
compute, scalable, compute.
This is an example recommendation service.
You have here.
Basically, here,
when you are going to open your application on your phone,
you get some recommendation about maybe new products to buy or the
services download.
This is from the largest,
one largest feedback,
one of the largest feedback company in the world.
And the application, when you look,
it looks at the high level,
it has three stages.
You get the data you do.
Some feature is asian.
You try to extract what are the things from the data which are important?
Like the user I ds or things like that.
Then you use that data to train the model,
the recommendation to improve the recommendation and then to sell them.
All right?
So this means that the next users or you and you are coming again,
or you are long on the application,
you are going to now to be served these recommendations based on a model
or just train.
So now one question is about how fast you can update this model, right?
Because presumably,
if you are going to update with the most recent data,
the model is going to perform better.
Right?
I think about if I am going to use a model to recommend whatever services
from last year probably not going to be that accurate.
Because in the meantime,
there are a lot of other products,
a lot of other services which are introduced.
That recommendation will not give.
A system will not even know about it,
and certainly will not know how my preferences have been involved.
But now the question, obviously,
it's obvious that if I train a model today is going to do
much better than the one and j train last year.
But what about the one last week?
Right?
Or yesterday, there's a base model.
The question is about how much it matters.
When this company started,
they started with this updating the model every one day.
And they wanted to reduce to 1 hour,
and they use a state of the art solution at that time.
And they get pretty good results.
Click through rate.
It's one of the main matrix for this application.
Basically,
it tells you what is a ratio between the times you click on the offering,
which was shown to you over the number of times that offering was shown to you.
If an offering was shown to you 100 times and you played 5 times
and the clinics through,
the rate is 5%.
So they got an increase in god as this clicks arrived by 5%,
which was massive,
then they want to get lower,
but they couldn't get lower,
because they're suggesting the solution at that time.
The main point here is that their solution,
and even today,
many of the solutions that remember,
each of this stage needs to be distributed.
We have good systems to distribute each of these daily studies of workload,
data ingestion, and visualization,
you can use spark or something else.
For training,
you can use themselves serving a sense of flow distributed by toys.
Like me may be horrible.
For selling, you can use another system.
But now in order to build all this entrance application,
you need to stitch together these stages.
And this is hard.
Development is hard because each of these stages different.
Then the deployment is hard because now you need to deploy
different distributed systems.
The management discard because you need to manage different distributed systems.
Different ap is and things like that,
and also is slow.
And that's why they couldn't read faster.
Because and now this is going to sound.
Now you can recognize this pattern to move the data between two different systems,
how it moves the data between the different systems.
Where is the way you move?
The data between the different systems?
Is to write a in a disagree story system and to read
from the disagree story system.
That's, again, was slow.
And this was a very simple application machine learning application.
In general, it's much more complicated.
You don't need only to do training.
You also need to do to tune their models.
And if you are thinking about something like reinforcement learning,
you also need to do simulations and things like that.
So it's very complicated.
The summary here today,
we need to to run all these workload distributedly,
because they need to scale.
And for each of these workloads,
we have good distributed systems,
right?
For training model, serving,
simulation, streaming.
But when you want to build an entrance applications,
we need to use many of these systems together.
And this is very hard.
Okay?
It's hard to build, hard to deploy.
And also on top of that, it's also slow.
So this is what is right.
Ray tries to solve this problem.
Instead of having this hodgepodge of libraries of systems,
you need to stitch together with ray.
You have one system,
which is very general.
It's a universal framework for this video computing.
And to support these workloads,
you build libraries on top of it.
Now, if you want to support the workload,
they just run a library,
but on top of the same system,
a aa short story is starting in 2016 as a class project.
Is here robert and philip,
they are taking a class.
And their projects I was teaching and their project
was to scale distributed deep neural networks.
Remember, the new spark was created before the neural,
before the neural letters took off and wanted reinforcement learning.
They struggle to use existing systems to do so.
And then,
for the reason we mentioned,
it was very hard.
So started to develop this array application area system.
2000s of 6, 17 are 11.
The radio not released.
These are live is reinforcement learning library.
Right here on its high parameter attorney library.
And version on zero was at least last year.
And any scary is a company behind rate,
like databases behind the spark.
Now,
ray core,
this is the things i'm talking.
This blue sinks.
This is a core.
There's a very mean honest, api the core,
api is this one.
Right?
They need to start with the rainbow.
They get raided, right?
And some decorators,
the back end is c plus.
The front c plus is what how the backend or phrase build the bindings.
The ab are in python,
the most popular one,
but there also is java and some experimentality in c plus.
This is what ray nutshell is doing.
So ray marshall is very general for the following reasons.
Think about.
This is a way to think about it.
What are the abstractions in most programming languages?
Think about c plus or python computer abstractions that are functions and classes.
So ray can take a function and can transparently run it remotely,
and can take a class on instantiate as an object is going to bring.
So instantiate it also remotely call them actors,
remote function.
We call them task remote in class instances, we call them up.
Stateless means that they don't have internal state.
They get the input process.
The input beats out that our results.
And they are that while actors is like,
they have internal state,
you call the methods.
And when you define a class,
you have internal state and you can modify the state.
That means stateful.
It's also have a future abstraction,
meaning that when I am going to run a task remotely,
the call is going to execute to return immediately.
I'm going to show you and also have any in memory distributed object stars.
It's not a new language,
is an existing extension to existing language.
So let me give you an example.
Let's have you have this python code,
your return r and you do some computation.
Now, you are just running on there on your laptop,
and then you run f of a you run this function once,
and it takes 1 second, you run twice.
It takes another second.
Basically, the program,
it takes 2 seconds.
Okay.
Let's see how the same program is going to run in.
But I let me see it's another.
Ii was talking here about classes is a programming class.
You is like a class in c plus or class in piper.
I'll show you an example.
I was on setting a question now.
This program takes 2 seconds.
Now let's see what happens in life.
Is ray.
If you want to run this function every monthly to on a different note,
you are this decorator, a dot remote.
And then when you call f you are the suffix,
f dot remote and f and now the things to notice here and you'll see that these
functions do not return the result.
While they return a pointer,
a future is so called a future,
a pointer to the result.
Okay?
And why is that useful?
Let's see.
So he says the driver is our worker,
so driver and workers are different machines.
When you are going to execute the first f dot remote on a now this function
instead of learning locally,
it's going to run remotely.
Okay?
This is a task,
but it returns immediately the result to this task.
Returns immediately is a pointer to the result.
This is returns even before the function is executed.
And also,
even before the function may be even have been scheduled on a different amount.
But now because it's written as immediately, so basically,
it's non blocking, if you remember,
about blocking and unlocking,
I can't execute immediately the next call.
So i'm going to create another task,
which takes the argument b the sad task.
It's return immediately a future,
a pointer to these result.
The beauty of it right now,
I launch both f and flf of a and f of b simultaneously.
They can run in parallel.
And now is the radar get is a blocking code.
If I pass the radar,
get the futures,
but they don't get to wait until all the results are produced.
Right?
It's a blocking code.
Now, fnfanfab run in parallel,
and returns the results.
And now my program from 2 seconds to takes only 1 second.
Here I am ignoring the message overhead and other overheads.
But as I keep another question,
the question about the classes which class at very clear was a project.
It was262 ai believe,
in fall 2015,
their projects was to do distributed training
for the neural networks.
I also asked them to do using spark.
And actually they developed an extension of sparkle spark net to work
with gp us to do it.
But then that was a little bit painful because again, sparkle java,
jbm and dozen design for this kind of photographs and started the work on
what are the solution before I could do this sort of distributed compute?
Yes, there are mainly domain specifics.
Another system, which is a little bit more general,
but it's a pain to use,
and it's not fault around.
It's mpi but it's for high performance message passing interface is called
is from high performance computing faults.
There are also some actor framework,
but none of them,
at least to my best of my analogy soldier,
it's as general,
got it.
Now this is the python class.
This is a class.
Iii miss.
And ii misunderstood the question.
This is a class.
Now it's a counter class,
and you can do the same thing with this one.
You basically to reiterate them out,
and you do,
when you invoke,
when you create the class and you invoke the mathematical class,
you have the suffix stock remote.
And just like that,
this class is going to be associated as an actor c and actors means that
are active.
It's like a mini service.
We sit there and waste for the methods to be able to process and methods,
which are invocated on it.
Okay?
Number of also you can specify here,
the number of gp us,
a number of cp us,
which is very useful for when you do deep learning, right?
Because a lot of tasks,
they may have a lot of needs.
Right now, ii said the last thing is to read the object star.
So let's see how this is working with them again.
A simple function, I call ii have a function f and g and it's very simple.
I am every terms of future,
which is going to get to be taken as an argument by g which
is going to return the result.
What is this distributed memory about distribute objects dot a new execute,
f dot remote?
It's like we seen before.
You are going to run this task on a different note.
You get immediately back to the future that is asked to have.
And again,
it's not only xi ds that are not x value.
Now you call, again,
not you call g right?
And you get the future.
At some.,
when f finishes is going to create this object,
result, object,
result,
it's going to put in this object store.
Now, this reference idea of x or future points to x and on that is ready.
G is going to wait for the reference,
for the argument to be ready.
So the system is going to be ready.
Then he's going to copy x to node three,
where the g is.
And now, the argument of g is,
it's available.
Now g can execute.
Basically, this is what it is.
Okay?
So the objects are passed by reference.
Now, if you don't have references what this she says,
imagine that you don't have reference.
If you don't have reference,
effort create a result, and the result has to be returned back to node one.
Now, the result is also passed.
Now to g g will evict that, you don't know three.
So g and including the the results from f are going to be copied to know three.
So the results from, if it has to be copied to one out one,
and then to know three,
right?
Needlessly, because no one doesn't do anything with the result from no two.
Okay?
That's kind of the point here.
It's like by reference when you pass it,
like even on a single machine will pass that when you pass arguments by reference,
one of the reason you are going to pass is to avoid expensive copies.
This is very similar, but for this to be decided.
So what happens?
With this example, I show you at the beginning,
they used ray to implement this pipeline.
So now everything is on different systems,
but there are different libraries.
They are able to do the model update every 5 minutes from 1 hour.
They increase the clicks to write by other 1%.
So the architecture i'm going to go very,
very quickly,
because I want into 3 minutes to finish and let some time for more questions.
There is a driver which runs a code the workers and you have cr actors
on different now to check they could this tasks or the actors which
are created.
There is a distributed scheduler to decide where to run the task
where and where to instantiate actors.
You also keep the lineage about for the task which are creating similar to sparks.
You can reconstruct the lost objects.
So today, raise this score and you have a lot of libraries on top of it.
These are native libraries which are built by us.
So to speak by the original team of ray are
a liberal enforcement learning library during high parameter tuning,
the race service about serving ag ds or ag ds training now is called great train,
but there are also a lot of third party libraries which run on the public.
Let me see,
let me just answer this question.
I should have asked what happens when every lies on data surroundings.
If the data it's on the disk,
then it's going to delete from the disk.
No difference that if you run it on us on your machine by object store,
does it just mean passing the references?
The object store means that you can pass the references.
You can put the results and you can put the data in the object stores.
And then you can pass the references to that object.
It allows you to pass the references without the object story,
you cannot pass the reference.
If it's on the disk of the original machines or not the remote,
if it shows a disk of the original machine,
what you are going to happen,
you need to be careful, right?
If it's a discount, the original machines,
the way you are going to do it, actually,
if you run it, obviously,
if its local disk is not going to work.
But typically, in this system,
you have a distributed storage system,
which is accessible.
But from all machines,
even in spite you have a distributed file system,
use hbfs hardcore distributed file system, for instance,
or you can use a blob store like s three.
But all these systems are they do assume there is a distributed story system.
This is a get up stars.
And this is comparing grey and spark with other popular system like cuff cart,
cure, flow,
a dusk and so forth and fling.
If you look here,
ray and spark a they are actually pretty much matching the slope,
and they are faster than the others.
There are a lot of contributors.
Now I think that are close to 600.
This is one system,
this and group build on top of ray and build the real is the entire platform,
is called fusion.
Seize them.
So build algorithms and application and services,
like for marketing, advertisement,
recommendation and things like that.
They deploy it actually double eleven and double twelve, a double eleven,
as you may, now,
is a largest shopping day.
This is uber.
They build a machine learning platform.
They are building on top of raise a new generation or machine learning platform.
But this, quote is great, right?
It's like you're saying exactly what I said to you.
But someone else is telling you saying that,
say, by leveraging ray,
we can combine the reprocessing,
this retraining and high parameter search,
always in a single job running a single training street,
a single machine.
And this is a fun example.
This is america's cup is the biggest selling competition,
the most prestigious.
They sold us away from 1841.
It's every 3 or 4 years.
I forgot.
It was a few years ago,
it was in san francisco.
Oracle team won one.
This 2 year,
the team who won was new zealand team,
and that new zealand team,
the boat and the team was trained with stools,
built by this quantum black,
which is a mckinsey company.
And those tools ends about or a design with the help of adelaide.
That was pretty cool.
I'm stopping here and i'm going to help you to take any questions
for the remaining time of few minutes.
Sorry, I couldn't leave more time.
The really good luck with the end of the semester and resolve your classes.
All your projects,
obviously, happy holidays.
And now i'm happy.
Let me take the questions.
Thank you.
How is this to migrate non distributed non email application?
Today?
I may be misunderstanding,
but why not just use existing scaling?
Solutions?
Are just Containers plus carbon at this plus traditional application?
That's a great question.
Why not containers and cooperatives could,
but medicine containers are orthogonal.
This Ray is intended for the programmer.
You as a programmer,
you build distributed applications by just adding this rating mode in the code.
And it's suppose,
ideally to be,
and it's easy, hopefully, to run, to build this.
Ray tries to reduce a gap between building applications,
writing Python code, for instance,
and running on your machine to developing the code and running on a cluster.
Right?
Try to reduce this gap.
Cuba.
Notice it's helping you its resource orchestration.
It helps you to manage a distributed applications.
It doesn't help you to write the distribute applications.
If you have a distributed application,
it helps you to manage it, right?
Where to run different parts and things like that.
In fact,
the Ray is running on Top of cabernet is and Dockers are
just obviously what it is.
It's it's a package right?
Package all the dependencies.
And also under the hood,
I can use Dockers.
But that's a thing.
They are a different level.
So it's a different goals.
And there are some level complementary.
So Ray it helps you to write is for intended for the developments
for someone like you.
But that is for the box.
In general,
it allows you to manage the distribute applications,
not to write it, to deploy it and manage it.
And Dockers is fantastic for packaging the dependencies,
for Python, and also can use conduct environments.
Hopefully, I answer the question.
Any other last minute questions?
We still have 23 minutes.
If not,
it's a good way to end.
So what are some systems related classes you recommend?
I think you can see us 262 a when it's offered,
the database is 26.
You may also get in if they are offered,
like 290 fours with graduate special graduate seminars,
which are focusing on system distributed systems that are a few of them.
But this has a few plus to look at.
By the way, I just want to feel,
I think it's a I'm happy that and I have to apologize to you
that almost all classes I went over time.
I was not over time,
but I was not able to finish my material.
So this is an exception,
and I'm glad to finish on this note.
Thanks, everyone and happy holidays and all the best.
I'm sure we'll see each other many more times in the future.
Bye, bye.